&gt;&gt; Ladies and gentlemen,
please welcome Vice President,
OS X platform experience,
Andreas Wendker.
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Good afternoon.
Welcome to the 25th WWDC.
[ Cheering ]
So, if you watched the
keynote this morning,
you will have noticed that this
year we have a very strong focus
on our developer technologies.
We're building out our
entire platform ecosystem,
and 2014 is going to see some
of the largest developed
releases in years.
We are adding an incredible
number of new APIs.
We're giving you access to
more low-level technologies,
and as always, we're moving
all parts of the ecosystem,
hardware, software, services,
and developer tools
forward together,
which is something
only Apple can do.
Our focus on developers
is paying off very nicely.
As we saw from some
of the numbers shown
in the keynote this
morning, there are now more
than 1.2 million apps
in the App Store.
They have been downloaded
over 75 billion times.
And this huge success story is,
of course, only made possible
by you, the app developers.
And you're part of a very,
very active community.
Since we shipped the last update
of our Xcode IDE just
a few months ago,
it has been downloaded
more than 14 million times,
and we are adding developers to
our community at an amazing rate
of more than 120,000 brand-new
developers downloading Xcode
every single month.
So, let's take a look
at what we're doing
with our iOS App Store to make
you guys even more successful.
This year, we're improving
how users can discover apps
by adding things like related
searches, trending searches,
and editor's choice badges,
which will help promote the most
noteworthy apps in the store.
It will also allow you to
advertise your apps better
by including preview
movies, which will play
for the users browsing
the store.
And if you're a developer
of multiple apps,
you can even bundle them
all together and sell them
at a discounted price,
if you would like.
Now, we're not stopping
at making the App Store
experience itself better.
We're also working very,
very hard on improving
the developer experience.
So later this year, we're going
to give iTunes Connect,
a new, cleaner look.
It will have a new-
[ Applause ]
It will have a new dashboard
that will show information
about your apps, and
most importantly,
we are adding variable
analytics.
[ Applause ]
These analytics will tell you
how many users visited your app,
your store pages, how many users
went on and purchased your app.
[ Applause ]
How many remained
active over time.
And best of all, collecting all
this information is fed right
into iOS and it's
completely automatic.
There's no need for any kind
of special libraries or code
on your part to turn
on analytics.
[ Applause ]
Now, many developers
have also asked for a way
to distribute beta versions of
their apps before they ship,
and we are pleased to announce
our new TestFlight service,
which will allow you
to do exactly that.
Users become beta testers by
downloading the TestFlight app.
[ Applause ]
The app will give them
access to the beta versions
that are not available in
the full App Store yet,
and they download
these apps simply,
and they download these apps
simply with their Apple ID.
There's no need for any
kind of special profiles.
[ Applause ]
Each app can have to, can
have up to 1000 beta testers,
and notice that this is a limit
of 1000 users, not 1000 devices.
So-
[ Applause ]
So, all these users
can run your apps,
your apps on multiple
devices at the same time.
And we will even allow you
to use the TestFlight service
to distribute apps within
your own development team,
in that case without
app review, and again,
without any kind of
special profiles.
[ Applause ]
Also, later this year, we
we'll ship the final version
of Xcode 6.
We will allow you to
include your app's symbols
with your App Store submissions
because later next year,
we will start servicing
fully aggregated
and symbolicated crash
reports for your apps.
[ Applause ]
And you'll be able to work
through these crash reports
within the Xcode IDE.
So, we have a huge update
for the App Store this year.
There are several
end-user features
that will help discoverability
of apps
and a completely revamped
iTunes Connect with analytics,
TestFlight, and later, also
better crash reporting.
Now, let's move on
to the surprise news
of this year's developer
conference-Swift.
Swift is the brand-new
developer,
brand-new program language
designed by Apple specifically
for Cocoa and Cocoa Touch.
It works beautifully with our
system APIs, and it's designed
with the common programming
patterns
on our platforms in mind.
Now, there are a lot of
program languages out there.
On the iOS and OS X, most of you
use an object-oriented variant
of C, C++, or Objective-C,
which so far has been our system
program language of choice.
The problem we were facing
was that pretty much all
of these languages either fit in
the category of high performance
but low productivity
or in the category
of high productivity
but low performance.
But we want developers
on our platforms
to have a language available to
them that gives them the best
of both worlds, and that's
why we created Swift.
Swift is very modern.
It has all the things
you would expect
from a new program language.
It has a nicely tuned syntax.
It allows you to write very
compact, very expressive code
with features like
clojures and generics.
Here are a few examples
of Swift code next
to some typically Objective-C
code you might write.
You can really see that
Swift is a lot more compact.
It even has dedicated syntax
for a common operation
like a respondsToSelector test.
And here you can also see that
we are using common dot syntax
for function and
selector implications.
Swift is also designed
to be safe.
It will prevent you from
introducing typical bugs
or stability issues simply
by enforcing best practices
for writing code, so that for
example you don't end up working
with an uninitialized
variable or running
out of bounds with
an array index.
And Swift is fast.
We've really tuned the compiler
and the language
runtime together
to optimize the most common
operations on our platform.
Here's an example benchmark.
This is a Complex Object Sort.
You can really see how Swift
outperforms Objective-C and,
certainly, scripting languages.
Now, the best way to tell you a
little bit more about Swift is
to simply write some code.
So, I'm going to ask Ted
Kremenek to come up on stage
and give you a demo
of the basics
of the Swift programming
language.
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Thanks, Andreas.
So, I'm going to take
you on a quick tour
of the Swift language,
and doesn't the terminal
look beautiful in Yosemite?
We're going to fire
up the compiler
in an interactive
coding mode called a
Read-Evaluate-Print-Loop,
or REPL.
I just type code
in, it gets compiled
on the fly, and executes.
We'll start it off with
a simple, "hello world."
This one line of code
is all you would need
to write your first
working Swift program.
Whereas we would naturally
want to move on now
to doing more interesting
things like declaring variables.
Now, you notice, I'm not
actually writing the types
for these variables.
That's because the Swift
compiler has powerful type
inference that infers that
X has the, has the type int
because I initialized
it with the value 42.
Similarly, for S we infer
that it has a type string
because I initialized it
with a string constant,
and this means it makes the
code feel very lightweight.
Now, I have a lot to show you,
so instead of me
typing everything,
I'm going to have
some assistance here
with the keystrokes but
everything is still going
to be live in the REPL.
Let's move on to simple
containers, like arrays.
Now, you can see the syntax
is very light and natural.
Here I have an array
of integers,
similarly, an array of strings.
Again, I didn't write the types
because type inference came in
and it inferred the types of
the arrays just by the contents
of the array that I used
to initialize the array.
Now, arrays behave pretty much
as you would expect, you know,
I have subscripting, which
can be used in, you know,
subexpressions and so on.
But an important thing
about arrays is all their
accesses are balance checked.
This is part of Swift's
safe by default design.
In a normal-running program,
execution would stop
at this point.
Since we're in the REPL,
we can keep on going,
but this is really kind of a
fundamental keystone of the,
of the Swift language.
Now, arrays are just like
any other type in Swift.
They have certain capabilities,
like computer properties that's
going to tell me the size
of the array, or methods
to remove and add elements.
And because arrays
are containers,
they can also be used
with this very generalized
for...in syntax.
It works for collections,
ranges of numbers, sequences,
and here I'm looping over
the values of the array
and printing them out.
And you'll notice I'm using
a very lightweight string
formatting called
string interpolation.
Essentially, I have a string
constant that I can just splat
in an expression that gets
converted into a string
and spliced into the rest
of the printed out string.
It's very really nice for doing
lightweight string formatting.
Swift also has
batteries-included support
for dictionaries, and these
are also strungly typed.
Here, type for instance inferred
that I have a dictionary
that maps from strings
to doubles.
I can also use the for...in
syntax with them as well,
but in this case, I get a
key value pair all in one go,
if I wanted to print
it out all the values.
Let's move on to functions.
And you still see the
syntax looks very similar
to variable declarations
and you'll see there's
this reoccurring theme
in the language with the, where
the syntax is, it's simple.
It's composable.
It's very regular.
It's very easy to read.
So, we start out
with the fun keyword,
the name of the function,
its arguments,
in this case we're taking
an array of integers,
and then the return
value is at the end.
In this case, we're
returning an int.
This simple function
just loops and, you know,
it loops over the
array and sums up,
sums up the numbers
and returns them.
Call syntax looks just
as you would expect.
This is a very simple example.
Let's say we wanted to
extend it, all right?
So, I'm, I'm doing
all this work,
I'm looping over the array.
Let's say I wanted to return
the average at the same time
as I'm computing the sum.
We can do that in
Swift via support
for multiple return values,
and all I have to do-
[ Applause ]
-is change the return
value to a tuple.
The rest of the function
looks pretty much as before,
except you see at the return
site we return a pair.
And so when we call this
function, we get a tuple back.
And if you notice at the
top, I put these labels,
sum and average, on
the tuple pieces.
It means I can access the
pieces of the tuple by name
and because the language has
powerful pattern matching,
I could just declare two new
variables, sum and average,
to decompose the value of the
return value all in one go.
[ Applause ]
And of course, the language has
been crafted to work beautifully
with Cocoa and Cocoa Touch.
With this one line of code,
I can import in all the APIs
from the Cocoa framework
on OS X.
And I can immediately
start playing with it.
So, for example, I saw
in Yosemite we have
this new look and feel.
Let's take a peek at the
new default system font.
Here's what's going on here, is
I am accessing a class method
on NSFont that returns
me an object
for the default system font.
And so this is a real
object from Objective-C.
I can access properties
on it, call methods,
do everything that you expect.
Now, another important piece
of Cocoa are protocols,
and Swift supports
protocols beautifully.
Syntax is also very
regular and simple.
Here, for example, I'm
declaring a protocol scalable
that models the idea that a
graphical entity is scalable.
I should be able to, you
know, scale it up in size,
scale it down, and I can,
it defines a single method
that returns a new
value that's scaled.
And just like Objective-C, I can
retroactively add conformants
to a protocol, to a class, using
something called an extension.
They're similar to
categories in Objective-C
but a bit more powerful.
And you see, I've just
defined the method right there,
and now I can call it.
And so I've returned a font
that's twice the point size
as the original, all on
the fly, here in the REPL.
Now, also in Cocoa, we
haves structs, right?
Structs are simple data
types for aggregating data,
but despite being simple,
they're really powerful
in Swift.
Let's take a look at
our old friend, CGRect.
Now, many of you who have used
this API are probably used
to creating instances of
CGRect using CGRectMake.
Well, in Swift, you can also
use just a uniform construction
syntax to construct
values in struct as well.
And here we see the actual
labels being put on the,
on the values that
we're initializing.
Now, looking at CGRect, wouldn't
it be great if it had a property
on an area that could tell
me the area of a rectangle?
You can't define
this in Objective-C.
Objective-C does not have
properties on structs.
But Swift does.
I can retroactively now
add this computer property
to the struct using
it in an extension.
This is what a computer
property look like.
It just looks like a variable
declaration with a bit
of code added on, on the side
for the value being computed.
And I just defined
it, and indeed,
laws of geometry have held up.
A 10 by 10 rectangle
indeed has an area of 100.
Now, once you have properties
and methods on structs,
why not have them conform
to protocols, all right?
And this is really, you know,
a really powerful concept.
So, I can also have
CGRect conform
to the scale of protocol.
It's a, it's kind of a, it's
a graphical entity as well,
and I could also, you know,
I can now call this method
and scale up the
rectangle I created.
Now I have a 20,
20 by 20 rectangle.
So, now we have uniform
capabilities between classes
and structs, methods,
properties, and protocols.
So, now I have the power to
write some really generic code.
Let's say I want to
write a function,
scale by sizing factor.
It takes an arrayable
array of scalable things
and it returns a new
array of the, you know,
those elements scaled
up by some factor.
I can use that, I can
implement this very easily
for both structs and
classes using generics.
A generic function
looks almost identical
to a regular function except
it has this additional bit of,
of type information
where I'm supposed
to find a placeholder type T.
And all that matters
is that T conforms
to the scalable protocol,
whatever it happens to be.
The rest of the function looks
pretty much as you expect.
It's going to take an array of
T, which, whatever T happens
to be when I call this function,
it takes the scaling factor
and returns in a
new array of Ts.
Now, all I want to do is I
want to create a new array
in which each element
is scaled up.
I'm going to use the functional
map algorithm on array,
which takes a clojure to do the
transformation on each element
when constructed in a new array.
The clojure syntax
looks like this.
It, it's akin to
blocks in Objective-C.
And we think clojures are so
important that we wanted them
to feel really great,
syntactically optimized
in a language.
So, if the clojure is the
last argument to the function
or method, you can use this
really selective trailing
clojure syntax where
you can omit the,
the parentheses around
the clojure.
And that's it.
That's my three-line
generic function.
I can use it now to scale
up an array of NSFonts.
They're twice the size of
the ones I created before.
Similarly, I can call the same
function and scale up an array
of structs, completely
different data types,
but they just conform to
the scalable protocol,
and it works as expected.
This uniform capability is
between structs and classes
with methods, properties,
and protocols.
This thing is going to really
finally change how expressive
your code can be.
And we can't wait to see
what you can build with it.
Now, this ends what I'm going
to show you in the REPL.
I'm going to switch the slides
and tell you a few more exciting
things about the Swift language.
OK. So, as we saw in the
REPL, in, it is really easy
to write natural
and expressive code
in Swift while readily
tapping into some
of the language's most powerful
features, like generics.
And as you saw, it's really
crafted to work beautifully
with Cocoa and Cocoa touch.
Now, there are many advanced
features in the language
that I didn't talk
about in the REPL.
One of them of particular
importance that I wanted
to mention are modules.
What is a module?
It's a logical collection
of code
that is intended to
be built together.
So, for example, any framework
you build, any target you build
in Xcode, automatically gets
a module associated with it.
And one thing you get from
modules are implicit namespaces.
This means you no longer
have to prefix the name
of your classes anymore for fear
of them conflicting
with somebody else's.
[ Applause ]
Now, a really great
feature we did touch
on in the REPL demo were
Clojures, or non-S functions.
They're extremely powerful in
Swift, and they work beautifully
with blocks-based APIs in Cocoa.
And we think they're
so important
that we've syntactically
optimized them so that was
like those one-liners that
you want to write, you know,
to do something simple,
can be written
with very little code while
maintaining readability.
And because Cocoa-based,
you know,
blocks APIs in Objective-C will
reflect as Clojure-based APIs
in Swift, APIs
like dispatchasync
will read beautifully
with a trailing Clojure syntax.
In this case, dispatchasync
reads like control flow,
which is more how the API
was intended to be used.
So, we think this really changes
the readability of your code
and how you reason about it.
And perhaps the biggest
feature of Swift is
that it's fundamentally a
thin language under the hood
with much the functionality
not baked into the compiler
but defined in a
Core runtime library,
which itself is written
in Swift.
To give you an example of what
I mean, Core things like int
and array are defined
in this runtime library.
They're not baked
into the compiler.
Thus, the language is really
designed from the ground
up to be extensible,
composable, layerable,
to build new things out of it.
And we think this really
embraces the soul and spirit
of Cocoa and Cocoa
Touch, where rich APIs
and rich frameworks can
be combined together
to build really truly awesome
behaviors in technologies.
Now, the Swift language is full
of a ton of great features,
which we think are going
to fundamentally change how you
think about and craft your code.
But beyond that, we designed
the language with the intention
that it would be the basis
for truly fantastic
interactive tools.
In Xcode 6, we have
a new feature,
Interactive Playgrounds.
They're akin to the
REPL in that it's
like a lightweight
coding environment,
but it brings forth
the full capabilities
and rich experiences that we
can only deliver in Xcode.
And to show you more, I yield
the stage to Max Drukman.
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Let me show you a little
bit of what you can do
with Playgrounds in Xcode 6.
So, I'm going to start
off with a new Playground.
I think I'll make
this a little bigger
so we have a little
room to roam.
Playgrounds start you out
with Cocoa already imported
and a string variable
for you to play with.
I'm going to change mine to
something a little more topical.
How about that?
Now I'm going to add, how
about a date constant?
Pretty simple stuff, but you
can see on the right side
of the editor, I'm
getting results
as I enter lines of code.
That is the results area.
I know it's a brilliant name,
but just like in the REPL,
as you enter code, it gets
evaluated and you get results.
So, if I were to do
something like style
that string, I get the result.
My string is styled.
Now, you don't have to take
my word for it because many
of the results in the
Playground can be Quick Looked.
The Quick Looks in the
playground are just like those
in the Xcode debugger.
You can even implement your
own for custom data types.
They're a great way
to see results
that aren't great candidates
for coming across in plain text,
like this attributed
string or images.
So, just like my
attributed string,
I can Quick Look these images,
but we've added a way for you
to see the results
of your Playground
in a more persistent fashion
by adding your results
to the Timeline Assistant.
Now, the Timeline
Assistant allows you to build
up a persistent representation
of the results
of your Playground so
you can really get a feel
for what your code is doing.
The next thing I'm going to do
is I'm going to mask that image
with a Bezier path
that I'll create.
Now, because Bezier paths are
created in multiple steps,
they're a great candidate for
visualizing in the timeline.
I can simply add each of
the steps to the timeline
and get a great sense of
how my path is constructed.
And it's especially good
for spotting how one
bad value can have
ripple-effect consequences.
I'm going to undo that one.
I think I'll get rid of
most of these, actually.
I'll just leave the
final result.
Now, as I said, I want to
mask my image with this path.
So, I'll do that here.
I'm also adding in my
attributed string to the mask
so that it's punched
out of the center.
So, the timeline is great for
getting a sense of how your code
and how your views are
doing, but it does more
than just present static views.
It can also render them live,
which is great for animation,
which is what I'm
going to do next.
To do that, I'll just import
a little bit more API.
See how simple this is?
Especially when you
don't have to type.
And I add in a little code
that takes my two images,
one that's been masked, applies
it on top of the other one,
and makes it animate
with Core Animation.
Now, as Chris showed you
earlier, you can also move
around in time in the timeline.
So, I can move back
and I can scrub
around to really
get a good sense
of how my animation is working.
Now, the, the next thing I
want to do is I want to add
that date I created
earlier to my mask,
and I'll do that up here, and
we can all cross our fingers
as I type live onstage.
How about that?
So, well, hmm.
I, OK, so I've added my date,
but that doesn't
look all that great.
Let's see if I can
make that look better
by reducing the font size.
Well, that's an awfully
big date.
I think what I want to do is I
want to make that date shorter,
and I'm betting NSDate has
some help for me there.
So, as with any class in Xcode,
I can command click on the,
the name of that class
to jump to the header.
In this case, I'll
command double click
to open it in a new window.
Now, notice that this doesn't
look like an Objective-C header.
It isn't. It's Swift.
That's because Xcode
creates Swift versions
of Objective-C headers
for you, so you don't have
to translate [applause].
That's right.
So you don't have to translate
what you see in the header
to what you implement
in your code.
Now, I have to come clean.
I don't know all that
much about NSDate.
So, looking at the header, well,
that's not really
doing enough for me.
Luckily, in Xcode, we have
lots of great sample code
and documentation
to help me out.
But wouldn't it be great if
you could combine the sort
of hands-on, do-it-yourself
style of sample code and the,
the sort of show-me-how-to-do-it
style of documentation?
Yes. Yes, it would.
That's why we created
Documentation Playgrounds.
[ Applause ]
Documentation Playgrounds
combine the best of both worlds.
Because it's a playground,
I can play.
But because it's documentation,
I get adult supervision
[laughter].
So, here is a Documentation
Playground talking
about converting between
dates and strings,
and here's what I'm looking for.
It's talking about
date formatters.
I'm pretty sure that's
what I want.
And it even very
handily tells me
to try setting different
values for time and date style.
And even more handy, it even
gives me the enums to try.
So, let's see.
I'm betting short style is
what I'm after, so all I have
to do is copy and paste,
and I can see my result
change in the timeline.
That's getting close.
Let's try this one.
Awesome! That's exactly
what I'm looking for.
Don't you want all
documentation to work this way?
So, now I know how to format my
date, and it's a simple matter
of doing that in my Playground.
I'm going to do that by
replacing a bunch of this code
with some code that has
my shortened date in it.
Hello. And my, my
fancy, there you go.
There it is.
Now my view is looking
exactly like what I wanted.
That's a small taste of
Swift Playgrounds in Xcode 6.
We think you're going to
love playing with your code.
Back to you, Andreas.
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Thank you, Max.
So, now that you
know a little bit
about what the Swift
coding language is,
how do you start using it?
Well, I made that
really easy for you.
Swift uses the same object model
and the same memory management
approach as Objective-C.
You can import all our system
APIs directly into Swift.
Foundation collections
are transparently bridged
to Swift language
arrays and dictionaries,
and we even went ahead
and modernized our
existing Objective-C APIs
so that they interact more
naturally for Swift code.
So, you can adopt
Swift at your own pace,
if you would like, file by file.
You can mix and match
Objective-C
and Swift in the same project.
We also wrote some great
documentation for you.
There's an entire new book
about Swift that you will find
in the iBookstore for free.
And we, of course, updated
our reference documentation
to cover all our APIs in
both Swift and Objective-C.
Now I know that all of
you guys really wanted
to be the first ones to submit
a Swift app to the App Store,
and I'm very sorry to
have to disappoint you,
but we've already done that
because, because this afternoon,
we're updating the WWDC app,
the app that you guys are using
to get around here
at the conference,
with a version that uses Swift.
So, this language is
ready for you to use.
It's real.
Now, one thing that is really
important to understand is
that we are planning to evolve
this language very rapidly.
Among other things, we really
want to hear what you have
to say about it and
incorporate your feedback
as much as possible.
And so we are not going to
promise source compatibility
between Xcode releases.
Some source conversion might be
necessary, and we'll do our best
to provide converters on the
way if we make major changes.
But the one thing we will
promise is binary compatibility
for your Swift apps because
we want you to be able
to try it without delay.
So, when we ship Xcode 6 later
this year, you will be able
to submit your Swift
apps to the App Store.
And they will run, your apps
will run on iOS 7 and later,
and OS X Mavericks and later.
So, Swift apps are not
limited to iOS 8 and Yosemite.
[ Applause ]
So, we are, as you can
probably imagine, really,
really excited about Swift.
We think it's quickly going to
become the programming language
of choice for our own
code as well as your apps.
We're looking very much forward
to hear what you think about.
Next we're going to
talk about gaming.
This is another technology area
that you are pushing
on very strongly.
We have many great techno-,
technology advances to announce
in this area this year.
To tell you more about
it, I'm going to hand
over to Jeff Schtie
[assumed spelling].
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Thank you, Andreas.
We have an amazing games
technology ecosystem with APIs,
tools, and hardware
that allow you
to all build brilliant games.
Let's take a look.
So, Game Center.
It's our social gaming
network providing features
like achievements, leaderboards,
friends, and multiplayer.
Many of you are already taking
advantage of Game Center
to differentiate your game,
and we have great
engagement with Game Center.
In fact, last month we had
over 130 million
monthly active users.
So, that's Game Center.
Game Controllers.
Last year at WWDC, we
introduced Game Controllers,
the Game Controller MFI program
and the corresponding
APIs for iOS and OS X.
One year later, Game Controllers
are doing really well.
Thousands of games taking
advantage of Game Controllers
for both the best of
touch and button inputs.
We have Game Controller demo
stations at Apple Stores
like the one right
here in San Francisco,
and we're introducing
controller forwarding.
So, what is controller
forwarding?
Now you can take an iOS device,
snap it into a Game Controller,
and then use the integrated
inputs of both buttons
and motion to control
iPads and Macs.
It's pretty cool.
So that's Game Controllers.
So now let's talk about
our graphics APIs.
We have SpriteKit, we have add,
we're adding many new features
to both SpriteKit and SceneKit.
We're bringing SceneKit
to iOS, and of course,
we're very excited
about our low-overhead,
highly optimized Metal API.
So, new for this
year is a major push
to making building casual
games easier than ever.
And SpriteKit is
our 2D graphics API.
We're introducing new features
like per pixel collisions
in physics, field
forces, inverse kinematics
with constraints, and,
of course, Shaders.
SceneKit is kind of like
SpriteKit but for 3D,
making it simpler than ever
to produce 3D games, and,
of course, it's now on iOS.
New for this year in
SceneKit, you, sorry.
SceneKit has everything you
would expect from a 3D graphics,
high-level 3D graphics API, like
the ability to load, manipulate,
and render complex 3D scenes.
It has some of the
same great new features
as we have on SpriteKit.
But what's really cool is
you can integrate SceneKit
and SpriteKit.
You can take a 3D object
from SceneKit and use
that as a sprite in
SpriteKit with no overhead.
You can take the output of
a SpriteKit scene and use it
as a texter in SceneKit.
It's really, really cool.
So, I'd like to invite Jacques
up to help me show you a demo
of both SceneKit and SpriteKit.
[ Applause ]
So, let's say you want
to use the built-in Physics
system for collisions.
Last year, you may have
gotten something like this.
So, that's OK, but
it's not great.
So, why is this?
Well, if we turn on Physics
Debug Draw, what we'll see is
that the Physics bounding
box, boxes do not correspond
to the exact shape
of the sprites.
So, new for this year, you can
turn on perfect cell collisions,
and now SpriteKit can use
the sprites alpha mask
to create pixel-accurate
collisions.
This allows you to create
complex interactions
and build things like
gears or even machines.
We've also added field forces.
Here you see an, an
attractor interacting
with the sprites in the scene.
We can add a repulser and
see how the tube field forces
interact together
with the sprites,
and we've added many real
and imaginary field forces
like directional gravity,
black holes, magnets,
repulsers, and spring forces.
And, of course, we have
everything you need
for dynamic lighting.
One AB, here's a basic scene kit
scene and one API call can turn
on lighting, and of course,
you can select the object
in your scene which you'd
like to cast shadows.
And if you want to take
this to the next level,
you can add normal maps.
So, what we've done here,
with a single API call,
we've turned on normal maps.
SpriteKit uses the
existing artwork
to generate a normal map
automatically, so there's,
no extra art was added here.
This kind of, this
kind of dynamic,
dramatic element can
really add to your games.
So, let's take a look
at the integration
of SpriteKit with SceneKit.
So, here you have a SpriteKit
application you may recall
from last year.
What you can do now is take
a SceneKit node and put it
into the, into the
scene as a 3D object.
That, that allows
with no overhead
to get a, a tremendous result.
Here we've replaced
both the hero
and the alien with 3D objects.
So what does this
allow you to do?
You can design your game in 2D.
You can set up your complex
interactions all in 2D,
then you could add
your 3D assets
in to give your game
that extra pop.
So, that's SceneKit
with a SpriteKit.
Now, let's take a,
take a look at some
of the features of SceneKit.
As I said, SceneKit is kind
of like SpriteKit but for 3D.
It makes it simpler than
ever to build 3D games.
Now, let's take a tour
of some of the features.
Here we have an example of,
the built-in 3D Physics Engine.
You have the blocks and balls
colliding with each other
and also with the room itself.
This is, game is using the
3D, built-in 3D Physics Engine
and it's obviously
fully interactive.
And we have 3D field forces.
Here you have an attracter
in 3D, which is kind
of like a space vacuum creating
this really cool effect.
What's amazing is you can
just add a simple attracter
to your scene to create
this great effect.
No other work was necessary.
And you can combine
SceneKit and SpriteKit.
So, what are you seeing here?
So, the paintballs are
being shot into the scene
as 3D objects using the 3D
Collision System to collide
with the Taurus,
another 3D object.
We then take a paint splotch
sprite, say that 3 times fast,
and paste it into a SpriteKit
canvas off screen you don't see.
We take the results of that and
texture map it onto the Taurus,
so it creates this really
convincing, cool combination
of SpriteKit and SceneKit,
made possible by the,
the integration of these APIs.
And finally, of course,
you have shaders.
We have vertex, surface,
and fragment shaders.
Here you have a simple
vertex shader,
which is manipulating the
model's geometry in real time.
We have surface shaders where
you can effect the surface
and lighting properties
of our model,
here creating this
cool caustic effect.
And finally, fragment shaders,
which can create amazing
pixel-level effects
like this glass globe
effect here.
So, that's seeing a
couple of shaders.
Now, I'd like to take a minute
to have Jacques show you how
easy it is to enable some
of these features
using our Xcode tools.
&gt;&gt; Thanks, Jeff.
So, new in Xcode 6
are built-in tools
for SpriteKit and SceneKit.
You can edit content
right within Xcode.
I'm going to give you a
quick tour of that right now.
So, here we have the
SpriteKit editor in Xcode 6.
You see the per-pixel scene we
had from the iPad demo earlier.
I'm going to make some quick
edits to it in edit mode,
which I'm currently in, and then
I'm going to switch to simulate
in simulate mode to
see the physics live.
So, I'm going to go over here on
the right to my media library,
which includes all the
images inside my project.
I'm going to drop one of
these squirrels into here,
and I'm going to place it
using the new snap-in feature
and then I'm going
to simulate this.
Well, this behaves
pretty much as expected
because the blue rectangles
are the physics body outlines,
so this is not falling over.
I'm going to correct that by
turning on per-pixel physics,
which is as simple as selecting
the objects I want to use,
changing their physics
definition
to use the alpha mask.
Then I'm going to simulate again
and the right thing happens.
OK, well that was easy.
Let's move on to showing you
the new feature of field forces.
So, field forces are super
easy to use inside Xcode,
and I implore you to try them
out and play with them here,
and it's one of the
best places to do that.
So, I'm going to drag a
theoretical field in here,
called a spring field,
which acts as if there
was a spring connected
between the field
and any of the nodes
that I'm going to enable it on.
So, I'm going to pick
some of these balls here.
I'm going to enable the
spring field on them
by setting their physics field
mask to something other than 0.
I've done that.
Now I'm going to simulate this.
Well, you notice they all
drag towards the center
of the spring there, and you
notice also as they collided,
they collided with the
inert pulser not enabled
on the field mask.
So, they actually,
full physics running,
and the field only affecting
the balls I selected.
Super easy and fun to use.
Next up, I want to
take you through how
to put 3D content inside
your SpriteKit scene.
So, just bear with me while
I go through the steps here.
All right.
I'm going to drag
that ship in and dump.
All right, so that was
step 1, 2, and that's it.
You can see it's 3D.
I'm going to try that again
in case you missed it.
So, here we go.
An alien. OK.
So, step 1, that's
everything you need.
So, this is just a
quick preview of some
of the great new features
we've added to SpriteKit
and SceneKit in Xcode 6.
Thank you so much.
Back to Jeff.
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; So, thank you, Jacques.
So, that was some of our
high-level, high-performance,
super-efficient 2D
and 3D games API.
Now, let's go from
the high-level right
down to the GPU.
We've been optimizing the
heck out of the graphics stack
with a new, low-overhead
API Metal.
So, why is that?
What, what does that give you?
Well, many games want to
run at 60 frames per second.
So, a little bit of math
shows you that you have a bit
over 16 milliseconds
for every frame.
We put that on a timeline, what
we can see is that you have
to get all your application
work done,
you have to issue your drawing
calls, and the system framer has
to turn those drawing
calls into GPU commands all
within that 16 milliseconds or
you'll start to drop frames.
And of course that's just one of
a number of frames you have to,
you have to produce to make a
truly interactive experience.
So, let's expand
that first frame out.
You see, there's
two distinct parts.
The first part is the
application piece.
The second part is that system
framework, that GPU API.
Well, Metal is super-efficient
at reducing the second
part to the bare minimum.
So, what this gives
you is more time.
More time for AI,
more time for physics,
more time for more drawing,
more time to make your
game even more brilliant.
So, Metal allows you to
unlock the power of the GPU.
It gives you easy
access and full control
over the rendering pipeline.
It has features like the direct
control over the creation
and encoding of GPU
command buffers.
It also provides a
unified shading language
for both graphics and compute
with offline compilation.
As you saw this morning,
Unity, Crytek, Epic Games,
and Electronic Arts have all
committed to supporting Metal,
and today we have
Johan Andersson
from Electronic Arts here to
show us what they've been able
to do with their Frostbite
engine on top of Metal.
Johan.
[ Applause ]
Welcome.
&gt;&gt; Thanks, Jeff.
It's really great to be here.
I'm one of those first-time Mac
and iOS developers, so hello.
We've been building for
the last couple of weeks
and you render using Metal
for our game engine Frostbite.
Well, our goal with
using Metal, this new,
low-overhead graphics API, is
to try and enable the wide set
of capabilities of our
Frostbite engine on iOS.
And to showcase this, we
built a new demo in the world
of Plants vs. Zombies
Garden Warfare,
one of our latest console games.
Let's have a look.
Yeah, will load in a little bit.
[ Music ]
So, here we have the
zombies, our enemies,
advancing on the plants who are
defending their garden center.
This is the same
Frostbite engine that we use
to power our triple-A console
games, such as Battlefield 4
and Need for Speed,
here running in iOS.
[ Sound from computer
game demo ]
One of the biggest changes we
saw with using Metal instead
of OpenGL was that our
rendering submission times
on the CPU became
five times faster.
This is really quite
impressive and it's a,
it's a really good benefit
because it frees up 80 percent
of one of our CPU cores which
makes it a lot easier for us
to build full games, games
with even more animations,
physics, and audio.
Uh-oh! It doesn't
look like it's going
that well for the plants here.
Let's see what they do.
[ Sound from computer
game demo ]
[ Applause ]
Thanks, everyone.
We're really happy with
the result we're getting,
and let's take a closer look at
some of the action we have here.
So, this is rendered in real
time in Frostbite with Metal
on an iPad Air, and
it's interactive.
Nicholas here is moving
around with the camera.
And one of the key benefits
that we're getting from Metal is
that we get fine-grain control
over the GPU and overall system.
We can build command buffers
efficiently in parallel
and we can control them.
We can explicitly
manage GPU resources,
which significantly
reduces overhead for us
and makes it a lot easier to
give a significantly better
and stable frame rates.
Now, Nicholas has paused
in this scene here.
This is really quite
the interesting scene
with tons of stuff going on.
And there's tons of
V effects, debris,
and this large animated
character is interacting.
And there's a lot of components
coming together to be able
to create these type
of environments here.
And here we have
two very detailed
and great-looking characters,
sunflower and cactus.
We're running dynamic shadows
for everything in this scene
and not just the characters,
but everything really.
And this is really quite heavy
but it makes the characters
and everything fit in with the,
regardless of where the lighting
condition is in the environment.
Well, let's look at it again.
We've been working on, on this
for just a couple of weeks
but we're really quite
interested in all
of the results we're getting.
We're really happy about it.
So, yeah. Yeah, so here we have
the big animated robot again.
It's a zombie robot.
I'm not sure how that
works, but he seems
to be very well animated
[laughter].
So, we're rendering up to 1.2
million triangles per frame.
That's really quite a lot,
and we're really happy
that we can do that.
And together with that,
we're doing around 20
different rendering passes
for our HER rendering, for
shadows, for aimed occlusions,
for particles, and
for distortion.
And as you can see
in the background,
we have this nice [inaudible]
effect going on that sort
of frames the action
a little bit more.
And we're really happy that
we can, I'm really excited
and really impressed by the
amount of geometry and effects
that we can push
through the GPU.
It's really quite extraordinary.
And this enables us to
use the same content
and the same features
that we're using
for building console
games but here on iOS.
It makes it significantly
easier to,
to work with this as a platform.
So, Metal for us is
literally a game changer.
It, it's a key enabler for a
new set of full 3D games on iOS,
and we at Electronic Arts are
super excited to support it
and put this in the
hands of our game teams
and see what they can create.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Thanks to Johan
and Electronic Arts.
That was simply stunning.
It's amazing the
power of the GPU
that Metal allows you to unlock.
So, it has never been easier
to take an amazing idea
and to brilliant, build a
brilliantly successful game.
We can't wait to see what all
of you are going to build.
Thank you very much, and I'll
hand it back over to Andreas
to talk about extensions.
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; All right.
Extensions represent, represent
another very important new
technology direction
that we are opening
up for third-party developers
on both iOS and OS X.
They represent the ability
to hook into various kind
of system behaviors, and
they allow users to expand
and customize our Core
operating system functionality.
Extensions are bundles
that ship inside your apps.
They get downloaded from the
App Store with your apps,
and they get removed
from your system
if you use an uninstall
to your apps.
So that the user
doesn't get flooded
with unexpected new behaviors,
they stay in full control
of which extensions
are active in the UI.
They get to expressly activate
each extension they wish to use.
It uses insisted
preferences and settings.
In technical terms,
extensions are short-lived,
out-of-process services that get
launched by our OSs on demand.
If configured to do
so, they can share data
with the apps they are
embedded in, for example,
to access keychain items or
any other kind of preferences.
Extensions are of
course sandboxed,
and we even developed this
cool new remote view technology
that hosts an extensions user
interface inside our system apps
and dispatches user events
back to the extensions process
without the app being
able to see it.
So extensions are
designed to be very secure.
And since extensions
typically share a lot of code
with their apps,
we now allow you
to use bundled frameworks
on iOS.
[ Applause ]
So you're not limited
anymore to static libraries.
You can now bundle
resources and binaries
in fully supported frameworks.
Now, here's a list of
the extension points
that we are making
available in this year's iOS
and OS X releases, and more
will follow in the future,
but we think this is a
great starting point.
Let's go over these
one after the other.
There are many online services
out there that allow users
to post comments or share
things like pictures and videos.
And while we support the largest
ones directly in our OSs,
we realize we can't
support them all.
So, if you are running one
of these online services,
sharing extensions are a great
way to let users post comments,
links, and media to your service
from within any app
they might be running.
Actions allow you to take
user data, anything from text
to images, audio, and more,
and transform that data
into a new representation.
For example, you could write an
extension that takes source code
and Xcode and reformats
it to your wishes,
perhaps with the
three-space indentation.
And Photo Editing extensions are
actions that manipulate images,
but we make sure that we
keep the original around so
that edits are nondestructive.
Safari actions manipulate
web pages.
Now, they have a
lot of flexibility
because they get accessed to the
full DOM on the way in and out.
So they can completely re-render
an entire web page while the
user is browsing.
For example, to do a
language translation.
Notification Center
widgets allow you
to place click-at-a-glance
views inside the iOS
and OS X Notification Centers.
You can use them for
displaying pretty much any kind
of status information
or for offering helpful
little utilities to the user.
They're mostly designed to
display short, concise data
but they also allow for
simple user interactions,
and among other things,
they're great launch points
to jump out into full app.
Document Providers extend the
newly designed iCloud Document
Picker and allow you to access
additional storage mechanisms.
For example, in an enterprise
that uses a third-party
Cloud service.
And we offer a similar
mechanism on OS X
and remote file-sharing
services can annotate Finder
with their sync status.
Another very important new
mechanism is the ability
to provide third-party
keyboards.
You can use them to support
additional languages or any kind
of input methods that
you might think about.
Creating extensions is as
simple as creating apps.
The extended export with all
the things you might need,
such as new templates,
additional scheme settings
so that you can launch the apps
that actually host
your extensions.
We improved our XPC service
debugging capabilities,
and we even added
additional simulators for some
of the extension points.
So, extensions are a very
powerful new mechanism
to customize our
operating systems,
and we think they're
going to be very,
very popular with our users.
Next, we're going to talk
about new APIs in iOS 8,
and for that I'm going
to hand over to Toby.
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Thanks, Andreas.
Good morning.
Well, as you heard this morning,
we've got a pretty big
release for you this year.
In fact, this is almost as large
as the original iPhone SDK.
Now, we took a focus, we
took a very focused approach
to this release.
The major theme this
year is integration.
Integration with the OS.
Andreas just told you how your
apps can plug into the system
and even other applications.
We're integrating across our
devices with our new Cloud
of Continuity features and we're
providing deeper integration
with the hardware and even
with the world around.
Let's start by taking
a look at two
of our more popular
applications.
Underlying each of these
is a very rich set of API.
We've introduced a new
Photos framework this year
and have greatly
enhanced the media API
with many long-standing
requests.
Combined, they form
the foundation
of a photographic platform
that brings your applications
in right alongside our own.
The new Photos framework
gives you direct access
to the user's photo library
with no need to import a copy
of anything anymore, and you
can even make changes directly
with the appropriate permission.
And with iCloud Photo Library,
you can access the user's entire
collection of photos and movies
without having to worry
about whether they're local
or stored in the Cloud.
We take care of that for you.
The new Camera API gives
you full manual control
over the camera settings, which
I think is something that many
of you have wanted for a while.
You can set the, the
lens position explicitly.
The white balance
or color temperature
and various exposure settings,
like the shutter speed and ISO.
And these are all the same APIs
that our applications are using.
A great new feature lets you
grab a burst of photographs,
each with different
exposure settings,
and with the video tool box,
you can now access the
hardware H264 encoder
and decoder directly.
[Background applause]
Yes, thank you.
Now, we announced a number
of great new initiatives
this morning, and we're going
to cover them all in
great detail this week.
I want to touch on
just a few of them now.
First, Local Authentication.
This lets you ask the user
to authenticate using touch
ID right in your application.
It's a very simple API,
and we tell you whether the
authentication succeeded or not.
At no time, though,
do you get access
to the user's biometric
information.
That's stored away securely
so that not even our own
applications can get access
to that.
Handoff lets you start a task
on one device and pick it
up seamlessly on another
Mac, phone or, or iPad.
You create an NSUserActivity
to encapsulate an activity
in your app such as
opening a web page,
and then as the context changes,
you update that activity.
And note that this contains only
the metadata for the activity
such as the document
URL or scroll position.
You need to find
an alternate means
for getting the actual data
across to the other devices.
Now, once you've created this
activity, we'll take care
of advertising it across
all of your devices.
We're going to tell
only the devices
which are actually near you,
so you don't need to worry
about your computer
at home revealing
when you're surfing
the web at work.
Health and wellness has become
extremely popular lately,
with new applications
and devices exploding
on the scene every day.
HealthKit provides a platform
where your applications
can store
and share health-related
information.
We can import some kinds
of data automatically
from standard supporting devices
such as your blood pressure
and glucose levels, and
your app can read and write
over 60 different
kinds of information,
ranging from fitness
to nutrition
to medical information.
Now, all of this is extremely
sensitive, of course,
and so we give the user
extremely fine-grained control
over who can access what.
Now, I'd like to talk
about design a little bit.
Last year, of course, well, we
completely revamped the iOS UI
and I told you at the time that
we were only just beginning.
Now, that wasn't a threat.
We've continued to add
refinements, but just not
at quite the same breakneck
pace as we have before.
Interactive notifications
let you provide the user
with custom actions right there
in the notification banner.
And as you heard this morning,
they even work on
the lock screen.
Now, because your users want
to focus on their content
and not the chrome
around it, in landscape,
we're automatically hiding
the status bar and shrinking,
or hiding, the navigation
bar and tool bars.
And we have a new compact style
for action sheets in landscape.
We're continuing to push support
for dynamic type throughout
our own applications,
and we've greatly enhanced
the API in UIKit and WebKit
to make it even easier
for you to adopt.
And finally, we have
a new settings pane,
which combines your applications
preferences with all
of the various system
privacy preferences
such as whether the user wants
to receive notifications
from your app.
We've put them together
in one place here now
and given you a simple API
so that you can take
the user right here
from within your application.
[ Applause ]
Now I read this quote on
John August's blog a couple
of months ago.
"Adding landscape to the
iPhone isn't impossible,
but it means not
doing something else,
and right now the many
'something elses' are worth a
lot more."
That really resonated with me
because we've been spending
a lot time thinking about how
to manage the proliferation
of UI layouts.
When we launched iPhone seven
years ago, it was pretty simple.
You had one screen size and
two user-interface orientations
to deal with.
A few years later, we
added iPad and now you have
to use a global user
interface idiom to select
between your iPhone
and your iPad layouts.
Then we added iPhone 5 with
its larger screen size,
and now you've got a
total of six screen bounds
to have to contend with.
And that's getting
to be rather a lot.
And so we've been working to try
and rationalize things for you.
Now, in iOS 8, you can
use a single storyboard
across iPhone 4, iPhone
5, portrait and landscape,
and here's where things get
interesting, on the iPad 2.
Now, hang on a second.
We've always encouraged
you to design explicitly
for iPad's larger screen
size and not just blow
up your iPhone UI, and
we're not backpedaling
on this message now.
Different screen sizes demand
a different user experience,
and so we've been
teaching storyboards
and our view controllers
how to adapt themselves
to the environment
that they're in.
In this example here,
it's actually the same
split-view controller class
running on both the
iPhone and the iPad.
On the phone, well
it looks and behaves
like a single-column navigation
browser, and on the iPad,
you get the split-paned
master detail view
that you're probably
pretty familiar with.
We're introducing a new notion
called size classes to try
and express this idea
of how big something is.
Broadly speaking, you can
think of the iPhone size UI
as a compact size class and the
iPad UI as a regular size class.
But don't make the
mistake of thinking
that size classes are bound
to a particular device.
They're a lot more
general than that.
For example, in this
split-view controller on iPad,
it has two child-view
controllers.
The one on the left here,
well, it kind of looks
like an iPhone UI, and in fact,
it has a compact size
class whereas the one
on the right has a
regular size class.
This idea of things adapting
themselves to the space
that they're contained in
forms the basis for something
that we're calling adaptive UI,
and this is what makes
it possible for you
to use a single storyboard
on iPhone 4,
iPhone 5, and the iPad.
Now, I'd like to ask
Max Drukman to come up
and give you a quick tour of
how easy this is to do in Xcode.
Max?
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; I missed you guys.
Especially you, Craig.
All right, I'm going to show
you how size classes in iOS 8,
if I can get the
right screen up,
allow me to create a single
storyboard that is adaptive
for both iPhone and iPad.
Here's my party finder
app, NO.SLEEP.
@DUBDUB. It's a pretty
simple little thing.
There's a login screen
on the left and a,
a list of parties on the right.
Now, the astute among you may
notice that my layout is square.
Why is that?
Well, because size
classes are, they're, wow!
Since size classes
aren't, they're not real,
one size class doesn't
necessarily map
to one device and
one orientation.
The layout canvas in,
in interface builder
is also that way.
Wow. Could've done that better.
Now, just because I'm, so,
I'm laying out my
interface this way.
I still want to see how
it looks on real devices
when it gets in peoples' hands.
For that, I have the
preview assistant.
In Xcode 6, the preview
assistant allows me
to add multiple devices
and orientations
so I can see how my interface is
working in as many devices and,
and layouts as I want.
And here you can see that I've
already specialized for one
of the size classes so that
my interface looks different
on an iPhone in landscape
orientation.
Now, if I select my
other view controller,
we can see my party table
and this I haven't
specialized at all.
That's because table
views, like many views,
are themselves adaptive,
and so there's no specialization
that's necessary at all.
Well, let's go back
to my login screen.
Now, Interface Builder starts
you out in the size class
for any width and any height.
So this is where you lay out
what is common about your app
across all size classes.
It's a great place to do edits
that you want reflected
everywhere.
For instance, if I want to
move this shiny little graphic
up into the corner,
that will get reflected
in both landscape and portrait.
But because one size
class does not fit all,
I can also tell Interface
Builder to edit
in different size classes.
In this case, I'm going
to choose compact height,
which is the size class
that maps to an iPhone
in landscape orientation.
And now, when I make an edit,
for instance moving
all these objects up,
that will only be reflected
in a landscape orientation.
Now, if I add an iPad to the
mix, we can see yet another take
at positioning and sizing
these same elements.
And once again, these
are all the same elements
with the same logic, styles,
connections still attached.
They're just positioned
and sized differently
because they have
different constraints.
So, if I were to change
the nature of something,
like the background image
here, that will get reflected
in all of the size classes.
That's a quick take at
size classes in iOS 8
and one storyboard
to rule them all.
Back to you, Toby.
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Thanks, Max.
Well, so that's just a taste of
some of the things that we have
for you in iOS 8, and we can't
wait for you to get your hands
on it and start playing with it.
Now, I'd like to
talk about iCloud.
iCloud is an important
and thriving part
of the Apple ecosystem.
We have well over 400 million
users, and we're continuing
to improve and add new
features to it all the time.
First, let's talk
about iCloud Drive.
So, we introduced documents
in the cloud a few years ago,
of course, and it provides a
seamless, in-app experience
to getting your files from
device, device, to the Mac.
And that's great, if you happen
to have the same application
running on your phone,
your iPad, and your Mac, but
that's not always the case.
iCloud Drive gives you a
folder right there in Finder,
where you can manage
your files directly.
And we're even making
this available
on Windows too, in the Explorer.
Now, if you're already
a document-based app,
it's actually pretty
easy for you
to add support for iCloud Drive.
On the Mac, well, you get it
basically for free with AppKit.
On iOS, however, you
can't access the files
in iCloud Drive directly without
some form of user intervention.
Well, that's done in this
new UIDocumentPicker class,
which lets the user select
the files that they want
to use in your application.
We then dynamically extend
your application sandbox
around those files
so that you can read
and write them directly,
without having
to make a copy of
anything anymore.
And this even works across
different application containers
so that multiple cooperating
applications can all work
together on the same files.
We told you earlier how document
providers let you extend your
device with alternate
file storage systems,
and these are all managed
by the UIDocumentPicker.
And so once you're adopting
that, there's nothing else
for you to have to do in your
application to take advantage
of these document providers.
And that's iCloud Drive.
We think it's pretty easy.
Now, I'm really excited
to be able
to tell you a bit
about CloudKit.
Simply put, CloudKit lets you
write client server applications
without having to
write the server part.
Let's say you've got a hot idea
for a coffee shop review
service or, I don't know,
a photo sharing service.
Well, here's what you don't
have to do with CloudKit.
You don't have to write any
server code, you don't have
to operate a 24-by-7
service, and you don't have
to deploy any servers.
And in fact, once you
become wildly successful,
here's something else
that you don't have to do.
All-
[ Applause ]
All you need to do to build
a client server application
with CloudKit is write your iOS
and Mac app, and we take care
of all of the rest
of it for you.
So, when we were
designing CloudKit,
we asked ourselves the question,
"What do you need in the cloud
to be able to all of this?"
Well, a database seems
like a good place to start.
We've got records and
relationships, queries,
all the things you
come to expect
from an OS-equal database.
We have an asset API
to efficiently store
and retrieve large
blobs of data.
And we have a subscription
service.
You can think of the
subscription service as kind
of like a long-running
query on the server,
and as new records are matched
by the query, iCloud will send
out push notifications
to all of the devices
that have registered an
interest in that subscription.
We've built a developer
portal so that you can go
and take a look exactly
at what's going
on with your service
in the Cloud.
And of course, you're
going to want users.
Well, it turns out, we've got
rather a lot of them in iCloud,
and every single one of those
iCloud users could be your user
as well.
There's no account to create, no
signup, or any hoops they have
to jump through, and we think
that's pretty huge for you.
[ Applause ]
As Craig told you this
morning, it's basically free
up to these maximum limits.
Now, that's one petabyte
of asset data.
To put this in perspective,
let's say that you're building
a photo sharing service
and you're using the
same image size as some
of your popular competitors.
That would let you
store 10 billion photos
in iCloud for free.
And we think that's
pretty huge too.
We're doubling down on
this technology ourselves.
iCloud Photo Library and iCloud
Drive are both built on top
of CloudKit and we see
this as the foundation
for our services moving forward.
We think this is really cool,
and we've been working on it
for a while and can't wait
to see what you do with this.
We think this is going to
open up a whole new class
of application for you.
And that's what we
have for iCloud.
Now, I'd like to turn
it over to Andreas
to tell you about OS X Yosemite.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; All right.
Let's talk about OS X.
Yosemite is a big new
release with an all-new look.
We carefully evolved this look
from our previous releases
to make it truly beautiful
without being disruptive.
The basic ideas behind
the redesign were
to increase consistency, to
reduce visual noise and clutter,
to make animations more subtle,
and increase the vibrancy
of the UI for more liveliness.
Let's go over the
cornerstones of the new look
and what they mean
to app developers.
We started by completely
redesigning our window chrome.
We made our toolbars and
our title bars simpler
and more compact.
But for non-document-based apps,
we went a whole lot further
and defined a new
style of window chrome.
Many of our apps now
use a combined toolbar
in which we merge the
title bar and the toolbar
into a single, compact row.
This is a great way to
give users more space
for their content,
but it only works well
if you have few enough toolbar
items to leave enough space
so that the user can grab
the window and drag it
around on the screen, so this
is not recommended for all apps.
Now, for several of our apps,
we also moved the search fields,
which have historically been
located at the far right side
of our toolbars, smack into
the middle of the window
if searching is the primary way
of interacting with that app,
such as is the case
in Maps and Safari.
And for sidebar apps, which have
essentially no toolbar items,
we went yet another step further
and used only partial
title bars.
These windows, they have the
normal window controls on top
of the sidebar, but
otherwise they stretch
out the content all the way
to the edges of the window.
Now, one thing that is
interesting about our new UI is
that it uses a number of
new transparent materials.
For example, if you
scrolled some window content
under the title bars, that
content will still show
through in a heavily
blurred way,
giving the user a better
sense for the entire document.
And the new translucent
sidebars still
at the desktop background
shine through,
so that really gives the user a
way to customize the entire look
and feel of the system.
Now, if you're using our
standard AppKit controls,
such as a layer with
scroll view,
your apps will automatically
inherit the right new look,
and for more custom cases,
you're exposing a number
of new APIs that will get you
the same effect that you see
in our, in our system apps.
One thing you should watch
out for is the readability
of your text.
While the new translucent
effects are very beautiful,
they are not a great fit
for primary user content,
so use these effects
selectively.
Now, we've also changed
the system font in our UI.
We changed it from Lucida
Grande to Helvetica Neue,
and that's how you
pronounce that.
[ Laughter ]
So, we hand-tweaked the
metrics of the new system font
so that they are very,
very close to the metrics
of the old Lucida Grande
font, with a result
that strings have almost the
same size and usually fit
in the space that you've
allocated in your UI so far.
Now, to help with
binary compatibility,
AppKit will actually detect,
AppKit controls will detect
if your strings are
being clipped.
And in that case,
they will ever so,
ever so slightly compress
the strings and make them fit
into the available space.
In addition to the system font,
we've also updated
our application icons
and the glyphs used
throughout the system.
We've tried to remove
unnecessary variations,
and we've standardized on three
basic shapes of app icons:
circle, square, and
tilted rectangle.
Our application icons are
now, now more uniform,
they use more vibrant colors,
and they also remove unnecessary
variations and adornments.
Our AppKit controls
now use animations
that are more meaningful,
and in general,
they support a lot
more styles for,
to support the new
appearance settings
in addition to vibrancy
settings.
Specifically for vibrancy,
they push out their
colors a lot more strongly,
which can really
help its readability
on translucent surfaces.
And another big change
that Jeff just mentioned is
that Yosemite strongly
de-emphasizes dashboard widgets
in favor of the new
Notification Center widgets.
While we still fully support
dashboard, we are now moving
over to running native widgets
inside Notification Center,
and if you're a dashboard
developer,
we suggest that you quickly
adopt the new technology,
which we believe will be even
more popular with our users.
I'd also like to take
a moment and talk
about our accessibility APIs.
Accessibility is a topic
we care about deeply,
and along with the new look,
we made it dramatically simpler
to let your applications
work with voiceover
and our other accessibility
technologies.
We took, we took some
lessons we learned on iOS
and created a new API that
requires much less coding.
So, please take some time
and add this important
capability to your apps.
It has never been easier and
it will change people's lives.
So, that was a quick tour
of the new look in Yosemite.
Once we've shipped this
release later this year,
users will expect
that your apps fit
in with the new look
of Yosemite.
So, please take some time
over the next few months
and change the style to fit
in with what we've done
in our system apps.
Next, we're going
to talk about Xcode,
and for that section
I'm going to hand
over to Matthew [inaudible].
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Thank you, Andreas.
Now, you've already had a sneak
peek into some of the features
of the new Xcode tools for
iOS 8 and OS X Yosemite.
Playgrounds.
A powerful and interactive way
to work with, and
play with, Swift.
The new integrated SpriteKit
and SceneKit design tools,
enabling you to design truly
amazing 2D and 3D applications.
And universal storyboards
with size classes.
A great way to conceptualize
and design your applications
for both iPhone and iPad.
Three great new features, and
we are just getting started.
Universal storyboards, size
classes, and autolayout combine
to enable you to design for all
devices using a single interface
document, and we're
bringing this
to another area, Launch Images.
With iOS 8, you can now provide
an Interface Builder document
and, at runtime, have
the OS generate all
of the necessary
Launch Images for you.
[ Applause ]
So now you no longer need to
provide the individual assets
and you can use the same great
design tools for your interfaces
and your launch presentations.
Now, storyboards have been a
great addition to the iOS tools
for development, and we are
extending their use even further
this year by bringing
them to you for OS X.
[ Applause ]
Storyboards work with
the new view controllers
in OS X Yosemite to
make it really easy
to design great Mac
applications.
You can design your
apps using scenes
and then connect those scenes
together very simply using the
familiar Interface
Builder gestures.
Interactive workflows, such
as popovers and sheets,
can now be designed wholly in
the Interface Builder canvas,
and containment relationships
such as tabs
and splits-those use the new
OS X view controller APIs
to make customization and
configuration really easy.
So now you can use storyboards
to design all of your interfaces
for both iOS and OS X.
We have some other great
design tool additions for you.
Asset catalogs now include
support for more asset types,
including vector art like PDF
and also supports marking images
as templates for the OS to
use as stencils at runtime.
Interface Builder
documents are now searchable,
both in the editor
and projectwide.
[ Applause ]
Now, this searching
works on both strings
and on property values like
connections and class names.
So, investigation and making
mass change is really simple.
And for iOS, we are
bringing custom fonts
into the Interface
Builder canvas.
[ Applause ]
So now these are rendered
live, and getting the layout
and precision you
want is really easy.
Now, in addition to
designing applications to work
on multiple devices, you
want your apps to ship
to as many people as
possible, and for this release,
shipping to a worldwide
audience is even easier.
For this release, we're
including support for XLIFF,
the industry-standard
format for managing
and exchanging localized data.
Xcode now includes a workflow
to automatically export
all the necessary content
for localization.
We'll run the necessary
processes on your source
and interface documents,
and in just a few clicks,
you have XLIFF to send
to your localizers,
and integrating the changes
back from them is just as easy.
Now, a benefit of this is
that you no longer need
to use strings files for
your development regions.
You can work solely in your
source and interface documents.
[ Applause ]
And if that wasn't enough,
we're going to bring
the localization content
into the Interface Builder
preview editor as well.
So, now in addition to
size classes and devices,
you can pick from any of
the localization languages
in your project and
view the results.
If you've not yet
localized, fret not.
You can use one of the
built-in pseudo localizations
to see how your interface
will respond.
So, now more than ever,
it is easy to ship
applications for everybody.
[ Applause ]
So we have a lot of great
design tools that work together
to make a really live and
interactive experience.
But there's been one
piece that's been missing,
and that's your custom controls.
Starting today, that
is no longer,
because your custom controls
are now rendered live
on the Interface Builder canvas.
[ Applause ]
I was pretty sure you
were going to like that.
So, let's go look at a
demo and see how it works.
So, here we have a photo kind
of scavenger hunt
application called Shutterbugs,
and on the main screen
we have a custom control.
It's showing the image from
one of the scavenger hunts.
It's masked to a circle and
has some adornments around it.
So, let's take a look in
Xcode 6 on how we will work
with this custom control.
Here's my project.
On the left-hand side we have
our universal storyboard,
and on the right-hand side I
have the code for my control.
It's written in Swift, and
I'm also taking advantage
of an iOS framework so
I can reuse this control
across my applications.
Now, in this case, we see our
custom control is currently
rendering as just the big
white box here on the left.
But surfacing it in the editor
as designable is really easy.
All you need to do is add
in the IB designable keyword
to my class, and the tools
will take care of the rest.
Now, my custom control
is just rendered inside
of the Interface Builder canvas.
[ Applause ]
Now, you're looking at it
going, "That doesn't look
like the picture did."
There are some values, like
the photo and the name,
that I typically
specify at runtime
on an individual instance.
We'll get to that in a moment.
There are some other properties
of my control that I would
like to allow people to
customize in Interface Builder,
and the metaphor for that
is using the inspector.
We've made that really
easy, too.
So, for any property
that I want to expose,
I can now add the IB inspectable
keyword, and I will do
that on a handful
of the properties
that I would like to expose.
Once I do that and go
back to Interface Builder
and select my control,
at the top of the
inspector are now controls
for my items, for my properties.
[ Applause ]
So, let's adjust
this a little bit.
I can make the border thicker.
I can also pick a different
color font for the bezel.
So, just like that, I've been
able to customize the control
with the limited
capability that I wanted
to expose to my developers.
Now, let's go back to the
image content I was talking
to you before.
In some cases, you really want
the closest representation
to your control as possible,
but you don't necessarily want
to set values that are going to
work for everybody at runtime.
We have a great mechanism
for you.
There's new API on our
controls called Prepare
for Interface Builder.
And this is your ability to
provide all the necessary setup
and configuration of your
control for how you want it
to look while you're designing.
Now, this is just for design.
It won't ship this way, but
it gives you all the ability
to surface your controls
in the way you want.
Now, I've been working with
my, thank you [applause].
There's still more.
I've been actually
working with my application
and localizing it, and I'd like
to see how my progress is doing.
So for that, I will
switch the assistant
over to the preview editor, and
here I will zoom in a little bit
so we can see the results.
Now, in the bottom right of the
preview editor is now a list
of all the localizations
for my project.
I can switch into any one
of them-let's pick
Spanish-and we'll see
that the interface updates.
Now, it looks like
I'm doing pretty well.
The controls at the bottom
updated, but we'll see
that the name for
the control did not.
That's an indication to me that
there's still more work for me
to do, but I didn't have to
build and run to find that out.
Let's select a, select
another language and make sure
that everything's
looking correct.
I've selected German
here, and now we'll notice
that our interface is doing
somewhat of the right thing.
I've been using autolayout
to lay out my controls,
and it's keeping the
items from overlapping,
but it's causing
one of the controls
to get clipped unnecessarily.
That's not quite
the UI I would like.
So, that's not a problem.
I can just go back over here
into the Interface
Builder canvas
and I can lower the priority
for one of those constraints.
Doing that, we'll now see
that on the right-hand side,
it lays out correctly.
So, just like that, I've been
able to design my interface
with my custom controls
and make sure it looks good
in all languages.
So, that's just a quick overview
of some of the great new tools
for Interface Builder.
[ Applause ]
Now, in addition to
great design tools,
we also have some great
new debugging tools
for you this year.
And it starts with
queue debugging.
Oftentimes when working with
blocks, it can be difficult
to keep track of where
your blocks are coming
from or going to.
Now, when you're debugging
your application and viewing
by queues, you will have not
only the executing blocks
but all of the pending
blocks available as well.
And disclosing the pending
blocks will show you the
enqueueing backtrace,
the backtrace
on where this block was
added to this queue.
[ Applause ]
And the pending backtrace is,
the backtrace is not
just for pending blocks.
As you are executing and
evaluating your own blocks,
the pending, the backtrace
is also included there too.
So, now even more of the
history is available to you.
Now, you may be wondering, as my
block moves from queue to queue
to queue, do you
keep track of it?
And the answer is yes.
If you have a very
well-traveled block,
all that information
will be available
to you during debugging.
[ Applause ]
Next up are debug gauges.
The debug gauges are a great
way to get an overview of kind
of the performance
of your application,
and for this release,
we're adding two new gauges
in the form of network
I/O and disk I/O.
These gauges give
you insight into some
of the more intensive
operations for your application,
showing read and write activity
and also giving you access
to the list of active
resources in use.
We've also updated the
debug gauges for graphics
to work great with Metal.
So, now you have all the same
debugging and profiling tools
to tune your games in Metal.
And we've also updated the
iCloud gauge and utilities
to work great with CloudKit
and with iCloud documents.
A new addition that's
really helpful is
that this iOS simulator now
supports custom configurations.
So, it's separate user
data and applications.
This allows you to simulate
having multiple users
on your machine so now testing
synchronization and sharing
with iCloud is a breeze.
[ Applause ]
Testing is a very
important and key area to us,
and we are bringing you
two great new additions
in our testing frameworks.
The first is asynchronous
testing.
XE test now includes a
flexible API to allow you
to test your longer-running
systems.
You can set up your tests
with predefined expectations,
and those expectations can be
evaluated as your test runs.
When you get to the
end of your test,
if your expectations have
been met, your test passes.
If not, your test fails.
This simple approach
makes it really easy
to test your asynchronous
systems right alongside
with your other tests.
But to go a step further,
for this release we're moving
beyond correctness testing,
and we're also adding
in performance testing.
With performance testing, you
have a simple blocks-based API
to identify areas of your
application that you would
like evaluated for performance.
Now, these blocks are
treated specially.
When the test executes,
we evaluate this
block multiple times
so we can get a sampling
of your performance.
And when the test ends,
we surface the performance
results right inside
of the editor.
Now, as part of this, you
can also establish baselines
as points of comparison
for your test,
which means that as
you improve your tests,
that'll be highlighted
in the editor as a win.
On the off chance though that
your performance regresses,
those will also be
highlighted in the editor
as areas for investigation.
Now, as part of this, you
also have access to all
of the details running
for the test.
So you have each of
the integration values,
you also have access
to the baselines,
and even the standard
deviations for your test.
So you have complete
control of your tests.
Now, as part of performance
testing, thank you.
[ Applause ]
I do agree, performance
testing is very cool.
Now, as part of this, a
part of performance testing,
you also want to
analyze your tests,
and we have by far the
coolest profiling tools
on the planet, Instruments.
So, for this release, we wanted
to bring together
testing and profiling.
So now, in the context menu
from any test or test bundle,
you can profile them
right into Instruments.
So, you can quickly look
down regressions or even look
for opportunities
for improvement.
Now, to sweeten the
deal even more,
Instruments has a
brand-new design and layout
that has been optimized for
a smoother user experience
and to make investigating
issues even easier.
In addition, in this release
we're also adding in support
for performance counters
for iOS,
which is a great new addition
to our profiling tools.
Inherently, though, when you
are writing performance tests,
you are identifying
areas of your application
where performance is
sensitive or critical.
Xcode and the compiler can
make use of this information
with a new feature called
Profile Guided Optimization,
or PGO for short.
With PGO, your performance
tests are used
to profile your application,
and that information is used
in subsequent builds
to optimize your code
for better runtime performance,
so the result is
performance testing
and performance improvement
all in one.
And that's PGO.
[ Applause ]
Now, to take advantage of many
of these new workflows
continuously during development,
we've also updated
the Xcode bots
with a new streamlined
interface,
more configuration
options, and support for all
of the new testing workflows.
The new integration reports for
bots give you even more details
about your integrations.
We separated out new
from pre-existing issues,
and we also tracked down
individual issues to committers
and individual commits.
So, you can quickly
find the guilty
or the more responsible party
for any issue that comes up.
We also have more
scheduling options and support
for custom triggers, which you
can run your own scripts before
or after any integration.
[ Applause ]
And the new testing reports give
you access to all of the details
about your tests, highlighting
regressions and improvements.
You have access to all the same
data for your performance tests
and including the
baseline workflows
for managing those
on your server.
These reports are also available
for the local testing workflows,
so you can take advantage
of them on your desktop too.
So, now even more great
reasons to use Xcode bots
in your daily integrations.
Now, we have one more
feature for you today.
And this feature really
brings together the liveness
of the design experience and
the debugging experience,
and we're calling this
feature View Debugging.
With View Debugging, you have
a live, interactive way to dive
into the details of
the user interface
of your running application, and
I'd like to give you a demo now
of the now more visual way
to debug your applications.
So, here we are,
back in our project.
Let's just simplify our
view a little bit here.
And remember, we were
running our application
over here in the simulator.
Now, if I wanted to
get more information
about this interface, I
could pause and use some
of the debugger introspection
tools,
but there's an easier way now.
In the debug bar,
there's a button here
to capture my view hierarchy,
and I will click that.
And you'll see that now
the main view is replaced
with a snapshot of
my application.
Now, this snapshot
is not a screenshot.
It's actually an encapture
of the entire view
hierarchy of my interface.
Let's change perspective a
little bit to see if that helps.
[ Applause ]