[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Thanks so much for coming
to What's New in Cocoa Touch.
It's really great to see
a packed house here today.
I know that we have a
lot of new attendees
in the house this week,
and so for those of you
who have never been to a
WWDC, who have never been
to a What's New in
Cocoa Touch talk,
this is really a great
opportunity for you
to get a taste of all of the
new things that we're releasing
in the SDK this year, and as
you know this is actually the
biggest SDK release
since the SDK itself.
So this WWDC is going
to be absolutely huge,
and this session is your
opportunity to get a taste
of those technologies, and
I'll be pointing throughout the
session and, again at
the end of the session,
to all of the other related
sessions to the technologies
that I'm talking about
so you can get an idea
of what other talks that you
want to see this week and one
of the labs you're going to want
to go to and that sort of thing.
So to begin, I want to
talk about this core idea
of what we've set up of
what iOS 8 is really all
about from the SDK perspective,
and that's this idea
of Adaptivity.
Adaptivity is going to
pervade everything that we do
in Cocoa Touch in iOS 8, and
adaptivity means several things.
On one hand, adaptivity
is a design philosophy.
It's a way of architecting
your app, and we're going
to give you an idea of how we
want apps to be built from now
on using a design philosophy
that encourages code reuse,
generic code that adapts from
context to context and is able
to go from devices like
iPhone and iPad seamlessly.
Additionally, adaptivity
encompasses a whole set
of things that we are providing
directly from UIKit to you.
Things like Adaptive
View Controllers.
Adaptive view controllers are
something that we have written
with the design philosophy of
adaptivity that when you use
in your app can allow
you to do things
like take a simple primary,
secondary view controller
pattern, have it on iPhone,
have the same code that puts
that on iPhone put on interface
that you'd expect on iPad and do
that without any device checks,
and it will all be the same
code running on both devices.
We'll show you how to do that.
Similarly we've taken the
philosophy of adaptivity
to view controller presentations
and we'll show you how
to build code that
presents something
like a full screen modal
view controller on iPhone
and something more appropriate
like a popover on iPad.
Again, without any
device-specific checks
because we're focusing
on reusable adaptive code
that is the theme of
Cocoa Touch on iOS 8.
Additionally, we're going
to be pushing a new
user interface concept
that we want all applications
to adopt and that's dynamic
or dynamic text and
adapting to dynamic text.
This was actually a feature
that was introduced in iOS 7
that users can change
their preferred text size.
In iOS 8, we've extended the
idea such that all apps built
into iOS respond to dynamic
type and are adaptive to that,
and we want to show you
how you can do that.
We recognize that one
of the common places
that users interact with
text is actually in lists
in the form of table views.
So we took it upon
ourselves to make it easier
to take a simple table like
what you would see in settings,
respond to the user's
dynamic text choice,
make the text bigger, and
make the rows bigger as well.
Finally, adaptivity
refers to the ability,
this opportunity actually
to extend the system,
to adapt the system to your
user's needs and desires
by bringing your functionality
into system apps as well
as other third-party apps.
We saw in the keynote
that we can do things
like add a photo filter
right within the Photos app
without ever having to
go to your application.
So these are the kind of things
that we're going to be talking
about throughout the talk.
The first part is particularly
about the design philosophy,
and then we'll move into
listing off a lot of the things
that are especially
new about the API.
So to begin, we'll talk
about this design
philosophy of Adaptive Layout.
So, I said it before
but I'll say it again,
the key of what we mean
by adaptive layout is
something that is reusable.
A bit of code that is generic,
that transcends device
boundaries
and orientation boundaries.
So the first thing we want to
talk about is the simple idea
of interface orientation.
This has been a stalwart
concept through the API
since the SDK was introduced,
and we actually want to move now
to a place where when
we're writing our apps,
our layout code doesn't have
to care what the interface
orientation is and that's going
to be the theme of what
we're talking about now.
So we can imagine that a
designer gave us a design
for a Photos app, and they
say, okay, this Photos app
on portrait in an
iPad looks like a grid
of rectangular thumbnail photos
and there's five
columns in that grid.
Similarly, they give us the
spec and say, if that iPad is
in landscape, show us similar,
show similar thumbnails
but seven columns of them.
Now, the naive way to
approach this would be, okay,
let's hard code in five
columns of things for portrait
and seven columns of
things for landscape.
But to become adaptive, we want
to take a deeper understanding
of why we have five
columns in portrait
and why we have seven
columns in landscape.
It's pretty easy to
understand with this example
that the reason is the portrait
view is 768 points wide,
and based on the thumbnail
size that we want to achieve,
it just so happens
that we can fit five
across so we have five columns.
Similarly when we
go to landscape,
we now have 1024 points
in the width dimension,
and based on the thumbnail
size that we wanted to achieve,
we can now fit seven columns.
The difference here is that when
we take that logic that we say,
okay, we can fit this many
columns in this space as opposed
to there are seven columns
in landscape then the actual
interface orientation is not a
relevant thing in determining
what your layout looks
like anymore.
All that matters is what
the canvas size looks like.
So there's also another decision
being made under the hood here
if we just sort of
focus in on this view,
and that's we've made
these rectangular spread
out thumbnails, but
the Photos app
on the iPhone has actually
much more compacted thumbnails
that are square in shape.
And the reason it's that way
on the iPhone is a very
similar vein reason.
It's because the size of
the iPhone is different.
And so, we compact the layout
when we are in a compacted size,
and so we can actually
think about that decision,
the compacted iPhone style
layout versus what you see
up here-the more spread
out rectangular thumbnail
layout-as also being determined
by the size and not
actually based
on a device, iPhone versus iPad.
So we're now going to begin
to think of this interface
as determined by the idea that
it has regular-sized dimensions.
The height is regular;
the width is regular.
And we're thinking of this
semantic-based sizing idea
as a new thing that
we call Size Classes.
Size classes are a
very simple enumeration
that gets us thinking
about canvas size
when we do layouts rather
than interface orientation.
We have independent horizontal
and vertical size classes,
and either one of these axis can
be either compact or regular.
And that simple choice
can allow us to choose
between what we may now think
of as an iPhone style interface
and an iPad style interface.
It really isn't about
the device.
It's about the canvas
size that we have.
And we'll continue to talk
about this idea throughout the
session, but part of what makes
that key is that you may
end up in a situation
where you are showing
something, displaying your view
on say an iPad where the size
of that canvas is actually
comparable to that of just being
on an iPhone, and if
you've written adaptive code
that simply uses the size
rather than the device
to do its layout, you'll
get an iPhone style layout
when appropriate in
smaller spaces on an iPad.
So, the situations that
we can end up in are
on the iPad having regular
height and regular width.
This is true in either
orientation.
On the iPhone, the width becomes
compacted and using that bit
of information, the Photos
app can choose to shrink
to its more compacted square
thumbnail-based layout.
Similarly, when the
iPhone goes to landscape,
it still has a compact width but
also takes on a compact height.
So you can use both of
those pieces of information
to decide what happens in
your layout in your app.
So, we've wrapped up this
concept of size classes
and are exposing it
to you via a new class
in UIKit called UI
Trait Collection.
UI trait collection is a
handy bringing together
of a few pieces of
information including the
horizontalSizeClass,
the verticalSizeClass,
the displayScale, and
the userInterfaceIdiom.
Now what makes trait collections
convenient is they're hung right
as a property on
UIViewController.
So you can access them
from your view controller.
You can also get them from the
current screen, and then using
that information, you
have your size class.
You can make the determination
of what is the right
thing to do for you.
So as a simple example, we can
think of what we did with Photos
and implement a size
class did change method.
And for Photos, it just needs
to consider what the
new size class is,
and based on whether the
horizontalSizeClass is compact
or not, the Photos
layout chooses
to use either its compact
squares-based layout,
if it is a compact
horizontalSizeClass,
or otherwise it uses its
rectangular thumbnail,
more spread out layout.
And then this particular
snippet is modeled to be
on a collection view
controller, so it just takes
that layout object and applies
it to its collection view
as a new layout object.
Now, some of you may be
noticing this unfamiliar scribe
to you on the screen.
If this is your first time
seeing Swift, congratulations.
Here is your intro, and you
can see just how easy it is
to understand.
And this will give you
an idea of how easy it is
to start adopting
Swift immediately
with all Cocoa and
Cocoa Touch APIs.
So with that, I'll talk
about quickly another new API
that we've added to
support your layout
in iOS 8, which is Margins.
So margins coincide with
an API release in iOS 7,
which is layout guides.
Layout guides help you know
about hard lines on the screen.
In this case, the top and
the bottom of the screen,
where the top is denoting
there's a navigation bar there.
So the layout guide tells
you about that navigation bar
in case you'd like to avoid it.
If there was a toolbar at
the bottom of the screen,
your layout guide would also
denote the top of that toolbar.
In this case, it just
denotes the hard line
that is the bottom
of the screen.
But there's another concept
in this UI that isn't covered
by layout guides and that is
the whitespace that is inset
in the content from the
edges of the screen.
So, in iOS 8, we're
introducing an API on UIView,
which is layout guides which
tells you about that whitespace
and allows you to set
whatever whitespace you want
for your layout.
So that's a property on UIView.
It also comes with native
support for autolayout,
and that's in the form of
new NS layout attributes,
including left, right,
leading, trailing, et cetera.
There's a bunch of these.
If you've been using
autolayout in your code,
you'll find this
natural and familiar.
So, to learn more tricks about
building adaptive layout apps,
there's going to be
a great talk tomorrow
in the Mission called Building
Adaptive Apps with UIKit.
So now I'm going to be moving
on to talking about some
of the ways that we have
adopted the philosophy
of adaptive size class-based
design to build things
that you can use out of
the box that are adaptive
without you having
to do any work.
So we'll start by talking about
Adaptive View Controllers.
This is a great new feature.
And to begin to dive into this,
I'm actually going to go back
and talk a little bit more about
this idea of orientation which,
or rotation, which we touched
on with the orientation
segment of the talk.
So, now I'm going
to have us kind
of ask ourselves this question,
what is rotation, really?
Because asking ourselves
that question yields a result
that helps us write
adaptive code.
And that result is, it's
just an animated change
of the size of the view.
So, if we consider a
view that's onscreen,
we might have been thinking
of when the device rotates,
that view rotates with it
and this is a rotating view.
That perspective actually
complicates the idea
of what we have to
do in our layout.
And so, beginning in iOS
8 we're encouraging you
to take a different perspective
towards how rotation works,
which is just think of it as
a view that happens to have,
in this case, a regular
height and a compact width,
and when the device rotates,
something happens to that view.
And the thing that happens
to that view is it undergoes
an animated size change,
and perhaps it goes to a compact
height and a regular width.
I don't want to confuse you
in that standard on an iPhone
in landscape, the width
is actually compact,
but this is an illustrative
example
of what might happen
to your view.
As your view changes size,
it can go to any new size
and any new size class,
and that's really
all that's happening
when you're undergoing
a rotation.
And part of the advantage
of thinking
about rotations this way
is merely as size change is
that once you handle
rotations as size changes,
any other situation
that you might end up in
where your size changes,
you will have handled
because you will have
written your code in a way
that it can handle size
changes especially those
that are animated.
So in order to move in this new
direction, we're taking a lot
of API that used to exist in
iOS 7 while it still exists
in iOS 8, but we're
deprecating it.
This is just a subset
of the rotation API
that is deprecated in iOS 8.
[ Applause ]
And what I really like is what
we're replacing this with.
Thinking about things
as size changes,
you can just implement
one method.
We'll transition to size.
And since that takes a
transition coordinator,
if there's interesting things
you want to do-if you want
to animate along with that size
change whether it be rotation
or anything else
that changes the size
of your view controller-you can
use that transition coordinator
to do an animation, and
you just send in a block
with that transition coordinator
and those changes
will be animated along
with the size change,
which may be a rotation
of your view controller.
So in this case, I've
used the size change
to simply change the
number of columns
in my photo layout
based on the new size.
So beyond just view controllers
themselves with rotation,
we've built some view
controllers that allow you
to adapt to the hierarchy
from device to device in a way
that makes it so that
you write less code.
And so, many of you have
probably written something
like you see on the
screen, a primary,
secondary view controller
pattern
and you do this using a
split view controller,
and then you embed a
navigation controller
as the master view controller
of that split view controller.
And then when you would go and
take this same design pattern
of a primary, secondary view
controller, you would end
up on the iPhone with
a navigation controller
as your view controller,
and that meant you would have
a device idiom check saying,
am I on an iPad?
If so, build this view
controller hierarchy.
If not, build this other
view controller hierarchy
with a navigation
controller as an iPhone.
While on iPad just
as we want to make it
so that you no longer need
to care what your interface
orientation is, we also want
to make it so that
you no longer need
to care what your
interface idiom is.
And to do that we're making it
so that you can build this
interface on an iPhone
with the split view controller
as the root view controller.
And it will still contain
a navigation controller
as its master view controller.
Then when you want to, you
know, push another view
onto the stack, you can just
call show view controller
on this.
It will do exactly
what you would expect
from a navigation experience,
pushing a view onto the stack,
and when you would
execute something
that would be the equivalent
of showing a detail on iPad,
you can just call show
detail view controller.
And on the phone, it will do
exactly what you would expect a
phone interface to
do, which is push it
onto the navigation controller
because that's all that's
available on the phone.
But that same set of APIs,
that same call sequence
calling show view controller
and show detailed view
controller on iPad,
will yield what the user
would expect on iPad,
which is a detailed
view controller
over on the right
of the split view.
So, UISplitViewController
is really a workhorse
to be used in iOS 8.
The key to it is that it's
now available on all devices,
allowing you to build view
controller hierarchies
that don't depend on
what device you're on.
It's the same hierarchy
on iPad and iPhone,
and split view controller
will adapt for you.
So with that it handles
the primary,
secondary controller pattern
transparently for you,
and also to go along with this,
split view controller has
a whole host of new updates
to its API and its release.
I can't even begin to
talk about what they are.
If you'd like to
learn more about them,
there will be a great talk
tomorrow morning called View
Controller Advancements
in iOS 8.
So, moving on to
Adaptive Presentations.
This is another way that the
view controller system is
helping you have code that
is simple and device agnostic
but that does the right
thing on each device.
We want to help you
build something
like a full screen modal
presentation on iPhone
and get something more
appropriate like a form sheet
on iPad or even a popover,
and do this without code
that checks what
device you're on.
It'll be the same
code on every device.
So in particular, one thing
that is really changing
its paradigm is popovers.
Prior to iOS 8 popovers
were only available on iPad,
and we would use them in the
form of UI popover controller.
Well, that paradigm is
changing significantly
because we're now no
longer requiring the use
of UI popover controller
to present a popover.
Instead, popovers are
presented via the API
as a presentation style
for view controller.
[ Applause ]
So that means if you present
a popover or a view controller
with a popover presentation
style
and the presenting view
controller horizontalSizeClass
is regular, it would just appear
as you expect a popover
to appear.
With that same code using a
popover presentation style,
if the presenting view
controller is compact
in the horizontal dimension
like you would see on an iPhone,
it would just appear
as an oversheet
so that you get what you
would expect on iPhone.
So we're taking this,
these concepts,
and we're bringing adaptivity
to some other view controllers
that we ran like search results,
which you may be thinking, well,
that's not a view controller.
Well, we're fixing that because
UISearchDisplayController is
replaced by UISearchController,
and UISearchController is
crucially a view controller
subclass, and that means that
it can take advantage of all
of the power of adaptive
hierarchies and presentations
that we've just talked about.
That's all at your fingertips
with the new UISearchController.
This new UISearchController is
also able to be fully customized
in the way that its UI
appears and how it's presented
so that you can adapt
the search controller
into your application even if
you have a fully customized UI
like that in FaceTime,
it will look the way
that you want it to look.
We're doing something
similar with alerts in iOS 8,
and we're taking UIAlertView and
UIActionSheet and replacing them
with UIAlertController.
[ Applause ]
I kind of thought you
guys might like that one.
UIAlertController is also
a UIViewController subclass
so that we can internally
use all of the power
of adaptive presentations to our
advantage and to your advantage
so that things look great.
Of course, UIAlertController
adapts its styling
to the context so that when
you present it on an iPhone
or on anything that has a
compact horizontalSizeClass,
you get an action
sheet appearance.
You can get an alert
appearance also
but in the action sheet style,
you get something that looks
like what you expect an
action sheet to look like,
and the same code that presents
that action sheet on an iPhone,
in a regular horizontalSizeClass
like an iPad will appear
in a popover without you having
to write any device-checking
code.
So you can learn
more about how all
of this adaptive presentation
machinery works by checking
out A Look Inside
View Controllers,
Thursday morning in the Mission.
I've seen this talk
a couple of times.
It's really great if you want
to understand the nitty-gritty
behind how all these
presentation controllers
work, and especially
if you're thinking, hey,
this built-in UIKit
stuff is fantastic.
I want to build my own
presentation controllers
that are also adaptive.
This talk will teach
you how to do that.
So, what we've been talking
about for a while is tools
that we're giving you via the
API to write adaptive code,
but there's another step
to writing great code
and that's Testing.
So we're giving you another
great tool that we're excited
about in the iOS simulator
and that is the ability
to resize the physical
simulated hardware.
And, so I don't know if you
can see it on the screen.
It's a little small, but
you'll find in your SDK
if you haven't found it yet, and
you launch the iOS simulator,
there are two new devices
that you can select.
One is a resizable iPad and
one is a resizable iPhone.
You can use these to actually
punch in custom values
for the hardware size of
the iPad or the iPhone
and test the adaptivity
of your code on the fly.
[ Applause ]
We're really excited for how
this kind of thing can make,
can change the way
we architect apps
because we can architect
things the way that we intend
and then test that our
intentions are doing what we
thought that they
were going to do.
So I actually stole this
app you see on-screen
from the A Look Inside
Presentation Controllers talk
that I just mentioned,
and it has a custom presentation
controller, which is the view
that slides out from the right
and it's designed to take
to take up a third
of the screen.
I went and tested it in the
resizable iPad to make sure
that if it was in
a compact width,
it would do the right
thing, and sure enough,
the guys who wrote
this are really great
and it does do the right thing.
It presents as an
OverFullScreen presentation
in the compact width.
So, let's talk about some of the
new things in iOS 8 for UIKit
for customizing user interface.
Of a new class called
UIVisualEffectView,
the UIView is subclass,
and it's a view
that takes UIVisualEffectObject
that parameterizes
custom rendering modes
for the view itself and
the content inside it.
So we're shipping a
couple of different effects
that you can use with the visual
effect view to get the effect
that you want, and the first
one is the UIBlurEffect.
[ Applause ]
Believe me I've been
waiting for you guys to get
to be able to use this too.
So UIBlurEffect will
give you a live blur
over the content
where you use it.
The second effect
that we're shipping is
the UIVibrancyEffect.
Now, a vibrancy effect if
you don't know what that is,
that refers to the separators
in Notification Center.
It may be a little bit
hard to see on this screen,
but you can pull out your phone,
pull down Notification Center.
Take a look at those
beautiful color-changing,
color-dodging separators,
and that's vibrancy.
Another thing-I heard a clap
over there, thanks [laughter].
Another thing that we're
introducing is Image Assets.
Image assets are something that
encapsulate the 1X, the 2X,
the iPhone, the iPad
representations of your image
in the home matrix thereof,
and it comes with some API
that makes it really easy
to get the right images
out of the image catalog
because we can use something
like image named and
add a parameter to it
that takes TraitCollection.
And since TraitCollections
are hung right
on your view controllers, you
can take that TraitCollection
from self and viewDidAppear or
something and apply it directly
to an image view in
your view controller,
and you'll have the right image.
The if statement that is implied
in figuring out 1X, 2X, iPhone,
iPad, et cetera, is all encoded
within the TraitCollection,
which you don't have
to do any work for.
It comes directly with
your view controller.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
Another UI feature
is Condensing Bars.
You may be familiar with this
if you've used Safari on iOS 7,
and it has a similar concept.
When the user scrolls, the
search bars [inaudible] shrink.
Well, we've extended that
concept throughout the iOS 8 SDK
and given you access to that
sort of behavior in your app.
So if you have a navigation
bar, you can make it so that
when a user scrolls the
navigation bar gets a little bit
smaller, or if you have a
view that has a navigation bar
and a toolbar, you can make it
so that when a user scrolls,
the navigation bar shrinks
and the toolbar disappears
all together.
[ Applause ]
So to learn all about some
great things you can do
with interface customizations,
we have a talk
that is tomorrow called Creating
Custom iOS User Interfaces.
So, I alluded earlier
to a feature that is,
that we're pushing in iOS 8,
which is dynamic
type everywhere.
All of Apple's apps have adapted
or have adopted dynamic type
and are adapting to the changes
that are required for that.
One of the things
that we realize is
that table views are
a very common place
where text is displayed and
something that we would want
to respond to user
text size changes.
And so we have made it easier
in iOS 8 for you to respond
to these types of
changes by allowing you
to have dynamic type rows
without actually
implementing the delegate method
tableView:heightForRow
AtIndexPath:.
[ Applause ]
I know that a lot of you
have been asking for this
over the years, and
so now our solution
to that is cells can
encapsulate their size
and logic inside themselves.
[ Applause ]
It gets better, actually,
because the cells natively
support autolayout.
So, yeah, it does
get better, right?
And so if you have
constraints in your cells,
UIKit can derive the appropriate
height for those cells
from the content in
them and the constraints
that you place on them.
You can do something like this
where I'm not implementing
the delegate
method heightForRowAtIndexPath.
Instead in my cells initializer,
I set some constraints.
In this particular
cell, I have a text view
that will hold some content.
I set a vertical constraint
that just adds some padding
around that text view using
the visual format language.
I do the same thing on the
horizontal axis, adding padding
on the right and left
of that text view,
and then when this
cell is created,
it will be populated
with some text.
The table view will
know how wide it is.
We'll be able to take the
content that's in that text view
and the margins that I've
set up with autolayout
and determine what
the appropriate height
for that cell should be
based on that content
and the width of the table.
If you really like to learn
more about that or if you just
like to hear me talk, come
back to this same room two days
from now where I'll
be presenting along
with my very esteemed colleague,
the beloved Dr. Olivia
Gunish [phonetic],
and we'll be telling
you all about what's new
in table and collection views.
So moving on to my favorite
feature of iOS 8 SDK.
It was actually kind of
hard to wait until this part
of the presentation,
but App Extensions.
App extensions are
just fantastic.
[ Applause ]
You've seen this in the keynote,
but app extensions are just
going to change the way
that we write apps and the way
that users enjoy what
we produce for them.
We can do things like in
Photos, taking a photo,
bringing up a sheet that shows
the extensions that we have,
selecting your extension
right there in Photos,
applying something like
a filter to that photo,
and ending up in Photos
where we always were.
We never had to leave the app.
And your content is right there
for the user at their
fingertips.
We can also have sharing
extensions, which allow users
to share to your
sharing service right
from whatever app they're in.
They can share photos,
videos, text, and other content
without having to do a
do-si-do over to your app.
This will be a better
experience for the user,
and it means more people
can share to your app
because it will be less
work for them to do so.
We also have Notification
Center widgets.
You can write a fantastic
Notification Center widget
that can end up on my phone
and I can see it every day,
and I can be extremely grateful
for you, to you for doing that.
So app extensions
open a lot of doors.
Some of the big things in iOS 8
that you can use app extensions
for, of course, Photos,
sharing, Notification Center.
It's also possible
to build extensions
that don't actually have a user
interface, and a great example
of this is the Bing
Translate action without UI
that we saw in the keynote.
Additionally, you can build
custom file providers.
This is something that will
allow the user to use documents
from your cloud storage
solution as seamlessly
as if those documents
were on iCloud drive,
just by your extension providing
them to apps within the system.
Additionally, iOS
8 makes it possible
to write custom keyboards
that will be shared
throughout the system.
[ Applause ]
The front row likes that.
Yeah. To learn more about
building app extensions,
we have two great talks today
and tomorrow that will explain
to you everything
you need to know
about building upon this just
absolutely tremendous technology
that is just going
to-iOS 8 is the sign post.
It's different from here on out.
So some updates to
notifications.
Notifications have changed a
bit in particular in the way
that we model how users approve
of notifications
that appear onscreen.
It's always been
true that users have
to approve push notifications,
and it wasn't true previously
that users would have to
approve local notifications.
You could show a
local notification
without the user
giving approval to that.
So in iOS 8, any
notification that shows UI
on the screen is going
to require one-time
approval from the user.
The flip side to that is you
can send push notifications
that don't show UI to the
user, that simply shuttle data
to your app, and those
will not, by default,
require user approval.
So you can just send
notifications to your app,
and the user doesn't have to,
doesn't have to worry about it.
[ Applause ]
Notifications can now also have
actions associated with them.
That is, if you want
to display something
that has a reply button or other
actions, those can be tacked
on to your notifications,
and whatever action the user
selects, that will be shuttled
over to your app for
your custom logic
to be invoked based
on that action.
Notifications can also be
location based in iOS 8,
so you can pop up a notification
when the user enters
or exits a significant
area that you want
to show them a notification
about.
[ Applause ]
Finally, we've increased
the payload push size
from 256 bytes to 1K.
[ Applause ]
Four times the love
for everyone.
If you want to learn more about
this, there's a great talk,
What's New in iOS Notifications,
tomorrow afternoon in Nob Hill.
So we're introducing
a doc picker in iOS 8.
And it looks beautiful-looks
like that.
It's, of course, available
on iPad and iPhone,
and what's great about this
is we now have system UI
for selecting documents.
You no longer have to write
completely custom code starting
from scratch to give a user a
document picking experience.
If you want to be able to
interact with documents
in your application,
you can use the
UIDocumentPickerViewController
[inaudible] and, of course,
since it's a view controller
it gets to take advantage
of all the adaptive presentation
and hierarchy machinery
that we talked about earlier.
This document picker has access
to documents in the local scope,
and seamlessly also in
the iCloud drive scope,
and finally anybody
who is supplying a
document provider extension
to the system, those
documents will also appear
in the document picker.
It's all similarly completely
seamless and easy for the user
and your application just gets
a URL back for the document
that it needs to open.
To learn more about
document picker support,
we've got a great talk on
Building a Document-based App
in the Marina on Thursday.
A quick word about
SDK Modernization.
We made a few changes throughout
the headers in the Cocoa
and Cocoa Touch APIs, and I just
want to give you a quick rundown
of what that's all about.
We've annotated all the
designated initializers of class
with an
NS-DESIGNATED-INITIALIZER
annotation so you know
which ones are the designated
initializers, which, of course,
you need to know if you're going
to be a good subclassing
citizen.
Additionally, all
of the return types
for initializers have changed
from id to instancetype.
[ Applause ]
That will make some of
our autocomplete better.
And we've introduced
additional properties in place
of classic Cocoa
methods, in particular
like the NS object protocol
where hash used to be a method.
Hash is now a property
for NS object.
And these changes enhance
the experience for use
with the Cocoa and Cocoa Touch
APIs, both in Objective C and,
in particularly, with Swift.
So, Handoff is an opportunity
for your app to participate
in a feature that we talked
about in the keynote,
which is continuity.
Continuity is the thing that
allows users to do something
like start an email on their
phone, go to their computer,
finish that email, and it's
all seamless experience.
Well, with handoff, we're
giving you the opportunity
to have user activities of
your own so that they can do
that not just with mail or
with other built-in activities,
but with your activities
as well.
So handoff has a built-in
support for activities in AppKit
and UIKit, both natively
support activities
in their document
classes, and you'll be able
to use that out of the box.
To learn more about handoff,
check out the Adopting Handoff
in iOS talk tomorrow
in the Mission.
So, there's a whole lot of
stuff that has changed here.
Lots of new things.
We also have several
brand-new frameworks in iOS 8,
and I don't really have time
to talk in any kind of depth
about these things, but I
want to give you an idea,
a taste of what is out there so
you can see what other sessions
that you'd like to attend
because these frameworks
allow you to build apps
that you simply could
not build before iOS 8.
And that's fantastic.
So, of course, first is one
that we've already touched on.
Notification Center will
support you building extensions
that add widgets to the
Notification Center on iOS.
So that's
notificationcenter.framework,
and you can learn
about that by checking
out the Building
App Extensions talk.
We also have a brand-new
Photos framework.
This will give you
complete read/write access
to the photos library.
This means you can do whatever
your application needs to do
to provide the best user
experience possible.
It can delete photos.
It can do non-destructive edits.
It can do whatever
it needs to do
so that the user
gets what they need.
While this isn't actually
in the Photos talk
or in the Photos framework, I
do want to take this opportunity
to point out that iOS 8 also
brings custom Core Image
filters, and so you'll be able
to use these on your photos
as well as videos in iOS 8.
[ Applause ]
With brand-new framework
called CloudKit,
and this framework is
absolutely spectacular.
I really can't say enough
good things about it.
It gives you more control than
you ever had over the data
that you put in the cloud.
And what really makes this
spectacular is you can use
CloudKit to build a
client server application
without building
the server side.
You can define that
on the client side
and let Apple take
care of it for you.
So, you know, I can't even wait
to see what startups
come out of this.
This will be fantastic, and
we love CloudKit so much
that we built iCloud
Drive and Photos
in the cloud on top of it.
It's a fantastic technology,
and you'll love building
your apps on top of it.
Another new framework
is HealthKit.
HealthKit brings all of
the biometric information
from the various devices
that your user has
all into one place.
So this information is shared
across apps rather than siloed
into one app that has one
biometric device information
and another app that has another
biometric device information.
It's all shared.
So you can use that to
create a perfect experience
for your user based on
all of the biometric data
that is available from
all of their accessories.
Similarly, we are
introducing a HomeKit,
which does the same thing
for connected home devices.
It puts all of that
information in one place
so that you can build an
app that does everything
that a user needs for their
connected home, accessing all
of those things in one place.
We also have a new local
authentication framework.
This allows you to
leverage the power
of biometric authentication
in your own app.
And as you probably know from
having watched the keynote,
this means that you get
to use Touch ID right
inside your application.
That's great and we have a
talk that you can go check
out to learn more
about how to do that.
We're also bringing
SceneKit to iOS 8.
SceneKit is a great framework
for building 3D renderings,
and we've had it on
the Mac for a year.
We're now bringing it to iOS.
Now we have a great
cross-platform solution
for doing 3D rendering.
Those of you who have already
used SceneKit, you're going
to love this; those
of you who haven't,
you're also going to love it.
Everybody is going to love it.
So that's all the
brand new frameworks.
That's not all the
changes though.
I'll point out one
other framework
that has made some significant
changes, which is Core Location.
Core location now
makes it possible
to get the user's
location details indoors,
and by that I mean, you can
get what floor the user is on,
not just where they are.
[ Applause ]
Isn't it great to build apps
that you just have
never built before?
I'm excited.
We also have new APIs
and core location
that will make it
easier to save power
when getting significant
location updates.
So that'll be better
for everyone.
I'm a big power magnet myself,
so using these will enhance
everyone's experience.
We're also changing
the user approval model
around core location so
that users can now choose
to approve your app either
all the time for location use,
or only give it,
you can just request
to be approved only
when you're in use.
So the user can rest assured
that your app is
not using location
and not draining the battery,
not stealing any secrets
when your app is not in use.
So that's a change
to core location.
So, to finish up here I
want to reiterate some ideas
about the design philosophy
because, really, iOS 8 is a mark
in the sand for how we think
about building apps in addition
to all of its new API.
So, we're going to be centered
around building reusable code
that is device agnostic, that is
interface orientation agnostic,
that is adaptive, so we can use
the tools that are presented
in iOS 8 to simplify our
layout by using things
like size classes so
we're not worrying
about what the specific
size of things are.
We use a size class to make
a determination whether it's
compact or regular, and
we can test those things
out using the resizable
simulator.
We can use the iPhone and
iPad code in a unified way
so that we only have one bit of
code that does the right thing
on all devices, and we're
bringing adaptive view
controller technology to you
that will allow you to do that.
You can integrate into the
system now using app extensions
so that the user can do
more things in more places
than ever before, and your
app can be more useful
for them than it's ever done.