&gt;&gt; Olivier Bonnet: My
name is Olivier Bonnet.
I'm the Interim Manager for the
CloudKit on the client side.
So up until today, Apple had
many iCloud technologies,
and they looked like
this to you.
We had iCloud Drive, iCloud
CoreData, iCloud Photo Library.
And how they interacted with
the Apple iCloud server was kind
of a mystery.
So today we're lifting
some of the mystery
in introducing CloudKit.
So let's look at
what we're going
to cover here in this session.
So first, we're going to
start with "What is CloudKit?"
We're going to walk you through
the couple of steps you need
to enable CloudKit in your
application and start using it;
we're going to do a walkthrough
of the different APIs;
we're going to talk about
how CloudKit interacts
with the Apple, the iCloud
user accounts; and last
but not least, we'll cover
when to use CloudKit,
as opposed to other existing
iCloud APIs we already have
on the platforms.
So let's start.
What is CloudKit?
You'll notice the new badge,
but the whole session is new.
So it's here only on that slide.
CloudKit is a way to give
you access to iCloud servers,
and we really mean it.
CloudKit is the foundation
for both iCloud Drive
and iCloud Photo Library.
Both features were written from
scratch on top of CloudKit.
CloudKit is supported
on both OS X and iOS.
It's a new public
framework- CloudKit.framework.
Check it out in the SDK.
CloudKit uses the iCloud
account's infrastructure.
That means that if there's
a logged-in iCloud account
on the device, we'll use
that to identify the user;
if there's not, we'll provide
read-only anonymous access.
CloudKit supports both a concept
of public and private databases.
You can see public
databases as a soup
of data-that's all your
user can access to;
private databases are meant
to store the actual data just
on behalf of a specific user.
CloudKits support both
structured and bulk data.
You can use it to store large
files on the iCloud servers,
and we'll take care of the
transmitting them efficiently up
and from the iCloud servers.
Importantly, CloudKit is
a transport technology.
It doesn't provide
any local persistence.
It enables you to send and
receive data from the servers.
So let's start.
How do you enable CloudKit
in your application?
So first, you'll want
to navigate your application's
Capabilities pane in Xcode.
See that big iCloud off switch?
You want to turn it on.
And you want to check the
CloudKit checkbox here.
At that point, you're ready.
There's no fourth step.
Your app is ready to
read and write data
to Apple's iCloud server.
And to walk you through
the API on how to do this,
I'm going to hand over
to Paul to chat about it.
&gt;&gt; All right.
Thank you, Olivier.
[ Applause ]
So, as Olivier said,
my name is Paul.
I work on the CloudKit
client framework.
And I'm very excited to talk to
you guys today about CloudKit.
And we're going to start off.
We're going to start talking
about the Fundamental
CloudKit Objects.
These are going to
be the set of objects
that you're initially
exposed to when you open up
and start playing with
the CloudKit framework.
Just running through
a quick list of them,
we're going to talk about
containers; and we're going
to talk about databases; we're
going to talk about records;
we're going to talk about record
zones and record identifiers;
we're going to talk
about references;
and we're going to
talk about assets.
It's quite a list.
This is going to be a really fun
and really jam-packed session.
So let's get started.
And we're going to
talk about containers.
This is sort of the
idealized model
of your application
talking to iCloud.
Now, you guys are
application developers,
you guys are client developers.
And you know that your
application running on a client,
whether that client is an iPhone
or whether it be a MacBook,
yours is not the only process
running on that client;
rather, yours is one of many.
Now, on your client, your
process is going to be siloed,
sandboxed in some ways.
In some cases, it's
a literal sandbox.
Certainly in others,
you're running
in your own memory space.
This concept of taking
your client
and actually running
it separated
from other clients is pretty
powerful and has got a couple
of advantages: It
helps with security,
it helps with stability,
and it helps with privacy.
So as we were figuring out how
we wanted to build CloudKit,
we thought to ourselves,
"How can we take
these three advantages
and replicate them
up in the server?"
And so here's what we did.
Just as your client is
one of many-I'm sorry,
your application is one of
many-running on the client, so,
too, the part of iCloud
that you're talking
to is one of many up on iCloud.
We call these different
silos "containers."
So containers.
Containers are exposed
in the CloudKit framework
as the CKContainerClass.
CK is our prefix; you're going
to see this all over the place.
By default, one application
talks to one container.
Containers afford us the
ability to segregate data.
That means that your application
can read and write data
to iCloud, another application
to iCloud, and the two datasets
up on the server will
not be intermingled.
In addition to data segregation,
this containerization
of iCloud storage allows us to
encapsulate user information.
Now, as Olivier mentioned,
CloudKit involves using the
iCloud account infrastructure.
And we want to give
you some limited access
to that iCloud account,
and we want to make sure
that we're doing so in a
privacy-conscientious manner.
So in order to do that, we
encapsulate user information.
User information available
to your application is going
to be container-scoped
and therefore different
than the view of
user information seen
by another application.
Containers are managed
by you, the developer.
You're going to be managing
them via the WWDR portal.
It's important to note
that the namespace
of containers is global
to all developers.
So when you're choosing a
name for your container,
make sure that you're
using a reverse DNS name.
Now, right up there, just
like a little while ago,
I said that by default
there is one container
to one application,
a one-to-one mapping.
We think that this is
going to be successful
for 99 percent of use cases.
And certainly as you go
start using CloudKit,
it's going to be great as you
start exploring the framework.
But we recognized that
there are some scenarios
where you need a
more complex mapping.
So we support a many-to-many
model.
What we mean is that multiple
applications can coordinate
on the same iCloud container.
Also, a single application
can talk
to multiple iCloud containers.
On to databases.
One of the chief purposes
of CloudKit is the ability
to take your object model in
your application and replicate
that up to the server.
And so when we started
thinking about how we want
to present this modeling to
you, we thought to ourselves,
"How can we divide up
application objects?"
Obviously, all objects
in my application are
not treated equally.
And one of the first
things that we noticed was
that there's a fundamental
difference
in the audience of data.
Some data is intended to be used
by the user that created it.
If you imagine an application
where I'm writing up notes
and I want to see my notes
everywhere else, that's my data.
I create it, I consume it.
On the other hand, there's use
for what we call "public data."
This is data that can be
A, created by the user
for the benefit of a
community-think, perhaps,
a review on a restaurant-or it
could be information that you,
the developer, has
uploaded to iCloud
because it's useful
to your application.
In either case, the audience
is not just a single user
but a community of people.
So how did we solve the fact
that we've got these
different types of data?
Let's break open a container
and have a look inside.
Inside of a container
you're going to notice first
and foremost the
public database.
This is the soup.
This is where all of the public
and communal data
co-lives, comingles.
Additionally, you're
going to notice
that there's private databases.
And you're going to find
that there is an
individual private database
for each user of
your application.
Now, this is sort of
the 50,000-foot overview
of what the iCloud
infrastructure looks like.
But, you know, how much do
you guys care about that?
What you guys are
interested in is,
"What does this infrastructure
look like to me, the client,
running on a phone
or running on a Mac?"
Obviously, you're only
going to have access
to the currently
logged-in iCloud user.
So rather than seeing
a public database
and a gajillion private
databases, your view is going
to look a little
bit more like this.
You're going to have a choice
between the public database
or the private database
that is correlated
to the currently
logged-in iCloud user.
So databases.
Databases are exposed in our
API as a CKDatabase class.
Every application
has access to two
of them-the public
and the private.
Let's have a look at
a little bit of code.
The container is the initial
entry point into CloudKit.
Here we see that I'm talking
to my default container
and getting its public database.
I can also talk to
the default container
and get its private database.
Let's have a look
at the differences
between these two databases.
As we mentioned, the
desired audience is going
to be different between
the public database
and the private database.
The public DB is for shared
data; the private DB is
for the user's own data.
As such, we have different
requirements for whether
or not an iCloud account
needs to exist on the client.
In the private database-since
I'm reading
and writing a user's data-if
we have no notion of the user,
that is, if we don't have
a logged-in iCloud account,
there's really no utility
in moving this information
to and from the server.
So we require an iCloud
account to be logged
in if you want use
the private database.
In the public database, since
the audience is more communal,
we allow you read-only anonymous
access to the public database.
You'll recall from
yesterday's talk
that CloudKit is
free with limits.
So we've got some
pretty aggressive quotas.
That being said, we
still need to account
for where data's being used
so that we can talk to you
when we start approaching
those limits.
Data stored in the public
database is accounted
for on the developer's quota;
data stored in the private
database is accounted
for on the user's quota.
By default, data written
into the public database is
world-readable; data written
into the private
database is user-readable.
Again, it's the user's own data,
so they're really the only ones
that have access to it
in the private database.
We recognize that world-readable
is not an appropriate permission
for a lot of data in
the public database,
so we give you the ability
to edit these permissions
on a record-class level.
The mechanism by which you edit
these permissions is something
that we call the
iCloud Dashboard Roles.
iCloud Dashboard is the
administrative interface
into CloudKit.
I invite you guys to
come back on Thursday
for the advanced talk.
We're going to go into a lot
of detail about the Dashboard.
Suffice it to say, there's
an ability to set ACLs
so that a user is
a member of a role,
and a role can have
certain enlarged access
to a class of records.
In the private database
things start out lockdown.
There's no need to edit them.
The user is the only
one to create data,
and the user is the only one
to be able to read that data.
And when I say that the user is
the only one to be able to read
that data, I really mean it.
You as the developer
do not have access
into somebody else's
private database.
Their data is their own.
All right.
So those are databases.
Let's talk about records.
So here's our model
that we have so far.
We've got a container.
Within containers are databases.
Let's keep going down the rabbit
hole and crack open a database.
Inside the database we see
that it's full of records.
Records are exposed in our
framework as the CKRecord class.
They are the mechanism by
which you move structured data
to and from CloudKit.
CKRecords wrap key/value pairs.
Lest you think that a CKRecord
is just a glorified dictionary,
there are some additional
attributes
that make it worthwhile
of being its own class.
To start off with,
records have a record type.
If CloudKit is the mechanism by
which you take your object wrap
from your application and
move it into CloudKit,
then let's continue
with that analogy.
An instance of an object in
your application is equivalent
to an instance of a CKRecord.
Similarly, the class
of the object
in your application
is equivalent
to the record type
of the CKRecord.
Records have a just-in-time
schema.
You do not need to tell CloudKit
about what your data looks
like before you hand
CloudKit your data.
Hand us your data;
we'll figure it out.
CloudKit-excuse me, CKRecord
also support a raft of metadata.
For example, a record
understands when it was created
and who created it;
it understands
when a record was last modified
and who last modified it;
and lastly, a record contains
the notion of a change tag.
A change tag is a
version of a record.
It represents a specific
revision of this record.
And it's used so that we
can have a lightweight way
of determining whether
or not a client
and a server had the
same version of a record.
Let's talk a little bit
about record values.
CKRecords wrap key/value pairs.
What are the acceptable
value types
that you can put
into a CKRecord?
Well, we've got your
usual suspects.
Your P-list types-your
strings, your numbers,
your datas, and your dates.
We think that-especially
in the public database
domain-location is an
interesting scenario.
So CLLocation is a native type
that you can set on a CKRecord.
You can set CKReferences
and CKAssets.
We're going to go over what
those are in just a moment.
And lastly, any value
can be a single instance.
I can have a string or a date,
or it can be a homogeneous
array.
I can have an array of numbers
or an array of CKAssets.
Let's have a look at
a little bit of code.
Here we see a CKRecord.
The CKRecord initializer
takes a record type
because that's a invaluable and
necessary piece of a record.
You can set objects
and get objects
from a record using
a dictionary syntax
or a keyed subscripting syntax.
We also give you the ability to
enumerate all keys on a record
so that you can dump the
entire key/value pair.
Let's have a look at
a specific example.
Now, throughout this
talk, my example is going
to be an application that I've
created for me and my friends.
This application allows us to
create parties, and we're going
to stick party records
in the public database.
A party might be a
structured data-it's going
to have a summary, a
start date, an end date.
And it might also have
additional metadata
that we associate with
it-pictures of the party,
etc. So how do I
create a party record?
Well, I create one, just
as you might imagine,
with a party record type.
I can now set values on
it, and I can read values
from it using either
the dictionary
or key subscripting syntax.
Those are records.
Let's talk about record zones.
So this is the model that
we've just presented.
And it was kind of a lie, but
it was a useful lie at the time.
So, records don't exist by
themselves, just as objects
in your application don't
exist by themselves.
There's going to be a
natural grouping of objects
within your application.
Similarly, we want a way
to express this grouping
in CloudKit.
Fundamentally we're trying
via CloudKit to take as much
of your knowledge about your
object graph and reflect
that up to the server.
So the way that we group
records is via something
that we call a "record zone."
There can be multiple
records within a record zone,
and there can be multiple
record zones within a database.
Every database has a
default record zone.
Some databases support
additional custom record zones.
Record zones are the
default granularity
at which you're going
to do atomic commits
and change tracking.
If either of those
sounds interesting to you,
I invite you back on
Thursday for the events talk.
We're going to go over
a whole bunch of that.
So those were record zones.
Let's talk about
record identifiers.
Record identifiers-let's get
the code up there-are a tuple.
They represent both a
client-provided record name
and also the zone in which
that record name exists.
So what are their
characteristics?
Number one, they're
created by the client.
You get to specify the idea of
the record name of the record.
But because we are coupling this
record name-which is scoped per
record zone, along
with a reference
to the owning record zone-they
become a fully normalized
representation of the record.
It's the full path to it.
We think that it's going to be
fairly common for you to try
and bridge an external
dataset into CloudKit.
If you're doing so and if your
external dataset has a unique
key, using that unique key
as the CKRecordID allows you
to have a foreign key back
into your external
dataset-totally an
approved usage.
Let's have a look at some code.
Here we are, you know,
creating a record.
You've seen that already.
And we've got multiple
initializers
for CKRecord-you can either
choose to provide us a record ID
or you can choose not to.
If you choose not to
provide a record ID,
we're going to assign a
random UUID to the record.
Also, note here that when
I created my record ID,
I chose not to give it a zone.
Throughout CloudKit's
API, if you choose not
to give us a record zone,
we're going to assume
that you meant the default zone.
So here, I am creating a record
ID with the name WellKnownParty
that exists within
the default zone.
So those are record IDs.
Now let's talk about references.
Just as there's a natural
grouping of records that we want
to expose via a record
zone, there's also going
to be a natural relationship
between objects.
For example, let's say that in
addition to being able to write
up parties, I can assign
different clowns to parties.
Because what is the
point of a party
if you don't have a few clowns?
So I want some way
of representing the object
relationship that I have
between parties and
clowns up to the server.
And the way we do
that is via something
that we call references.
Now, you'll note here that
in this contrived example,
parties own clowns; that is,
we've got a parent-child
relationship with the party
as a parent and the
clown as a child,
and that the reference
goes from the child object,
from the clown, up
to its parent object.
We call that a "back reference."
References are exposed in our
API as the CKReference class.
They are a way of letting
the server understand the
relationship between records.
When the server understands the
relationship between records,
it can do very interesting
things, such as cascade deletes.
If the server notices that
you've deleted a record
and that record is the parent in
a parent and child relationship,
the server will automatically
go ahead
and cascade delete all
the children of that item.
With any database the scope
and scale of CloudKit,
dangling pointers are going
to be become a necessary
and inconvenient truth
of your use of CloudKit.
By the time you fetch a record
and you read a reference,
then you go and fetch the
target of that reference,
that target may not exist.
So it's important that your
code is resilient to this.
Again, as I mentioned, we
prefer back references.
It's not a requirement, but it's
more efficient if references go
from child objects
to parent objects.
This is the tip of the iceberg
in a very large topic
called data modeling.
And if you come back
on Thursday,
we're going to tell
you a whole bunch
about data modeling
and CloudKit.
Let's have a look at some code.
Here we see creating a reference
between two CKRecord instances
that I have in memory.
But it's not necessary
that I have the target
of a reference in memory.
I can make a reference
that points at a record ID.
This allows me to refer to a
record that I've got, you know,
reason to believe
exists up on the server.
If I were to save this record
and the target didn't exist,
I'd actually be creating
a dangling pointer.
And that's okay because the code
you're going to write is going
to support and be resilient in
the face of dangling pointers.
So those are references.
Now let's talk about assets.
Here we have our model
again, just a refresher,
container database record.
And now let's take the idea that
I want to write a record-I want
to write a party
record-up to the server.
But let's say that I want
to associate a large
file with that record.
Let's say, for example,
that we're going
to have a get-together after
the presentation and I'm going
to read you a screenplay
that I've been working on.
Now, I know-I understand-that
there's different
characteristics between
these different datas.
I understand that the record
about the party is structured.
You know, it's got a summary,
it's got a got a start
date, it's got an end date.
And, you know, just innately I
believe that I want the server
to understand those
bits about the record.
If we contrast that to
the screenplay, well,
the screenplay is just
essentially a bag of bits.
Right? I don't feel
any real need
to tell the server how
my screenplay breaks
down into amazing acts and,
you know, dashing scenes.
But I do know that
I want to treat them
as just an opaque bag.
So how do we solve this?
Well, we're going to
solve this and we're going
to solve the fact that data
has different characteristics
like this in two different ways.
Up on the server we're
going to introduce a notion
that we call "bulk storage."
As you might expect,
bulk storage is great
for storing bulk data.
Similarly, on the client
you're, going to tell CloudKit
about the different
characteristics of your data
by treating some
of it as a CKRecord
and other bits of
it as a CKAsset.
A CKAsset is the representation
of this bag of bits.
Now when with you ask
CloudKit to save this record,
the appropriate bits are going
to in the appropriate
database-structured data
in the public database,
bulk data in bulk storage.
So assets.
Assets are exposed in our
framework as the CKAsset class.
They represent large,
unstructured data.
Because you don't necessarily
want large, unstructured data
in memory, the way you
communicate assets to
and from CloudKit is
via files on disk.
Assets are owned by records.
This gives us a nice,
tight coupling
between a record and an asset.
What this allows the server to
do is garbage-collect assets.
Even though that we're storing
this data in two separate areas,
when the server detects a delete
for a record, it can go ahead
and clean up any assets that
were owned by that record.
Lastly, because we expect
CKAsset to be large,
opaque data, we go through some
great pains to try and move
that data to and from the server
as efficiently as possible.
This is all sort of inside
of CloudKit, but we're going
to send only the bits that,
the minimal amount
of bits that we can.
Let's have a look at some code.
Here I'm creating a
CKAsset based on a file URL
to my screenplay on disk.
And just like any other
CKRecord value supporting class,
I'm setting it on CKRecord.
So these are the fundamental
objects in CloudKit.
The first thing you
talk to is a container;
within a container are
two different databases;
databases contain records;
records are wrapped and grouped
within record zones;
you identify your record
via a record identifier;
records are related to one
another via references;
and large bulk data
is transmitted to
and from CloudKit via CKAssets.
All right.
You guys made it
through the nouns.
Now let's get into the verbs.
CloudKit, we offer two different
APIs for using CloudKit.
We call them the "operational
API" and the "convenience API."
The operational API
has every single bell
and whistle you might
care about.
And in some cases,
you're going to want
to tweak every single
bell and whistle
to fit your application's model.
But not every application really
wants to do all this tweaking,
and not every application
has enough knowledge
to set these bits correctly.
Sometimes you want to let
the framework make some
of these decisions
on your behalf.
And so we offer the
convenience API.
It's convenient.
It's going to be what you
want to start off playing
with when you start
looking at CloudKit.
For many uses of CloudKit,
it's all that you're
going to need to touch.
So quickly, we're going to
go over how you save a record
in the convenience API;
how you fetch a record
from the server via
the convenience API;
and how you can take a
fetched record, modify it,
and save it back
up to the server.
Let's start off with
saving a record.
Here I am, creating a record.
You guys are now very
well familiar with this.
When I want to save the
record, I have to choose
which database I
want to save it into.
Here I'm going to save the
data into the public database.
And how do I do that?
Well, I call the save record
with completion handler method.
Now, I want you guys to
note three separate things
about this code right here.
First of all, it's very simple.
Right? You guys aren't
providing a lot of options.
You're delegating a lot of
the bells and whistles like
"How important is this?
What interface should
I send this data over?"
You're delegating those
choices off to CloudKit.
Second, it's asynchronous.
As Olivier mentioned, CloudKit
does not have local persistence.
We are a transport technology.
We are going to transport
your data up to the server,
we'll store it on the server,
and we'll transport it back
down to other clients.
So when you save a record
via CloudKit, we are going
to attempt to save that
record directly to the server.
If it fails, we're going to tell
you about that immediately or,
you know, as quickly as we can.
Now, we don't want
to block threads
and we don't want you
to block the user.
So we don't want to make
this a synchronous call.
So here we've got an
asynchronous call.
Now, the third thing
I want you to note is
that even though this
is a very simple method,
we do provide an error
as part of the callback.
Now, if you've been
to WWC in the past
or if you've watched
any presentations,
you've seen something
that looks like this.
We get an Apple developer
up here,
and the Apple developer says,
"You need to handle errors
that are returned
from our framework."
Now, I'm not calling them liars.
It's true; you do need to handle
errors returned from frameworks.
In many applications it's the
difference between, you know,
a good and functioning
application
and a great application.
CloudKit is a little
bit different.
CloudKit, by its very nature,
is going to be talking
over the network.
Networks are inherently lossy.
Phones like to fall off
the network all the time.
So in CloudKit the difference
between handling an error
versus not handling an error
is really the difference
between a functional
and a nonfunctional app.
Error handling has got to
be one of the first things
that you look at when
you start using CloudKit.
I'm going to be a little bit
glib throughout the slides here,
but every time you
see a comment,
imagine that you're seeing just
some really nice error handling.
[Laughter]
So let's talk about, now
that we've saved a record
up to the server, how do
we fetch a record back
down from the server?
I'm going to start by
deciding which database I want
to fetch a record from.
I'm then going to construct
a record ID-the identifier
of the record I care
to fetch down.
Here I've gotten this name
either via some side channel
or something that's built
into my application.
I then can ask the database
to fetch a record with ID
with completionHandler.
Again, asynchronous, simple,
amazing error handling.
Once I fetched a
record-let's get that code back
up here-I want you to note
that the successful return value
is an actual CKRecord instance.
And this is a live,
honest-to-God CKRecord.
Let's say I'm having so much
fun at this party I pulled
that I want it to last
a little bit longer.
I can take a record off of it,
I can bump out the end date
by half an hour, and I can set
that record-that
value-back on the record.
Once I've done that, I can
take my CKRecord instance,
and just like one that
I've create the locally,
I can turn around and save it
back up to the database, again,
with amazing error handling.
All right.
So that's the convenience
API, the initial typical flow
that you're going to go through
when talking with CloudKit.
You're going to be saving
records; fetching records;
and taking those records that
you fetched, modifying them,
and putting them back
up to the server.
So now let's say my party
application starts becoming
really popular, and it's grown.
My user base is no longer me and
my friends, but it's all of you.
You know, everyone's
really excited
about joining into the parties.
What are some of the problems
I'm going to run into?
Well, let's assume that
when I started out,
I was a relatively
naive developer.
And because the developer
on stage said CloudKit's all
about taking your object
graph and moving it to
and from the cloud,
that's exactly what I did.
I had one-to-one mapping.
My objects went up to the cloud,
and on every client I would
fetch the entire cloud state,
and that would become
my object graph.
What are some problems
we're going to run into?
Well, at that point we've got
big data and a very tiny phone.
The more popular my app becomes,
the more data on the database,
the less reasonable
it is to have a cache
of that entire data
locally on my device.
So how are we going
to solve this?
Well, let's think about
what we want to do.
We want to keep the large
data up in the cloud.
The cloud is very good at
storing large datasets.
My client wants to view
a slice of that data.
Because I'm writing an
application for my users
and my users have their own
preferences, I want each client
to be able to view a
different slice of that data,
and each individual
client might want
to change its view of that data.
The way we solve
this is via something
that we call "queries."
Clients use queries to
focus their viewpoint
so that they can see a small
section of a large dataset
that exists up on the cloud.
So what is a query?
Well, as you might
imagine, it's exposed
in our API as the CKQuery class.
A query combines three
different things:
It combines a RecordType,
a predicate,
and optionally a
sort descriptor.
If you've used NSPredicate
in the past,
you know that NSPredicate
is very expressive.
CloudKit supports
most of NSPredicate.
We document the parts
that we do.
And if you hand us a predicate
that we don't understand,
we're going to throw
an exception.
So you're going to learn
pretty quickly which ones are
and are not supported.
Let's have a look at
some that are supported.
Here we see a predicate
that would match records
where name is equal to a
value that I had in memory.
Predicates allow you
to use dynamic keys
so that I don't have to know
the key name at compile time.
We can do relative
ordering comparisons,
as opposed to strict equalities.
We mentioned that location
is an interesting aspect
in the public database.
So you can query with
a location as a filter.
This is every location
within a hundred meters
of where we're standing
here in Moscone.
CloudKit supports a
tokenization search.
So what this predicate is going
to do is it's going to tokenize
that string after session,
and it's going to come
up with two different
tokens: "after" and "session."
This predicate will
match any record
that has those two
token as values.
These two tokens don't
need to exist side by side,
they don't even need to exist
in the same key/value pair,
but so long as the record
has the token "after"
and the record has
the token "session,"
the record will be a match.
And lastly, CloudKit supports
compound predicates joined using
the "and" operator.
Here we see a predicate
that does that.
Here we see the creation
of a query.
And as we mentioned,
it's combining both a
record type and a predicate.
How do I perform queries
after I've created them?
Well, just like saving records,
performing a query is going
to be a database-specific
operation.
So I'm going to choose
the database
on which I want to
perform a query.
Even in the simple API-in the
convenience API-we give you the
ability to restrict these
queries by record zones.
You see here that we're
not choosing to pass
on a record zone filter.
So this query is going to search
across the entire
public database.
Let's have a look
at what happens
in the completion handler.
First, of course,
amazing error handing.
Second, if we don't have errors,
let's have a look
at the results.
And you'll see here that
the results are actually
CKRecord instances.
These are live objects.
If I wanted to, I could
pull data off of them;
I could set data on them;
and I could even choose
to save them back to the server.
So a way to think about queries
is that queries are polls,
and polls are great
in some scenarios.
They're great for slicing
through large datasets.
If your application wants to
start up and, for example,
show all the parties-the
top ten parties
that are near me-a query is
absolutely the way to go.
But there's other things
that you might be tempted
to use a query for
that are not perfect.
If you find yourself issuing
the same query over and over
and over again, and you're
getting back a static,
a mostly same data result set,
well, then you've got a large,
mostly static dataset.
And queries are bad for that
use case for a few reasons.
They're bad for battery life.
You have to constantly
wake the device up, poll,
run the same query, and get back
more or less the same results.
They're bad for network traffic.
All those questions get to the
server, if they're not pulling
down new and interesting
data, why do we bother?
And they're also bad
for the user experience.
By definition, you're only
going to learn about new results
on the period of how
often you're polling.
Users nowadays have
come to expect push.
So as opposed to using
a client-generated query
in this scenario, what you
really want is you want the
server to be running the
query on your behalf.
You want the server to be
running the query on your behalf
in the background, and
you want that to happen
after every single record
save, whether it was you
or somebody else that
saved the record.
And lastly, of course,
you want pushes
when the results set changes.
Well, we've given you this,
and we call that subscriptions.
Yay! [Applause] So subscriptions
are exposed in our API
as the CKSubscription class.
They combine a record type,
a predicate, and push.
Push is delivered via
the Apple Push Service.
If you've used APS in the past,
you're largely familiar
with this.
But note: CloudKit pushes
are slightly augmented.
They contain CloudKit-specific
information
about what caused
the push to happen.
Let's have a look at an example.
Here we have a phone, and that
phone is interested in parties
that are going to be
happening in the future.
This phone, when it sees that
happening, wants to be alerted
with a push that
says "Party Time!"
The phone's going to go ahead
and save that up to iCloud.
And iCloud's going to,
you know, shuffle it away
with all the other
subscriptions.
Now along comes the Mac.
The Mac creates a new record.
It's a record-type party,
and it's happening tonight.
And because the Mac didn't
choose to give us a record ID,
we created that random
UUID you see.
The Mac goes ahead and
saves that to iCloud.
iCloud is then going to loop
through all the subscriptions
that it knows about.
Eventually it's going
to come across this one.
It's going to check
and say, "Yeah.
Okay, this is a new party.
And, yeah, it's happening
in the future."
So at that point it's
going to create a push.
And it's going to
take some information
from the subscription.
Here it took the alert
string "Party Time!"
It's going to take
other information
from the record itself.
Here we're pulling
in the record ID.
Now that I've constructed
this augmented payload,
I can send that augmented
payload down to all clients
that are registered
and interested in it.
So let's look at some code.
How do I create a subscription?
Well, a subscription combines
a record type and a predicate.
Because a subscription
is also in charge
of telling the server how
you want to be alerted,
we introduce a notion
called CKNotificationInfo.
Here we're requesting that
the server badges our icon,
that it plays a particular sound
pulled out of my resources,
and that it shows an alert
string based on a string
in my localized strings file.
I can associate that
notification info
with the subscription, and now
I've created everything I need
in my subscription.
Let's go ahead and
save it to the server.
As you might imagine via the
convenience API, it's simple,
it's asynchronous, and it's
got great error handling.
Let's look about
how you're going
to be handling subscriptions,
to handle pushes
as they come in.
If you've used APS in the
past, you're probably familiar
with this code snippet.
This is your application
delegate implementing the
application
didReceiveRemoteNotification
method.
Now, in most scenarios
if you know the format
of the push payload
that's coming in,
you would just then iterate
through that dictionary,
pulling out the key/value
pairs that you care about.
However, because
CloudKit was the one
that generated this push,
we asked that you let
CloudKit do that parsing.
So the way you would do
that is via CKNotification,
then that really long one
I'm not going to name.
Once we've actually parsed
out a CKNotification,
you can pull off APS-level
information from it
and you can also pull off
CloudKit-level information
from it.
Here we're taking the record
ID of the saved record
that caused the push to happen.
So between queries and
subscriptions, we have an answer
to the big data, tiny
phone problem: You're going
to leave your large data up
in the cloud, and you're going
to use these two capabilities
to give your users a quick view
into that large dataset.
Now I want to talk about
CloudKit user accounts.
As Olivier mentioned,
CloudKit is built on top
of the iCloud account
infrastructure.
So what does that mean?
I want to focus a little bit
on how accounts are exposed
to you explicitly
throughout the API.
When you think about
an account system,
the first thing you think
about is authentication.
And CloudKit supports
authentication via the logged-in
iCloud user.
But that's not-you know, that's
sort of behind the scenes.
You guys don't care about that.
That's implicit.
Let's talk about
the explicit things.
What do we give you
because we're built
on top of iCloud accounts?
We give you identity, a way
of identifying the user.
We give you metadata,
the ability to save
and retrieve information
about users.
We do all of this in a
privacy-conscientious manner;
we don't want to
disclose anything
if the user hasn't agreed to it.
And lastly, we give
users the ability
to discover their friends that
are using your application.
Let's dive into each
one of these.
First of all, we're going
to talk about identity.
So here's our model.
We've got our client,
our application running
on the client, and all
of these different users
and their private databases
up in the container.
Your specific client is
going to be linked to one
and only one of those users.
This is related to
the user that's logged
in via iCloud locally
on your device.
Because this is iCloud,
we've got a rich backing
store of user information.
And because iCloud is the one
that is hosting your container,
we can correlate users.
For example, here we see
that the user whose email
address is c@iCloud.com is
linked to your current client.
So given this setup, how are we
going to present an identity?
How are we going to let
you know, your client,
your application, know
what user is logged in?
Well, naively you might think,
"Let's just give them
the email address."
We're not going to
do that, obviously.
That's private user-identifiable
information,
and we don't want
to give that out.
So instead what we do is on a
container-by-container basis,
we come up with a random ID.
This is an identifier
that is stable.
So that is your application,
no matter what client
it's running on,
talking to this container
will get the same identifier.
But it's not identifying
the user via any
personal information.
So we feel confident
giving you this identifier.
You can take this identifier
and do with it what you will.
Note that different applications
running on your phone,
because they're talking
to different containers,
are going to get back different
container-scoped record
identifiers for the same user.
This goes back to what we
talked about in the beginning,
that we've got user
encapsulation.
So user identity.
We expose user identity via
our API as a user record ID.
It is a stable identifier
for this user.
It will be the same for
your application no matter
where your application
is running.
It's scoped to the container,
so two different
applications are going to come
up with different
identifiers for the same user.
This is a feature.
And lastly, this is
an independent API.
This is a section of
the CloudKit framework.
You can use this
in collaboration
with the database API,
or you can use this
completely separately.
We've given you enough
support that if you wanted to,
you could implement a
login via iCloud flow
in your application using
the CloudKit framework.
Let's have a look at the code.
[Applause] All right.
Because identity is a
container-scoped notion
and not a database-scoped
notion, we go to our container
to learn about our user.
Here we're asking our container
to fetch the user record ID.
Now, because we may have
to talk to the server
to figure this out, for example,
the first time you access
and try and learn about a record
ID, we have to go to the server
to do that translation and come
up with the container-scoped
info.
So asynchronous, and we
have to do error handling.
That's user identity.
Let's talk about user metadata.
And quickly, to recap
the problem,
what we have here is we
have a stable identifier,
and we've got a desire
to set key/value pairs
based on that identifier.
I don't know about you, but
to me that sounds very much
like what a record
was built to do.
So we expose users
as user records.
Looking inside a
container within a database,
we see that there is one user
record in the private database;
that user record
represents your user.
There are many user records
inside the public database,
representing each one of the
users of your application.
One of them will
have a record ID
that matches your
currently logged
in iCloud user's record ID.
So user metadata exposed via
our framework as a user record.
There's one per database that
represents your current user.
User records in the
public database,
like any other default
record, are world-readable.
They're treated mostly
like a ordinary record
with a record type
that we expose
in the framework
CKRecordTypeUserRecord.
But there are a couple
of caveats.
First off, these records
are reserved by the system.
You do not create a
user record; rather,
you fetch an existing
one from the server.
What that means is
that you can be assured
that when you fetch a
record for your current user
that it has not been spoofed.
It was indeed iCloud
that created
that record in the first place.
Secondly, we think that it
doesn't make sense for you
to be able to query the
entire set of user records
in the public database.
It doesn't really make sense to
be able to say, "I want to look
at all users whose first
name begins with A."
It's a little bit too
coarse-grained for something
that we want to protect
privacy around.
So we don't allow you
to query user records.
Don't worry, we're going to
fix that in a couple of slides.
All right.
So what does it look like?
Here we have the same
code that we saw earlier.
We're fetching a user record ID.
Once I have that CKRecordID,
I can go ahead and I can fetch
that record from either
database that I choose.
Here I'm choosing to fetch a
record with that identifier
from the public database.
Assuming that I don't
get an error,
I now have a live CKRecord
that represents this user.
And I can treat it like I
would any other CKRecord.
I can pull records-excuse me-I
can pull key/value pairs off of,
it, I can set key/value
pairs on it.
And if I wanted to,
I could go ahead
and save it back to the server.
Now let's talk about privacy.
We care very much about
our user's privacy.
Therefore, we disclose no
information-no personally
identifying user
information-about the current
user by default.
Now, we recognize that in some
cases your application is going
to want to have limited access
to metadata about the user.
So if you want that data, you
can request that from CloudKit.
When you do, we're going to
go to the user to make sure
that they're okay with that.
Here we see an example
of the party application
requesting the ability
for my user account
to be discoverable
within the application.
The user can either choose
to allow or deny that.
Assuming that the
user has acquiesced
to this privacy request,
we can go onto the next
phase, which is discovery.
So let's talk a little
bit about user discovery.
Here's our image.
We've got our client
talking to a container.
And the container
is backed by iCloud,
and iCloud has all this
rich user information.
If we look a little bit
more on the client side,
we see that there's actually
two different processes involved
here-there's your
client process,
and then there's the
CloudKit process.
And it's the CloudKit process
that's the one that's actually
talking over the wire.
So let's examine what
user discovery would look
like if you want to
discover information
about a user given a record ID.
You take that record ID, and
you can send it off to CloudKit.
CloudKit is going to in turn
send it up to the container.
Once it hits the container,
we're going to ask the iCloud
account info to exchange
that for different
information-for information
about that user.
If that user has opted
in to discoverability,
we're going to get
information back.
That information can
traverse back to CloudKit
and back via the process
boundary over to your client.
But we're not restricted
to just record IDs.
If your user enters
in an email address,
we can do the same
sort of dance.
This email address is sent from
your client over to CloudKit.
CloudKit is then going to hash
it up a whole bunch of times
so that we're not sending
personal info off the client.
And we'll send that
up to the container.
That container exchanges
it with iCloud.
And if the target of
this discovery has opted
in to discoverability, we're
going to get a result sent back.
Those results can
go back to CloudKit
and can traverse back
up to your client.
Now, I'd like to think
that we are pretty good
about naming things in
CloudKit, but this one we sort
of didn't really do well.
So we offer a different
way of doing user discovery
that we call the
whole address book.
And it's a way for you to
discover the whole address book.
And the way this works is that
your client is going to say,
"I would like to discover
the user record IDs
and more information about
every user that is friends
with my currently
logged-in iCloud user."
You send that request over
to the CloudKit process.
The CloudKit process
is then going to pull
in the user's address book.
We're going to take
all the email addresses
in that address book; we're
going to hash them up;
and we're going to
send, you know,
a non-personally
identifying version
of that address book
up to the container.
The container's going to
send it off to iCloud.
And for those members of my
address book that have opted
in to discoverability, I'm going
to learn information about them.
That information's going
to come back to CloudKit.
That's going to be sent over the
process boundary to your client.
Now, if you'll note, at
no point did your client
in this little flow have access
to the user's address book.
What this means is that we
can give you this support
without requiring that your
user allows your application
to the address book, meaning
that you don't have to have
that blue alert-which is now
the white alert-giving your
application access
to the address book.
You can leverage it
without access to it.
[Applause] So user discovery.
These are the three
different kinds of inputs
that we can have
for user discovery.
You can start off with a user
RecordID, an email address,
or a request to view
the entire address book.
What do you get back
from user discovery?
Well, you'll get
back a user RecordID;
in the latter two cases,
that's new information.
You also get back the first
and last name of this user.
Now, of course, it
bears repeating,
first and last name
is personally
identifying information.
So you're only going to get
discovery results for users
that have opted in
to discoverability.
Let's have a look
at some code here.
Here we are asking our default
container to discover all
of my users that are a
part of my address book.
In the response-again,
asynchronous error handling-in
the successful response case,
what we see is that we get back
a CKDiscoveredUserInfo object.
And that user info, from that,
I can pull a user record ID
and a first and last name.
So these are really
the four tent poles
of how we do user accounts: We
give you a stable identifier;
we give you the ability to
store and retrieve metadata
about users; we protect
users' privacy;
and we give your
users the ability
to discover their friends
in your application.
Now to tell you when it's
appropriate to use CloudKit
versus some of the other
iCloud technologies
that we already have exposed,
I'd like to invite
back up Olivier Bonnet.
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Olivier Bonnet:
Thank you, Paul.
So CloudKit is the
new framework,
but it doesn't obsolete
or deprecate any
of the existing tools;
it's really just a new
tool in your toolbox.
Let's look at all the four
tools you now have and look
at four different use cases
where we think they make sense
and they're appropriate to use.
So first, iCloud
Key Value Store.
iCloud Key Value Store
keeps small payloads of data
up to date between your
app and the iCloud servers.
This is done asynchronously.
Your app doesn't
really need to care
about when and how this is done.
We think this is great
for small amounts of data
like application
preferences, game states.
Conflict resolution is pretty
simple, last writer wins.
So that's iCloud
Key Value Store.
iCloud Drive builds on top
of the existing iCloud
documents APIs.
Doing so, it provides a
full offline cache on OS X.
All the files on
the iCloud Drive
of the user are downloaded
on OS X.
It's completely unstructured and
totally tied to the filesystem.
You use the file coordination
APIs to read and write data
in your application iCloud
container in the filesystem.
The iCloud Drive daemon
takes care of uploading
and downloading those changes
up and from the iCloud servers.
We think it's great for
document-centric apps or apps
that need to deal with
an extinct file format.
iCloud Core Data, built
on top of iCloud Drive,
replicates off specific
user data
between all the user's devices.
It's great for keeping private
structured data in sync.
But because it downloads
all the data to all devices,
you're also constrained
to the size
of the smallest device
in that case.
Enters CloudKit, the
new kid on the block.
And we think there are a
number of interesting use cases
where CloudKit makes sense
and complements pretty well
the existing technologies.
So first, any public data.
If your app-if you need to
give access to all the users
of your app to large datasets,