welcome to core IO s application
architectural patterns
my name's bill that me and I were
you like at thanks for being here so
exciting
so much cool stuff this year okay so
by way of introduction what we're gonna
talk about today is the
through the list of common patterns that
we find across
all the frameworks in I O S in Cocoa
Touch
we're also gonna spend some time talking
about how we can apply
these patterns to your code
how we can make your applications better
by understanding these patterns 1
and then applying the concepts defined
in those patterns
to the code that we write aren't so
common patterns and you like it and
beyond
the great thing about these common
patterns is that once you understand it
in one context
the way that we use them across all of
Cocoa Touch ends up being
very similar so when you first look at
the list documentation we have all these
frameworks a core video Corradi ok or
animation
foundation core data and so forth can be
a little overwhelming you look at that
list and say
holy Caleta giant fire hose that I have
to ingest right now
all the great thing though is that again
these patterns are used in a common way
throughout this whole stack love of
remarks so when you understand one
pattern in one framework
you can apply that knowledge across the
whole stack of remarks
so it really levels out the amount of
learning that you have to do
let's get started with the first pattern
next target action
now target action is a consistent way to
connect
controls to custom logic things in your
user interface connected to the code
that makes your application
what it is so if you've ever done this
in Xcode
you have seen target action in action
when you drag that connection from the
button
to your view controller it saying hey
whenever this button is activated
kick off this message here's an example
from 10 our applications
this is the message application and we
have
several buttons on here that top when
the cancel button
course when that's tapped that's gonna
send
cancel message gonna delete the message
in and get rid of this
this presented view controller when the
user taps on send
it's going to package up the message
push it off into the interwebs this can
end up
in whoever's device you're having a
conversation with now
the really cool thing is these two
classes that make
these instances the classes for these
instances are from completely different
places in the class hierarchy
you I Barbara might bar button item
is a subclass a business object you I
button is a subclass
a UI control but both have them apply
this target action paradigm
so that you don't really have to think
about the fact that they're different
classes
they both applied his pattern in a very
consistent way
so once you understand it for one you
understand it for both
getting a little more abstract talking
about target action
the idea is you have a control or an
initiator something that kicks off
the message sent
that has a target object that it sends
the message to
and in the particular message that it
sends is called the action message
what you understand this again where
were ever we use this its use in such a
consistent way that if you understand it
in one context
you understand it in all the contacts so
with gesture recognizers
same thing a gesture recognizer has a
target
an action in when you create that
gesture recognizer you specify that
so again it's exactly the same kind of
concept is what we see
with the control objects so that's
target action
a way to specify a connection between
two objects and get those
control objects to invoke custom code in
your application
next up is the responder chain
the responder chain let your application
handle events
without knowledge which particular
object is going to be used to handle
that event
responder chain kicks off with some sort
of initiators just some object in your
application
that kicks off the process it could be
user action it could be a control
for controller that's an action to the
first responder
and that first responder might respond
to it and if it does then the process is
done
that responder has handled that message
and its its complete but if it doesn't
its gonna ask its next responder eighty
you respond to this message
and if it does then of course it will
handle it but if it doesn't keeps going
up the responder chain
until it finds some responder that
actually
implements the message whatever that was
that was asked to be done
change the color of the text field or
copy the contents of a text field or
whatever you happen to send
up the responder chain a particular
place for use this
is with motion events on user shakes the
phone
we send this motion begin motion in did
in motion cancelled to the responder
chain
and so that travels up the responder
chain looking for the object that
response to that message
the great thing is you can use the
responder chain to respond to things
like that like motion in did
by implementing it wherever it makes
sense in the responder chain so here's a
picture that
die grammatically expresses what what
all applications have as their responder
chain
it starts off in the view hierarchy it
travels up the hierarchy till it gets to
a view controller
the view controller it doesn't implement
it passes it up to the window the window
to the application and finally the
application to
the application delegate and that's the
responder chain
it lets you build a group of objects
that are going to eventually find out
who's responsible for
implementing a particular message next
up
is composite
composite let's manipulate a group of
objects
as a single object and we use this
extensively
and the view hierarchy so start off with
a single view
created Alec and it was frame I create a
new view
an incall add some view
now these two objects the parent view in
blue here
and the child be the one in green are in
this composite relationship so now I can
treat the whole hierarchy and I could
have
hundreds views underneath up luv you but
I get to treat all of them
as one composite object so I can do
things like
move that pay review and when I do all
that's abuse move along with it
same thing with other actions that I
tell that you do move it back and then I
rotated
all this abuse in that composite are
treated together as one
object
we also use the a you hierarchy
as I said earlier in the responder chain
so as you add child abuse to a view
its super view the new child beauty was
just added it's super you becomes that
use
next responder and so that's how it gets
up to the point where it finds a view
that has a view controller Zach
travels up its super view hierarchy
and again we use the same pattern in
multiple places
you spent much time using the UI
dynamics
a dynamic behavior is able to have a
child dynamic behavior
and if you group them together in a
composite by calling add
child behavior than those two behaviors
are treated together as one thing
by the physics simulation that's running
in the background
so that's composite allowing us to build
a group of objects
into a tree that then we can treat as
one
single object
next up is delegation
that allows us to customize behavior in
our applications
with out subclassing the object whose
behavior
we are customizing so great example that
you see an almost every introductory
it introduction to doing I listed on
this talking about
the application delegate the application
is delegating to the application
delegate
to customize the way it behaves there's
a send a message that the
application delegate protocol specifies
application is gonna go into the
background
application is gonna come into the
foreground application
wants to open this URL and so forth all
those methods that you implement in your
delegate
customize the way you I application tax
but you don't have to know anything
about the details view application
so this is a very particular decision
made by
you I kid to use this form
love delegation we could have
on the other hand we could have asked
you to subclass UI application
and that would work there's actually do
we frame works out there that ask you to
some class the object to come out and do
a free market
but if we ask you to subclass UI
application you would have to understand
a lotta detail about you I application
which methods are safe to override which
methods are not safe to override
if I do override this method do I have
to call super or is that of tional
we don't wanna put that cognitive load
on you we don't you have to think about
that stuff
so instead using this idea delegation
allows us to delegate to your code to
say what do you want
custom what you want special to have
happened
when the application goes into the
background or when it comes into the
foreground
that allows you to customize the way you
application works without us having
to force you to understand all that
detail about you I application
now of course there's still a lot to
detail the afternoon on but that's what
makes you awesome developers
and again we use this in many many
frameworks throughout I O S
here's just a few a V Foundation makes
extensive use it delegates
coronation has delegates on their layers
game kit has a couple different classes
including GK session that had delegates
and in every case that delegate is about
customizing the behavior those other
classes without you having to subclass
from them
okay so that's delegation next up
is datasource
that allows you to customize data
retrieval
without having to subclass the object
that needs the data
common example from you I kid you I
tableview
has a UI tableview datasource
that allows the table view to know how
many sections it has
how many rows are in each section what
data belongs in each of the rows that
are in that section
so the table view asks its data source
all these questions that gives you the
chance to customize how the data is
retrieved where it comes from and so
forth
and provided to the table view but you
don't have to subclass tableview
be the same situation subclassing table
tableview would require you to know also
to detail about that
that we didn't have to force you to
think through
so here's some other examples inside you
like it same basic store you I pick your
views as hey how many things belong in
my picture view
page view controller hey how many things
show up in my page view
give me the next thing is gonna show up
in here so again if you understand
datasource in one context when you see
that word
datasource it means the same thing
throughout all the frameworks
so again you to leverage that learning
across all these different things
so back to the definition here
datasource customized data retrieval
without subclassing
now looks an awful lot like customize
behavior without subclassing
and in fact these two ideas are really
similar
its it's the idea of composing an object
rather than
extending a class and so you use a
couple projects compose them together to
get custombehavior
rather than subclassing into powerful
idea that we use like I said in many
different places
so that data source it allows you to
customized where data comes from
for an object that needs data without
having to subclass that object
alright next up is model view controller
model-view-controller zine lots and lots
over documentation water broke at what
have a lot of things to say about
model-view-controller there's probably
a definition for Model View Controller
for every person in here
or maybe more the way I like to think
about it is model view controller gives
us
away to organize to to build an
organizational structure
around the responsibilities that our
application has
would start off talking about the model
so I like to think at the mall or the
way like to describe how to think about
the model
is it's the data it's the stuff that
makes up your application
this is typically something that that
people don't have trouble getting their
heads wrapped around the typically can
look at what their application is doing
and say oh I see
that a model object
the view also ends up being a pretty
pretty well understood peace
a the NBC puzzle it's the thing that
displays the information to the user
intakes user interaction taps and moves
and so forth
interns those into state changes on the
model are sorry and and
allows the user to make those kind of
gestures and the controller is then
what's responsible for shuffling that
back and forth so it takes information
from the model
and shuffles it so that it can show up
in the view and then takes the user's
interaction in the view
and shuffles that back into state
updates on the model side
so that model view controller an
organizational structure for how we can
think about
the objects and their responsibilities
in our applications
so now let's take these ideas the set of
patterns that we've discussed
and talk about how they apply
in our applications how they're used to
do that we're gonna SRU
bit think through a sample application
and wind you build an application I hope
that olive you have downloaded The Hague
The Human Interface Guidelines
its in iBooks is well it's very near the
swift book if you look at this with book
and then you tap on related but you
should see
The Hague book in there in there there's
a whole section where we spend time
talking about something called an
application definition statement
many people who have unfocused
applications art able to come up with
this their architecture ends up being
very
a dispersed for whatever not well
thought through
so I like to tell people to really spend
some time thinking about this 30-second
elevator pitch
what your application is and who it's
for
so our application is going to allow
people to share simple
short updates about what's happening in
their lives
so this simple phrase here has a bunch
of architectural implications for water
application needs to look like
and some requirements that the
application has
so the application needs to share
so far I'm gonna share some information
with you and we happen to be in
different places
we need to have a network so I can take
that information push it out to the
Internet
and then you're able to pull it down
it's going to be short updates that's
worth implies there's going to be a lot
so we have a scrolling list information
and then finally what's happening and
since it's what's happening now
it needs to be fast so call our
application twinkling here's a few
ideas love seems that
this application needs to do or we might
want to do
mark items edit post add photos
so in the process is sort of thinking
through water application doesn't and
what the architecture of it is going to
be
missus or the process I go through
whenever I'm building an app
what's the application definition
statement from that I get a list
features that I think might fit in that
and then the all important step
figuring out what to say no to she had
this long list
then you run it through the filter of
what is my application about what's the
first thing that I need to focus on
what's the most important thing that I
want to focus on
and so that's gonna allow us to drop
these last three entries and we're just
going to focus on these first four
things
for our application is going to work
now let's go through and talk in a
little more detail about the application
now we have a a sort of a picture on it
so here's a wireframe at the application
we have a list updates from our friends
they have avatars and then we have this
plus button on the top
where we can add a new entry
the first thing to do is to spend some
time conceptualizing what is our
application look like
through the lens the
model-view-controller design paradigm
and the first thing I like to do is talk
about the model
in I a really good sorted first
cut approach at how to come up with what
is the model look like
I think is to write down some user
stories or maybe if you've ever use
irssi cards like
the titles are those the list of things
that you know that the application
is going to have to do and then pull the
nouns out so here we have a statement a
user can specify avatar
well that tells us user and avatar these
other statements
a user can have an entry a user can
follow a friend
so there's relationships between these
users all these items all the nouns out
on this list
tell us what the model objects are and
so from that we come up with this simple
modelleri have Quakers have friends they
have avatars and they have a list
going so that's the model
next up is the view so how we're going
to display this since we're using you
like it were on top of the IRS
and we're gonna make a beautiful
application we're going to use
a table view that table views
arranged in a composite Corsi at the
table view at the top
it has a list if table who sells the
stable you cells have a TextView
Anna image you since they are arranged
in a composite whenever this
tableview scrolls and I move its bounds
I only have to move the table view
aren't you glad you don't have to
iterate through all the table view cells
in your tableview and move them by the
appropriate amount
I do enough math without having to do
that
alright so that's the view
next up is the controller now remember
the controllers roellinger application
is to shuffle the data between a model
interview and then take state updates
and apply that back tomorrow
so our view controller is going to act
as the datasource for tableview
wherever you like he will view it has
this dotted line or weak relationship to
its
you controller and that you control or
implements the datasource protocol
sorry view controller is going to tell
the table view here's the number
sections and here's the number rose
based on interacting with the model
our view controller will also be
activated
will be told to do things by the user
interface
and will use target action of course to
make that connection so when you tap on
the plus button
it says what's my target oh my target is
this object here which happens to be the
quick view controller
what message that I send oh that's the
add a new entry message
our view controller is also responsible
for dealing with the networking stuff
so the view controller has to manage the
networking it has to be able to get the
data from the internet
turn it into objects that we can display
on the screen
we'll talk in more detail about that
shortly
so that is the model
view and controller for this initial
seen in our application
we have our public time-line view
controller which axe as the data source
for the table view and his able to get
information
from the model and shuffle that into the
view
by implementing that table view data
source protocol method
the interview I'm sorry the table view
is a composite when we scroll it
everything moves together as one
the next piece that we talked about was
adding a new entry so when user
is adding a new entry we're gonna have a
new view controller
and a new view because we have a
different way to present stuff
but the model class the senate model
classes is going to be reused we're
going to use the same classes to
represent that date
so it's a different amount shuffling or
a different kind of shuffling right
because we're shuffling data
for a particular entry into the view and
of course the viewer to view does is
different so there's different
stuff for the controller to do the model
class ends up being the same so we're
able to reuse that
so the user taps on the bun
that since the action message to its
target which is the public time I view
controller
we present to add a new entry
and in these cancel and done buttons
would be connected via target action
to the new entry view controller
now this view controller also has to
interface with the network
when user finishes insuring this new
entry in a tap Done button
we need a package at this information
push it out to the Internet it's gonna
live
on some server somewhere there's a
potential smell going on there
because now we have two controllers that
have to manage the same kinda stuff
and that's probably not good we'll talk
more about it shortly
last piece up taking our said are common
set of patterns and looking at the way
they work in this application
the UI application is of course can have
an app delegate for application and
that's gonna handle things like state
restoration
it's gonna happen there is gonna handle
background downloading and the
application becoming active in going
into the background and so forth that
whole
stack of stuff
so now we have this built and change
happens
our users come up with new things that
they want to do our designers come to us
and say hey can you change this and make
this thing do this other thing so forth
so we have our initial table view
controller and
our next to requirements that we want to
address it is to be able
to send private messages so now
we have our initial view controller
which has this networking code in it
what do you do about this new view
controller it also
needs to have networking code in it
this is really starting to be some
pretty smelly code great like we can't
we don't wanna
copy and paste this if we took the
understanding of how to download
information from that initial view
controller we could have course
copy and pasted into our new view
controller
but then what happens over time if
something changes a URL changes or who
knows what else the interface that thing
changes
and we have copy and paste code now we
fix in one place it's not going to get
updated in the other so
bad idea so instead what we'll do
is let's reef actor this and poll that
URL code
out love the view controllers and put it
into a download service
when we do that we factoring will start
off with their public time when you
controller which
probably had the debt networking code in
it to start with
will pull all that from the view
controller
into the download service
so will call download on that object
and when it's done it's gonna send back
a response
now I put a solid line in here
specifically because I want to talk
through the idea
love making the hard relationship
between these two things
the public timeline view controller has
to know the download service because
it's going to be responsible for
creating it
but if the download service also has a
hard relationship back to the public
time when you controller
then we're gonna have to add a property
that download service and it's going to
have to have a relationship to his
public timeline view controller
when we add a new view controller do we
add a new property like we don't want to
go down that path
so instead let's make that a weak
relationship
NU's delegation so notice how we took
the idea delegation that we have
in you like it and now we're applying
that to the code in our application
we're gonna define a delegate protocol
for this download service to call back
to our code so that we can customise
what happens when that download service
does things
like when it finishes downloading her or
are downloading
Jason file and so forth
now when we need to use this again
to interface with the private message
view controller it implements that
download service delegate
in the download service doesn't have to
know anything about either of those
types
other than the fact that the implement
that
protocol all right in with that much go
take a look at the demo
all right when I started writing the
demo I sorta went off the deep end and
i'd
tried to build this whole application
those building a service and
and I realized is just too much for us
to cover in the last 15
minutes or so that we have left so
instead what I've done is made and
vastly simplified
idea this application when we run it for
you now talk through what it does
so I started with the Master Detail
template and Xcode which creates for you
a table view
in that he will you when you tap on
items in their navigates to a detailed
view controller
I took out the detail view controller
just so we would have focus on this one
view controller
I added to refresh control so that when
you pull down
it kicks off to refresh to download some
information in it logs in the background
to let us know that it was successful in
downloading that information
so in in a real application for sure
gonna be processing the chase on the
comes back from that downloading doing
all sorts of fancy stuff but for demo
we're gonna be simple and just have this
have this down that happen
so let's look at the way the code works
over here
briefly so here's our you controller and
notice
its implementing all these delicate
protocols for the in issue RL stuff
we want to move that from our view
controller
over to this new object to download
service that we're gonna implement
is we don't want are you our table view
controller
to understand all these detail about how
networking works wanna captured and one
place so we can reuse it
so we're gonna go through all this code
here that does all that and just move it
now I'm not gonna make you said and
watch me type all this stuff and copy
and pasted in and have me mess it up and
have it not work
so instead I have gunship get
tags in here
boss
okay so our view controller now
no longer has this a knowledge about the
URL session and how it works we removed
all those
and move them over to our download
service we also took all that code from
in here that was
interfacing with the network and moved
that
over to our download service
and that's the URL that were using to
download and so forth
so our view controller did have all this
knowledge
and we've moved it over into our
download service now the download
service has all the information
our download service though
doesn't have any API on it yet so we
haven't made it so that we can actually
interface with it
our view controller still has to manage
making the network all right we don't
want to download service just going
rogue and downloading stuff whenever it
feels like it the view controller being
in control
how things happen with the user taking
the user's
input from the screen and turning that
into stuff that happens on the back end
we want the view controller to be in
charge of making that happen
so we need to add a couple message to
our download service
to allow it to first do the connection
creating this URL session
all the configuration stuff that goes
along with that and then we also want a
method to start that to kick it off
so we'll do another magic switch you
change it all
and/or download service now has these
two methods
connect and start in the connect method
were creating an S
a URL session configuration stuff and
then in the start method we create a
down note asking tell that to start
former master view controller
we are still kicking off
the download from our re fresh control
and of course that refresh control uses
target action
in order to make the connection between
the control
and our custom code but we've greatly
simplified what's happening in our view
controller instead having any knowledge
about
this networking it only has knowledge
kicking it off about starting in about
making it happen
alright so now
we can run the application again
and when we pull down notice here is
telling us in the log that it finished
but I really fresh item hasn't stopped
so the issue what's going on
is our downloader now has all the
knowledge about what's going on with the
downward
but no one is informing the controller
that that happened that it's finished
and so it finishes just fine but I
refresh
isn't able to stop because our view
controller doesn't know that the
download is finished
if only we knew away to customize
the behaviour reusable class of course
we do right will use delegation to make
that happen
so now we need to do is we need to
create a delegate protocol
we need to create a property on our
downloader
to have a delegate property and make
that delegate property
implement that protocol
sore download service has this method
spelled out in the in the delegate that
says
hey the download service did finish
downloading this URL
which is the original URL that was asked
for it downloaded it
to a particular URL in that last
argument
is an error saying everything is fine if
we turn if we pass until their
or hate something went wrong in this is
what happened
now we're gonna build a more
sophisticated
networking stack here what we want to do
is provide many more
delegation points many more places for
customization things like
hey I need some authentication
information other things like that or
I have finished downloading 10 bites at
the 100 bytes I'm gonna download so that
you could update the spinner
appropriately from the view controller
but we'll just leave it at this for
right now
and then in our download service
really important piece to the puzzle
is when the URL session finishes
downloading
when the the a you know we kick off the
the
download when it finishes it's going to
call back the
in this URL down the task is gonna call
back and say hand-finished
we need to make sure and tell our
delegate that that happened
so that call back
goes from our download session to the
view controller
which is then going to use that
knowledge that the download has finished
to
and refreshing we also put
the responsibility love what to do with
that document
into the view controller so if you
notice appear
further up we're doing some file moving
around taking the final movie and so
forth
in a real application this is another
place where I would create
another service probably something like
a chase on parser
and I would take that Jason parser and
say hey here's the stuff that just got
downloaded
would you please take care love parsing
it in turning into real objects
create another delegate protocol for the
Jason parser
energies on parser would call me back
and say hey everything is finished
parsing
and then that's what I want action
that's when I would actually have all
the information I need
to change the way the user interface
looks one other thing
that I that I always like to talk
through with with developers
is we have stepped over the boundary
where we
understand and can start thinking about
how you like it and foundation
are implemented so let's take a step
back and take a look at our download
service
so the download service
specifies that it implements this set of
protocols
every one of those protocols names
ins indelicate the responsibility of
anything that is a delegate is to
customize the behavior
up the object for which it is the deli
in rain so
what we are doing is specifying that we
are able to fulfil that role
now in the code I don't have to go show
it to you because there's so much code
there but in the code
I am be kind making this download
service the delegate
above the download task in Eunice URL
session
so imagine with me if you will what the
code looks like
in in this URL session or in in as
download task there's got to be a chance
to code in there somewhere
that does something very similar to this
I hope that helps
you think through like how does the
puzzle fit together how does all this
work
we do the same things that I'm asking
you to do
we define a protocol that says he hears
the customization
past years the customization points the
you have for this reusable object
if you implement this method I will call
it
at a particular time now you're building
that for your own application
your defining this download service deli
protocol
and it has a single method in it right
now that says
hey I finished downloading this stuff to
this particular URL
that would be a perfect place for us as
I said earlier to take that URL
pass it off to a Jason parser but the
Jason purser crunch on it for a little
while perhaps but the data
through core data into a database
messages back and say yes all that
information has been parsed
and all that information is sitting in
your database and you're ready to update
your table view
okay so one last piece love
stuff in the demo here that I'm not
particularly
happy with
well let me go ahead and run it again
just for funs we can see it stopping
so now we're back to the functionality
that we had before we started hacking
and slashing doing
surgery on her application alright so
one last like I said one last piece have
stuff in here that are not particularly
happy with if we go appear in the
download service
and I glance over this earlier because I
didn't wanna
confused where we were in the talk if we
go on the download service we see this
thing recalling out
to you I application shared application
giving your delegate
in there were casting that to a class
that we know about and we had to import
that header file
so now we've made our download service
dependent
honor application delegate that is
that smelly cat you don't want to do
that because you're at Delhi it
its responsibility is not providing
information to download services
the application delegate is supposed to
be about maintaining the relationship
between your application
and the rest to the OS the methods on
there are things like
I'm about to go in the background I came
back from the background
that's the stuff that you should focus
on for your application delegate
I see this pattern repeated in many
people's code
and it's a really bad idea if you're
casting
shared application application delegate
to your class and then you're sending
your messages
that's a bad idea so let's do a little
bit more
cleanup to fix that up
so a couple things that we did the first
part is
adding an additional call back into our
delegate protocol
so we added a new method download
service did finish with identifiers
so that's gonna let the download
services delegate no
that this download has finished
that's related to this particular
identifiers
and bring a call that in the same place
where we were
calling out to the UI application
delegate then in our view controller
in the implementation that additional
delegate method
we're going to invoke that background
session completion handler
not to go too far into the into the
details around there because it's not
germane to
talking about delegation but that's just
a call back that we tell the OS
hey we're finished processing this
download and you can take a snapshot of
the application
I have a link to the talk on an issue
are all session from last year
and there was also one this year that
has a lot more detail about how all that
works
now we have gotten rid of the dependence
from our download service
to our application delegate so we no
longer have this sort of Marion if these
ideas
or placing too much responsibility on
the application Delhi
the application delegate is responsible
for one thing
keep it focused on that one thing and
don't start spreading it out
throughout your whole application in
using it for many different things that
do not
included Center responsibilities so in
summary
there are lots of remarks in iowa's
but the cool thing is that once you
understand these common patterns that
are used throughout all these frameworks
delegation datasource target action
responder chain
once you understand that in one place
you understand across
the whole stack of remarks she to
leverage your learning
understanding these patterns gives you
power to use
all these frameworks in your application
and the next thing I want to say
in terms of summary is just go for it
there
I have talked to many other developers
who spend time
like fretting about is this the new
controller is this thing a model is this
thing %uh view
just go for it build stuff go out there
and make
amazing stuff you can always re factory
like we did here
not quite live on stage but pretty close
you can always do that so just make
stuff
and you will learn so much from doing
that alright so for more information you
can talk to my buddy Jake
on there's also the Deaf forums here's a
link to those related sessions I was
telling you about the talk this
afternoon
on advanced I was application
architecture patterns has
tons a fantastic stuff in it and it's
got a little bit think a little bit as I
information about swift and some other
new patterns that we're gonna see emerge
because I've
the new language which I'm really
excited about and then here are two
other talks
from previous years that have more
information thank you very much for
being here and I hope you have a great
rest your WBC