&gt;&gt; All right.
Good morning everyone.
Welcome to this morning's
session.
My name is Mark Miller.
I'm an iTunes Engineering
Manager on the store
and we're going to be talking
about affiliate tools
for app developers.
Now, just in case anybody is new
to the program, or unfamiliar
with what it's for, we're going
to go over a quick overview
of how it works,
what its purpose is
and how you can use it.
It's also been a couple years
since we've last presented here,
so we'll talk about
what's new in the program
and what new things
you can do with it.
And finally, there's going
to be a deep dive on tools
and services that you can use
to interact with the program.
So first off, we kind of
need a cast of characters.
Who's involved with
the affiliate program
and how do they interact
with each other?
As you might guess, they
are the customer, yours,
and the iTunes Stores and they
are talking to you and talking
to the iTunes Store,
but what might not be
so obvious is behind the scenes,
there's an affiliate network.
And the affiliate network
mediates the interaction
between you and the store,
and the affiliate network is
where you go to sign
up, set up payments,
manage and track your campaign
performance and go to check
on any support issues you have.
So what's it for?
The key thing that
you're trying to do
with the affiliate program
is to drive customers
to your apps and other content.
So you might have a game
and perhaps you've
released a sequel to it.
You want to promote
that app and you can do
that using the affiliate
program.
Similarly, you might
already have a website used
to promote your apps and you
can affiliate those links
and start getting the benefits
of the affiliate
program that way.
But it doesn't have to be your
own apps that you're promoting.
You can promote other
app developer's apps
and other content, and this is
pretty much all of the content
on the Music Store --
excuse me, on the store.
So that's music, movies,
TV shows, books, podcasts,
anything you can think of
is supported by the program.
And the Use Case here is
-- there's pretty much --
there's a wide Use Case for
what you can do with it.
You might have a soundtrack
that's related to your game
and you can promote that.
Or if you're a productivity
app, and there's a similar app
that works well with it,
you can promote that from
within the app or
on your website.
Most of all, you are trying to
connect your users with content
that they're going
to want to download.
They're -- you're interrupting
their workflow a little bit
to send them to the store,
so make sure it counts.
Make sure that link is relevant
to what they're interested in
and something that they're
going to want to buy.
Now, the key to the
program is that all
of your links need a
little bit of data on them
to function correctly.
So you add a bit
of affiliate data
to an existing iTunes
Store link and that's it.
You're ready to go with
the affiliate program.
In return for marketing
and promoting the iTunes
and App Stores, you
earn a commission
on sales generated
from that referral.
For you, you get the benefit
of tracking the effectiveness
of your marketing
with our tools.
And best of all, this works
on both web and in your app,
so there's no reason
to limit the usage
of the affiliate
program to the web.
You can also do it
within your app.
Now, under the covers, those
links are going to be clicked on
or tapped on in iOS and the
data from the URL is going
to be copied into a cookie,
and that cookie lives
for 24 hours on the
user's device.
And it's important
that you realize
that the data is
tracking the cookie
and not somewhere on the server.
This means that if the user
clicks on one of your links
and then moves to
her iPhone or iPad
to continue browsing the
store that any purchase made
on the device will
not credit to you.
So it's the same device that the
tap happens on and the purchase.
Now, once the purchase
happens, the data is copied
into the database and
the database is synced
to the affiliate network,
and that's how you get paid.
Now the terms are really great.
You earn 7% commission
on all sales.
That means that if you
link to, for example,
an app and the user winds
up buying another
app, you get credited.
If the user actually leaves
the App Store and goes
to buy something on the Music
Store, you also get credited.
And it's 7% for all
sales within 24 hours.
Now this is kind of important.
It's a case of last one wins.
You are operating in
an ecosystem of a lot
of other developers and it's
whoever is the most recent
referral gets the
credit for the sale.
So if some if a user
taps on your link
and then three hours
later taps on another link
from another affiliate,
that affiliate gets credited
for the next 24 hours
worth of sales.
Now best of all, this
is a seamless experience
from the point of
view of your users.
An affiliate link
looks and acts just
like a regular iTunes
Store link.
So here, we've got an
example of Cut the Rope,
and they're promoting the sequel
to their app, Cut the Rope 2.
So when the user taps on Get
it Now, an affiliate link,
everything acts just
as you expect.
The store carousel's in
and they can preview, buy,
look at reviews, look at screen
shots and browse the store.
And again, after they've
clicked this, it's not just apps
that are credited to that
affiliate, its music,
movies, TV shows, all of it.
So that's the affiliate
program in a nutshell.
Let's talk about what's happened
in the last couple years.
Most importantly, we have had
a massive territory expansion.
This was the state of the world,
or at least the affiliate
world in 2012.
We were on three continents
and we had program
support in 45 countries.
Since then, we have
introduced the affiliate program
to 147 countries.
That's a 3X expansion and 50
of those countries
happened in 2014 alone.
Now, that's pretty great.
You're promoting your apps
and other content worldwide
with the affiliate
program, but best of all,
you only need one network
to work in the entire world.
If you're familiar with the
program from a couple years ago,
you had to sign up with
one program to work
in the America's, a second
program to work in Europe,
and a third program to work
in Australia and New Zealand.
Nowadays, one network
gets you worldwide access
to 147 countries.
This is really huge.
Now that means one sign
up, one payment set up,
all your tax information,
all that sort
of financial transaction stuff
that you need to get started
with the program,
you do that once
and you're working
across the globe.
Even better, we have a
common link structure
for the entire world.
Now this is what a normal,
unaffiliated iTunes
Store link looks like.
You can see that it's
in the U.S. storefront.
It's an app called iMovie
and there's the iTunes
Store content ID at the end.
It used to be that if you
wanted to add affiliate data
to this URL, you would
end up with something
like these two options,
and you would have to do it
in a region specific manner.
So the URL on top was
for the America's.
The URL on the bottom
was for Europe.
These URL's are messy.
They're confusing.
They're even suspicious.
If a user were to
look at the link
that you're calling
an iTunes link
and examine it a little more
closely, they would say oh,
I'm this is I'm not sure
what I'm clicking on anymore.
They might be turned
away by that.
So no more of that.
Nowadays, we take an
existing store link
and we add just a
small bit of data
and the host is still the
same; iTunes.apple.com.
So what we're adding here
to the base URL is a small
bit of affiliate data.
The first part of that is
the AT Query parameter.
This stands for affiliate token
and the value is
essentially your user ID
within the affiliate program.
This is how we identify you and
this is how you get credited
for purchases made after
a user taps on your link.
So it's very important
to get this one right.
Also, in the affiliate data,
is the CT Query parameter,
and CT stands for
campaign token,
and this is an optional query
parameter so you don't have
to put it on, but
you can do a lot
of really important
things with it.
If you have a campaign that
you want to track separately
from the rest of your
marketing efforts,
you can use this
campaign and it will show
up differently in our UI's.
So for example, you might have
a campaign for your website.
You might have a campaign,
a separate campaign
for the interior
pages of your website.
You could have campaigns
for each email blast
that you send out.
If you're doing online
advertising
and you're buying keywords,
you can have a campaign
for each of those.
You could have campaigns
for links within your apps.
You can do a lot of analysis
to find out what works
and what doesn't with
your marketing efforts.
Now it's important to note
one thing about these URL's.
I said that there's one
link structure worldwide,
but content is not necessarily
available around the world.
The situation for
apps is pretty easy.
Most apps are available
in every country.
But if you're linking to
music or movies or books,
the rights may not carry over
from one storefront to another,
so you need to if you're
trying to send your user
to a particular piece of
content, it's best to check
if it's available in their
storefront before you present
them with that link.
Another common mistake that
you make when first interacting
with the program is getting
your query strings wrong.
The URL's are fairly simple,
but there's a few gotcha's
that you need to avoid.
The first thing to make
sure of is to identify
if there's already
query string on the URL.
Now the query string, the start
of the query string is
identified by the question mark,
and if there's no question mark
and you blindly append your
affiliate data using ampersand
that URL probably won't
even load for your user.
They're just going to have
an error, so don't do that.
What you want to do is
check for the question mark
and if it's not present on the
string, add the question mark
and then your affiliate data.
Now the reverse is
also a gotcha,
and this is just as important.
If there's already a
question mark in the URL,
that means that there's
an existing query string,
you need to use the ampersand
as a delimiter instead
of using another question mark.
If you click on -- if
a user clicks on a URL
with two question marks
in it, it's not going
to parse correctly
and you're not going
to be credited with
the referral.
So the key thing is look
for the question mark
and if it's already
there, use ampersand
to attach your affiliate data.
Now I mentioned one network.
One of the key benefits of
having one network worldwide is
that you can have a
global unified view
of how your marketing is going.
Now this is a dashboard
that shows you
in real time who's
clicking and what,
what links they're clicking on
-- excuse me, not who's clicking
but the type of links
that they're clicking on.
So the first thing you'll
notice about this UI is
that you can track clicks
over time and you can zoom
in from a year's worth of data
all the way down to a day.
And again, these graphs are
updating in near real time.
So in this case, we're looking
at the month over month view
and our current month
is plotted in orange
against the previous
months' performance.
So you can see if your
graph is trending down
or if it's different
compared month over month
and adjust your marketing
campaign accordingly.
Also of note is that the
conversion rate is mentioned
here and you should pay close
attention to this value.
If the conversion
rate starts diving,
that might represent a problem
with your marketing efforts.
Maybe your URL's are not really
exciting users into buying,
or maybe there's a
problem with your links
and something needs
investigating.
So keep an eye on that one.
Also on the global
dashboard, you can zoom in
and get a per country
view of things.
The if you're operating
in more than one country,
you can see how well you're
doing in the U.S. as opposed
to the UK or in South
America or wherever.
Also, if you are promoting
more than one type of content;
so for example, apps and
books or movies and music,
you can slice and dice and
get reports on how each one
of those is performing.
So there's a lot
of rich data here.
And furthermore, there's
more utility up at the top.
You can see additional tools for
interacting with the program.
You can get more in-depth
reports of what's going on.
You can manage your
payments and other settings.
So make sure to check out all
the options that this provides
because it's a great way to
actually see how you're doing
with your marketing efforts.
So that's the Global Dashboard.
It's a single, unified view
of a single network that's
operating in 147 countries.
I can't tell you how
excited I am about the fact
that we have one network that
lets you operate worldwide.
It's a huge simplification
of what we used to have
to do, so very exciting.
Hopefully, at this point
you are similarly excited.
You want to you're ready to go.
Go sign up with your program and
you want to know how next to --
what the next steps are
in terms of integrating.
So for that, we've got a
Tools and Services section.
We're going to start
talking about simple tools
to get you started quickly.
These are things that you don't
need a computer science degree
to work with.
It's maybe just a matter
of creating a couple links
and adding them to an
email or to your website
or somewhere in your app.
These tools are really great
for the one offs the
manual sort of set up.
There's also more
advanced tools.
So if you want to find what's
going on really in the now
on the store, and promote
that sort of content,
these tools will
let you do that.
We also provide Smart
App Banners.
Smart App Banners allow
you to promote your app
from your websites in
a very seamless way.
There's a lot of power there,
and in the right situation,
can be very, very useful.
The Store Kit Product Sheet
and iTunes Radio have been
recently added to the program,
and we'll talk about how
to work with those and how
to get the most out of that.
And finally, we'll finish
with the Collection feature
that allows you to define
dynamic playlists for the store.
This can be really useful
for customizing content
for your users.
Let's get started
with the simple stuff.
The simplest of all
is the Link Maker.
This is a simple search
box where you can come in
and type a search term,
get results and get links.
Especially if you
click into Link Maker
from within the affiliate
network, your URL that you come
in with is going to have
all your affiliate data
pre-populated so you
don't need to worry
about adding the affiliate
data to the URL itself.
You don't need to worry
about question marks
and ampersands and
URL encodings.
It's all dramatically easier.
So in this case, we're going
to do a search for Ed Sheeran.
He's a UK singer/songwriter with
a lot of awesome great songs,
and we can see that his
albums are available
in the research results
and by taping on one
of these search results, we
get a nice pop up of HTML
that we can drop
right into a webpage.
Not only that, this
HTML has a number
of different options
for the formatting.
So this is the small
format for the Badge.
If you prefer a large Badge,
we've got HTML to do that.
Similarly, if you just want
to have a raw text link,
maybe this is for an HTML email
blast or something like that,
you've got the raw text
available, as well.
So that's Link Maker
in a nutshell.
It's simple.
It's all UI oriented.
It's a bit of HTML
that you can drop in.
It's a great way if you haven't
started and you only want --
interested in linking to a few
pieces of content, to find that.
But maybe you've already
got a website up and running
and you've got a
couple hundred links
to various pieces
of iTunes content.
In that case, you might be
interested in Auto Link Maker.
Auto Link Maker is a way to on
the fly, attach affiliate data
to existing iTunes
links within a webpage.
It's a small bit of Java scripts
that you paste into your page
and on load, it actually
finds all of the links
to the iTunes Store and
when they're clicked,
the Event Handler attaches
affiliate data to the URL
and you get credit for the links
that you're already
sending to the page.
So if you don't want to go in
and edit hundreds or thousands
of pages in your content website
to you know annotate all these
links with affiliate data,
Auto Link Maker can
really help you out there.
So that's the simple
stuff that you can do.
You might be more interested
in the advanced stuff
for finding content,
and for that,
one of the best tools are
the Search and Lookup API's,
and this provides metadata
access on the web up to date
and very, very easy to do so.
There are two main actions.
The first is Search.
This is probably
like you expect.
You can find content by name.
If you know the artist name or
the song name or your user wants
to type something in and find
specific pieces of content,
you can do that with
the Search API.
The Lookup API allows you
to cross reference your ID's
with the iTunes Store.
So you might have a set of
content that you're interested
in and you know the
iTunes Store content ID's,
you can get the latest data
about that content
using the Lookup API.
And all these responses
are in the JSON format.
That's Java script
object notation.
It's pretty much
the lingua franca
for data transfer on the web.
So let's take a look
at the search API.
The only thing that's
required to get started
with the search API is
the term Query Parameter,
and this of course,
is the search term
that you're interested in.
But there's a lot of
modifiers available
and you could do some
really interesting stuff
to find specific
pieces of content.
You can also change the nature
of the content that comes back.
So the Language Query
Parameter allows you
to specify the localization
of the response.
So let's say you're searching in
Canada for a piece of content,
but you know you want to
localize it to French.
You can pass in Language
equals FR
and get a result back in French.
Media is a constraint
for the search itself.
If you only are interested
in movies or only interested
in books, you can specify
Media equals Movies
or Media equals Books and
get content back that way.
But what if you're actually
just interested not just
in say music, but you're
interested in songs,
or you're interested
specifically in albums.
You can use the Entity
Query Parameter
to specify a very
specific piece of content
or collection of
content that way.
Attribute is another
query parameter
that focuses the search
term on a specific case.
So the search will only be
applied to a specific portion
of the content, and this would
allow you to for example,
if your query is for
Madonna, you might be looking
for the musician Madonna,
and you could use Attribute
equals Artist's name
and the searches would only be
for artists whose
name contains Madonna.
On the other hand,
maybe you're looking
for the Beatles' popular
song Lady Madonna.
You can specify Attribute
equals Song term
and get song results back.
The Limit Query Parameter is
another one where it can come
in handy in many situations.
By default, you're going
to get 50 results back
for a given query, but
if you only want five,
there's no reason to spend time
parsing the results and waiting
for the response for
a larger data set.
So you can either decrease
or increase the size
of the response set you get.
And finally, there's Callback.
Callback is very useful for web
developers if you are trying
to do something that operates
within the Java excuse me,
the browser security model.
So if you're running
Java script in a browser,
you may not have access to make
a call to iTunes.apple.com.
But you can use the
Callback Query parameter
to essentially call a function
with the result of the query.
This can be very useful and just
about every Java script library
like J Query, what have
you, supports Callback.
And all these responses,
once when you do a query,
all the results are in the JSON
format and they're dictionaries
of content sorted by relevancy.
And relevancy is an
important concept.
It's not -- it's our best guess
at what you're actually
searching for.
So it depends on how
appropriate is the content
to the search term.
And it also depends on other
factors like popularity.
So that can be -- so your
search queries are not
necessarily static.
They're not going
to be set in time.
If another piece of content
becomes more popular,
it might move from rank number
three to rank number one
and your search results will
change even though the query
parameter is the same.
Now the Lookup API uses a lot
of similar query parameters
to the Search API, but the
only thing required is an ID,
and the ID can be an
iTunes Store content ID
or it can be a list, comma
separated of those same ID's.
The Lookup API also supports
other identifier standards.
So if you have UPC's for albums,
or ISBN's for books, or ISRC's,
or any number of other
standard ID schemes,
you can pass those in as well.
So we support similar
modifiers to the search API.
Language is a, as
you would expect,
Callback is as you would expect.
The results are the exact
same content dictionaries
and you can pass them into
some function you define
in Java script.
Entity is slightly
different in the Lookup API.
So you're passing in
one or more content ID's
and you can use the Entity
ID to actually navigate up
or down the content tree.
We'll go into how you
can use this in a bit.
And again, the results
are JSON dictionaries
so it's the exact same content
whether you're using Search API
or Lookup API.
And the responses you get back
are very, very rich in data.
Now I know this is a wall
of text, but there's a lot
of information here that you
can use to populate your UI's
or to populate your
recommendations.
There's the expected.
You can get the artist ID, the
artist name, the album name,
the song name, app
name, what have you,
but there's also
you can get the --
what's the most recent
version on the store?
What are the release
notes for that version?
When was it released?
How much is it?
What's the file size?
Maybe you only want to recommend
small files to your users
on some sort of constrained
device.
You can see screen
shots, album artwork.
What is the user rating for
this particular content?
What is the age rating
for the content?
All this can really be useful if
you're trying to populate a UI.
So that said, let's go
through a couple examples.
Let's say we are developing
a music app and we want
to show the user a search API
so that they can find
content on the store.
So we might have a search box
that they can type something in,
and we would put that
content into this sort of URL.
And I want to highlight
that we're specifying the U.S.
Storefront and we're passing
in the term that
we're trying to search
for in the query parameter term.
In this case, the user
has typed in The A Team.
Excuse me.
Now this query alone
is going to be --
what you're going to
get is basically one
of Ed Sheeran's popular songs
from the past couple years,
which is called The A Team, and
that's going to be very popular,
so that's going to be
at the top of the list.
Following that, you're
going to see something
like the The A Team's movie,
which came out a
couple years ago
and is second behind
the song content.
And following that, you're
going to get about 45 results
for the The A Team TV
show from the '80's.
Now, The A Team show is awesome.
Who doesn't like the The A Team.
That's great.
But we're a music app so
we might not be interested
in getting TV show results.
Now the simple thing to do
in this case would
just be attach a limit.
We can say "Oh, well I'm only
interested in the music stuff.
The music stuff is
ranking highly,
so I'll put Limit equals 1 and
I only get one result back."
That's great, but
what if another sequel
to the The A Team's movie comes
out and suddenly that's highest.
Our music app is suddenly
showing content for movies,
and that wouldn't be good.
So that's one option.
There's a couple other
things we could do.
We could say well, we're
only interested in searching
for the song term The A Team or
we're only interested in songs
that are related to the
search term The A Team.
But that's not really -- that's
going to limit us a little bit,
because what if we want to
show albums or what if we want
to search on albums that
are called The A Team.
There's probably
several of those.
So for our use case, this is
probably not such a great idea.
Instead, we need to find the
right thing to specify the type
of content we're
interested in, and here,
it's Media equals Music.
We're a music app.
We want people to be able
to search for artists
or albums or songs, whatever.
So we can specify
Media equals Music
and we get just the
results we're looking for.
So we run this query and we
get the results we want back,
which is great.
Now, this is just one piece of
results, or one result back.
Let's say our UI, we might
have an album focus rather
than on a specific song.
And let's say that
our UI we want
to know how much does the
content cost in the storefront.
And furthermore, we want
to show them all the songs
on that album in
that storefront.
Now, I like to say that
if you have a problem,
if no one else can help,
and if your problem relates
to content metadata
on the iTunes Store,
maybe you can hire
the Lookup API.
In this case, we have
figured out that our user is
in Great Britain and so we would
just change the country code
in the URL to be GB, Great
Britain, and we're passing
in the ID of the
collection itself.
Now the Lookup API has
a very simple model
for content on the store.
There are tracks,
which are individual,
indivisible pieces of content.
So this would be songs, books,
movies, TV episodes, apps.
There are collections, which
are albums, TV seasons,
that sort of thing,
and there are artists.
These are musicians, actors, app
developers, that sort of thing.
Three levels, and you
can use the Lookup API
to navigate that hierarchy.
So we're passing in the
collection ID or the album ID
to the Lookup API, and we're
going to get results back to see
if it's available for
sale in Great Britain.
What we're not going to see
is what tracks are available
on that URL.
What we need to do in that
case is attach the entity
that we're looking for and the
Entity equals Song will tell the
Lookup API okay, give me back
the results that I asked for,
but also give me back the
songs that are on that album.
And here, we get the awesome
results back that you expect.
So we get the album name, which
is Plus, and the first track
on that album is the The
A Team and so on the rest
of the songs on that album.
You can also go -- navigate
up the content hierarchy,
so if you've got a song and
you want to know the artist,
you can pass in Entity equals
Artist and track that that way.
So there's a lot you can
do with the Lookup API.
It's all up to date.
You might want to know
about price changes
for particular things.
The Lookup API allows
you to do that.
Now, that said, you might have
slightly bigger needs in terms
of data, and for that, we have
the Enterprise Partner Feeds,
or EPF as we commonly call them.
These are bulk metadata
and it covers virtually
all iTunes Store content,
and this is very much for --
intended for big data needs.
And when I say big
data, it's a lot.
It's something like if you
download the full data set
for this week; it's
going to be 10 gigabytes
of textual data compressed.
So it's not for the faint of
heart, but it can be very useful
if you're trying to
establish an understanding
of the entire iTunes universe.
Within the feeds
are multiple files
and the files represent
database tables
in a relational database sense.
So there is for example,
an artist table representing
artists; you know musicians,
app developers and the like.
There's an application
table for iPhone apps
and Mac apps, that
sort of thing.
And as you might expect
if you are familiar
with relational databases,
there's a relational
artist application table
that represents which
artists produced which apps.
So you can ingest this data
into a relational database
or other data store for analysis
and run your queries that way.
And again, it's aimed
at organizations
that have really
deep data needs.
There's a lot of data.
There's pricing for
all countries
that the iTunes Store supports
and analyzing that and dealing
with the data, especially
on an ongoing basis can
be really a huge effort.
Fortunately, we do have
an Importer script.
The script is available as a
Python app and it's intended
to ingest a feed into
a MYSQL database,
but it's the sample code
is open, so if you'd like,
you can provide a different
back end and maybe write
to a dupe HDFS or something like
that if your needs go that way.
So the Enterprise Partner
feeds; it's a great way
to get the whole content
database for iTunes.
You can do a lot with it,
but it takes some doing.
Slightly simpler
is the RSS feeds.
These are dynamic feeds for
kind of what's hot in a store.
And by that I mean, you've
got a couple options.
You can see what's most
popular for each piece
of content and in each genre.
What's selling really
well right now?
What's new, what's
recently added,
whether this is you know the hot
new single from today's artists
or maybe a piece of an album
that has been out of the store
for decades and is
just arriving now.
That's shows up in the New
and Recently added feeds.
You can see featured content;
what's actually showing
up on the store right
now, what's a user see
when they open iTunes to the
main page and check that out.
And finally, you can
see customer reviews
for a particular
piece of content.
What are people saying about it?
There's -- if you want to track
your own apps' performance,
you can see recent customer
reviews using that RSS feed.
RSS is available in Atom format.
That's pretty much the
standard for RSS these days.
It's also available in JSON if
you don't want to parse a bunch
of XML you can get a JSON
format returned to you
and ingest it that way.
So that's the advanced stuff.
There's all this and more
is very well documented
on the website and
we'll have a URL for you
at the end of the session.
Smart App Banners are a way for
you to cross reference your app
from a website, and you've
probably seen this browsing the
web with the Mobile Safari.
You link to a website and
this little banner slides down
and allows you to download the
app if you haven't already,
or open it if you've got
it installed, or dismiss it
if you're actually not
interested in the app.
So from the user's perspective,
it's really powerful.
It's -- if you want it, it's
there, and if you don't,
it gets out of the way.
What it does allow you,
the developer to do,
is to show your content from
your website in a native,
custom experience that
your app can provide
that Mobile Safari maybe can't.
So this is really powerful
if you want to show or --
have people look at the content
on your website in
your custom app.
And again, if a user is not
interested, a simple tap
and it goes away and
they're not bothered by it.
So how do we integrate
with that?
It's actually fairly simple.
You drop a simple metatag
into the head of your webpage,
and the metatag has your
app ID defined in it.
That's pretty obvious.
We've got to know
how to find it.
And when Mobile Safari
sees that,
it's going to fetch the
content, get the latest price
and show it to the user.
You can also pass in
your affiliate data.
So here we've got our affiliate
token, which defines us
to the affiliate program, and
we're setting the campaign token
as Smart Banner so that we can
see how many people are actually
clicking on the Smart
Banner from our website.
Now the app argument is actually
a really important piece
of data here.
If we are running a news website
or a music recommendation
website,
and we're asking the user
to leave Mobile Safari,
leave all that context and
launch into this custom app,
we don't want to lose -- we
don't want them to, you know,
start at the home page
of our site again.
The app argument is
actually provided to the app
on a command line and you
can see the same content
that the user was
looking at on the store.
So it's a way, you know,
it's easy, easy integration
without really interrupting
the flow of things.
So that's Smart App Banner.
If you've got a large website,
it's a very useful tool
for cross referencing
your website and your app.
The Store Kit Product Sheet is a
brand new feature that we've got
and for the affiliate program.
It actually exists since
iTunes 6 and allows you
to show iTunes Store content
without actually leaving your --
the workflow that
your user was in.
So for an example, we've
got here on Twitter,
the user sees a link to
the iTunes Store and taps
on this icon and the store sheet
slides up and allows the user
to do all the expected things
that you would do in the store.
So you can read reviews.
You can look at screen shots.
You can buy it right
then and there.
Most importantly,
when they're done,
they can dismiss the store
-- or the Store Sheet,
and they're right back in the
app on the page that they were
in before, so there's no
double tap to the home screen
and going back to your app.
It's all right in the same flow.
Now the Store Sheet, as I
said, has existed in iTunes 6,
but only recently have we added
it to the commission structure.
So that means if you
add affiliate data
to the Store Sheet, you're
going to get paid that same 7%
over 24 hours that
you did before.
And to go over a demo of how we
can use the Store Kit Product
Sheet in our apps, I'm inviting
my friend Rick Rubenstein
up to show us how to use
Xcode and drop it in.
&gt;&gt; Thank you Mark.
So I'm Rick Rubenstein.
I write tools and automation for
the iTunes store and App Store
and other related products.
And Mark asked me to
put together a quick app
to show how the Store
Kit product works
out in the lobby
before the session.
Kidding, I wrote it a
little while before that.
So let me switch
over to iOS here.
So I'm going to fire up the
app that I wrote right now
and then I'll explain how
it was built afterwards.
So here we have your typical
stick figure doing a juggling
trick app.
I'm sure you all have
several of these loaded
on your own iOS devices.
And if I'm a user and I'm
mesmerized by this juggler,
I might say to myself you
know, I would like some sort
of a juggling related game.
Oh look, there's a button
right here in this very app
that will let me
get that content
from in this case,
the App Store.
So if I tap on that
link, it will bring
up the Store Kit Product
Sheet, just as Mark showed,
and in the case, the Store Kit
Product Sheet is displaying a
juggling themed ball app.
Now the key thing here is that
while it may look as if I'm
in the App Store right now,
the Juggling Dude App is still
running there in the background.
So if I had wanted to
when I brought that up,
I could've actually
decided to buy this app.
I'm not going to do that
right now because I'm cheap,
but if I were an actual
customer, I might do that.
And then you, the affiliate,
would receive credit
for that purchase.
I'm going to bring
this up one more time.
Now if I had decided
to click on --
to tap on the store
link in the upper right,
then the user would be
taken to the App Store.
That same content would
be displayed and anything
that that user bought within
the 24 hour bounty window, you,
the affiliate, would
receive a commission
on all those purchases.
So I'm going to switch over now
and show you what
actually happened there.
So here we have the
new affiliate dashboard
that Mark showed before,
and this is live in Safari,
and you can see that
there are the clicks
that I made during the demo.
They've already showed
up, the taps that I made.
This bump here is when I
was rehearsing beforehand.
And so this shows the near
real time tracking of all
of the affiliate data.
So I'm going to put this
away and bring up Xcode
and show exactly how you can go
about putting the Store Kit
Product Sheet in your own apps.
It's very simple.
So the first think you need
to make sure you do is link
against the Store Kit framework.
This is a public
framework that is available
to any iOS developer,
and it lets you interact
with the iTunes Store, the
App Store in various ways.
In this case, the way is by
the Store Kit Product Sheet.
So here we have the header
for our main view controller
and again, just showing here
that we are importing
the Store Kit framework
that lets us access the
Store Kit Product Sheet.
Sorry, this is all objective
so you haven't had a chance
to write it in SWF just yet.
So here we have the
implementation
for the view controller,
and this is the key
method right here.
This is the method
that I have defined
on the view controller class,
which I've called simply
Store Sheet for Product;
takes three parameters, the
iTunes ID, the affiliate token
and the campaign token.
Now this is the new
difference in iOS 8.
As Mark mentioned, the Store Kit
Product Sheet itself has been
available since iOS
6 but previously,
you could not include
the affiliate data.
Only one parameter was accepted,
which was the iTunes ID.
So now you can add
the affiliate token.
That's your usual affiliate
token that identifies you,
and the campaign token,
which as Mark mentioned,
can be any string up to
40 characters in length
that you can use to identify
your different campaigns,
group your data however
you want to analyze it.
So I take these three
parameters and I put them
into a standard NS dictionary.
Move this so you
can see this better.
Simple dictionary; these
are symbolic constants
that are defined in the
Store Kit framework.
The SK Store product parameter
iTunes item identifier is the
iTunes ID.
That's this one that you
passed in and the two new ones,
the product parameter
affiliate token
and the product parameter
campaign token.
Those are optional.
You don't need to include them,
but since you are an affiliate,
you probably do want
to include them
so that you earn
your commissions.
So the next thing you need
to do is actually create
to the view controller.
You do that using a standard
objective C, alloc init model,
which you're probably
familiar with and you need
to set a delegate for it,
which will be called back
when it's time to
dismiss the sheet.
And in this case, we're
simply setting the delegate
to ourselves, the same view
control object that we're using.
So here's the key
call right here.
We need to load the
product into the controller.
So this is the method
on the Store Kit View
Product Controller.
Load product with parameters.
Parameters is the
dictionary we just created
that contains again, the
iTunes ID, the affiliate token
and the campaign token.
It also takes a completion
block,
which is the standard
objective C block,
which will return a
result, simply yes or no
as to whether it successfully
loaded and in the case
that it didn't successfully
load for some reason;
say that you somehow had an
incorrect piece of content
that didn't actually
exist on the store,
there's an error parameter.
And in the block, we define
what we do in these two cases.
In this case, if
there's an error,
we're just logging it normally.
In an actual app, you
would probably want
to display some sort of dialogue
or UI to the user saying
that this content for
whatever reason failed
to load in the sheet.
And if it successfully loaded,
here we're simply
logging that it loaded.
Normally you wouldn't
need to do anything
in that case, just go on.
So at this point, you
have loaded the product
into the sheet but you
haven't actually displayed it.
So that's what this call is
here, so we call on ourself,
which is our view controller,
present the sheet controller.
Animated, you normally
want a yes,
and that also takes
a completion block.
And in this case again,
we aren't doing anything
in particular in the
completion block.
Just for reference, we're
logging that we completed.
One more important method here
is Product View Controller
Did Finish.
This is the call back method
that gets called whenever the
sheet action is complete either
by the user clicking cancel,
clicking outside of the sheet
or going elsewhere
from the sheet.
And this is where you
actually dismiss the sheet
to get it to go away.
Otherwise, it will remain up.
The cancel action won't
appear to have done anything.
And this is simply
the IB action,
the Interface Builder action
that we tied to the button
that was in the top of the
app and simply in this case,
preloads it with the iTunes ID
of that juggling pinball app
that I showed, and the affiliate
token and the campaign token.
The code for getting the guy to
do the juggling trick is left
as an exercise for the viewer.
So that's the Store
Kit Product Sheet.
It's very simple to implement.
It's just a couple of calls
and it's pretty powerful
in conjunction with
the affiliate program.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Back to you, Mark.
&gt;&gt; All right.
Thanks very much, Rick.
That was awesome.
So like he said, Store Kit
Product Sheet, you can do a lot
with it and best of
all, for your users,
it's very unintrusive,
so take a look.
Next up on our list of things
to talk about is iTunes Radio.
Now iTunes Radio launched
recently and even more recently,
we have added it to
the affiliate program,
which means that if you link
to an iTunes Radio station,
you get credited
for that referral.
And again, it's very easy to do.
Here's another example using
our friend Ed Sheeran and we're
in the Sound Hound app,
and they've got a link
down near the bottom of
that links to iTunes Radio,
and when the user taps on that
the radio station is going
to be created and added to
their stations and the song
that the radio station
starts with begins to play.
So this is a great
way to tell your users
or to recommend a certain
set of content to your users.
Maybe they don't want to buy
it but they want to listen
to music that's inspired by
a particular artist or song.
You can get them into the
iTunes Radio experience
and listening to
music immediately.
Best of all, this is supported
with the affiliate program
with the same terms
as everything else.
So 7% over 24 hours, and
that applies not just
to purchases made within
the iTunes Radio app,
but any other store on that same
device where the cookie exists.
So that means music of
course, apps, books, movies,
all the rest are all supported
under the affiliate program.
Now to construct a
link to iTunes Radio,
we've added some functionality
to the Search and Lookup API's
so that the content result
that you see will have links
to the radio stations
themselves.
So here, we're looking for Ed
Sheeran and in the result set
that we get back, we're
looking for an artist,
the JSON has a radio station URL
and you can use that special URL
to launch into the
iTunes Radio application.
You would of course, have to add
your affiliate data to this URL
as we've been discussing.
So that's iTunes Radio.
It's a great set of music
for users to listen to
and you get a bonus
for any purchases made
after clicking that link.
We're going to end up talking
today about collections
and collections are something
you might be familiar
with from previous talks.
It used to be called Web IMix,
but this is a dynamic playlist
that is defined entirely
by a URL,
and here's what it looks like.
This is a collection
we've defined
by creating a special URL
and we've set the title.
We've set the description.
Now there's a limit on what
kind of text you can put
in the description,
but it's fairly broad.
And finally, we can
actually define the content
of the playlist itself.
So here we've got four
songs by Ed Sheeran
and the user can buy each
of these individually
or tap a single click and
buy the whole thing at once.
So how do we do this?
The -- to create a collection
like to you need set
something up beforehand.
What you need in addition to
the normal affiliate signup is
to get a special
collection account with us.
We will tell you a
special web developer ID
and a shared secret, and
the shared secret is used
to cryptographically assign
these URL's so we know
who the author is of that title
and description and the content.
Collections support songs,
albums, movies, TV shows
and music videos, so you can
have kind of a wide ranging set
of content that you link to,
and this could actually
be pretty high value.
If you know your
user is interested
in six different movies,
and they're ready to buy,
they're ready to go, you can put
a single link in front of them
and they can buy six
movies with one tap.
That can mean a lot of money
in terms of commissions.
To get started with the
Collection system, you --
there's a bunch of
documentation available online,
but let's take a look at what
these links actually look like.
They're rather intimidating
at first,
but we can break
them down for you.
We start with the
Prefix, which --
has a little bit of
history, View Web I Mix.
There's the title that we
defined, of course URL encoded.
The description is also
in there, and the ID's
that we wanted, URL
encoded again
so that the link actually
works are in there.
Additionally, we've
passed in a WD ID.
That's the Web Developer ID.
And we've signed -- we've done
a little bit of cryptography
and we've added a key
to the URL and we put
that into the key parameter.
And finally, we've got our
affiliates hooking up at the top
because we want to
get a commission
on this link of course.
So this is a great way to
make things happen on the fly
if your user has a special set
of desires that you know about.
You can put together a single
collection with this on the fly.
You don't to do --
you don't need
to register a particular
collection beforehand.
Once you're signed up, you
can do this any time you want.
Now on the other hand,
maybe you don't want
to have the difficulty
of defining these
URL's programmatically.
For that, we have
Collection Builder
and this is a very simple UI to
define the title and description
and the content, and
the Collection Builder,
if you pass in a WD ID and your
shared secret will create the
URL for you.
So if you've got maybe
a game and you want
to promote the sound
track to the game
and maybe you've got a
comic iBook that kind
of expands the game's
universe; something like that,
you can define that very
easily via Collection Builder.
Once you've got your
title and description,
you can start searching
for additional content,
add that to your dynamic
playlist and you hit go