[ Silence ]
&gt;&gt; Good afternoon everyone.
[ Applause ]
All right.
Let's have some fun today.
Thank you for coming.
This is a session not
just creating app previews
but creating great app previews.
And I really believe that.
After this session, I believe
you're going to be able
to create a great app preview.
My name is Paul Turner and I'm
from the iTunes Engineering
Division.
And what that fancy title behind
you says, is that I have a job
that requires many talents.
It's true.
Not only do I run several teams
that keep content processing
such as your apps, processing
and flowing to the store.
But in my 10 years at Apple,
I've been lucky enough
to be able to participate
in producing and engineering
and launching incredible
projects.
One of my first projects was
with some of these people
in the front here,
it was actually the
original App Store launch.
Since then, we've done
iBooks Store and HD films
and iTunes Extras and LPs and
iTunes Match and The Beatles.
It's been awesome.
This isn't about me.
What's actually relevant to
you guys though is that one
of the teams that I run is
actually the logistics team
for apps made by Apple.
So, not only do I help engineer
and support iTunes Connect
but I am a customer of
it, just like you guys.
All right.
So, let's talk about you and
your apps and your app previews.
First, I want to talk about
how content is previewed
to customers on the store.
Currently, with our
amazing and innovative
and boundless music store,
we have those great
90-second previews.
I love them.
I sit and click and
buy all day long.
And for my favorite
store, the film store,
we have those great
theatrical trailers.
And for the TV store, we
have episode previews.
And for everyone's
favorite, the iBooks Store,
we have those enticing
downloadable samples.
So, what do we have
for the App Store?
This week, we're
introducing app previews.
So, let's get to know them.
Yeah, whoo!
You're allowed to clap.
[ Applause ]
This is great.
This is good.
This is amazing.
All right.
Let's get to know app previews.
This is fun.
Let's pick it up where
Tim left us on Monday.
With that app that he
showed, Monument Valley.
And let's take a look at the way
that it's previewed to customers
on the store right now.
It's pretty.
All right.
So, on the store, on the store's
product page, you're going
to have description text.
You're going to have other
information but, you know,
a picture is worth
a thousand words.
Let's look at these screenshots
and they're beautiful.
They're beautiful.
They're gorgeous.
It's an amazing app.
But I'm curious as a customer,
I don't fully understand it.
I don't understand
how the app functions.
This is app previews.
So, if a picture is
worth a thousand words,
what's a video worth?
And this is it.
[ Music ]
Right before our eyes, Monument
Valley becomes this immersive
puzzle game.
And you make an immediate
emotional connection.
And that's app previews.
So, I want to start off,
get us all on the same page
with just some basic
information.
App previews are up to
30 seconds in length.
App previews are not really
brand or campaign-focused.
They are not full of cut scenes.
They're definitely not
theatrical trailers.
They're just brief videos
meant to demonstrate the UI,
the features or the
functionality of your app.
App previews are made
primarily of captured footage.
And we're going to show you how
to do that live on stage today.
And once you're finished
producing your app preview,
you're going to export out
a high-resolution source
that you're going
to upload right
into iTunes Connect very easy.
It's going to be reviewed
along with your binary.
We're going to re-encode
it for streaming
out to devices all
around the world.
It's incredible.
So, with that, let's talk
about the agenda today.
First off, we're going to
go over a little bit more
of the details in app
previews, the characteristics,
what makes them different
than anything you've
really seen before.
We're going to help you
take that first step.
And that's kind of the
most important step is,
the planning step, how to
plan your video creatively
and technically.
We're going to show you
that capture feature
and it's amazing and I love it.
We're also going to do
a little bit of editing.
We're going to show your
editing options with iMovie.
Next, we're going to show
you some composition tips.
We're going to demonstrate
the uploading right
into iTunes Connect.
And we'll round out everything
at the end with some guidelines.
Does that sound good
to everybody?
Yes, OK. It's OK to talk.
It's interactive.
All right.
Let's talk about those details.
App previews.
App previews are a feature
of the iOS App Stores.
And as you saw on the
Monument Valley that Tim showed
and we just showed here, app
previews are going to show
up in the first slot
of the new section
for screenshots and videos.
So, that first slot will be
dedicated to app previews
and show up on the product page.
App previews are
device specific,
meaning that if you
have a universal app,
you will upload a distinct
iPhone and a distinct iPad video
for your app previews.
Also, we're making it very easy.
You're going to upload just
that single set of videos
to your apps primary
localization and we're going
to disperse them to
the other storefronts
that your app is for sale on.
A couple more details, we need
those beautiful widescreens
to show off your app preview.
So, app previews are going
to be a feature of iOS 8
and they're going to
display on those iPhone,
those widescreen iPhones, the
iPod touches, the iPhone 5,
the iPod touches, the iPads
and the Desktop Store.
One question I get a lot,
they're not required,
but they're strongly encouraged.
And I'm glad you guys
are all here today.
You've taken the first step.
We didn't want to
launch app previews
until we made everything
available
and accessible to
every developer.
And now that we're doing that,
we're strongly encouraging
everyone to get on board.
We really want you
to get on board.
We're here for the session.
We're going to be in the lab.
We're here to help you get
on board with app previews.
We just think they're amazing.
This is my favorite.
This is my favorite
of all, my favorite.
We have native aspect
ratio support built in.
No longer will you have
to stretch or pinch or add
that to your videos to fit
in a widescreen player.
I want that off the screen as
bad, it's just burning my eyes.
We have native aspect
ratio support right in,
built right in.
So, you get the full UI
video in the playback.
It's fantastic.
I want to talk about
planning next.
I'm sure you guys
are sitting here.
I'm giving you a little
bit of information.
Maybe the wheels are spinning.
Maybe you think about your app.
Maybe you're wondering
what you're going to do.
So, let's talk about planning.
Planning is the biggest part
about making your app preview.
The rest of it we
made really easy.
So, planning is where you're
going to have to start.
First, you're going
to have to figure
out the goal of your
app preview.
Are you going to highlight
a feature, many features,
maybe the utility of your app?
Maybe you have a
really innovative UI.
Start thinking about
what your goal
of your 30-second app
preview is going to be.
And a great way to think
about this is what
makes my app magical
or what makes my app magic?
And an easy way to kind of put
yourself in that question is,
if somebody walked up to
you with your app, you know,
"Hey, I've got this app."
It's your app.
What would you want them to
say to you about the app?
You know, "Oh, I've
got this app.
It does this for phone basics."
Or, "Oh, I've got
this really cool app.
It revolutionizes
the way I...that"
or "What's your plan
over there?"
"Oh, this new cool
new game, it does this
and this character does that."
What makes your app magical?
You know, that's going to
make your magical app preview
and your app preview magical.
That's going to get people
to purchase your app.
Just like Monument Valley, you
saw those beautiful screenshots
and screenshots are
a very powerful tool.
But now, you have
this story to tell.
You have this...you have app
previews to fill in that story.
So, you're going to look
beyond your screenshots.
How do you tell your story
now with these videos?
It's fantastic.
A couple more things
on content planning.
So now, you started to figure
out what makes your app magical.
You're starting to
understand what your goal is.
Now, it's time to start
listing out these elements,
maybe list out the
elements that you want
to put in your app preview.
If you're an app that's already
on the store, a great place
to start would probably
be a description text,
that's probably your
first list today.
I bet every one of
you got bulleted list
in your description text right
now, you can just steal that,
put that in your list.
But add to it, start
playing with things.
Start thinking about what
your app is all about.
Or, "Oh man, I spent so much
time on this great level.
I really want to show this off.
Kids love this."
Or, "I get so much feedback
about this portion of my app,
that's a great thing to
put in my app preview."
And I-- having said that,
now I highly encourage you
to make some kind of
outline or storyboard.
And you see the storyboard
that we have
up on here-- on the screen.
This is for storyboard
but we're going
to actually show the app
preview this is based
on in a little bit.
But, it doesn't have
to be fancy.
You don't have to
be a greater drawer.
This is a fantastic drawing.
[Speaker laughs] It
could be on a napkin,
it could be on a
Chipotle napkin.
You know, it doesn't matter
what you're drawing it on.
It could be a series
of arrows and boxes
but start storyboarding it out.
What do I want to
show in my video?
How am I going to put the
story together, right?
And along those lines,
you probably want to work
with that list of
elements, your storyboard
and start working
with the timing.
Remember you have a
finite amount of time.
So say, "I like this element,
I really want to
show off this UI."
That takes about
5 seconds to load.
Let's start working
with the timing here.
This is the time in
the planning stage.
You don't want to get bogged
down in the production stage.
You don't want to be
working on your app preview
and still not know what you're
trying to accomplish by it.
So, part of the planning stage,
and these are all basic
things I'm telling here,
but I think it's good to
remind everyone, it'll get you
out of the weeds if you're
on the production process.
And one last thing on content
planning, just like screenshots,
you have to disclose all
your In-App Purchases.
So, that's a good time in
your planning stage to figure
out how you're going to do that.
If you're going to show the,
you know, the sword of thunder
and that cost 10,000 coins,
you're either going to have
to figure out how to
disclose that with some kind
of textural element or
maybe you want to show how
that in-app purchase was
purchased in your app preview.
So remember, you have
to disclose all your in-app
purchases, plan for it.
It's a good tip.
All right.
A couple of technical
things to go over.
If you're a universal app, you
might have a great storyboard,
might have a great plan.
But your iPad app
and your iPad version
and your iPhone version may
have different UI elements
that you want to highlight or
need to highlight or capture
in a different way to edit
into your app preview.
And the planning phase
is good to identify those
so you can capture them when
you need them to edit them
into your production process.
Next one. Oh, this
is a good one.
You know your customers
best, and so therefore,
we're going to allow you
to pick your language
for your app preview.
And remember, it goes on to
your apps primary localization,
but you need to choose
a language.
Now, yet again, you know
your customers best.
If your app's primary
localization is Japanese
and it's primarily sold
in Japan, but yet you know
that your customer is
expecting an English video,
as long as it passes guidelines,
we're going to allow it.
So, in the planning
phase, it's good to figure
out what language
you're going to use.
This is probably the most
obvious thing I'm going
to tell you today.
The demo accounts, if you're
app opens up to a login screen,
it's going to be a
really boring app preview.
So, you're probably going
to need some demo
accounts, you know.
And along those lines,
you may need
to stage some information
into those accounts.
If you're a social app,
you're going to need
to put some social media.
And if you're a calendar
app, you're going to need
to put some calendar
information in.
If you're a game and you really
want to show off that 4th level
that you, you know, kids really
love, you're going to have
to figure out a way to
get to that 4th level.
And I caution you, don't stage
anything in your app preview
that cannot be accomplished
in your app.
Your app preview has to
be represented of the app
that customer will buy.
It's just a caution, I know
none of you guys would do that,
but I just want to
warn you about that.
Also in staging, it's a good
idea, just like screenshots,
we can't have any advertisements
in the app preview,
so it's a good time
to stage those out.
Sound good?
All right.
Let's show you a
cool app preview now,
enough of me talking.
This is a preview from
our friends at Toco Boca,
for an app called Toca Labs.
And they just have put a
few captured clips together.
They demonstrate their quirky
art direction, their fun UI.
This is an app that gets
kids really involved
in experimentation in science.
It just gives you a
great picture of the app
in a brief amount of time.
Love to show it to
you right now.
[ Music ]
Cool, right?
It's really neat.
I like it.
Yes, please clap for
Toca Boca, come on.
[ Applause ]
That's a great app preview.
Just a series of
clips, it's very basic.
My kid is addicted to this app.
She loves them, she loves them.
All right.
Now, I want to move
on to my favorite part
about this, the capture.
And you need a really
expensive cable for this
and really lots of...no,
I'm kidding,
you just need a Lightning cable.
It's...we've made it
so easy, it's amazing.
All right.
A couple things about capture.
In OS X Yosemite and iOS 8,
you're going to be able to hook
up your device via a Lightning
cable, right to your Mac,
open up QuickTime Player and
your device's screen output
and audio are available
as inputs just
like a camera would be.
Yes, there we go.
[ Applause ]
Yeah.
Super easy.
I love it, I love it.
It's fantastic.
All right.
So, to do this obviously,
you're going to need iOS devices
that require Lightning cables.
So, that's your iPod
touches, your iPhone 5 series,
your iPads, you needed the
Lightning cable support,
it only works over Lightning.
But, in true Apple
form, it just works.
No special modes, no clicking,
no shaking it over your head.
Stamp on it three
times and it works.
It's plugin, select
it in QuickTime,
we're going to show it to you
today, it's really amazing.
It just woks, I love that.
A couple tips for capture.
We want to display the
highest quality video and audio
to the customers and so
we've made this capture tool
so that you can capture
the highest quality video
and audio of your app.
You spend a lot of time
making...perfecting every pixel
in your UI and we want to
capture every single pixel
and make sure that the
customer sees how much love and,
you know, everything that
you put into your app.
So, we're hoping that you're
going to use these Apple tools.
A tip just like Toca
Boca did there,
you can start your capture
or, you know, you can edit
in from your splash screen.
It looks really kind
of cool if you want to.
But please don't
capture straight
from the home screen
going into your app
or if your app has inter-app
operability, don't switch back
and forth between apps.
This is about your single app
and its functions, let it shine,
capture only your app.
Go slow. I know that 30
seconds is scary to some of you
but really, you can make
some amazing app previews.
We're going to show
you a really awesome--
a couple awesome
30-second app previews
in a second, but go slow.
If your customer can't follow
along with what you're doing,
they're not going to
understand your app preview,
understand your app,
and they're probably going to be
discouraged by it, so go slow.
Use intentional moves, smooth
moves, smooth moves, you know?
And there's no film or anything
to load into this camera.
The only limitation is your hard
drive so rehearse it, retake it.
You know, if you flub it and
you try and continue on, don't--
don't-- no, no, just stop,
retake, rehearse it, retake it.
You got plenty of time.
Make it look right.
This is a face that's now
going on your app, you know,
for 30 seconds for
your customers to see.
So, rehearse, retake, have--
you know, take some time.
And along those lines, I want
to show you a really
cool app preview.
This app preview is from
our friends at UpTo.
UpTo is a calendaring app that
deals with the different levels
of events in your life.
And what they've done
is an example of what we
like to call a one take.
Instead of editing
clips together,
they've literally taken a one
take shot at their app preview.
Click Record, they've
added a couple graphics
in the front and the back.
But they click Record
and they go
through this nice smooth
intentional movements.
They've populated it with
a lot of, you know, data.
They've staged their
app really well.
And in their one take video,
you get a great picture
of their innovative UI
for their calendaring app.
I'll show it to you right now.
[ Music ]
Awesome, right?
[ Applause ]
I love how they synced up
the music, I mean, it just,
it's got this great feel.
You get the whole
app, 30 seconds.
It's fantastic, which
is a great segue
into our composition section.
A couple tips on composition.
You have been developing your
app for days, weeks, months,
years, you know a
lot about your app.
Well, the customer
probably doesn't have
that same perspective.
So, when you're making
your app preview,
think about their perspective.
If you're going to barrage them
with a bunch of information
or assumptions about
what your app does,
they might be confused,
maybe put off.
So, think about your
customer's perspective.
And, you know, this is a
great, great tip is, you know,
use your friends, your family,
or everybody at your office.
Show your app preview
off and look
for what their feedback
is, you know.
See if there's something missing
to your story 'cause
you might have something
in your head that, you know,
somebody else doesn't
have in their head.
This is a common mistake; a
very, very common mistake.
If you're going to put
text up on the screen,
you need to put it up there long
enough for people to read it.
People do this all the time.
They throw a text up on the
screen and they don't make it--
you know, they've-- it's
gone before you can read it.
So, make sure if you're
throwing text up there,
allow people to read your text.
This one is easy for me
'cause I'm always positive.
Stay positive.
There's no worst sales pitch
than a negative sales pitch.
This is about your app and
why your app is the best
or why your app is awesome.
So, don't imply anything
about other applications.
Just keep it about your
app and stay positive.
This is real opportunity
for your app to shine.
A couple more tips.
You may be a cross-platform
developer,
but for these 30 seconds,
you're all App Store.
So, go ahead and leave
off those platform logos.
In fact, leave off
the App Store logo,
use the 30 seconds for you.
We like our logo
just and-- it's fine.
These are your 30 seconds.
Leave off the platform logos.
You might have this great idea.
"New for Spring" in your app
preview, and then, you know,
you think you're going
to upload a new binary
or upload a new preview and your
cat gets sick or your car breaks
down and it's eight months later
and it's winter or
whatever season.
And now, it says,
"New for Spring,"
and it makes absolutely
no sense.
So, keep it timeless.
Allow your app preview just to
be about your app in some kind
of neutral time space.
Straightforward transitions.
Now I love a star wipe
or barn doors or confetti
as much as the next guy.
Remember this is about your app,
so straightforward transitions
are really recommended
when you're making
an app preview.
Straightforward transitions
we actually have found just
in our tests can actually
sometimes be confusing though.
Jump cuts is what we
recommend for everyone.
You've seen a lot of jump cuts
here and I'll show you a couple
of app previews that have
a lot of great jump cuts.
But in a couple situations, we
noticed that in jump cutting,
you can imply that
your app does something
that your app doesn't
actually do.
So, another great
straightforward transition is
like a dissolve or
a fade-through color
to give your user-- oh, OK,
this is a fade to another clip.
Make sure you don't imply
that your app does
something that it does not.
You don't want to
confuse your customers,
we love our customers.
My last point is,
remember the tone.
These aren't in your
face marketing videos.
This is just simple short app
usage videos, they're fantastic.
Remember the tone.
All right.
This is my things
to avoid slide,
I'll put my deep serious
voice on for this.
All right.
Things to avoid.
It's not that serious,
don't worry.
Blinking, crazy, flashing,
loud, obnoxious things,
this isn't the '90s and
these aren't banner ads.
If they're watching
your app preview,
they're already on
your product page.
They've already clicked Play,
you don't need a
gimmick to draw them in.
Please keep it simple.
You don't have to do this.
Pricing, if you're going to
put pricing in your video,
it's going to get lost,
it's going to put
you into the corner.
Remember, your app preview
or your app is sold
internationally.
You may put your
app on sale one day.
If you block yourself in
the pricing in your video,
it's not going to
make any sense.
Leave the pricing out.
These are going to display
in your product page.
The product page
already has pricing.
It already has storefront-based
pricing.
Leave the pricing
for the product page.
Local-- yeah, you know,
local colloquialisms, memes,
things like that,
references to Game of Thrones
that I don't even understand
because I don't watch the show.
I'm probably the
only one who doesn't.
But this is about
your app preview.
It's not about anything that's
going on in the media nowadays.
So, just keep it about
your app, keep it simple.
And here's the big one.
You can't put anything-- this
is just like screenshots,
it's just like your app,
you can't put anything
in your app preview that you
don't have the rights to use.
And this includes, but
isn't limited to, imagery
or photography or text or
sounds or music or videos.
If you don't have the rights
to use it, do not put it
in your app preview, all right.
That was as serious
as it's going to get.
One thing we added in
here 'cause we got a lot
of questions on it,
is narration.
Absolutely, it's a powerful
tool if used correctly.
So, here's a couple of tips.
There is an incredible
voiceover community out there.
Look for them, they're
so talented.
Use professional voices.
Not everyone has the intonation
and clarity for voice over work.
Obviously, I don't either, um.
But remember, this
is a voice now.
This is the voice of your app.
So, choose your voice wisely.
The second one is use
professional equipment.
It's available everywhere.
Condenser mics, pop filters,
just recording studios
in general, quiet rooms.
Nobody wants to listen to an app
preview with a narration on it
and they can hear your dog
barking at the background.
Or maybe for some of our younger
developers, you know, "Jenny,
come down to dinner," you know.
No, no. And lastly,
narration is a powerful tool,
but sometimes, it
can be overused.
You don't want to narrate your
entire video, but you want
to let your app speak.
So, just use narration wisely
is what I'm going to say.
And having said that, I want
to show you a really
cool app preview.
It's for a game called
Leos Fortune which I think,
they got a design
award this week?
Got a design award--
hey, good for them.
Really cool.
[ Applause ]
So, they have done
something really neat
with their narration.
They have their character
narrate
in the intro to their games.
So, they integrated
that narration
with some capture
gameplay footage.
So, you kind of get a picture
of the story of the game as well
as the gameplay all in one.
Leo's Fortune preview, I'd
love to show it to you.
&gt;&gt; [Background Music] I used
to be Leopold the Golden,
but when my fortune
was stolen from me,
I was only Leopold the Fool.
Around me, the world
was crumbling.
The lands decayed.
Order was lost.
I am on a journey
with one purpose only,
to find my fortune
and get it back.
&gt;&gt; Cool, right?
I love that.
[ Applause ]
That was an app preview that
I saw and I immediately went
and bought the game and, you
know, now I'm on like level 12
or something like that.
OK. So, to give you
a lot of information,
but really there's no better
way to get to know all this
than to demonstrate it.
So, what I'd like to
demonstrate first is capture.
And to do that, I'd like
to bring up Mr. John Danty,
who is the Senior
Product Manager
for GarageBand who's going
to help us capture some clips
for a GarageBand app preview.
John?
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; I'm going to go over
our demo machine here.
&gt;&gt; I will tune up my iPhone.
&gt;&gt; In tuning.
&gt;&gt; Well.
&gt;&gt; All right.
So, we have a Mac
Pro under here.
It's just a straight
Mac Pro and it's plugged
into this USB cable,
Lightning cable.
I'm going to hand that to John.
John, what do you have there?
&gt;&gt; I have an iPhone 5s--
&gt;&gt; All right.
&gt;&gt; -- with GarageBand loaded.
And I'm going to plug this in.
&gt;&gt; Go ahead.
&gt;&gt; Like so.
&gt;&gt; Like so, that was it.
&gt;&gt; That was it.
&gt;&gt; All right.
That's the end of the demo.
&gt;&gt; Thank you and good night.
&gt;&gt; Thank you.
All right.
So, on our box here on
our Mac, we are going
to open up QuickTime Player.
We're going to go up here to
File, New Movie Recording.
Ah, hello.
Look at this.
That's couple of
handsome guys there.
So, right here on the
Transport bar is our Inputs menu
and you can see John's
phone now shows
up as a video and audio input.
So, we're going to
switch it over right now.
Ahhh.
And now, we're going to
switch over that audio, too,
because we want to get the
great audio out of GarageBand.
All right, and I'm going to give
you a little sound here, John.
&gt;&gt; OK.
&gt;&gt; Feel like a warm up maybe?
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
&gt;&gt; I'm a little nervous--
&gt;&gt; Get your fingers.
&gt;&gt; -- get the fingers,
you know, kind of thing.
[ Music ]
&gt;&gt; Pretty good sound.
&gt;&gt; Thank you very much.
[ Laughter ]
Do you have anything--
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Thank you.
&gt;&gt; Do you have anything
less Liberace,
maybe a little more Metallica?
&gt;&gt; I think so.
How about this?
[ Music ]
&gt;&gt; All right, John.
So, now--
[ Music ]
[ Laughter &amp; Applause ]
This is WWDC, not Woodstock.
&gt;&gt; Oh, yeah.
[ Music &amp; Laughter ]
&gt;&gt; All right.
All right.
We're going to do
an app preview now.
[ Laughter ]
So John, I was thinking
of doing an app preview
like a one take first.
Maybe we'll do an
example of a one take.
Is there something
about GarageBand
that makes it magical, the
one feature that really stands
out that we could kind of
capture in under 30 seconds?
&gt;&gt; Well, a lot of users
love our smart instruments.
But I think the Smart
Strings is pretty cool.
So, let's show that.
&gt;&gt; OK, OK, OK.
&gt;&gt; All right.
&gt;&gt; Let's get set up here.
So, we have our input
setup and, I'm just going
to click Record,
are you ready to go?
&gt;&gt; I'm ready.
&gt;&gt; OK.
&gt;&gt; Here we go.
So, I'll swipe through the
Touch Instrument Browser,
land on Smart Strings.
And then I'll play a
little didi [phonetic].
[ Music ]
It sounds better when you
close your eyes apparently.
[ Laughter &amp; Applause ]
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Are you available
for weddings?
&gt;&gt; And bar mitzvahs.
[ Laughter ]
&gt;&gt; All right, we just
hit Stop on the screen.
We're just going to save
that out and we will call
that the one take right there.
Now, it's a good time
just to let you guys know,
the QuickTime Capture captures
at the native frame rate
that your app outputs.
So, when you're uploading
it to iTunes Connect,
we're going to ask
you to normalize
that to a standardized
frame rate.
So, that one take video
will still need to go
through something like
iMovie and be exported
out to a standardized frame
rate before it gets uploaded
into iTunes Connect, all right?
&gt;&gt; But John, we're going
to do a different one.
We're going to do a--
maybe a clip-based.
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
&gt;&gt; So, we've got a song we
started in GarageBand already
that would be a good soundtrack.
And then we could
capture some instruments
and then edit them all together.
&gt;&gt; OK. I'm just going to
set right back up here.
And check our inputs, all good.
And make sure-- I forgot
to mention this before,
make sure quality
is set to maximum.
Remember, we wanted to deliver
the highest quality video
and audio to your
customers, all right.
So, you're all set, you
probably have some audio.
You want to play that
song just a little bit?
&gt;&gt; Yeah, just a little sample
here so we can hear it.
[ Music ]
&gt;&gt; That's right.
&gt;&gt; Snappy number.
&gt;&gt; Sounds good, I
can dance to it.
All right.
So, what we're going to
do is capture the clips
of the instruments
used to make this song.
So, what's the first
instrument we're going to here?
&gt;&gt; So, we're going
to do a synth base.
&gt;&gt; Well, I like this
control panel.
&gt;&gt; That's kind of cool, right?
&gt;&gt; That's really nice.
&gt;&gt; Yeah, so we can
relive the '80s, right?
&gt;&gt; The '80s never die.
&gt;&gt; Oh, there it is, yeah.
OK, so ready to go?
&gt;&gt; I'm ready to go.
&gt;&gt; OK.
&gt;&gt; So, I'm just going
to hit Record.
Anytime you're ready.
[ Music ]
&gt;&gt; It's like Depeche Mode.
&gt;&gt; I love it.
I love it.
That is fantastic.
I'm just going to hit Save and
I'm going to call that the bass.
OK. How about another one,
you got another one in you?
&gt;&gt; Yeah, I got another one.
&gt;&gt; How about, let's do a synth.
&gt;&gt; A synth.
&gt;&gt; Let's bring up a synth here,
and [Background Music]
I can just play that.
Now, what's cool here is we
have this feature in GarageBand
where we can do what's
called pitch mode.
So, as we play, [Background
Music] hopefully we get the blue
dots, but you also can
slide between the notes.
&gt;&gt; I like that.
&gt;&gt; Really cool.
&gt;&gt; That's kind of neat.
That's kind of neat.
What about the control panel?
Do you have that
same control panel?
&gt;&gt; Oh yeah.
Yeah. So, we pop that open.
&gt;&gt; OK. Can we show
that possibly?
&gt;&gt; Capture that.
&gt;&gt; Capture that, OK.
&gt;&gt; OK. Whenever you're ready.
&gt;&gt; OK. So, control
this, tap here
and then what do you
think, start now?
&gt;&gt; That's good, that's good.
Go ahead.
[ Music ]
&gt;&gt; All right, fantastic.
[ Laughter ]
&gt;&gt; I said we're going to
have fun today, right?
&gt;&gt; With pitch mode, you can.
You got to play it.
&gt;&gt; It's great.
All right.
One last instrument from John.
&gt;&gt; Oh yeah.
&gt;&gt; I know you got a concert
tour to get to, right?
&gt;&gt; Everyone's wondering who
the band will be tonight.
&gt;&gt; It's you and your iPhone.
&gt;&gt; Me and my iPhone.
So, yeah. So, let's
do the Smart Drums.
&gt;&gt; I love Smart Drums.
Yeah. So, when we capture,
I'll bring the dice in
and we'll put it together.
&gt;&gt; Easy enough?
How does it go?
&gt;&gt; Here we go.
[ Music ]
&gt;&gt; Cool.
&gt;&gt; Move some stuff around.
[ Music ]
&gt;&gt; Cool.
&gt;&gt; Cool is right.
Save and that's QuickTime
capture.
Can I get a big round
of applause for John?
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Thanks Paul.
&gt;&gt; Thank you so much.
&gt;&gt; See you, man.
&gt;&gt; Great. OK.
So, this is a great
transition to where we can now--
We've captured our clips.
Let's now open up iMovie
and let's just show you
how really easy it is
to drag those clips in and
create your app preview.
And pop open iMovie.
I've got a blank
project waiting to go.
Look at that.
All right.
We're going to grab those clips
that we just did with John.
I'm going to drag
them in to our event.
We have our event right here.
This is where we can browse our
clips, we can favorite them,
we can work with them.
And then we have our
timeline down here
where we can start
building our preview,
add titles and transitions.
So, let's just start
with some drums.
These are drums we captured off
stage, a little hard to capture
in this room with the echo.
So, I'm going to
drag those in here,
make this timeline a little
smaller so I can work with it.
What was that next instrument?
That was the bass.
So, I'm just scrubbing
along here.
You can see I have the
waveform view up right here.
So, you can kind of see
where my audio clicks in.
I got...there we go,
that's a good amount.
It's the bass right there.
And what was next?
That was the synth, right,
with the cool controllers.
Let's get that.
Let me grab a little
bit of that.
That is cool.
We have that pause there so,
I am going to just
slick my way from up.
I can see the little--
There we go.
We get right as those come
in, can I get that hit?
How about four seconds for that.
That looks good.
OK. We exported out
John's song earlier,
I put that in the folder too.
So, we're going to
drag that down
into the soundtrack
section just right there.
Now, I could add maybe
some titles to this
from the content library.
But I really do like to
end on a fade to black
in any video that I do.
So, let's just drag
that on there,
make that look really pro.
What I want to do also is
I want to mute these clips
so they don't conflict with
that soundtrack, all right?
That was it, let's
give this a whirl.
Are you guys ready?
[ Music ]
How about that?
[ Applause ]
Is that cool?
So, cool, I love it.
All right.
So, we could do--
what we could do
for this is we could add
a couple more instruments,
we could work on our timings,
we could fill it out a little
and that's actually what
we did the other afternoon.
I want to show you that.
This is a completed
app preview made
in GarageBand with
captured clips.
I'm going to show
it to you right now.
[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
All right.
I can tell by your
applause, you approve.
So, if you're happy
with your app preview,
if that's what you love,
you're going to go up here
to the Share, you're going to
export that file, you're going
to export that high
resolution file and you're going
to get it ready to go
into iTunes Connect.
But we have already taken
the time to do that.
We've exported that file
out into this GarageBand
folder on the desktop.
And to show us how to upload
these into iTunes Connect,
one of my colleagues from iTunes
Engineering was Karen Posnansky,
who's going to come up
and show that to you.
Caryn?
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Hello. I'm Karen Posnansky,
Software Engineer
at iTunes Connect.
I'm here today to show you
how simple and intuitive it is
to upload your app previews
along with your images
in the newly redesigned
iTunes Connect.
So, let's check it out.
All right.
Let's open up iTunes Connect.
And here we are in
iTunes Connect.
As if creating a new version
of GarageBand, as you can see,
there's currently
only one screenshot.
So, let's add to it.
And this is where we add new
screenshots and the app preview
that Paul and John just created.
We could add them
the old fashion way
with the file chooser.
But it would be more
fun to open up Finder
and simply drag and drop.
[ Applause ]
As you can see, the video ends
up in first position followed
by the screenshots to its right.
The screenshots can
be rearranged
into whatever order you want
by dragging and dropping.
Whatever order you
choose is the order
that ends up in the App Store.
The video will always remain
fixed in first position just
as it does in the App Store.
So, this is all looking
really good.
But I don't love the poster
frame on the app preview.
By default, we select a poster
frame for you, but if you'd
like to choose another one,
just click Edit Poster Frame,
up pops a dialogue with
the video on the left
and the currently selected
poster frame on the right.
To select another poster
frame, we can play the video.
[ Music ]
[ Inaudible Remark &amp; Music ]
Or, we can scrub through
the video story frame.
[ Music ]
And set those frame anytime.
Or we can get granular and step
through forward or backward
until we get to just
the right frame.
I like that one.
So, let's choose that one.
And once you found the
perfect frame, just click Done.
And voila, there it is.
Once--
[ Applause ]
Once you have your screenshots
and your poster frame
looking just the way you want,
you can click Save
and Submit for review.
And once the app has gone
through the approval process,
we can check out what it
looks like in the App Store.
And there it is.
[ Applause ]
So, simple as that.
In just a few minutes, I
went into iTunes Connect,
dropped some images, dropped
a video, set a poster frame.
And now, how my app looks to the
world is completely different.
Thank you.
That's all.
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Thank you, Karen.
That was awesome.
All right.
So, let's go back, just rewind,
just a second back
to that exporting.
We wanted-- yet again, I'm
going to reiterate this--
we want to show the
highest quality audio
and video to your customer.
So, we want to-- we will--
we're going to accept.
And we'd like you to export out
at the highest quality of media.
So, that's going to coincide
with the iOS device captures
highest quality video settings.
And that is for the iPad
900 x 1200 in portrait mode,
1200 x 900 in landscape mode.
For the iPhone, in the 4-inch
series, that's the 1136 x 640,
I guess you can-- bet you can
guess what the next one is going
to be, 640 x 1136.
But also, we know that you
guys have some already--
have already captured footage
in 1080 workflows, maybe you're
in a 1080 workflow already.
So, we're going to take
variance of 1080 as well
for those iPhone dimensions.
And here is some technical data.
Don't everybody grab your
pen, this will all be
in the documentation,
although, you can take a picture
if you want some poses, my Sears
Roebuck catalog poses things
like that.
A couple takeaways here.
We're going to take two
codecs that are very familiar
to the Apple ecosystem, that's
H.264 and ProRes 422 HQ,
remember, high quality.
We want take the
ProRes, so you'd--
highest quality video
to your customers.
A couple takeaways is
the 30 frames per second.
We'd like you to upload your
sources in 30 frames per second.
And we're going to take stereo
audio either in AAC or PCM wave.
Basic, all this documentation
will be available to you,
don't worry about
writing it down,
I see this guy writing
it down, I'm sorry.
It's OK. All right.
I'd like to end out with a
couple review guidelines.
Now, the review guidelines
will be published
as this feature is rolled out.
And obviously, I'm not going to
be able to go over every single,
applicable review
guideline to you.
But, I'd like to highlight
a few that'll help find you
safe passage.
Remember things like
inappropriate content,
trademarked items, all
apply to app previews.
So, consult the app review
guidelines before uploading your
app preview.
First one, keep it relevant.
If your app has screenshots,
or app previews
that are absolutely not relevant
to your app, it will
be rejected.
So, don't sneak in a plug for
your Uncle Murray's car wash
or a, you know, surprise
proposal to your fiancee.
This is not the time.
Keep it relevant to your app.
By the way, she said yes
and we're married, I know.
Yay, all right.
Next one, just like screenshots,
you got to keep it 4+.
And I know you're sitting
there maybe have a game called
Mortal Kombat.
And that you're like,
"Paul, do I have to make it
into a tickle fest or
something like that?"
No. But you're going to have
to get creative, you know,
what did Spielberg do when
the shark didn't work?
He made "Jaws" and
it was awesome.
So, get creative, creative
editing, just, you know,
leave the violence,
those things out.
It has to be 4+ applicable
to all audiences just
like screenshots, easy enough.
All right.
Use captured footage.
No people in-- you know,
videos of people interacting
with your apps, no
hands in the shots,
so let's remove that hand.
This is captured footage.
You can use some
textual elements.
You can use graphic elements
that highlight points.
But, this is mostly about your
app and your app preview needs
to be made mostly
of captured footage.
And we've given you those tools.
So, use captured footage.
This one, simulated data please,
this goes without saying.
Please don't use any
celebrities, don't use anybody,
don't use your neighbor, your
friend, the person sitting next
to you, anybody that
would have issue with use
of their likeness
in your app preview.
You know about Johnny Appleseed,
we use it all the time.
You need to find your own Johnny
Appleseeds and if you're going
to use any data in
your app preview.
This last one, I've gone over it
before, I'll go over it again.
You got to identify your
in-app purchases, you know,
the sword of truth, the missiles
in our Touch Fighter app here.
You got to figure out a
way in your app preview--
if you're going to use those
in-app purchase content,
you got to figure out
a way to disclose them
in your in-app purchases,
simple as that.
Just a couple guidelines to
keep in your head, very easy.
We want to make this
very easy for you guys.
All right.
Time for a summary.
App previews are just 30
seconds of app usage footage.
They need to be 4+ and
appropriate for all audiences.
Device capture using a Lightning
cable, Mac OS X Yosemite
and iOS 8 into QuickTime player.
You're going to edit on
your Mac using iMovie.
iMovie will be updated
to support those native aspect
ratios and device dimensions.
For more advanced editing,
Final Cut Pro is
always a great option.
Love Final Cut Pro.
And we've made it super easy as
Karen showed you to upload them
into iTunes Connect along
with your binary reviewed.
We're going to re-encode
that for streaming
all around the world.
Simple. I want to close out
with a really cool app preview.
And this one's kind
of personal to me.
This one came in and I believe
this app also won a design award
this week which is kind of neat.
This app preview came in
and it just touched me.
Ever since I was a kid,
I was one of those people
that would kind of sit
and look out of the stars.
And everybody does this, right?
You've put your finger out, you
kind of trace the Big Dipper
or you track Orion or
something like that.
And this preview came in
and it showed me an app