&gt;&gt; Howdy. I'm Daniel Delwood
and I'm excited to welcome you
to Session 418, "Improving
Your App With Instruments".
I've got a lot of fun stuff
to cover today, so
let's get started.
So there are five items
on our agenda today,
but really only one
goal and that's
to give you the tools
you need to go out
and proactively profile
your apps,
looking for memory
problems, CPU problems,
and overall to increase the
efficiency of your applications.
So I'll start by
talking about what's new
in Instruments this year, and
then we'll have three sections:
memory management,
time profiling,
and performance counters,
each with associated demos.
Hopefully, so that whether
you're a new profiler
on our platform
or an experienced Instruments
veteran you should be able
to take away some tips and
techniques from those demos.
And, finally, what
session is complete
without covering
DTrace, and so we'll talk
about some new DTrace
improvements in OS X Yosemite.
So to get started what is
new in Instruments this year?
Well, we've got two
major themes,
and the first theme is a new UI,
and so you'll notice it
looks quite a bit different
than before, but this is
to match the style of Xcode
and OS X Yosemite, and we think
that you'll really like it.
At the top I'd like to
point out the toolbar.
Of particular note is the path
control there, it allows you
to quickly select both
target device and process
in one gesture, which we
think will really speed
up some of your workflows.
And on the right we've got
a centralized place for all
of your configuration options,
so whether this is recording
options before you run,
viewing options, or an
extended detail, stack traces.
There's one place now to go and
that's called the Inspector.
Now the reason we did this
is mainly for your content,
and we all spend a lot of
time looking at statistics
and call trees and
having more real estate,
more space to clearly dive
into your problem is
really what we did this for.
So that's the first theme.
What's the second theme?
Well, as you may have noticed,
Swift is a pretty
big deal this year,
and we're really excited
about what it offers.
But as you go out and adopt
Swift in your application,
whether it's by adding
a new Swift class
or even converting some of your
current code to Swift we want
to make sure that you
have the confidence
because you can measure and
you can understand what's going
on with the technology.
And so Instruments has support
for Swift, and this will run
across all of our demos today,
so we'll be using both hybrid
and pure Swift apps for those.
Now there's a host of other
features and Instruments,
some of which we'll get
to today in the demos,
like simulators behaving as
devices and Instruments now,
some counters improvements
and the like,
but those are the two sort of
high level things that are new.
So let's dive in and talk
about the first problem
that you may face when
developing your application,
and that's memory usage.
So how can you reduce the
memory usage of your app?
Well, what we're talking about
here is persistent memory usage,
so that helps narrow it down a
little bit, but we also needed
to find out like what
is your app using?
And for doing that, we
can think of the memory
in your application
as sort of an iceberg,
you've got the heap memory
on top, which you know
about because these are the
objects you interact withview
controllers, NSImages,
managed object context,
these are the objects that your
code directly interact with.
And then under the surface
there's everything else,
there's the layer memory
backing those images
or your managed object context,
there's a lot of
objects, as well.
And so if you've managed the
memory sort of on the surface
and you manage it well, it turns
out that you actually do a
pretty good job managing the
whole usage of your application.
So how do we manage those
objects that we deal with?
Well, for that there's
an ownership model.
And Objective-C's Ownership
Model is pretty straightforward.
It's a reference guide model
based on retain and release,
and when the object drops
to zero the object is freed.
These rules are well-known,
the rules are documented,
and the key point here is
that it's deterministic,
simple and pretty fast.
So what about ARC?
Well, this makes
it so much easier
because it manages the
retain/release for us.
And so it transforms
that problem from dealing
with retains and releases to
dealing with your object graph
and managing relationships
at a semantic level.
So what about Swift?
Well, Swift's Object
Model, understandably,
is a lot like Objective-C's,
although I should point
out that there are a
couple of differences,
namely that the retains and
releases are inserted for you
and there's really no
need to worry about them.
If you're working with
Objective-C, though,
you do still have to manage
autoreleasepools and for
that there's a nice
standard library function,
which accepts a closure,
and it's really easy to use.
And so just make sure
that you're inserting
autoreleasepools as makes sense
with the objective C
code that you're using.
So if these are the ownership
models what tools do we have
available to us?
Well, one of the heavy lifters
that we have is the
Allocations Instrument,
and this provides back traces
and information for all
of your heap allocations,
so it gives you things
like class names,
like NSMutableArray.
If you're dealing with Swift
objects, it's important to note
that your Swift objects will
be prefixed with a module
that they are contained in.
And so for your application this
may be just your app's name.
But for Swift objects, the heap
only will contain your reference
types, and so if you're thinking
about this at a code level,
these are your classes,
not your structs.
But once you identify
these allocations,
the allocations will provide
you the reference histories
for them, so retains, releases,
and even allows you
to pair these.
It also provides a
lot of information
for anonymous VM usage and
so you can use a Call Tree
and track it back to the source.
So I would actually like to show
you a demo of using allocations
and profiling and app extension.
So I have here a
simulator of an iPhone 4S,
and I'll launch Instruments,
and you'll immediately notice
that we have a new
template chooser.
And the template chooser
allows you to select
at the top your device or
even manage some devices.
For simulators we can
go ahead and choose
to launch a different
simulator, and allowing you
to choose the target
that you want
to profile before even selecting
your template matches the
workflow from Xcode
a lot better.
And so if you're used to
choosing what you want
to profile and then the
tool you can do that
or you can just go ahead and
select it as always the tool
and configure it first.
So I've selected
the Leaks Template,
which has 2 instruments,
the Allocations and
Leaks Instrument.
And for this demo I'll pull
up the list of apps installed
on my simulator, and you'll
notice it behaves just
like a device.
It gives me installed
apps, and now,
new in iOS 8 it gives me
app extensions, as well.
If I select, say, a
sharing extension,
the popup will also let me
select what app it's hosted in.
And since app extensions are
accessible to multiple apps
in the system, even system
apps can have behavior provided
by your extension, you may
want to select a process other
than your main app executable
when you're profiling
your sharing extension.
Now for this demo
I'm actually going
to select a today extension,
and since we know what
view it's going to appear
in there's actually no need
to select a hosting app.
So I've actually launched
my app in the simulator,
and it's an app extension
bringing in today view.
And what I have is an extension
that allows me quick access
to my game, and so maybe I'm
playing a move very slowly,
I'll play a move every other
day, and I just want to pull it
down and make a quick
move, but it's a way
of me guessing what
the pattern is,
it tells me how many I get
right, how many I get misplaced
or wrong, make a couple
of random guesses.
You'll notice the memory
usage and Instruments is going
up slightly, but what I'm
really interested in is finding
out how I'm doing cleaning up
memory when I create a new game.
And so I can just create a
few games here at the end,
and in Instruments you'll notice
we detect quite a few leaks.
Let's take a look at that.
So, first of all, in
Allocations it's showing me all
of the categories that I've
recorded, things like CFString,
and I can type in
for my example, dot,
and we see four different
categories.
We see the colored button
and the DotsTodayViewController
are prefixed by my module
because these are Swift classes,
and the other two
are Objective-C,
so they're running
together, working fine.
If I select one of these
Swift classes and dive
in even more I can even see
the retain/release history,
paired or not, and if I go back
to the summary I'll
quickly notice
that the persistent number,
which is the one I want to check
if I'm looking for memory
growth, is, well, 100%.
Now this is where
your expectations
as a developer come into play.
I expected my colored buttons
to be reused, so there's a few
of them persistent, a
few of them transient.
But my games, I expected there
only to be on active at a time.
So this I've immediately
identified a bug and I should go
at this point and fix it.
Now there's a couple other
ways to find memory growth.
I'm going to show you two more.
First, we've got leaks,
and leaks will tell
me all the memory
that it could find
was unreferenced.
This is a type of
persistent memory growth,
and so we've got malloc
blocks, a couple of colors,
and those games again.
And when it comes to
persistent memory growth,
there's really three types.
There's leaked memory,
there's abandoned memory,
and there's cached memory.
Leaks will tell us the first
of those three, but if I want
to investigate all three I
can use a technique called
generational analysis.
Now normally you'd used this
Marked Generation button while
you're running and set down some
flags for you to then later know
when you were doing
certain actions,
but in this case I actually
know when I did them
and I can add them
after the fact,
which is a really
powerful technique.
So if I select Marked
Generation, it creates sort
of a baseline snapshot, and what
this is doing is categorizing
all the persistent
memory in my application
by where it came
from on the timeline.
So anything before this flag
is grouped into generation one,
anything between flag one
and flag two is generation
I guess B, as it's labeled,
and I can keep marking these.
I can even actually choose
to move them around just
by dragging them, and it
updates the generation
information immediately.
So if I turn down generation B
here, you'll notice that, oh,
well, we have those
dots games again,
and we also have an equal
number of NSMallocBlocks.
Well, that's kind
of interesting,
I wonder where these
are coming from.
Perhaps we've got a retain
cycle involving a block.
So on the right in the
inspector area, I take a look
at the stack trace,
and I'll notice
that here we have a Swift
frame calling new game,
an action on my view controller.
Let's take a look
at that real quick.
If I jump to Xcode, here's
my new game function,
and it's just creating a dots
game, assigning it to my library
and then it's registering for
state changes on that game
and passing in what
looks like a block.
Well, this is actually
a Swift closure.
We can take a look at the
header, and we see here
that registerForStateChanges
takes a dispatch block,
and here when we're providing
it we just give a very
natural syntax.
Well, if you're familiar
with blocks
and retain cycles it's very
easy to capture the game
in the block registered
on that game.
And so what we really need to
do here is actually declare
that we would like to
capture new game and, well,
it's probably safe to capture
self weakly as well here.
Now Swift offers a really
good technique for doing this,
and that's Captureless.
So we can just say that we
would like to capture self
and new game weakly
in this block.
Now we get a compile
error real quick,
and that's because when we
declare something weak it gets
implicitly converted
to optional.
Well, that's fine, if self
is nil, we really don't care
to call that method,
so we'll go ahead
and add some optional chaining,
and there we go, we're done.
So, as I showed you,
Instruments now supports app
extension profiling.
You can specify your host
app either in the menu,
in Instruments or in
your scheme, in Xcode.
And app extensions, while
they are transient processes,
memory does matter
because if they crash,
if they flicker it's a very
bad experience for your users
and you want to make sure
that when they're running
in other people's applications,
when we're running on a system
that you get the best
user experience possible.
Now I'd like to direct
you to two other sessions,
if you're interested
in learning more
about app extensions
on iOS and OS X.
So let's talk briefly about
memory management with Swift.
Objective-C code can still
mismatch retain/release,
especially if it's a code
that you've handwritten
and you haven't converted
to ARC.
So when you're using Swift
objects and passing them
to Objective-C code you may need
to do some retain/release
pairing
and track down those problems.
Also, more important, is
that you can still
form cycles in Swift.
Luckily there's two great tools,
language tools available to us
to manage that graph and not
have toand break these cycles.
So the first of them is weak,
and this actually
converts your type,
it requires that you
use an optional type
because what it does is it
returns the type of nil,
depending on whether the object
that it references
is still alive
at the time you attempt
to use the variable.
Now for unowned you may think
this is a lot like unsafe,
unretained and ARC, and it's
actually safer than that.
What it does is it
returns the type always,
but if the object doesn't
exist you don't get an unknown
selector bug or an
indeterminate crash later.
It actually validates if
the object is still there
and then gives you a
deterministic crash,
so some very powerful
tools at your disposal
when dealing with Swift.
And, as I showed in the demo,
with block captures this
is a really easy way
of creating retain cycles
and something you
should be aware of.
In Objective-C, if I
reference self, like this,
it's going to capture it
strongly, as well as new game,
and I would have to use these
weak type of declarations
and then use them
inside the block.
In Swift, like I
showed you, it's very,
very easy using capture lists to
quickly change the memory type
of your variables
within the closure,
and so just by declaring
the weak
and the capture list we can
use them and no problems.
And Swift is also really
powerful here in that
if you reference a property
it will force you to declare
that you really do
intend to capture self
by using self.property.
To learn more about Swift we've
got a lot of sessions this week,
"Swift Interoperability
In-Depth", "Advanced Swift",
and if you want to learn more
about the generational analysis
that I did during the
demo I'd refer you back
to last year's talk on
"Fixing Memory Issues".
So, with that, I'd like to
turn it over to my colleague,
Kris Markel, for telling
you about Time Profiling.
&gt;&gt; Time Profiler at a high level
is a tool within Instruments
that helps you make
your apps faster.
The real question, being faster,
in and of itself probably
isn't your real goal.
Why is it that you actually
want to use Time Profiler?
And the answer, I think,
in a lot of cases is
to provide a great
user experience.
And what does that mean?
That means you have
faster app launch times.
If it's important that
your frame rate stay
at 60 frames per second,
Time Profiler is a tool
that can help you do that.
Buttery-smooth scrolling,
Time Profiler is great
at finding hiccups
in your scrolling
and helping you get
past those problems.
And kind of a more
general category,
you want to have
a responsive UI.
If the user does
something in the app,
they need to see the app
respond as quickly as possible.
You don't want them to click a
button and then wait and wait
and wait for something
to happen.
So what exactly is
Time Profiler?
Time Profiler is an instrument
that samples stack traces
at pre-described intervals, and
its goal is to give you an idea
of how much time is
spent in each method.
There's an important
distinction here
in that Time Profiler
is not actually tracing
through every method and
function calling your app
and measuring how long it takes.
It is capturing stack samples
and recording how often frames
appear in those samples.
Now this can be important if
you have a function or method
that doesn't run enough
to show up in any samples
or it's too fast to
show up in any samples.
This isn't an issue
most of the time,
but it's an important
distinction to keep in mind
when you're using Time Profiler.
When should you use
Time Profiler?
Well, there's a couple
different situations.
If you have a specific
problem that you know about,
Time Profiler is great, you
know, if you have stuttering
or frame rate slowdowns,
some portion
of your app is taking too long,
parsing a file or something
of that nature, but it's also
fine to use Time Profiler
to identify and fix hot spots
before they become problems.
You don't have to wait until
you have a problem before firing
up Instruments and
using Time Profiler.
And, actually, it's a
good idea to keep an eye
on the CPU gauge
inside of Xcode.
If that's spiking in
ways you don't expect
or it just seems higher than
you want, that's a little clue,
you know, something should go
off in the back of your heads,
maybe I should look
at Time Profiler
and see exactly what's
going on here.
And so now I'm going
to show you a demo
of how you can make your app
faster with Time Profiler.
And what I have here
is a hybrid app
and it's got some Swift files
and it's got some Objective-C
files, and I've been working
on it for a while, and
I want to get an idea
of how well it's running
before, you know, I don't know
of any specific problems, but
I want to kind of take a look
and see if maybe there's
some hot spots in there.
So I'm going to go ahead
and Time Profile this app,
and to do that I am going
to press and click and hold
on the Run button in
Xcode and choose Profile.
And this is going to
launch Instruments
into the template chooser,
and once it's done building I'll
show you a nifty little trick.
And if you're familiar with
Instruments in the past,
what would happen here is it
would give you the template
chooser, what you see here, and
you would choose, you would go
down to the button down
here, and you would click it,
and Time Profiler or
whatever-actually, let me choose
that now while I'm
thinking about it.
Whatever instrument you had
chosen would automatically start
running and recording
for your app.
With the new Instruments
it gives you a chance
to change your configuration
before it starts running.
Now if you want the old
behavior it's still there,
if you hold down the Option key
you can see the button change
to Profile, and that'll
launch your app
and start running
it immediately.
In my case I don't want to do
that, I'm going to go ahead
and go to Choose, and
I'm actually going
to make a couple adjustments.
And, actually, I'm right here,
this is, you can't quite see all
of it, but the two changes I
want to make and why is going
to become clear soon
is I want to choose
to record waiting threads,
and this means don't only
collect samples from the threads
that are doing work, but
that are idle, as well.
I happen to know
that I want to do
that because I've
rehearsed this talk before.
If you choose that option
another really great option
to choose in the
view options is just
to select running sample times,
and what this means is even
though you're collecting the
idle samples, don't use them
when computing time spent
because they really sort
of water down the results.
You're going to have
a lot of idle time
and get some very small
numbers that you don't expect.
So, with that, I am
going to zoom out,
I'm going to click
the Record button
to start my app,
and let's see here.
So here's my app, I've got a set
of pictures over on the left,
I can select them
and get the thumbnail
and then get the big view.
And now I'm going to go
ahead and click on my button,
and whoa, that's awesome.
So let's go through
and use a little more.
One thing I notice is
that between the time I click
the button there's a little
pause before the eyes actually
show up, and I don't like that.
My app is supposed to be
eyemazing, if you can read
that title bar that's
clear, and having to wait
for your googly eyes is not
an eyemazing experience.
Well, fortunately, I was
capturing a time profile,
let's go ahead and see
what's going on here.
So now if we look at the track
view, we now have new gestures
for working on the track view.
And to select a time profile
all I have to do is click,
or to select a time filter all
I have to do is click and drag
and that applies
the time filter.
So it's much simpler,
hopefully far more intuitive
than it was before.
And then to actually zoom in you
do the same thing, but you hold
down the shift key, so I'll do
that now, and I can zoom in,
and then I'll go back out.
And so now I can see, if I come
down here I can see that most
of time is spent
in the main thread
and in the start method
and, oh, you're not here
to watch me click
disclosure triangles all day.
I'm going to go over and I'm
going to use Command 3 to bring
up the extended detail pane,
and this over here gives
me my heaviest stack trace.
And what I'm looking for
is in this column here.
I'm looking for a big
drop in the numbers.
And I can see right here
I go from 120 to 180,
that kind of gives me an
idea of where my problem is,
and when I select it in the
stack trace, it selects it
in the Call Tree view.
And there's still a
lot of stuff in there,
a lot of which I don't
really care about.
So I'm going to hit Command
1, well, actually Command 2,
and go into my view options,
and one of the ones I'm going
to choose over here is
to hide missing symbols.
No, I'm going to choose
hide system libraries,
and this narrows it
down to just my code.
And it's kind of nice, if
you look in here you can see,
I'm going to expand
this one more.
Oop, you can see here's
an Objective-C call,
here's a Swift call.
Oh, I got this backwards, right?
This is the Objective-C call,
this one down here
is the Swift call,
and it's at Ob-C is the
bridge between them.
And if you're using a
hybrid app you'll see those,
and just so you're aware
that they're there,
they're not causing
any harm or anything,
it's not anything wrong.
Another thing I want to do is
I want to invert the Call Tree
because this makes it a
little easier to kind of see.
Frequently the most
expensive calls
in your app are towards the end
of the Call Tree, so that kind
of helps you narrow in on that.
And another thing that makes
this nice is I can see per
thread really quickly what each,
what's the expensive calls.
So I'm here, so I'm
spending a lot of time
in this method right here, so
I'm going to double click on it,
and it brings it up, let me make
this window a little bigger,
and I can see my Swift code.
Ooh, and it scrolls
really quickly,
and thanks to this big red
bar I can see that most
of my time is being spent on
this particular line of code.
What is this code doing?
Well, I'm using the core image
face detection to find faces
and then to find eyes on those
faces, and that's where most
of my time is being spent.
What are my options here?
Well, I can either change the
accuracy level of the detection
so it doesn't find
faces, as well.
I can maybe turn off
the blink detection.
Those two things
might make it faster,
but I don't think
they would provide
as an eyemazing experience
as having high fidelity face
detection and getting, you know,
the googly eyes need to be
on the closed eyes, as well.
I could maybe write
my own face detection
and maybe that'll be
faster than what's provided
in the kit, probably not.
So what are my choices here?
Well, I actually notice
using the app that even
if I can't make this faster
maybe I can change the way the
work is being done.
And to do that, I actually
am going to change it so that
when you click on the app in
the sidebar, when you click
on the thumbnail in the
sidebar, we'll go ahead
and build the googly
eye image then,
and then by the time you click
on the button it'll be
already ready for you.
And so I'm going to scroll
down to my didSelect,
tableViewSelectionDidChange,
and I happen
to already be caching my googly
eye images, but I'm now doing,
I'm currently doing it
when you click the button.
So I'm just going to add a
little code here to generate
that when the selection changes.
We're going to just move
the work around here,
and I'm actually cheating
a little bit here,
I want to point this out.
I'm using a mutable dictionary
as my cache, and so instead
of having to deal with a mutable
dictionary and multiple threads,
I'm actually dispatching
this back to the main thread
so that all of my
dictionary access happens
on the main thread.
I can do this because this
is a fairly simple app,
it's not a lot of
threading going on,
but if you're doing more
complex stuff you're going
to need a more involved
solution, but this works for me.
And if we scroll up
to the actual-this is
when you click the button,
you can see here we basically
get the selected row,
we see if the image
is in the cache.
If it's not, we go ahead
and build it and put it
in the cache, and
then we display it.
So let's go ahead and see
if this makes it any better.
So click the Profile button,
you can see it profile again.
Now if you keep your eye on
the track view you'll see
that it still does work and you
can still see the spike, right?
But by the time I actually go
to click the button the
work is already done,
so now there's a little
spike, click the button, oh,
scroll down here, try this
one, oh, I love this app,
I could do this all day.
Oh, wait, what's going on here?
Where is my scrolling?
What's going on?
Oh, it's stuttering, oh,
this is not eyemazing.
I need to fix this.
Okay, let's see what we can do.
This is really terrible.
Fortunately, I'm still running
Time Profiler, so I'm going
to go ahead and select some of
these little spikes in here,
and I apply a time filter
and hold down the Shift key,
and go ahead and zoom in.
And then if I look, I still
have this invert Call Tree,
so if I expand my main
thread I can see its most
expensive calls.
And right here the thing that's
really hurting us is the scaling
the image, that's where
we're building the thumbnail
and making it smaller.
But the other thing
I happen to know:
that I can see the CPU spikes
and there's a few of them,
but it doesn't really quite
explain that much stuttering.
I would expect the CPU to
be doing a lot more work
if I was stuttering like that.
So another thing I'm going to go
check is I'm going to go up here
in the toolbar to our new
strategy buttons, and I'm going
to check out the
thread strategy,
which is this button over here.
And this is going to show me
what each thread is doing.
So now you can see
the whole thing.
Each of those little
stopwatches represents a sample
that was taken on that thread.
The ones that are solid are ones
where the thread was doing work,
and the ones that are
translucent are the ones
where the thread idle.
So if I go ahead and click on
one of these and you can kind
of see if you look up at the top
it says idle call stack sample,
not running on CPU, so
this is an idle case.
And now I want to make one
thing clear here because, again,
this demo is well rehearsed,
I know exactly which of these
to click on to find my problem.
When you're dealing
with your app,
there's thousands
of these samples.
You're going to have to use some
detective work to really narrow
down where in your app
you're seeing the stuttering
or you're having the problem,
and you're probably going
to have to click through
several of these to find
out exactly what's going on.
But in my case I can look
through and in each of these,
I can see in here, what is this:
NSURLConnection
sendSynchronousRequest..Whoa,
that's a big red flag;
synchronous request, bad idea.
Synchronous request on the main
thread-what the heck is going
on here?
So let's go back to the app,
I know there's something going
on here, and I actually
know associated
with building the thumbnail.
So I'm going to go into my
photo class, and go to where-oh,
there's a little comment
here, what does this say?
I read on the internet:
Kris from six months ago.
I don't even need to
read this whole thing.
That guy is a fool, if
only there was some tool.
I'll show you a tool.
Okay, I'm just deleting
all this code.
We don't need to
use a URL request
to load a local resource.
I happen to know that-that's
good-bye-that the image we're
looking for, that we're looking
to create the thumbnail for,
if you look down here
in my initializer,
I actually have a property that
already contains that image.
So instead of doing
whatever that guy
from six months ago was
thinking, I'm just going
to use the image
that I already have,
and that'll free
up my block thread.
Now I also happen to know,
this is a well rehearsed demo,
that doesn't quite
solve the problem.
It helps a bunch, but there's
still a little stuttering,
and to fix that we're
actually going
to do another little cheat,
we're going to move
some work around.
I'm actually going to go and
pre-generate those thumbnails
when the app starts, and
I'm going to do that here.
This, my Swift class here
has a load photos method,
and this just goes and
pulls all the photos
out of the bundle
and creates a list.
And in here I'm going
to add some code
that actually goes through, and
just simply touches each photo,
asks for its thumbnail, and that
gets-that causes the generation
of the thumbnail, and
that work happens.
We're doing this in a
background thread, basically,
as soon as you load all the
photos the next thing we do is
we go and generate
all the thumbnails.
This doesn't actually
technically make my app more
efficient, it just
moves the work around,
but I think for the user,
from the user experience
they won't really know.
So now if I go ahead and
profile my app again,
we take a look, you can watch.
At the beginning of the thread
you can see it doing more work,
if you actually use the app.
I should have some nice
buttery-smooth scrolling here.
Oh, this is a good
one: fun at the park,
fun at the park with
googly eyes.
So now my app is great,
it's super responsive,
buttery-smooth scrolling,
it's just so much better.
And that's an example
of Time Profiler.
[ Applause ]
So to real quickly, or I
don't know, maybe I won't be
that quick, we'll see,
review what we've done.
We talked about the new track
view, you can identify and zoom
in on the problem areas.
You drag and select to
apply a time range filter.
Shift+drag zooms in, and
control+drag will zoom you out.
We also talked about
the new inspector panes.
There are some new
keyboard shortcuts,
so you can quickly
move between them.
If you're familiar
with a certain IDE,
this should kind of ring a bell.
Command 1 is the
record settings.
These are the settings
that apply
to the next recording session.
Command 2 is display settings,
so it alters how you see things,
either in the detail
and extended detail
or in the track view itself.
And then Command 3 is
the extended detail,
so you can see basically
it's details
on whatever is selected
either in your detailed view,
like the Call Tree view
or in the actual
instruments tracks itself.
We also looked at two
of the strategy views.
The one we didn't look
at is the CPU strategy,
and this will show
you what worked,
each core on your
machine is doing.
We did see the Instrument
strategy and a few Instruments
that all of you are probably
familiar with this strategy.
Each track shows you what
an individual instrument
is recording.
And then, finally,
the thread strategy,
which shows you what
each thread is doing.
And then just a quick reminder,
if you're in Time Profiler
you can enable record winning
threads and see any
blocked threads you have,
and then you can go through them
and see maybe there's something
in your code that's
preventing your threads
from doing work when
they should be.
We also talked about a
few Call Tree settings.
Since expensive calls are
frequently near the end
of the call stack, you can
turn on Invert Call Tree.
It's also a great way
to see what each thread is
spending its time doing.
And then you can hide system
libraries to help you focus
on your code and not
really, you know,
what the frameworks are
doing-you probably can't do a
whole lot about.
And now I want to
discuss a couple tips.
In the Context Menu, on the
Call Tree view, you can choose
to focus and prune
current settings.
Charge moves the
associated cost based
on which option you select.
Prune removes the
associated cost,
so those things aren't
even sort of part
of the calculation anymore.
And then focus you can think
of as a prune everything but.
And then, finally, I want to
talk about two more guidelines.
Some things you should always do
when you're using Time Profiler.
First, you should always
Profile Release builds.
The performance characteristics
of a debug build
versus a release
build are significant.
And profiling debug builds
could cause you to fix problems
that aren't actually there,
that get optimized away.
The default in Xcode is
to profile Release builds,
but this is not necessarily
the best option
for every Instrument.
For example, the
Allocations Instrument
when using Objective-C Code,
the debug information provides
it extra data it can use
to report on your allocations.
And you can change this in
the Scheme Editor in Xcode.
You just choose the Profile
button and you can change it
from debug to release.
And then, finally, for iOS it
is really important for you
to profile on the device.
The simulator, for
some things it is much,
much faster, for many things.
for some things it's actually
much slower than the device.
It really is not a good use of
your time to run Time Profiler
in the simulator, all right?
And, with that, I'm going to
hand it off to my colleague,
Joe Grzywacz, who is going
to show what options you have
when Time Profiler
is not quite enough.
&gt;&gt; Thank you, Kris.
My name is Joe Grzywacz.
I'm going to talk to
you about a few things,
starting with what are
Performance Counters?
Each of the processors in your
machine contain some small
number of these 64-bit
hardware registers.
Now you have typically like 4
to 8, some very small number,
it's a very limited resource,
and these are separate
from the regular floating
point and integer registers
that you may think of
when you're talking
about your program actually
executing and doing work.
Now what can you do
with these registers?
Well, they're good for counting
some small number of events,
things such as number of
instructions you've executed.
It'll do cache misses,
branches taken, you know,
low-level CPU-specific things.
Alternatively, you can have them
take a call stack every time
some predetermined
number of events occurs.
So what does that look like?
The called performance
monitoring interrupts,
or PMIs for short.
So let's say we have a program
is actually getting here
over time, and the blue
bar represents the number
of branches we are executing.
And so higher means we actually
did more in this period.
With time based sampling we just
saw in Time Profiler we're going
to take samples at a regular
periodic interval, 1 millisecond
by default, and this is
true for the Time Profiler,
as well as the counters
instrument.
But if we're really interested
in what our program is doing
when it's being very branchy,
what we can do is set up one
of these PMIs so that we
actually get more samples during
the periods we cared about.
So we do, let's say, every
10,000 branches or so,
let's actually take a
sample, and so we get more
in the areas we care
about, fewer everywhere else
because that's just noise to us.
And this should let us
hone in on the problem
in our application just
a little bit quicker.
So what else can you do
with Performance Counters?
Well, you can get
more information
about your app's performance
beyond just time that we saw,
so it's sort of a Time
Profiler on steroids,
and this is why we consider
it maybe a little bit more
of an advanced instrument,
but it's something you should
still have in your toolbox.
So what can you learn?
Things about how you're
utilizing your CPU resources,
things like the various levels
of caches in your machine,
the execution units,
translation look aside buffers,
if you know what that is.
So you can look at all
sorts of low-level details
that might be bottlenecks for
your particular application.
You can also learn more about
your application, itself.
For instance, how often
are you branching?
How often are those
branches mis-predicted?
You can even look at your
instruction mix, you know,
how many integer
operations are you doing,
how many floating point
operations are you doing?
These are things you can't
always determine statically
by looking at your program
because you're depending
on some user input or
something from the internet
of that sort of thing.
So we've had counters
for a few years now,
but this year we've
added a few new things.
First, you can now
specify formulas,
so now you can get
those raw events in,
but then actually apply
some basic arithmetic
to them on top of that.
So you can see, we
can generate IPC,
which is instructions per cycle.
That's a measure of how
much work you're doing
in a given clock tick.
Generally, a higher number here
means you're doing more work
and performing better.
You can calculate branch
misprediction rate or things,
like your L1 cache
miss percentage,
take the total number of loads
to your L1 cache that missed,
add them to the total number of
stores I missed, and then divide
that by the number of
total loads plus the number
of total stores, and multiply it
by 100 for a missed percentage.
Now we've had x86 support for
a few years, and this year
with iOS 8 you can get
64-bit ARM devices,
tab counters, as well.
And then the event profiler
instrument, if you're familiar
with that, that's where
you used to go for any kind
of PMI-based information
for that kind of sampling.
You can just do that right
within the counters instrument
now and there's actually no need
to go do two separate
instruments.
Anything counters-related,
head over to counters.
And, with that, we'll
do a little demo
of iOS Performance Counters.
So I have a little basic
Matrix Multiplication app,
so if your linear
algebra is a bit hazy
to do a Matrix Multiplication
of a two N by N Matrices,
for each element in your
alpha Matrix C you have
to multiply piece by
piece an entire row
of the input Matrix A
times an entire column
of the input Matrix
B, and then add each
of those parts together.
So in pseudocode it's basically
just this triple-nested
for loop here, where all
the work is really the sum
of products happening here.
So in Swift code, this
does scroll fast-all right,
so we have our, basically, this
is our triple-nested for loop,
and with all that work being
done again and that summation
of the Matrix A times Matrix B.
And so what I want
to do is go ahead
and profile this in Instruments.
So now this is going
to run on my device.
I'm going to use the option
profile, so that's just going
to launch Time Profiler,
and it's going
to start recording on my device.
And I can tap a button, and it
starts my Matrix Multiplication.
Now this is going to
take a little while
because I'm multiplying two
1,000 by 1,000 matrices,
each of them contains a
double, so that's 8 bytes,
so it's 8 megabytes per
matrix, 24 megabytes in total.
And so it takes us here
about-well, it took about, what,
12 seconds to do
that calculation.
So I'm going to go ahead and
stop, click drag to time filter,
to the region of interest.
Let me make this
a little bigger.
And what I want to see is
where was my app spending time?
So if we zoom in here on
our extended detail view,
where we can follow
that really big number,
that's how many samples
there were.
It gets really small
as we drop down here,
so the problem is most of the
samples are actually occurring
in this Matrix Multiplier
routine.
And if we double click on
that routine we get taken
to the source code, just
like before, and we can see,
just as I expected, 92% of
my time is being spent right
on that summation line.
I don't have much code,
it's all being spent
on the one line I wrote,
so I'm kind of at the end
of the road with Time Profiler.
I mean, I think I've done
as much as I could do.
Well, we can actually
dig a little bit deeper
if we're willing to go
look at this assembly.
And what we have here is
these ldr instructions
that are taking a bunch of time,
and an ldr is basically just
loading a register from memory.
And so we can see these
two ldr instructions,
one of them is loading Matrix A,
one of them is loading Matrix B,
and they're taking a long time.
So now I can use the
Counters Instrument
to actually go and
figure out why.
So I'm going to start
a new template,
select Counters, there we go.
And now I want to add
some interesting events
to record using Counters.
And so if we choose to add
an event, we can see the list
of all of the events that
this device supports,
and I'm interested in my
L2 cache, so I'm going
to add the number
of L2 cache loads.
And I have a favorites list here
already of the L2 cache loads
that missed, the number
of stores, and the number
of stores that missed.
So I have those events.
I'm going to create
a formula using them.
So I want to get
one number that kind
of represents those four
things, and what I'm going
to do is actually generate a
miss rate by saying the number
of loads plus the number
of stores that missed,
and divide that by the summation
of the total number of loads,
which is loads plus
stores, okay.
And if I multiply that by 100,
now I have my missed percentage,
that's a little negative
for me, I prefer to think
in hit percentage, so I'll
just take 100 minus that number
and give it a name,
L2 Hit Percentage.
Add that event, and as I
mentioned before IPC is one
of those handy guys to have.
There's a predefined formula for
IPC, so I'm going to go ahead
and add that, as well.
And so I'm going to
start my recording again,
and this time I'm going
to see the Call Tree view,
as well as the track view has a
bunch more things being drawn,
and those are all my events.
So I'm going to start my
Matrix Multiplication again,
you can see all those
events going by,
and those are being calculated.
And as this wraps up we
can actually start looking
at the information in detail.
So it just finished, and what
we have here is the number
of L2 cache loads,
was at 462 million.
Okay, that's a lot.
124 million of them missed,
and there's a much more
insignificant number of stores.
Our overall hit percentage
was 72% or so.
Okay, that's not too bad.
Our IPC was 0.6, that
means we're doing less
than one instruction per clock.
I don't know, I think
that sounds kind of bad,
I thought computers could
do multiple things per clock
these days.
But the number that
sticks out to me most is
that L2 cache load number: 462
million loads to my L2 cache
when my input matrices are
only 1 million elements each,
so a kind
of back-of-the-envelope
calculation says I should only
probably do about 2
million, so why is it so big?
Well, it turns out if
you go online and search,
there's actually much better
ways to do Matrix Multiplication
that are a lot more cache
friendly for today's processors.
And one of those ways
is actually go and block
up our Matrix Multiplication
instead of trying
to do an entire row and
an entire column at once,
we're going to do it
in smaller pieces.
Because this Matrix is so
big trying to do it all
at once means we're going
to load in a lot of data
and then kick it back out to
memory and then load it back
in again and kick it back out,
and that's very inefficient
and slow.
So I have another implementation
where I actually block
this matrix up into, oh,
like 50 by 50 pieces,
so much smaller.
And we can see it execute here
and there, it already finished.
So we did this in about, let's
see, time filtered down to
that region and we can see
where our running time now is
at 3.5 seconds, so we already
split it up about three times
and it took about 3 lines of
code, very straightforward.
And our L2 cache load
number is now at 24 million,
so we went from 450
million down to 24 million,
so that's much improved.
Cache stores are still
somewhat insignificant,
although they're growing
in size relative to loads.
Our L2 hit percentage,
interestingly enough,
has come down.
We were in the low 70s
before, now we're at 64%,
that's a little bit odd.
Our IPC, though, is much
better, it's at 1.6.
Now we're actually doing
1.5 instructions per cycle,
so that's a lot better.
So this is where we kind
of consider this a little
bit more advanced instrument
because you can generate a
lot more of these numbers,
but you have to know how
to interpret the results.
And so our IPC got
better, so that was great.
Our cache hit rate went
down, but was that a problem?
Well, no, because we actually
did hundreds of millions
of loads less to that cache, so
the fact that that hit rate came
down a little bit, not
really that big of a deal.
To kind of wrap up, this Matrix
Multiplication thing you could
continue, keep on iterating and
try to write a better version,
however, we've already
done that for you.
There's an Accelerate framework
that has that done, and if I tap
on that version, see it
actually finished here
in about 200 milliseconds
and it's one line of code
and it works, and it's optimized
for multiple cores,
multiple devices.
A piece of cake, please
don't go write your own
Matrix Multiplication.
Now the last thing to point out
on this demo is I spend a lot
of time over here, down
here, adding these events,
adding these formulas.
They're really useful.
I'm going to come here to this
instrument many, many times.
I don't want to type them
in again, so be sure to go
up to File &gt; Save As a Template,
give this some interesting name:
L2 Hit Rate Counter,
or something like that.
And then save that off, and
then the next time you go
to the template chooser,
use the custom filter,
load up this template,
you don't have to type
that in again and
again and again.
[ Applause ]
So what did we see?
With counters you're
basically going to collect data
by default, similar
to Time Profiler.
It's a statistical sampling
of your application.
This is an important
point: that basically
for the past 1 millisecond
by default,
we're aggregating the
time and all the events,
and then we're going to
attribute it to that one moment
in time where we take
a call stack sample
of your application.
This means you want to
get a lot of CPU samples
to get really an
accurate picture
of what your application
is doing.
If you're not very
CPU-intensive,
this isn't the instrument
for you.
You can tweak that slightly
by using the Performance
Monitoring Interrupts.
So this allows you to vary
the sampling rate based
on the number of events
that are happening.
So if you're really
interested in branches
or L2 cache hit rate you
can actually sample based
on how many of those
things are occurring
and get more refined results
on what you're looking at.
Note that the PMI
instructions can be slightly,
a little bit imprecise in that,
by the time the interrupt fires,
let's say you take a call
stack, a small number
of instructions may have gone
by, which means you won't be
on the precise instruction that
caused this, but you're going
to be right in the
neighborhood and it'll get you
to the problem a
lot more quickly.
And be sure to use formulas,
so you can gather
all these raw events,
but a lot of times it's a lot
easier to generate one metric,
that makes it a lot easier
to see the problem at hand.
So generate those formulas
and then save them inside
of a template so
that you can get back
to them quickly in the future.
Changing gears entirely.
DTrace, if you're
unfamiliar with DTrace,
I recommend you go
online, there's plenty
of information about it.
Basically, it's a kernel-based
recording technology,
it'll let you get
more information
about your application,
especially how it
interacts with the kernel.
Today we're only going to talk
about what's new
with OS X Yosemite.
First, there's a
dynamic tracemem.
So a tracemem is a
way to actually print
out the contents of your memory.
So previously you had to
know the size of your array
and compile time, and
that happens to work a lot
of the times, but not always.
Now it'll work with
variable size arrays.
So say I want to trace this
CGContextFillRects guy?
Arg1 is a variable size rects
array, and Arg2 is the count
of how many things are in there.
So you can write this DTrace
script that upon entry
into CGContextFillRects, what
we're going to do is copy
in Arg1, which is the
array, and then the size
of that array is the size
of a single CGRect times
Arg2, which is the count.
So once you have that copied
into the kernel we're going
to call tracemem on that, so
we pass the array, we pass 512,
which is the maximum size
we ever expect it to be
for our application, and then
again we pass that same count.
So now tracemem works on
your variable sized arrays.
The next big improvement
is the Histograms
that have been improved vastly.
There's a number of new options,
too many to discuss here,
but basically you'll get much
better, improved Histograms,
easier to read, better
ASCII art on your terminal
when you're generating
these things.
I refer you to that excellent
blog post on DTrace.org
that will describe to you all
the options and all the ways
that it will be helpful to you.
There's a few other
new features.
Previously, if you wanted
to make sure you got every
single probe firing from DTrace,