[ Silence ]
&gt;&gt; Good afternoon, everyone.
Name is Alexandre Naaman and
I'm here today to talk to you
about developing custom
Core Image kernels
and filters on iOS.
So let's start with a
little bit of history.
We've been able to write custom
kernels on Mac OS X since 2005
with the advent of Core Image.
And now, with iOS 8, we're
going to show you how you can do
that on our imbedded devices.
So the main motivation,
why would you want
to write custom kernels?
Well, you can -- there are
-- although we provide many,
many built-in kernels and
filters, there are situations
where you can't use an
existing set of filters
or some combination of
to create the effect
that you're trying to achieve.
So if you were trying
to do something
such a hot pixels effect
or a vignette effect,
which is an example
we're going to go
into complete detail a little
bit later on, that's something
that you wouldn't
have been able to do
without writing a custom kernel.
Or if you wanted to create some
sort of interesting distortion,
such as the Droste deformation
that we showed how to do
in our talk two years ago,
that also wouldn't
have been possible.
But now, on iOS 8, with
custom kernels, it is.
So let's talk a little
bit about our agenda.
First off, we're going
to start about --
we're going to talk about the --
some core concepts
involved in image processing
and how to use Core Image.
We're then going to go through a
whole series of examples on how
to write custom kernels
of your own,
and that's where we're going
to spend the majority
of our time today.
And then, at the very
end, we're going to talk
about some platform differences
in between OS X and iOS
and what you need
to keep in mind
when you're writing
kernels for either target.
So key concepts.
And this is going to
sound familiar to you
if you were here for
the earlier talk.
I'm just going to go
over this really quickly
and explain how Core
Image works.
So if you had, for example, a
input image, the original image
on the left, and you wanted
to apply a sepia tone filter,
you could easily do that.
But Core Image lets you apply
much more complicated effects
and create arbitrary
filter graphs
and not just necessarily
daisy chaining images
up in this manner,
but also creating more
complicated graphs.
And these are all
lightweight objects
that eventually get
combined together.
And each one of these
filters can be represented
by some number of kernels.
And internally, what Core Image
does is it will combine these
all to -- into one program,
such that we minimize the number
of intermediate buffers
that you might have
and maximize performance,
which is our goal.
So let's talk about the
classes that we're going
to be dealing with today.
And again, if you
were here earlier,
you've got a brief
glimpse of this already.
The first class we're going
to deal with is CIKernel,
which is what we're
going to spend most
of our time working on today.
And it represents the object
that encapsulates the kernel
that you'll be writing to drive
-- to interact with your image
and is written in our Core
Image kernel language,
which is based on GLSL.
The next object is a
CIFilter, which you use
to drive the parameters
of the kernel.
And it has any number of
inputs, and they can be images,
NS numbers, or CIVectors,
and one output,
which is a new output image.
We then have CIIMAGE,
which is different
from other images you may
have seen with other APIs
because it's an immutable object
and only represents
a recipe the image.
So it doesn't actually
contain any real data.
It's just a recipe for how
to produce the final result
and it's also based on Cartesian
coordinates, lower left corner,
and may have infinite bounds.
So it's not necessarily
a bounded rect.
It can be infinite as well.
The final object that
we're going to be dealing
with is a CIContext and
a CIContext is the object
that you use to render all of
your images, your CIImages,
whether that be to CGImage
Ref or to an EAGL context
or whatever other
destination you desire.
So let's take a look at
how you might do this
if you were dealing with
standard C code and dealing
with just, you know, trying
to produce some new output image
given some bucket of bytes.
So you would typically write
some for loop over all the rows
in an image and then
iterate over all the columns.
And then, for each input
pixel, input buffer
at ij produce some -- you
know, run your algorithm here,
indicated by processPixel, and
create some new output value,
and put that into your result.
What we like to do inside
of CoreImage is abstract all
of that for loop away
for you and have it
such that all you need
to do is concentrate
on your core algorithm, in
this case, processPixel,
and we will take care of running
that in a parallel fashion
for you on the GPU, and running
it as oftenly as possible.
Now, in order to use a CIKernel,
you need to subclass
from CIFilter.
And CIFilter is going to tell
us, given some number of,
let's say, 0 or more input
images and some parameters,
how to apply that kernel
onto your input image
and produce one new
output image.
So let's take a look
at the workflow in iOS.
And if you've written
kernels -- I'm sorry.
If you've written filters on
iOS or on desktop in the past,
this is going to sound
very similar to you,
but we've got some new things.
So first things first, create an
input image with CIInputImage.
Then, we subclass CIFilter.
We're going to get our
output image eventually,
once we're done running
the CIFilter.
And then, when we have our
output image, we can display it,
as I said earlier, using
either CGImage or --
rendering to CGImage
or an EAGL context.
What's new and what
we're going to talk
about today is how you
create those kernels
and how you apply the parameters
that you have from your filter
to the kernel to get
your final output.
So let's talk about what
exists currently in Core Image.
Right now, in iOS 8, we
have 115 built-in filters.
Take a little closer detail
-- closer look at this.
We can see that they're
actually -- from this --
set of 115, there are 78,
which are actually just
purely modifying the color
of the images.
There are another 27, which
are pure geometry distortions.
And then, there are a final
7 that are convolutions,
which brings us to
our next point,
what is the anatomy
of a CIKernel on iOS?
So in iOS and on OS X, we
now have a CIKernel class,
but on iOS, we now have
two new classes that allow
for greater performance and
are specializations of CIKernel
and allow us to do higher
performance optimizations
than we do currently elsewhere.
So we have CIColorKernel and
CIWarpKernel and we're going
to talk about three of those
today in order of difficulty.
So let's look a little
deeper into the interface
for what a CIKernel looks like,
and you can see there are
really only two methods
that we care about.
The first one is
to create a kernel,
you call kernelWithString.
And then, to create
a new CIImage
after having running your
kernel, you call applyWithExtent
and a few other parameters.
And again, it's important
to remember
that calling apply doesn't
actually render anything.
It's just a recipe so you
can daisy chain these up,
create whatever graph you
want, and no work is performed
until the last moment when you
actually need those pixels.
So what is CIKernel's language?
Well, it's based on GLSL and it
has extensions for imagining.
So to deal with tiling
and all kinds
of other optimizations
we've put in.
It also -- all the inputs
and outputs are floats.
So fairly easy to use.
Let's now take a look
at what is involved
in writing a CIColorKernel.
So as I was saying,
all the inputs
for CIColorKernel are
going to be float data
and that doesn't -- it --
regardless of what your input
data is, whether it's RGBA8
or 16-bit ends or float data,
it will come into the kernel
as float data, as a
VEC4, and the output
from every CIFilter is
also going to be a VEC4.
So let's take a look
at the simplest possible
example we could come up with,
which actually does nothing.
So this is a no op.
It just takes an input.
In this case, it's going to be
an underscore underscore sample,
and you can see we
just returned --
which is effectively
just a VEC4,
and we just returned s.rgba.
So if we were to apply this
filter to the input image
on the left, we would get the
exact same image on the output.
We can make things a
little more interesting
and just swap the red
and green channels.
So this is a very
simple process.
We just take our red channel and
put it in the location of the --
where the green was and take
the green channel and put
in the location where
the red was.
And if we were to apply this
kernel to our input image,
we get a new output image,
and you can clearly see
that the macaroon in the
foreground has changed colors
and same thing for the green.
We can make things a little
more interesting and so,
what it looks like
when you actually want
to have an input parameter
that controls how much
of this effect gets applied.
So here we have a new variable
called amount that's applied --
that's used in our kernel.
And we just use a mix function
to do linear interpolation
in between the original
unmodified pixel value,
our final destination value
as if it was at value 1.0,
and then the input value amount
that is going to be something
that goes between 0 and 1.
And if we were to apply this
kernel and vary the value
between 0 and 1 interactively,
you would get very quickly a,
you know, an animated blend
in between these
two extreme images.
And that's pretty much
all you need to do
to write a color kernel on iOS.
The next thing we need to
do, once we've done our work
in kernel land, running
the CIKernel,
is we need to subclass CIFilter
in order to drive that kernel.
So in this case, we
derive from CIFilter.
We've created a new filter
called SwapRedGreenFilter.
It has two properties, the first
property being the input image
that we're going
to be working on
and the second property
is the input amount.
So how much of that along
01 do we want to go?
So let's take a look at the
methods that we're going
to be implementing today.
First things first, we're going
to be using this throughout
our presentation today.
We're going to have the
convenience function
for creating a kernel such that
we don't recreate these kernels
at every frame, because
we don't want to do that.
We're going to have a
customAttributes method,
which is oftentimes used
to drive UI elements,
such as what we saw in Core
Image Funhouse earlier,
in the previous talk.
And the method that you
absolutely must implement,
which is outputImage, and that's
where you take all
your input parameters
and you drive your kernel to
producing your output image.
So let's take a look at
the actual implementation.
As you can see, creating a
CIColorKernel is just done
by calling CIColorKernel,
kernelWithString:,
and passing along
our kernel code.
The next thing we need to
do is call self my Kernel,
and then we apply that and
we pass in two arguments,
the input image, which
maps to the first parameter
of our kernel, and
an input amount,
which maps to our second
parameter of our kernel.
And that is literally
all we need to do
to create a custom
color kernel on iOS.
So now, let's look at a slightly
more complicated example,
where we, in addition
to modifying colors,
we also use position
to determine how much
of an effect should be applied.
So let's pretend we wanted
to do a vignette effect
and take the image on the
left and produce a new image
on the right that looked
like it had been vignetted.
So in this case, you
can see that the --
we want the pixels at
the center of the image
to remain unmodified
and as we go further
out towards the corners of
the image, we want those
to be as dark as possible.
So we can think of those as
being, like, values between 1
and 0 and we're going
to be linearly interpolating
along that vector.
So if we were to look at what
an image looked like if we were
to create that 0 to 1
mapping for the entire image,
we were to get this gray
image in the middle here.
And then, if we take
our image on the left
and we multiple the red, green,
blue values by that
new computed value,
we would get our
vignetted effect.
And it's really that simple.
So now, let's take a look
at how we use position
information inside of a kernel.
So this is the signature for
our kernel and we're going to go
over through each step about how
we would create a simple color
kernel that depends on position.
So as I mentioned
earlier, CIImages may
or may not be --
have a 0.0 origin.
In this case, you can see that
the image is not at the origin,
and what we need to do is
find out where the center
of the image is because
every pixel that's going
to get darkened is with
respect to the center.
So we need to know
how far away we are.
The next thing we can do is we
can take the size of the image
and just divide that in two, and
we have a vector that takes us
from the lower left corner
of the image to the center.
And then, if we add these
two vectors together,
we have a new vector called
center offset, which takes us
from the origin of the image
to the center of our image.
We then are going to compute one
more value, which we're going
to be passing into our
kernel, which is the extent
of the image divided by
two, and that's going
to be the longest length
of any point in our image,
and we're going to be
dividing values by that
such that we can
determine how much
of the effect needs
to be applied.
So as I was saying earlier,
we have many extensions inside
of Core Image to
deal with imaging.
One of them is called destCoord
and this is going to tell you
which current pixel
you're trying
to render in global space.
So what we need to do is
figure out how far away
from the center is every
single destCoord that's going
to get evaluated.
And this function
will get called
on every single fragment you're
trying to render in the image.
So you can see here,
it's a simple matter
of just subtracting one
vector from the other.
We just take destCoord
minus centerOffset
and we get a new vector
called vecFromCenter.
So inside the kernel, this
is what it looks like.
We're then going to get
the length of that vector,
called distance in this case.
We compute a darkening amount
by doing distance divided
by radius, which,
like, half our diagonal
of the original rectangle.
1 minus that is going to
give us our darkening amount.
And then, finally, we call --
we return a VEC4 that
takes our input sample, s,
multiplies the RGB value
by that darkening amount,
and maintains alpha as is.
And we have the vignetting
effect.
So now, let's take a
look at what we need
to do in Objective-C land.
First things first, the
DOD, which stands for domain
of definition, and we're going
to talk in more detail what
that means in a bit,
but this is how much --
what is the extent of the
output image going to be?
And in this case, it's --
our output image is the same
size as our input image.
So that's constant.
We're then going to compute our
radius and then create a vec2,
which takes us to the
center of the image.
And then, all we need to do
is call self myKernel apply
WithExtent dod and then pass in
an array of arguments, which,
again, you can see the input
image matches the first
parameter of our kernel,
centerOffset matches
the second parameter
and radius matches
the third parameter.
So that's how we pass
parameters from Objective-C land
into our kernel language lan.
So let's talk a little bit more
about domain of definition.
Oftentimes, domain of
definition is equal
to the input image size.
But there are situations when
that's not going to be the case.
So if, for example, we
have two input images
and we were doing a source over,
you can image that if either one
of these images didn't have a
0.0 origin, the output image
that you would want to
create would be larger.
And so, you would want to
take the union of those two
and that's what -- all
you need to think of.
What are the non-0 pixels
that your kernel is going
to be producing by taking a
given set of input images?
And that is what a
domain of definition is.
And as a parameter, you
have to always specify.
And that's really all you
need to know about how
to write color kernels on iOS.
So now, let's talk
about warp kernels,
which is our second
subclass of CIKernel
and let's you do geometry
modifications to an image.
So in addition to
specifying DOD,
you also need to specify
an ROI, and we're going
to explain what that
is in a minute.
But let's take a
look at the workflow.
The workflow is basically
that you get an input position
and you're asked to produce
a new output position.
And those are both
going to be vec2s.
So let's, once again, look
at the simplest example,
which is a kernel
that does nothing
and just returns destCOORD.
If we were to apply that kernel
to our input image, no change.
And so, if we were to look at
a random pixel in our image,
what we always need to think
about is, in our output image,
where does that pixel come
from in our input image?
And that is the equation
that we need to come up.
In this case, you can see
that it's just identity.
There's no change, which is why
we can just return destCOORD.
Let's take a slightly more
interesting example, where,
instead of just returning
destCOORD,
we're going to flip the image
around the center of it.
In this case, it should be
fairly clear that if we look
at a pixel near the shoulder
of this woman on the right
and the output image, the --
where we need to read from
in the input image is not the
same location.
Instead, we're going
to be reading
from a different location.
The y value won't be changing,
but the x value is different.
So destCOORD.y is fine,
destCOORD.x needs to change.
How do we do that?
Well, we have an x value,
destCOORD.x. We know what
the width of the image is.
We can pass that in as a
parameter to our kernel.
And using that, we
can do imageWidth-x
and that gives us the location
in our original input image
from where we want to read.
And if we do that, you can see
that the kernel above, mirrorX,
that's all we need to apply.
We just take destCOORD,
imageWidth-x
for our x coordinate, and
return the same value in y
and we get a mirroring effect.
So let's take a look at what
we need to do in Objective-C.
So now, instead of
creating a color kernel,
we create a CIWarpKernel.
We pass along the source
code we had earlier
and then, we call apply.
And now, apply you'll see has
one additional parameter we need
to pass, which is
an ROI callback.
And I'm going to -- the next
thing we're going to do is talk
about what is an ROI callback
and why do we need to do
that for warp kernels
and why it's important.
So ROI stands for
region of interest.
The basic idea is that
internally, Core Image is going
to tile your image and
perform smaller renders,
such that we can deal
with larger images
and do things --
optimally on the GPU.
Now, as I'm sure you can
imagine, what we need to do
when we're producing
a rectangle,
let's say rectangle 5 here,
is determine where the data
in the original input
image comes from,
such that we can load that.
And we can't figure that out on
our own and you need to help us
to provide that information
for us.
And you do that by
providing an ROI callback,
which is the additional
parameter that you need
to specify for a warp kernel.
So in this case, it
should be fairly obvious
if we take our mirrored
kernel that,
if we look at the
rectangle on the output image
and the rectangle on the
input image, that the --
we overlay our coordinate
system over these once again,
we can see that the width of
the rectangle isn't changing.
The height of the
rectangle isn't changing.
The origin and y of the
But we do have a new origin.
So all we need to do, given an
output rectangle 5 on the right,
we need to figure out
where the one on the left
and the input image comes from,
is compute a new rectangle,
a new origin, and that's simply
equal to the image width plus --
sorry, minus the origin and
the width of the rectangle
that we're currently
trying to render.
And that is basically all we
need to do for our ROI function.
So now, let's take a look
at a little more detail
of our mirror kernel.
Now, it -- in this case,
we're going to start off
by doing a check that
I mentioned earlier.
We -- that CIImages may
be of infinite extent.
And in order to keep the kernel
a little simple, we're --
we decided to just show you what
it looks like if you are dealing
with flipping around
the center of the image.
In this case, it
doesn't deal with images
that have infinite extent, so
we're just going to return nil.
This wouldn't be a difficult
modification to make,
but too long for
doing on a slide.
So first things first, inside
of our output image method
for the mirror kernel,
we're going to make
sure we're not dealing
with an image of
infinite extent.
We're then going to
get a few parameters
that we're going to be reusing.
So first things first,
we're going to create
and AffineTransform that
moves our image to the origin
and then applies that
translation onto the image
to create a new output image.
We then apply our mirror
kernel and once we're done,
we create a new translation that
moves it back to where it was.
In our case, where we're
looking at the previous slide,
there was no actual translation,
but if the image wasn't
as 0,0 we would have
had to do that.
And it's oftentimes easier
to think of a kernel in terms
of how would this be either
when its image is centered
or if it was at 0.0 and then do
the work about moving the image
in Object-C world than it
is to do in the kernel.
So let's take a look
at a slightly more
complicated kernel.
So let's pretend you had an
input image or some input video
and the size of this
image was 1024x768,
but what you really wanted was
an image that was wider and was
of -- in the width of 1280.
So we can do that with
an anamorphic stretch
and we're going to do that
by maintaining the center
of the image and just
stretching it out further
as you get away -- further
away from the center.
I should be fairly clear that,
based on this vector field,
that the y values for
this kernel aren't going
to change as well.
We're only going to be
modifying values in X.
So we can think about
this problem purely
in terms of x values.
So let's take a look at
a little bit of math.
It helps oftentimes to
have invertible functions
and let's take a look
at how we're going
to model this problem
in our head.
So let's pretend we
have an input value x
and some output value f(x).
If we weren't -- and we're
going to use these with respect
to the center of the image.
All this math is going to be
with respect to the
center image.
So it's going to go from
minus width/2 to width/2.
If we were not to modify
the scale of this image,
so if we were taking an input
image of size, you know,
1024x768 and producing 1024x768,
we would just have identity.
So a slope of 1, some
input value xi is going
to produce a new
-- the same value
on the y axis, f(xi)
is equal to xi.
But what we want instead is
that as we get further away
from the center of the image,
we want our points
to be moved more.
And we can do that by
creating a curve like this,
which maintains a slope of 1
through the center of the image.
And the equation
for this is just x
over 1 minus absolute value
of x/k, and we'll talk
about that k constant
in a moment.
And this is the same equation
that we're going to use
to compute the DOD, or
domain of definition,
that we spoke about earlier.
So now, if we take that
equation, we put a source value
of x into it, we get new
destination value of X,
which shows how far
away we moved.
In this case, the
equation is really handy
because it's very
easy to invert.
So if we were to
isolate the value of x
in the previous equation
from sourceToDest,
we would get a new equation
called destToSourcex,
which would just be 1/ -- sorry,
x/1 plus absolute value of x/k.
And this is the function
that we're going
to be using internally in
our kernel and our ROI math.
Because, as I said earlier, you
always have to think in terms
of where does this pixel
come from in the input?
So how do we compute k?
It's a relatively simple matter.
We just do desiredWidth, so in
this case 1280/inputWidth, 1024.
We get some scale value.
The k value is just equal
to inputWidth/1-1/scale.
And then, if we were to plug
these values into our equations,
we would see that sourceToDest
of 1024 would gives us 1280
and to destToSource of
1280 would gives us 1024.
So all the math works out.
Now, what does a
kernel look like?
It's relatively simply.
We get to reuse our equation
that we talked about earlier.
First things first, we're
going to translate it
such that we're working
with respect to the center.
We then apply our equation
and then translate it back.
And that's all we need to do to
create to an anamorphic stretch.
But we do have to
specify an ROI function.
So let's talk about what
an ROI function might look
like for this kernel.
So if we have an input rectangle
r, we're going to be asked
to produce some input,
rectangle r'.
So for a given rectangle
we're trying to render,
where does the rectangle in
the input image come from?
Now, if you didn't have
an invertible function,
you could always
return something larger,
but that might hurt you
if you were trying to deal
with very large images.
So it's helpful to
try to get this to be
as optimal as possible.
In this case, we have
easily invertible functions,
so we're going to be able
to compute this exactly.
So let's take a look
at the left --
and again, nothing changes in Y.
So all we need to worry about
is what's happening along the
x axis.
So we have our left point,
which is equal to r.origin.x,
from our original input
-- output rectangle,
and we want to find
out where our r' is.
We just need to put it
through our equation
for destinationToSource and
we get a new left point prime.
And then, if we look at
the point at the other end
of our input rectangle,
our -- so --
which is equal to
r.origin.x plus the width
of the rectangle we're
currently trying to render,
we can put that through
our same equation
and get a new right point prime.
Should be fairly obvious.
We have all the information
we need now
to produce the rectangle for our
ROI function and it's just going
to be computed by calculating
a new width, which is equal
to right point prime
minus left point prime,
and then we just
return a new rectangle,
which has the left point prime
as its origin, the same origin
in y that we had for the input,
a new width, and
the same height.
And that's how you would
provide your ROI function
for this kernel.
So let's take a look
at how we get
to reuse our code once
again from our kernel.
We have our equation and if
you look at the code here,
now we're back in
Objective-C land and we got
to reuse the exact
same math, just written
in C instead of CIKernel
language.
We can create a function
that just does the equivalent
of what we've shown in the
previous slide in PseudoCode,
and returns a new rectangle,
given three input parameters,
input rectangle r, a float
center, and a float value k,
which is our constant
in the equation.
The domain of definition,
similarly can reuse
the same math
that we talked about earlier.
And instead of using
as denominator 1 plus absolute
value of x/k, we use 1-x/k,
but it's exactly
the same otherwise.
And we can take that same
PseudoCode and apply it
to any given input
rectangle r to figure
out what the output rectangle r'
would be that we were producing,
given a certain scale
and the center.
So now, let's take a look
at the output image method,
which is what we used
to drive our kernel.
We need to compute three
constants that we're going
to pass into our kernel,
and it's oftentimes good
to compute whatever -- as much
as we can outside of the kernel
if it's a constant
and isn't changing
on a per fragment basis.
So in this case, we have our --
a value k that we can compute
in Objective-C land that
gets computed just once,
which is great, and then we're
going to compute the center,
which also we can compute
outside of the kernel, and then,
finally, the DOD, which is
what are the output pixels
that we're going to
be actually rendering?
And then, all we need to
do is call applyWithExtent
on the kernel that we
created given the DOD,
and now we have an ROI callback,
which is a block callback,
that has three parameters that
we pass in rect, center, and k.
Rect is given to us.
And in the case of a warp
kernel, index is always going
to be equal to 0 because
there's only one image.
We'll talk later
about other examples
about how this can get a
little more complicated.
And then, finally, we pass our
2 parameters to our kernel,
center and k, and
that's all we need to do.
So earlier, I alluded to one
more function that's useful
for deal with UI elements,
and that is the customAttributes
method.
The customAttributes method
lets you return a dictionary
and a whole bunch of keys, such
as what is this filter going
to -- what's its display name,
what kind of categories
does it apply to?
So for example, this
is a distortion effect.
It would apply equally
well on video
or still images, et
cetera, et cetera.
And then, for each input
parameter, you can talk
about what are its limits,
and this will help
us automatically put
up UI for your elements.
So if you were using this
in the context of something
like CI Funhouse, it
would be very easy
to just interact
with your kernel.
So that's all I have
to say so far
about color kernels
and warp kernels.
Let's do a brief overview.
So in the case of color kernels
we have zero or n input images.
The input type is going to be
an underscore underscore sample
which is effectively
just a vec4.
The output type is
going to be a vec4.
You do have to specify a
domain of definition or DOD.
And you do not have to specify
a region of interest function.
In the case of a warp kernel
there's only ever one image
that you'll be modifying.
You can get to that location
that you're currently trying
to render by calling
the function destCoord
which is going to
give you a vec2.
The output image is
basically just going
to be a vec2 location
once again.
You do have to specify a DOD and
a region of interest function.
The next thing we're
going to talk
about is the more
general-purpose kernels
which are just CIKernels,
and they have the
properties listed below.
And on that note I'm going to
hand it off to Tony who's going
to explain that in
a lot more detail.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; All right, thank you, Alex.
Good afternoon, everyone.
My name is Tony, and
what I'm going to talk
about now is the
third and final type
of kernels called
general kernels.
So here -- here again
are the three types
of kernels we support in
iOS, and what we've seen
so far are the first two,
color and warp, which allow you
to implement the
majority of filters
with as little code as possible.
And now the third type called
general kernels basically
completes the set
by allowing you
to implement any kind of filter.
So when would you need to
write a general kernel?
Well, it's simply whenever
you cannot express your kernel
as either a color or a warp.
One scenario could be that your
kernel needs multiple samples
of your input image, so for
example, any type of blur
or convolution filter
would need that kernel.
And a second -- a
second scenario would be
that your kernel contains
a dependent texture read.
And by that what I mean is you
have to sample from image A
in order to determine where
to sample from image B.
And in a moment we'll take a
look at a couple of examples
that actually illustrate
these two use cases.
But first let's just go
over some basic principles
behind general kernels.
If you recall this diagram
earlier for color kernels,
this shows that you can have
one or more input image --
images to your kernel
along with an output image.
But the key difference here
is that instead of each input
to your kernel being just an
individual color sample what you
actually get instead
is a sampler object
from which you can take as
many samples as you like
and order them however you need.
So let's take a look at
how you would actually go
about spreading a
general kernel.
So here we have a
very simple kernel
that effectively does nothing.
It takes an input image as
a sampler, samples from it,
and returns the color unaltered.
But in order to sample from
this input image you have
to provide the coordinate
in sampler space
and not in destination space.
And there are several
reasons why the two spaces
are different.
One could be your
input image is tiled,
but at the very minimum
the sampler space is
in a coordinate space
that's between zero and one.
But instead of having
to call destCoord
and samplerTransform every
single time you could also
conveniently call another
CI language extension called
samplerCoord, and
these two pieces
of kernel functions are
actually effectively the same,
and in fact compile up to
the same kernel program.
So now you might wonder why
would you use samplerTransform
when you can just
call samplerCoord
and write less code?
Well, let's imagine
you have a kernel here
that actually does something,
and in this case it's just going
to apply an offset of two
pixels in a vertical direction.
And let's walk through what
would happen in this --
if this kernel were
to be executed.
So assume we have an input image
here that's just 600 pixels wide
by 400 in your destination
space, and we're just going
to render that out to with
the exact same dimensions.
And assuming this image --
input image is not tiled our
sampler space is just going
to be normal -- in normalized
coordinates between --
with a range of zero
to 1 in both axes.
And let's imagine we're asked
to render out this pixel
in the center which has a
value of 300 in x and 200 in y.
In the first call the
samplerCoord will actually
transform this value
over to sampler space
and give you a value
of 0.5, 0.5.
And then if you were
to apply that offset
in that space you'll get
a value of 0.5 and 2.5.
And as you can tell
you'll end up sampling
from outside the image, and
the result you'll get will
be incorrect.
Instead what you want
to write is a kernel
that looks like this.
So again, let's walk through
what would happen in this case
if the kernel was executed.
You're going to first
call destCoord
which will give you a
value of 300 and 200.
And then you're going to apply
the offset in that space,
and you'll get a
value of 300 and 202.
Then you're going to call
samplerTransform with that,
and it'll give you a
value of 0.5 and 0.505.
And as you can tell, this will
give you the correct location
to sample from.
So this is the right way to
apply an offset in your sample.
So now that we got the basics
out of the way let's take a look
at some examples that are a
little bit more interesting.
The first one we're going to
look at is a motion blur filter,
and this is an example
where your kernel actually
requires multiple samples.
So imagine we had an
input image like this,
and in our kernel we're
going to compute the average
of N samples along a
bi-directional vector.
And in this particular
example we're just going
to apply a horizontal
motion blur.
And if you were to run this
kernel on all the pixels
of this image you would get a
result that looks like that.
So let's take a look at
what the kernel function
for this would look like.
So here we're going to define
our motion blur kernel called
motionBlur, and return
a vec 4, and it's going
to take two arguments.
The first one is your
input image as a sampler,
and a velocity vector that
will describe the direction
in which you want to blur.
And then we're going to
arbitrarily define a number
of samples to take
in each direction.
In this case it'll
be 10, but which --
but it may be larger depending
on what your maximum
blur radius is.
Then we're going to
declare a variable S
to accumulate all our samples.
And we're going to
first call destCoord
to get the current destination
of the location we're
rendering to.
And we're going to initialize
offset at the opposite end
of your velocity vector.
Then we're going to loop
through starting with one end
of your velocity vector, take
10 samples along the way,
applying the offset in each
iteration, take the center pixel
which -- which corresponds
to your destCoord,
and then take another 10
samples on the other direction.
And then once you've got all
your samples accumulated you
just need to average
them all and --
and that will give
you your final result.
So again, you would
put this all together
with a CIFilter subclass.
To initialize that kernel
that we just saw you just
call CIKernel kernelWithString
in path of the source
that we just --
that we saw earlier
in the previous slide.
And that string could
either be hard coded
in your objective C file or
loaded from a file off this.
And then in your
output image function
for this case our filter has
two parameters, an input radius
and an input angle from
which you can derive your
velocity vector.
And then you just call
apply on that kernel,
giving it those arguments as
well as a DOD and a region
of interest call back function
which we'll see in a moment.
But first let's take
a look at how
to calculate the
DOD for this filter.
So again, here is the input
image with given extent.
And if you were to
focus on the pixels
that are just outside the edge
of that image these pixels
were initially clear,
but because those pixels end
up sampling inside the image
when the filter is applied it
will actually become non-clear
pixels, and so your domain
of definition here is basically
expanded out in both direction
that is the distance
of the velocity vector.
And in this case this is
just along the x direction.
But for the general case your --
the expression that you can use
for your DOD is just that.
Similarly for the ROI if you
were to consider a region
that we need to render to that's
outlined here in -- in blue.
and focus on one of
the edges of the --
of this region, and
imagine if you were to --
if you needed to render out
that pixel in our kernel we need
to sample along the
bi-directional vector
and take N number of
samples along that vector.
You'll end up with a
region that you would need
for that input image
that corresponds to
the region in red.
And so again, the ROI
callback function would have an
expression that -- that is in
this case the same as your DOD.
And the reason for that is
because your blur kernel is
symmetric in all directions.
But now let's take this
effect one step further.
Imagine you had this input
image where you did not want
to apply the motion
blur uniformly
across the entire image.
Instead what you want is keep
the vehicle in this mage nice
and sharp and blur out the
background of the image.
And on top of that you
don't want to apply the blur
in the same direction for
all pixels; instead you want
to blur them out radially
to achieve an effect
that looks like this.
And so one way to imagine
this image is a camera that's
anchored to the car as it's
traveling through the road,
and the picture was snapped, and
you got the blurry background.
And so in order to achieve this
affect what you actually need is
a mask image that not
only masks out the vehicle
but provides a vector field
that describes your per
pixel blur velocity.
So let's step through -- let's
break down this filter step
by step to see how we
would implement it.
So you start with you input
image, and you're going
to generate a mask from that
to -- to mask out the images --
the pixels that you
not want to blur.
And then using that mask image
you can generate a vector field
that will describe on a
per-pixel basis the velocity
that you want to blur your
-- apply your motion blur.
And in this case the velocity
vectors are encoded in the red
and green channels in
this image, and the pixels
that are gray basically
represent a
zero-velocity vector.
Now you can -- that's -- you can
generate this mask image either
offline, or you can even
write a color kernel
to generate this image.
But let's assume for the --
this example that we
already have this mask image.
Then in our kernel what you
need to do first is read
from this mask image to
get your velocity vector,
and then you would sample
from your input image
and apply the same motion blur
effect that we just saw using
that per-pixel velocity vector.
And if you were to
run that kernel,
that will give you the resulting
image that we just saw.
So let's see how you would
implement this kernel function.
So here again was the motion
blur kernel that we saw earlier,
and the nice thing about CI's
kernel language is you can reuse
this function in this new
kernel by converting it
into a helper function.
And this function has
the exact same code
that we saw earlier
minus the kernel keyword.
And then you can
just layer on top
of that your new kernel function
that we have called
motionBlur WithMask
which in this case will
take an input image as well
as a mask image and a
parameter called radius
that will specify your
maximum blur radius.
And then in your kernel the
first thing that you do is read
from that mask image which
will contain the vector field
in the R and G channels.
And because those values are
stored in a range of zero
to 1 you need to
denormalize it to a range
between negative
1 and positive 1.
And once you got
that directional vector you
just multiply that with radius
to get a velocity vector.
And then you just pass
that velocity vector
into that motionBlur
helper function,
and that will do the
calculation for you
and give you the final
result that you want.
And again, you put this all
together with CIFilter subclass
which here is actually
very similar
to the first example
that we just saw.
The difference here --
the difference here
is the slight change
in the DOD calculation
where instead
of a velocity vector we have --
we just have an input
radius parameter
that basically represents
the maximum velocity vector
in your vector field.
And the other difference here is
when you apply the kernel the --
the roiCallback function
actually needs the
index parameter.
And this is the first
example where we see
that because we have more
than one input images.
So let's take a look at what
the roiCallback function
for that looks like.
Well, it's actually
pretty straightforward.
You just need to check the index
parameter for which your --
for which the ROI
is being called for.
And if the index is equal
to zero that corresponds
to our input image, and you
would return the same expression
that we saw earlier.
But if index -- index is
equal to 1 that corresponds
to our mask image, and for this
it's actually even more simple,
you just return the
same [inaudible] rect
because we just take one sample
from our mask image
using sampleCoord,
and so that maps one to
one to the same location.
So as you can see from these two
examples we can implement any
kind of filter using
general kernels,
no matter how complex they are.
And the reason for that
is because it was designed
to be a desktop-class
kernel type
that has the exact same language
syntax and semantics as OS X.
And as -- and as a byproduct
of that you can actually port
these general kernels back
and forth between
the two platforms
with very little effort.
And in fact some of the new --
new built-in filters that David
mentioned earlier were actually
ported over to iOS
using general kernels,
namely the glass
distortion filter
and the histogram
display filter.
So with the great flexibility
that general kernels offer
you there are some performance
and memory considerations
to keep in mind.
With respect to performance one
thing you should be aware of is
in order to get past
sampler objects
to your general kernel we have
to render out each input image
to an intermediate buffer first.
And so effectively
each input image
to your CIKernel adds
an extra render pass
to your filter graph.
And because we need to render
out intermediate
buffers you may need
to decide what format
is most appropriate
for a given situation.
In the case of your
working space being null,
i.e. your color management
is off,
you can just safely use
the 8-bit RGBA format
without worrying about any
quantization errors being
introduced in your
image pipeline.
But in the case of your
working space being the default
within your Rec.
709 you can use the
default 8-bit format,
but that would require
a conversion from linear
to sRGB space when writing
out the intermediate buffer,
and vice versa when reading back
from the intermediate buffer.
Alternatively, and this is
new in iOS 8, is the ability
to specify a 16-bit half-flow
format, and so you can do that
and not -- and avoid having it
incur the cost of a conversion
at every single pixel,
but it would require twice
the amount of memory.
So the right choice
will ultimately depend
on what your requirements are.
Now with these considerations in
mind you should be careful not
to think that every type of
filter needs to be implemented
with the general kernel,
even if it's a complex one.
Consider, for example, a square
kaleidoscope filter which,
by the way, is very similar
to the kaleidoscope filter
on the photo booth, but instead
of repeating triangles we
just have repeating squares
and -- like so.
So at first glance
you might think
that this filter would
need a general kernel
because it contains both
a geometric transformation
that warps the space that
you're sampling from as well
as a color kernel -- as
well as a color falloff.
And so you cannot
represent this kernel
with either a warp
or a color kernel.
So you can use a general kernel,
which is fine, but we'll see
in this case that you
actually don't have to.
Let's see if there's a
better way to implement this.
If you were to break
down this filter
into stages you will notice
that the first stage is just
the geometric transformation
for which you can just
apply a warp kernel.
And then the second stage is
the color falloff or attenuation
from the center, and for that
you can apply a color kernel.
And so in this example
you can see
that you can just chain together
a warp and a color kernel
and achieve -- and
get the same effect.
And this is actually the better
way to implement this filter
for some of the reasons --
for some of the advantages
that we heard earlier
with using these
specialized kernel types.
So here are the -- here
is the kernel code --
kernel function for
the warp kernel.
But in -- in the interest
of time we're not --
I'm not going to bother walking
through all the math
that's involved in this.
But I recommend that you
review this on your own later,
or even copy and paste it
into your own custom filter
to convince yourself that
it all works correctly.
Similarly, this is the kernel
function for the color kernel
which you can review
at your leisure.
But assuming we have the two
kernel functions already written
let's actually take a look
at how you would put
them all together.
So you start with your input
image, and the first thing is
to apply the warp kernel.
And if you were to run that for
all the pixels you would get
your intermediate image
which just has the
geometric transformation.
And for this example the DOD
for this filter is
actually an infinite rect
because the repeating
squares extend
out indefinitely
in all directions.
In the ROI callback function for
this is actually very simple.
It's just a constant
rect that is defined
by this little orange
rectangle in the input image,
and that's because all
the pixels that need
to be rendered just
needs to sample
from that small little region.
And then the next step is
to apply your color kernel,
passing in as input the
result from your warp kernel,
and the result that
you get after applying
that is the final
result that you want.
And again, the DOD for your
final result is infinite
because the warp kernel
image was also infinite.
So the key takeaway from all
this is you should only write a
general kernel when
needed, namely the --
the scenarios we saw with
the motion blur examples.
But if you're not sure you can
also write a general kernel
initially for rapid prototyping,
but then you should
try replacing it
with some combination of warp
and color kernels to get the --
for the sake of better
performance
and lower memory usage.
And with that I'm going to
hand it back over to Alex just
to say a few more words
before we wrap up.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Thank you, Tony.
Okay, so let's quickly talk
about platform differences.
I have some good news.
There is only one slide about
the platform differences.
They actually aren't
that dramatic.
There are some slight
differences, for example,
what type of renderers
are supported,
also the kernel language
on iOS allows control flow,
so you can express
more complicated things
in the language.
We have three kinds of classes
to do kernels on iOS whereas
on OS X we have just one.
You cannot specify
a sampler mode
on iOS, but you can on OS X.
Filter shape is different.
It's only a rectangle on iOS
versus a filter shape on OS X.
The ROI function on iOS is
done via a block pointer,
whereas on OS X it's done as
a selector from the filter.
And then there is some
tiny, tiny differences,
CIFilter setDefaults gets
called automatically on iOS,
whereas on OS X you need to do
that explicitly on your own.
And then finally,
the customAttributes method
is a class method on iOS
and is an instant method
-- instance method on OS X.
So let's talk about what
we've learned today.
First things first, we learned
how to write color, warp,