&gt;&gt; Hello and good afternoon.
[ Applause ]
Welcome to our session on
What's New in Core Location.
My name is Stephen
Rhee and I work
on the Core Location framework.
So Core Location is available
on both iOS and OS X but today,
the new features that
we're going to be talking
about today are specifically
for iOS.
Now some of you may be
new to Core Location
or even iOS, in general.
This will not be a review
of existing Core
Location functionality.
For that, we recommend
that you go
to our past WWDC
presentations online or check
out our great documentation
also available online.
Also, we'll be having a
lab session this Thursday,
so I recommend you all
come out and join us there
with any questions that
you have for us; however,
I think that today will
still be equally applicable
and interesting to those
of you who are new to iOS
and Core Location, to those
who are seasoned app
developers familiar
with both iOS and Core Location.
So what's new in Core
Location and iOS 8?
Today we're going to be location
authorization, visit monitoring,
and finally what's new is
indoor positioning; however,
we won't have time to talk
about that in this session
but directly following
this session here
in Marina [phonetic],
there'll be a dedicated session
to indoor positioning,
so I recommend you all
stick around for that.
So before we go on,
I'd like to start
with a brief history
of location on iOS.
Location was first introduced
in iOS 2 and then in iOS 3,
we added the ability
get heading updates.
In iOS 4, with the
introduction of multitasking,
came a whole slew
of new functionality
for location including
continuous background location,
which allows your app
to get continuous location
updates while in the background,
and region monitoring,
also known as geofencing,
which allows your app to
be launched and notified
when the user enters or
exits a predefined region,
to significant location changes,
which also allows your app
to be launched and notified
when the user's location
has changed significantly.
In iOS 5, we introduced
new APIs for geocoding,
both forward and reverse.
This allows you to take a
position that is a latitude
and longitude and
convert it to an address
or place mark and vice versa.
In iOS 6, we introduced
a power-efficient means
of getting location updates,
referred to as deferred
location updates,
in which locations will be
batched up and delivered
to your application
at a app-specified time
and/or distance interval.
And just last year in iOS 7, we
introduced iBeacon technology,
which has really
been taking off.
This allows you to determine
proximity via ranging
and region monitoring APIs,
which brings us to iOS 8,
which is what we're here
to talk about today.
As you can see, location
functionality has been growing
in iOS, as have the
number of apps
that you guys have
been developing.
In fact, there are over 680,000
apps using location on iOS.
These are all kinds of apps
ranging from navigation
to help users find their
way home, to travel apps,
to help users find interesting
things to do around them,
to fitness apps to allow users
to track their exercise
sessions, and shopping apps
to help users find stores
and deals around them,
to social apps to allow users
to interact with their friends,
and even gaming apps to
allow interesting uses
of their location.
So what does location look
like on the device today?
There's a visual
indication of location
in use via the status
bar location arrow icon.
This can be solid, as we see
here in the example of maps,
which is displaying the
user's current location.
Generally, the solid arrow
indicates that location
or ranging, or significant
location changes is in use.
Here, even on the home screen,
if there's an application
using location
or significant location
changes in the background,
the solid arrow will remain lit.
In addition to the solid arrow,
we have the hollow arrow,
which indicates that
region monitoring is in use.
Here, we see a traditional
example of region monitoring,
the Reminders app, which
uses region monitoring
to deliver reminders
when the user has entered
or exited a pre-defined
location.
And again on the home screen,
if there are still apps
using region monitoring
in the background, the
hollow arrow will remain
in the status bar indicating
that region monitoring
is still in use.
Next, the user can control
and get a finer picture
of location usage via the
Location Services settings.
This is the Settings app under
Privacy, Location Services.
At the top we provide global
control of location services.
And down below, we provide
individual per app control
of location.
In addition, per app,
we provide an indication
of location usage by that app.
This can be indicated by a
solid purple arrow indicating
that location has
recently been used,
to a solid gray arrow indicating
that location has been used
within the last 24 hours, or a
hollow purple arrow indicating
that region monitoring
is in use by the app.
So what does authorization
look like today?
Authorization is
a single request
that is prompted
implicitly on first usage
of location by your app.
This is for all location
functionality including location
directly in the app,
location from the background,
location use via
region monitoring,
and significant location
changes.
The text is also
customizable by the app.
Here we see a camera would like
to use your current location
with a description of
why camera uses location.
When location was
first introduced,
the request for the user's
current location was pretty
clear; however, with the
advent of multitasking
and all the powerful location
functionality that we talked
about was introduced allowing
you to create very cool
and powerful apps, we felt that
the user could use more clarity
of when location is being
used and more importantly,
we felt that your apps
could benefit too.
We don't want the user to
disable location, overall,
either globally or for
your app, disabling some
of the cool functionality that
you've developed using location.
We want them to understand
exactly how location is being
used, so ultimately
they can make better,
more informed decisions and
we believe that this is better
for battery and better
for privacy.
So to that end, we're
changing the way
that location services
works in iOS 8.
We started by looking at
first at all the functionality
that location services
provides and categorized it
into continuous updates,
which includes location,
background location,
and ranging,
and also location
monitoring or events,
which may launch the application
to deliver callbacks.
This includes region monitoring
and significant location
changes.
And we broke it down into
two authorization types,
the first being Always.
This is just like what location
authorization provided in iOS 7.
It provided both access
to continuous updates
and location monitoring even
when the app is in
the background.
But then we also introduced
WhenInUse, which is only
for continuous updates
and it's only
when the app is clearly
in use by the user.
So let's take a closer look
at Background Location.
Starting with continuous
background location,
which is specified statically
by the app either via the
Capabilities tab in Xcode
for background modes,
location updates
or via your app's information
property list via the UI
Background Mode key
specifying a value of location.
This, as before, must be started
in the foreground, otherwise
or if your app is using
significant location changes.
And this is available with
WhenInUse location authorization
because now in iOS 8,
we'll provide an indication
in the status bar that
your app is using location.
This is just like the
status bar for navigation,
when navigation is
running in the background.
Here, we'll indicate which
app is using location and,
if there are multiple,
we'll indicate the number
of apps using location, and the
user can tap on the status bar
to quickly return to the most
recent app using location
in the background.
One note is that if the
application is authorized
for Always location access, the
status bar will not be presented
because the user has
granted access for that app
to use location at any time,
which is what is needed in order
to access location anytime
from the background.
For example, when your app
is running the background due
to Background App Refresh or
due to region monitoring or due
to significant location changes,
this requires explicitly
Always authorization.
So on the topic of multitasking,
I'd like to clarify
location behavior.
When the user quits an
app from the App switcher,
this will immediately stop
Continuous Background Location;
however, this will not
stop location monitoring
such as significant location
changes or region monitoring.
This latter point is the
behavior as of iOS 7.1.
And now in iOS 8, disabling
Background App Refresh will no
longer disable any location
functionality because we believe
with the introduction of the new
location authorization types,
the user is now in complete
control of location usage.
So how does this all
look like to the user?
Apps must now explicitly request
authorization via new APIs.
We'll get into the exact details
of what this looks
like in just a bit.
Apps can request
for either WhenInUse
or for Always authorization.
Here, we see an example
of the authorization dialogue
presented to the user.
For compass, it says
Allow Compass
to Access Your Location
While You Use The App.
And below, we see
that customizable text
that your app can provide
indicating why it is
that your app uses location.
This text is now mandatory
and no longer optional.
This dialogue will be
presented only once to the user
for either request to location
access for WhenInUse or Always.
And as we said, that
text is customizable
and is mandatory to provide.
Quickly, we see an example
of the Always authorization
dialogue,
where it states Allow Weather
To Access Your Location Even
When You Are Not Using The App.
Again, the text description
below describing why it is
that the app would like to
use the user's location.
So as we see, this
Always authorization,
which is what users got in
iOS 7, is pretty powerful.
Because of this, if Always
authorization was granted
by the user, the
user will be asked
to confirm a few
days later and only
if their Always authorization
was exercised,
that is the app did use location
in the background perhaps due
to region monitoring or
significant location changes.
Here we see an example of
what that dialogue looks like,
where it says Weather Has
Been Using Your Location
In The Background.
Do You Want To Continue
Allowing This?
And again, we see that
the text is customizable.
It's the same usage description
provided in the original request
for location authorization.
So now let's take a look
at the new Location
Services settings pane.
Apps can support WhenInUse
and/or Always authorization
types and this is specified
statically by the app.
Again, we'll see the details
of exactly how you can
do this in just a bit.
And now in the Settings
pane for each app next
to the Location Usage
indication,
it will have the text
describing exactly what
that app is authorized for.
In addition, the user
can tap on the app
to see what authorization and
status types are supported
by that app with a text
description below indicating,
describing that current
selection.
Here we see an example
for WhenInUse app.
And quickly, another example
for an app that supports Always.
Note that in this pane, we don't
show the app description of why
that app would like
to use the location
in the current [inaudible];
however, you, as developers,
should prepare for
this because we believe
that this may present
another great opportunity
to inform the user why it is
that your app uses location.
Now also new in iOS 8, when the
user goes to the Settings apps
for your apps specifically,
a link to Privacy
will be included,
which also includes a link
to Location Services,
if applicable.
Here we see an example,
Fitness app.
The app Settings pane,
we see the Privacy.
The user can tap on that and get
to the Location Services
pane specifically
for its app right there
and change the authorization
status immediately.
Now this is going to be
even more powerful for you
as app developers because now in
iOS 8, your app has the ability
to programmatically
jump directly
to your app Settings pane.
This is done with the
existing openURL method
on UIApplication providing
the new constant in iOS 8,
UIApplicationOpenSettingsURL
String.
We'll see exactly how useful
this can be later in an example.
So you all are probably
wondering, that's looks great
and well, so what is it that
I as a developer have to do?
Well, starting with the
actual interface changes,
there are only three changes
that you need to be aware of,
the relevant Info.plist
keys that we talked about,
the authorization
status enum values,
and finally the new
authorization request APIs.
So let's dive right
in, first starting
with the Info.plist keys.
Previously we had the
NSLocationUsageDescription,
which was optional
and allowed you
to customize the text
displayed to the user why it is
that your app uses location.
This is now deprecated and
replaced by two new keys,
NSLocationAlways
UsageDescription
and NSLocationWhenInUse-
UsageDescription.
Note again that's
specifying one or both
of these is now mandatory,
depending on which
authorization type it is
that your application supports.
The value is the
string describing
to the user exactly why it is
that your app uses location.
We believe that this
is really going
to help users understand how it
is that your app uses location.
Moving on to the
CLAuthorizationStatus enum.
Previously there were
a number of values,
one of which was
kCLAuthorization
StatusAuthorized.
Now, this is deprecated and
replaced by two new values,
AuthorizedAlways and
AuthorizedWhenInUse,
depending on which authorization
was requested by your app
and which authorization
was granted by the user.
Accessing authorization status
for your app has not changed.
This can be done either
via the class method
on CLLocationManager
AuthorizationStatus
or via the delegate callback
via ChangeAuthorizationStatus
on the CLManager
delegate; however,
requesting authorization
has changed, which brings us
to the third interface change,
Request Authorization APIs.
Requesting authorization
is now explicit either
for Always or for WhenInUse.
Your app can make calls to
these requests APIs repeatedly;
however, it will only prompt
to the user the first
time and not per type.
So if you support both
authorization types,
you'll need to carefully
consider which you want
to request in your app.
We'll go further on this in
an example in just a bit.
So putting it all together,
there are three simple steps
to adopting the new
authorization in iOS 8.
First, you want to decide
which authorization it is
that your app supports by asking
yourself these two questions.
What location functionality
does your app use and is
that a mandatory functionality
or a nice-to-have
functionality for your app.
Second, you want to explain it
to your user exactly how
your app uses location.
And third, you want
to make the right call
to request authorization and
you want to do it when needed.
For example, when your app first
launches, don't make the request
to access location because the
user won't understand why it is
that your app is requesting
location authorization
and they may be inclined
to just deny that.
Instead, do it in response
to explicit user action
so that they have
context and in addition
to the usage description string
that you provide why
your app uses location,
the user can then make an
informed choice of whether
to allow or disallow
location access to the app.
Let's go through some examples.
First, let's say you've
developed this great fitness app
that tracks the user's runs.
You want to start by first
determining how it is
that location is used.
Obviously, this app is
going to use location.
In addition, it's going to use
background location in order
that the user may home-out
of your app and switch
to the music app and play
their favorite tunes.
So background location
can be enabled via Xcode
in the Capabilities tab, making
sure that background modes is on
and that location
updates is selected.
Alternatively, you can edit
your information property list
for you app specifying
the UIBackgroundModes key
with the value of location.
Second step is to add
the appropriate key
to your app's information
property list.
Here in Xcode, we'll go to the
Information Property List Editor
and add a new key
for NSLocationWhenInUseUsage
Description providing the
description to the user
that your location is
used to track your run.
And third, the final step is to
make the appropriate API call
to request authorization
and do it when needed.
So here, after creating
your locationManager setting
to delegate and right
before making the call
to startUpdatingLocation, all
you need to do is make the call
to
requestWhenInUseAuthorization.
Pretty simple, right?
Let's move on to
another example.
Let's say you've created this
great WelcomeHome app that's
going to automatically
turn on the lights
and maybe even unlock
the front door
when the user has
arrived at home.
Again, you'll want to start
by determining how location
is being used by your app.
In this case, it's using
region monitoring to detect
when the user has
arrived at home.
Next, you'll need to add the
appropriate usage description
key to your app's
information property list.
Again, you'll go to the
information property list editor
in Xcode and this time add a key
for NSLocationAlways
UsageDescription providing a
description to the user
here in this example,
here location is used to
determine when you arrive home.
And finally, you'll want to
make the appropriate call
to request authorization
and again, do it as needed.
In this case, right before
the call to start monitoring
for region, you'll
want to add the call
to requestAlwaysAuthorization.
Again, pretty straightforward.
How about if your app
actually supports both
authorization types.
Let's say you've developed this
great app for an amusement park.
In the general use case, it'll
show the app's current location
in the AmusementPark map
but let's say you've
developed this cool feature
that will additionally
deliver cool information
about nearby attractions
to the user.
And in this case, you'll want
to determine exactly how it is
that your app is using location.
Obviously for the general use
case displaying the user's
location on the map,
your using location,
but for that cool
feature that tells them
about cool attractions
nearby, you're going
to be using region monitoring.
So again, we follow
the same steps.
First, we're going to add the
appropriate usage description
keys to the app's information
property list again by going
to the property list
editor in Xcode.
We'll first start
by adding a key
for NSLocationWhenInUse
UsageDescription specifying
that your current location
may be shown on the map.
In addition to that, because
your app also supports Always
authorization, you'll add a key
to NSLocationAlways
UsageDescription,
again providing a
description to why it is
that your app uses location.
Here, this app will use
your location information
to identify nearby attractions.
So in your app's
information property list,
you'll actually have both of
these usage description keys
because your app supports both
of these authorization types.
And finally, you'll want to make
the corresponding authorization
request API calls.
Again, you'll want to
do this when needed.
For example, in the map view
that displays the
AmusementPark map,
you'll want to right before
startUpdatingLocation,
you'll make the call to
requestWhenInUseAuthorization.
And for that power user
use case, still in response
to user action, perhaps the
user has now enabled the feature
that enables the automatic
attraction info mode
that delivers information
about ride times
for the nearby attractions
or store sales
or restaurant specials, but
in this case, you may want
to check your app's
authorization status first
because if it's denied
or when in use,
you'll need to tell
the user that they need
to authorize your app
for Always authorization.
And in this case, you may want
to present an alert indicating
that and offer to take them
directly to the Settings app
for your app's settings
pane using
that mentioned openUrl method
with the new
UIApplicationOpenSettings
URLString.
And then finally, right
before you start to call
to start monitoring for region,
you'll make the call the
requestAlwaysAuthorization.
So some additional
details, what if you want
to support both iOS 7
and iOS 8 with your app.
Well there are three things
that you want to consider,
the lineup with the three
interface changes we
discussed earlier.
First, you'll want to continue
to provide the deprecated
NSLocationUsageDescription
string if you were
doing so before.
In addition, to specify
one or both
of the new Always
usage description
or WhenInUse usage
description keys.
Next, you'll want to guard the
request authorization API call
with respondsToSelector so
that your app will still work
on iOS 7.
Here's a quick example of
exactly how to do that.
And third, you'll
want to continue
to use the deprecated
kCLAuthorizationStatusAuthorize
value in addition to
the new authorize Always
and authorize WhenInUse values.
So I bet you're wondering,
what about legacy app support,
what if you don't
update your app
but your user upgrades
his system to iOS 8,
what's going to happen?
Well, your app will
still continue to work
but it will use Always
authorization.
So you don't want
to rely on this
because when the user uses
your app and uses location
for the first time, it's going
to pop that dialogue asking
for location access Always even
if your app only uses WhenInUse
location functionality,
such as location in the app or
background location or ranging.
So your user may at
that point decide
to disallow location usage.
So you don't want
this to happen.
You want to update your app now
and you saw exactly how
simple it is to do so.
So what about updating your app?
You can change the supported
authorization types anytime you
update your app and so when
your user updates the version
of the app, the version of your
app on his phone or device,
it will preserve the
user's authorization
if still supported.
Otherwise, it will go
from Always to WhenInUse.
For example, if your app
no longer supports Always
authorization but now
supports WhenInUse and it'll go
from WhenInUse to prompt again.
For example, again if your app
no longer supports WhenInUse
in this case and may now
support Always authorization.
But again, don't wait to adopt
because if the user denies
location access to your app,
it will stay denied even if you
subsequently change your app
to support the WhenInUse
authorization type.
So what about other frameworks
where location is used?
Let's go back to the
example WelcomeHome app.
Let's say that you don't want
your app to automatically turn
on the lights or even more
dangerously unlock the front
door automatically.
Instead, all you want
to do is notify the user
and let them decide to choose
to take action on
that notification.
In this case, your app actually
doesn't need to be launched,
just a notification needs to
be provided and now in iOS 8,
we've added region-based
triggering
to UILocalNotification
via the specification
of the CLRegion property
on the UILocalNotification.
In this case, your app doesn't
need Always authorization
because your app
will not be launched
in response to region
monitoring.
Instead, the system will
provide the notification
that you specified to be
provided to the user on behalf
and only when the user decides
to respond to that notification
and launch your app will
your app actually be in use.
So usage of this API
requires either authorization,
Always or WhenInUse but only
needs your app to be supported
for WhenInUse authorization.
And the steps to use
this API are the same
as any other location
functionality.
You'll want to specify the
desired usage description key
in your Info.plist with the text
string describing how it is your
app uses location and call the
corresponding authorization
request API, as needed.
What if you use MKMapView on
your app to display a map view
with the user's current location
via the showsUserLocation
property on the MKMapView class.
Again, this requires either
authorization for your app
but only needs your
app to be authorized
for WhenInUse authorization.
And the same steps as
before, you need to specify
which authorization
your app supports
in your app's information
property list
and make the corresponding
API call
to request authorization
when needed.
One last one I'd like to
talk about, Web views.
To allow web content that
uses HTML5 geolocation
to access the user's
current location,
this one also requires
either authorization
but again only needs the
WhenInUse authorization.
Again, you'll specify in your
app's information property list
the usage description
keys relevant
with a text description why
it is that your app would
like to use the user's
location; however, in this case,
the authorization request
will be made automatically
for WhenInUse on your behalf
because you may not know
when the user navigates to a
web page that uses geolocation;
however, if your app uses
Always authorization,
you'll want to make that
authorization request
in advance, if so desired.
So a quick recap, get ready
for the location authorization
changes that are coming in iOS 8
by following these
three simple steps.
First, think about how
your app uses location.
Second, explain it your users.
And third and finally, make the
call to request authorization.
Don't wait.
Do it today.
And then if you have any
questions, on Thursday,
you can come to us in our lab
session here this week at WWDC
with any issues or
questions that you encounter.
Next, I'd like to introduce
Brad, who's here to talk
about Visit Monitoring.
&gt;&gt; Thanks Stephen.
I'm Brad Jensen.
I'm a Core Location engineer
and I'm excited to introduce
to you Visit Monitoring.
But first, I want to
write an app with you.
See, Apple engineers aren't
allowed to publish apps
and I really want a journaling
app, so you're going to have
to help me out with this.
Journaling apps are
really interesting to me
but more importantly,
they're a great example
of Visit Monitoring.
It's a great type of
app that makes use
of this new technology.
So, what constitutes
a journaling app?
Well, first and foremost, it's
got to provide the user a list
of locations of where
they've been during their day.
But more importantly, that
list of locations needs
to be relevant to them.
If we list every time they
stopped at a interaction
or a stop sign, then
they're not going to find
that list especially useful.
Finally, we want to make sure
that our journaling
app can last all day.
If it's going to drain
the user's battery in two
to three hours, it's not
going to be very useful.
So, let's take a look at the
different Core Location APIs
that exist today and
we'll see why none
of them really work well
for journaling apps.
If you're working
on a check-in app,
you might find this
awfully familiar.
First up is the standard
location service.
This is where we
provide your app
with periodic location updates
as they become available.
Naturally, if we're going to be
providing updates to your app,
this requires the phone to be
awake and even more importantly,
the radios have to stay awake.
We have to periodically
scan for WiFi networks,
for cell towers or GPS.
Now, all of this is fairly
expensive and that means
that the app is going to be
consuming a lot of power.
In addition, the app is going
to receive a lot
of irrelevant data.
You're going to have to take
the stream of locations and try
and make sense of it, try
and identify those locations
that are probably
significant to the user.
So this isn't really a good
fit for a journaling app,
but if we were instead
writing a navigation app,
this would make a lot of sense.
You need the most up-to-date
information available in order
to tell the user when
to make their next move.
Before we totally throw out
standard location service
for journaling apps,
there are a couple
of improvements we
might consider.
A while ago we introduced
the automatic pause feature.
This allows Core
Location to save power
by pausing location
updates once it's determined
that the device probably
isn't in motion anymore.
This is really exciting
because it means,
well, we get to save power.
The device gets to
keep journaling longer.
Unfortunately, once the
user starts moving again,
your app will have to resume
those location updates.
And so we won't actually help
or this won't actually save
standard location service
in terms of writing
journaling apps.
If we were writing that
navigation app, however,
this would be a huge win.
Once the user stops
at a gas station,
automatic pause will save
their phone's battery.
Another option we might consider
is deferred location updates.
This one is really
interesting as well.
It allows Core Location
to save power
by waking up your app list.
App wake-ups cost power
and so fewer app launches
means more power saved.
Unfortunately, generating
locations is still quite
expensive and so even
though we're saving power
by not launching your app
every time there's new data,
we're still generating
all those locations
and not especially great.
So, deferred location updates
aren't exactly what we want;
however, if we were
writing a fitness app,
they would be great.
If you're writing
a run tracker app,
you don't necessarily
need the latest location
in the moment that's available.
It might be okay to
receive it every mile
or every 15 minutes or so.
All right, what else
do we have for us?
Well, there's the standard
or the significant
location change API.
This one is a lot
more power efficient
than continuous location
updates,
but there's a cost to this.
Instead of getting all of the
data, you get very coarse tracks
of where the user went.
Specifically, you only get
location updates every few
hundred meters the device moves.
This is going to make it
incredibly difficult for us
to identify places that
the user stopped at since
when the user stops, we stop
giving updates to your app.
If we were writing a
different app, for example one
that showed the user the path
they took home maybe identifies
the freeways they drove on,
then significant location
changes would make a lot
of sense.
But we're working on a
journaling app today,
so we're going to
have to keep looking.
Our last option is
region monitoring.
Region monitoring is really cool
because it's highly
power efficient.
Region monitoring can continue
while the phone is asleep
and your app only
receives information
that is directly relevant to it.
Unfortunately, you
have to specify
which locations are
interesting to your app
and that won't exactly work for
our use case because we want
to know about all
of the interesting
locations the user might go to
and there are far too
many interesting places
to monitor for them all.
So, that's all that
Core Location has today.
Do we give up, I have to
give up on my dream app?
Not yet. There's another one.
We're introducing
today Visit Monitoring.
What makes Visit
Monitoring different
from the other Core
Location APIs is
that it monitors
for destinations.
So instead of giving
you information
about how the user
got from A to B,
it gives you information
about A and B.
It will launch your
app when it detects
that the user has departed
from a location or arrived
at a new one and so
naturally this will require
Always authorization.
Visit Monitoring is
incredibly power efficient.
We employ all sorts of neat
tricks behind the scenes
to ensure this.
For example, while
the device is asleep,
it periodically performs
WiFi scans.
If Visit Monitoring is active,
we're able to harvest all
of those scans that would
otherwise have not generated
locations and use them to
enhance our visit detection.
Visit Monitoring is
also opportunistic.
So, if your app is using Visit
Monitoring and the user pulls
out apps and starts
navigating, all of the locations
that maps requests are fed into
the visit detection algorithm
and so your app benefits from
other apps' use of location.
Finally, it utilizes information
from across the entire system.
For example, suppose the
user arrives home and plugs
in their phone to
start charging.
It's much more likely that
the user would consider this
location where they started
charging to be an important part
of their day and so
we'll use that as a hint
that the user has just
arrived somewhere.
When we see hints, we'll
trigger arrival events much
more readily.
Finally, I'd like to point
out that Visit Monitoring
is not tied to landmarks.
I mean, when you receive
information about a location,
it's not necessarily an
intrinsically interesting
location, it's just a
location which is interesting
because the user has spent time
there or we've seen some hints
which indicate the user
might think it's interesting.
So, let's look at what
a visit actually is.
Suppose your user has
turned on Visit Monitoring
through your app and they
decide they want to go get a cup
of coffee, so they start walking
from their home to
the coffee shop.
At some point, Core Location
will get its first location
of the user at the coffee shop.
I don't know about you
but I can't see the future
and so Core Location
is going to have
to wait a little while
before it can say
for sure whether the user is
passing by the coffee shop
or whether they're there
to say for some time.
After we get a little bit more
data, it becomes clear that yes,
the user intends to stay
at the coffee for a while,
maybe it's time to
notify some apps.
At this point, Core
Location will launch your app
and provide it some
information about the arrival.
Most importantly, however,
it will do its best
to estimate the true
arrival time
of the user at the location.
Departures work similarly.
After some amount of time,
we'll get our last location
of the user at the coffee shop,
but Core Location will wait
until it gets a little bit
more data until it's sure
that the user has left.
At that point, we will
wake your app again
and we'll provide a departure
notification, doing our best
to estimate the true time when
the user left the location.
So, let's take a
look at the API.
We've added two new methods
to the locationManager,
specifically
startMonitoringVisits
and stopMonitoringVisits.
When we have information
to deliver to your app,
we'll do it through
the new delegate method
locationManager didVisit.
Some of you may have
noticed there's a new class
in that method's signature,
specifically CLVisit,
so let's take a look at that.
CLVisit is a fairly
simple class.
It's got four properties.
The first two are
arrivalDate and departureDate;
these describe when
the user arrived
and departed, respectively.
The coordinate, which represents
the place the user was visiting,
and horizontal accuracy, which
is an estimate of the error
on the location,
on the coordinate.
A few things you might want to
know about Visit Monitoring.
The values of horizontal
accuracy
and coordinate may differ
between an arrival event
and a departure event.
This shouldn't be
too surprising.
These are estimates based
on the data we have seen
and as we get more
data, we'll be able
to produce better estimates.
You should also note
that horizontal accuracy
should be no worse
than the horizontal accuracy
on a WiFi-based position.
So, if you find WiFi-based
positions are suitable
for your app, Visit Monitoring
will probably produce things
of equal value.
Naturally, since this is a
background monitoring service,
we'll launch your app even
if it's been quit,
as Stephen mentioned.
In addition, if the phone is
rebooted or your app crashes,
we'll still launch
it and provide it
with this information.
You should also know
that there are cases
in which Visit Monitoring might
detect multiple visit events
at the same time
and deliver them
to your app in a single launch.
So, when you receive visits,
you should be prepared
to handle multiple.
You may have noticed that
CLVisit doesn't have a isArrival
or isDeparture property,
so let's take a look
at how you can determine whether
a visit represents an arrival
event or departure event.
The secret is to look
at the arrival date
and departure date properties.
On an arrival notification,
the arrival date will
unsurprisingly be our best
estimate of when
the user arrived.
The departure date, however,
will be NSDate distantFuture.
On a departure notification,
the departure date will
be our best estimate.
The arrival date, I'd
like to point out,
could be distant past.
This happens if your
app wasn't authorized
for the arrival moment.
So, how do we check if a
CLVisit represents an arrival
or a departure?
You simply compare the departure
date to distant future.
Now, let's get back to that app.
There should be four
steps to implementing it.
First, we need to adopt
the new authorization model
that Stephen described.
After that, we need to
create our locationManager,
write our start and
stop methods,
and finally handle the visits
that are delivered
by Core Location.
Adopting the new authorization
isn't too difficult.
The hardest part is coming up
with a great way to describe
to your users how you intend
to use their location.
For this example,
journaling app, we might say,
this app needs your location
to automatically detect
the places you visit during
your day.
After that, we create
our locationManager.
I went ahead and did that
in the application delegate
because it provides a
great main thread context
for us to allocate it in.
The start and stop
methods are fairly simple.
The only catch is
you have to remember
to requestAlwaysAuthorization.
And the stop is even easier, you
just call stopMonitoringVisits.
Finally, the delegate, this
is where you take over.
Please keep in mind
that background execution time
is limited and, as I mentioned,
you may receive multiple visits.
So you shouldn't kick
off some long-running,
computationally-expensive
processing task here.
For a simple journaling
app, it might be best
to just record this visit in
a database and then save it
for later when the user
actually launches your app.
If you're writing a check-in
app, now might be a good time
to take a look at the location,
see if it's accurate enough
for you to actually
determine if the user is
at a specific restaurant,
for example,
and then maybe fire off a
UILocalNotification saying would
you like to check in.
Before I give the
stage back to Stephen,
I'd like to give you some advice
from the Core Location team
about Visit Monitoring.
Visit Monitoring is
not a replacement
for region monitoring.
If you're currently
using region monitoring
to receive useful information
about the user arriving at
or departing from
specific locations,
you should continue to do so.
Region monitoring is
more power efficient
and will give you more timely
information about those events.
In addition, Visit
Monitoring is not a replacement
for significant location
changes.
They provide you very
different information.
Significant location changes
is about the path the user too,
whereas Visit Monitoring
is about the destinations.
So, what do you do when you
encounter new technology,
you should try it out and
evaluate it for your use case.
See if Visit Monitoring covers
something that your app needs.
Then, on Thursday,
we're hosting a lab.
You should come to
our lab session,
bring any questions
you might have,
any problems you might
have encountered,
and we'll do our best to help
you get your app up and running.
Finally, please respect
your users' privacy.
This is an incredible technology
that will give your app a new
level of location awareness
but you should try to
respect your users' privacy.
Just because you can
obtain this data,
doesn't mean you
necessarily should.
If you have any questions,
there's going to be a session
about security and
privacy later this week.
I highly recommend
you attend it.
With that, I'd like to invite
Stephen back up onto the stage
to tell you about what's next.
&gt;&gt; Thank you, Brad.
So what else is new in
Core Location on iOS 8?
Well there was that third
bullet point we talked about,
Indoor Positioning.
Unfortunately, we
don't have enough time
to cover that in this session.
In summary, we talked about
location authorization
and changes and recall that
there are just three steps
that you need to follow to
adopt the changes in iOS 8.
First, you want to think about
how your app uses location.
Second, you want to
explain it to your users.
And third, you want to make the
call to request authorization.