&gt;&gt; Good morning.
Welcome to Session 709, Cross
Platform Nearby Networking.
My name is Demijan, and
I'm a Software Engineer
in the Real-time
Networking Team at Apple.
Last year we introduced a new
framework called Multipeer
Connectivity in iOS,
which makes it really,
really easy to discover and
communicate with nearby devices.
Building a network with nearby
devices can be accomplished
with only a few lines of code.
Many, many apps have decided
to adopt Multipeer Connectivity
for their nearby
networking needs.
And some of the use cases we've
seen have really made us smile,
so I'd like to mention
some of them to you today.
First, iTranslate Voice,
iTranslate Voice is an app
that brings real-time
translation to iOS users.
They use Multipeer Connectivity
to connect multiple devices
together and enable people
who don't share a
common language
to communicate with each other.
One person speaks a
sentence into their device
in their language, and the other
person hears the translation
of that sentence on
the other device.
It's really, really cool.
Second example is an app
called Metronome Touch.
Metronome Touch synchronizes
multiple metronomes,
and a metronome is a tool
that musicians use to play
to the same beat or
follow the same tempo.
Now Metronome Touch uses
Multipeer Connectivity
to accurately synchronize
multiple iOS devices
so that the metronome on each
devices picks in perfect sync.
And, third, FireChat,
FireChat brings nearby chatting
to our customers.
People who are nearby can now
communicate with each other even
when there is no internet
connection available.
This type of application
can be particularly useful
in environments, like subway
stations or airplanes,
for example, but
also in countries
with limited internet access.
We've seen many other use cases
for Multipeer Connectivity
and some of the prevalent ones
have been to exchange data,
such as files, and to
to-do lists for example,
and remote control
functionality.
Now throughout the year we've
heard a lot of good feedback
from you guys and we've
heard a lot of good ideas,
but one request that has come
up over and over again has been
to bring Multipeer
Connectivity to the Mac.
So this year I'm
really happy to announce
that we're bringing
Multipeer Connectivity
to OS10 starting with Yosemite.
From now on you will be able
to do cross platform nearby
networking between iOS
and OS10 devices just as easily
as you have been so far on iOS.
And the API is exactly the same,
so you should be
ready in no time.
All right, so let's talk
about the agenda for today.
First, I want to talk about
some basics so we set the stage
for the rest of the talk.
Then I will talk about
Multipeer Connectivity on OS10,
where I'll focus on some of
the specifics that are true
for development on OS10 and
for the OS10 experience.
Next, I will talk about
a few best practices.
And, finally, I'd like to cover
a few more advanced topics,
namely custom discovery
and authentication.
So let's start with the basics.
Multipeer Connectivity supports
three wireless technologies
on iOS -- Bluetooth,
Infrastructure Wi-Fi,
and Peer-to-Peer Wi-Fi.
On OS10 we will support
Ethernet, Infrastructure Wi-Fi,
and Peer-to-Peer Wi-Fi, as well.
So I'd like to talk about
Peer-to-Peer Wi-Fi for a moment.
Peer-to-Peer Wi-Fi
enables you to communicate
with other nearby devices
even if they're not connected
to the same access point,
or if they're not connected
to an access point, at all.
So, many of you have wondered
which devices support
Peer-to-Peer networking,
so I'd like to talk
about that a bit.
Well, on iOS it's pretty simple,
if your iOS device has the new
Lightning Connector then it
supports Peer-to-Peer Wi-Fi.
If it doesn't, it won't
support Peer-to-Peer Wi-Fi,
but on those devices you
can still use Bluetooth
and Infrastructure Wi-Fi.
For Macs the story is
also pretty simple.
If you have a Mac that
was released in 2012
or later then it will have
support for Peer-to-Peer Wi-Fi.
Okay, so let's establish
some terminology
that we will use throughout
the rest of the talk.
First, nearby, by nearby I
will mean anything that is
within the range of supported
wireless technologies.
A peer, a peer will be a device,
either our own or
a nearby device.
An advertiser will be a device
that makes itself discoverable
to other devices nearby.
And the browser will be a
device that is searching
or discovering other
nearby devices.
Multipeer Connectivity
happens in two phases.
First, the discovery phase,
where the devices
discover each other
and establish a communication
session
by sending invitations
to each other.
Then when they're connected
into a session the second phase,
called the session
phase, begins,
where they can exchange
data with each other.
So let's start with
the discovery phase.
The first approach
to discovery phase
that we support is UI based
and it's the most simple one.
We have a browser
and an advertiser.
An advertiser has to
instantiate a peer ID object,
a session object, and an
advertiser assistant object.
It then starts by
calling the start method.
The browser similarly
instantiates a peer ID,
a session, and the
browser view controller.
It then presents the
browser view controller
to the user to start browsing.
The rest of the process will
be entirely user driven,
and you will be notified when
the peers connect into a session
with the session delegate
method, peer did change state,
where the state will be
specified as connected.
So that was the UI
based approach.
The programmatic
approach requires you
to do a little bit more work,
but it gives you much
more flexibility.
So, again, we have a
browser and an advertiser.
The advertiser instantiates a
nearby service object instead
of an advertiser
assistant object
and the browser instantiates a
nearby service browser object
instead of the browser
view controller.
The browser starts by calling
start browsing for peers method,
and the advertiser starts by
calling start advertising peer.
So now both of them are --
the browser is browsing,
and the advertiser
is advertising.
When the browser discovers the
advertiser you will be notified
with a delegate method,
found peer.
At that time the browser
can send an invitation
to the advertiser by calling
the invite peer method.
When the browser calls the
invite peer method an invitation
will be sent out
to the advertiser,
and when the advertiser receives
the invitation you will be
notified with the did receive
invitation from peer method.
At that time the advertiser
has to decide whether it wants
to accept or reject
the invitation.
And let's say it
accepts the invitation,
then a message will be
sent back to the browser,
and they will start
connecting into a session.
When they connect with
each other, again,
you will be notified
with the delegate method,
peer did change state, where
the state will be specified
as connected.
So this was the discovery phase.
Let's now cover the
session phase.
So in the session
phase we assume
that the nearby peers
are already connected
with each other, and now what
they want to do is they want
to exchange data
with each other.
While Multipeer Connectivity
supports three sets of APIs
for exchanging that data --
messages, streaming,
and resources.
Let's start with messages.
A message is a chunk of data
with well defined boundaries.
If you want to send a message
you can use the sent data
method, where you will pass the
message as the first parameter,
encapsulated in an
NS data object.
You will also have to specify
an array of peers that you want
to receive the message.
When you receive a message
you will be notified
with a delegate method, did
receive data, which will pass
to you the message
and the sender.
Now if you want to send really
large amounts of data or data
without well defined boundaries,
such as a live audio stream,
for example, then you might
be better served using our
streaming APIs.
And to start a stream you can
call the method, start stream
with name, which will give
you an NS output stream object
that you can use to stream
data to the recipient.
The recipient will be notified
where the delegate
method did receive stream,
and that method will give
it an NS input stream object
that the recipient can use
to receive streaming data.
And, third, resources, we
support files and web URLs
to send as resources, and
you can send a resource
by using send resource at
URL method, where you specify
that the URL method of the
resource you want to send
and you specify which peer
you want to send it to.
You will also have to pass
to the framework a
completion handler,
and that completion
handler will be called
when the resource has
finished transmitting
or if something went wrong
during the transmission.
Now the receiver when it starts
receiving a resource will be
notified with a delegate method,
did start receiving resource
with name, and when the resource
finishes being received it will
be notified with
a delegate method,
did finish resource with name.
Okay, so in summary, we've
covered the discovery phase
and the session phase.
You can do UI based discovery
or programmatic discovery
which gives you a
bit more flexibility,
and in the session phase you
can use APIs to send data
where we support messages,
streaming, and resources.
Much more in-depth information
about these topics can be seen
at our last year's
WWDC presentation,
which you can see online.
All right, let's proceed with
Multipeer Connectivity on OS10.
The good news is that the APIs
on OS10 are exactly the same
as APIs on iOS, nevertheless,
there are some differences
that are different to the
OS10 experience and I would
like to talk about those now.
Let's start with
UI based discovery.
Imagine I have an app, I have
a Mac, which is running an app
that uses Multipeer
Connectivity.
I want to see if
somebody is around,
so I bring up the
browser view controller.
The browsers view controller
is presented as a modal sheet,
and in the lower left corner you
can see an activity indicator,
which indicates to us
that we're browsing.
Currently there is
no one nearby.
Let's then assume
that Gabe comes nearby
and Gabe is also running an app
that uses Multipeer
Connectivity.
Moments later we'll see in
our UI that Gabe is nearby,
and if I want to invite
Gabe into a session I have
to press the invite
button in the table view.
So I go ahead and do that.
When I do that an invitation
will be sent out to Gabe,
and when Gabe receives the
invitation we will present,
the framework will present an
alert that will notify Gabe
that I want to connect to him.
At this time Gabe needs
to decide whether he wants
to accept or decline
the invitation.
So let's assume Gabe is
game and wants to accept,
and accepts the invitation,
so he clicks on accept.
And an accept message
is sent back to me.
At that moment we
will start connecting,
and when we're finished
connecting it will say
so in the UI next to Gabe,
and I will be able to click
on the done button, which
will dismiss the browser view
controller, and I
am connected to Gabe
and start exchanging
data with him.
So this was the flow for
UI discovery on Mac OS10.
Let's now see how you can
implement this in code.
Now, first, you have to
instantiate and advertiser,
and this is done much
the same, like on iOS.
First, you instantiate the
advertiser assistant object
and you start it.
Now for the NC browser
view controller on OS10,
subclass is NS view controller,
unlike UI view controller
in iOS.
Note that NS view controller
has seen substantial changes
in Yosemite, and you can see
or you can hear much more
about those changes
in the session storyboards
and view controllers.
So to set up the browser view
controller on OS10 I have
to instantiate it, and I
have to set the delegate.
Then I have to -- then I present
the browser view controller
by using one of the new
NS view controller APIs,
present view controller
as sheet,
and I pass the browser
view controller object.
Note that self here
is a subclass
of an NS view controller.
We realize that you might be,
that your architecture might not
be based on NS view controllers,
and in that case you might want
to present the view controller
using the NS app begin
sheet method.
Well, if you want to do
that you can do that,
but first you will have
to get an NS window object
for the browser view controller.
And you can do so by using
one of the new methods
on NS window called window
with content view controller.
That method will give
you back an NS window
for the browser view
controller, and once you have
that NS window object you
can use the begin sheet API
to present the browser view
controller to the user.
When the user is done using
the browser it will click
on either done or cancel button,
and when that happens you will
be notified via the delegate
methods, browser view
controller did finish
and browser view controller
was cancelled, respectively.
In those methods you'll have
the opportunity to react
to whatever action the user
has taken and you will have
to dismiss the browser
view controller
by using the dismiss
view controller method.
Next, I want to talk
about entitlements.
If you are sandboxed, either
voluntarily or because you ship
on the app store you will have
to set entitlements
appropriately.
Multipeer Connectivity you
need support for both incoming
and outgoing connections,
so you'll have
to enable entitlements
for these operations.
If you don't do that then
Multipeer Connectivity
on OS10 just won't work,
so make sure you do that.
And that's really
everything that is different.
Everything else, like
programmatic discovery
and sending data, for instance,
is exactly the same as on iOS,
so you should be
ready in no time.
Okay, at this point I would
like to invite Eric on stage,
who will show you a demo.
&gt;&gt; Thanks, good morning,
everyone.
My name is Eric, and today I'd
like to show you a quick demo
of Multipeer Connectivity,
so let's switch over.
Great, so let's say
we're at a party
and everyone is taking photos.
It would be really cool if we
could collect all those photos
onto a map and display them
on a really large screen
for everyone to see.
To simulate this
sort of application,
today we have two iOS devices.
Here I have a white
iPhone and a pink iPhone,
and we also have a Mac,
and we'll be using
Multipeer Connectivity
to connect them together.
And whenever the iOS devices
take photos they'll transmit
them over to the Mac.
So let's take a look
at this in more detail.
Over here we have the Mac app,
on the left-hand side
we'll have a photo roll,
where the new photos will
pop in, and over here
on the right-hand side
we'll have a larger view
of the latest photo that we got.
Down here in the corner we
have a little browse button.
So let's get started.
I'll go ahead and click
on the browse button.
So here's the browser
that we saw earlier.
Right now it's currently empty.
When I launch the iPhone app
it will start advertising,
and the browser will
be able to discover it,
and it'll pop up in the list.
So I'll go ahead and do
that here, so there it is.
And I can go ahead and do
the same on the other iPhone.
Great, so now we have
both of the devices.
We can go ahead and
invite the white iPhone.
Over here I received the
invitation, so I'll go ahead
and tap accept, and we
can see that it connected.
I'll do the same for the
pink iPhone, so invite it,
and over here I'll accept.
Great, so now both of the
devices are connected,
we can go ahead and
click on the done button
to dismiss the browser, and we
can start taking some photos.
So I'll grab the white
iPhone, and let's see
if we can get a shot of
this camera right here.
Great, so it's sort of an
antique camera, I guess.
Let's see that with the
phone, we can compare them.
So you can see how far
we've come with the cameras.
Here's let me switch over
to the pink iPhone phone,
and let me take a picture
of this little rabbit thing.
Great, let's see, maybe I can
take one of myself, and then,
let's see, we'll switch over.
Here's a little thing of
Dismos [Assumed Spelling].
Great, okay, so let's see
if we can take a quick look
at what the iOS side looks like.
Okay, great, now that
was a quick demonstration
of cross platform nearby
networking with Multipeer.
So let's talk a little bit
about how I built the demo.
On the iOS side I took a piece
of sample code called AB Cam
that teaches you how
to use the camera.
Whenever we save a new still
image all we do is we take the
URL for the new file and we
use the send resource API,
we just saw, and that sends
it over to the Mac side.
Over here on the Mac
side I took a piece
of sample code called
image browser
and it just teaches you how
to display a grid of
images, like this.
I added in Multipeer
Connectivity to bring
up the browser, and whenever we
receive a new resource we just
add that into the image
list data source array.
So if you'd like to
learn more about how
to use Multipeer Connectivity
in your own apps we
hope you will check
out last year's iOS sample code,
it's called Multipeer
group chat.
And we're really looking
forward to seeing what sort
of new apps you guys
can come up with.
With that, I'd like to
hand it back to Demijan.
Thanks, everyone.
&gt;&gt; Thank you, Eric.
So Multipeer Connectivity
on OS10 is much
like Multipeer Connectivity
on iOS.
In this section we've shown you
the UI based discovery on OS10,
and we've told you which
entitlements you need to enable
to make Multipeer
Connectivity work in OS10 apps.
Next I'd like to talk
about a few best practices
that we thought you
guys should be aware of.
So let's assume we have two
devices, a Mac and a phone,
and let's say the
Mac is advertising
and the iPhone is browsing.
Moments later the iPhone
will discover the Mac
and it will have a reference or
it will have its peer ID object.
Then let's assume that for
some reason the Mac goes away.
For instance, the user
could have closed the lid
for some reason or the user
could have reset the system
because of a software update.
When the Mac comes back it will
instantiate a new peer ID object
and a new advertiser, and
the iPhone will discover it,
but it will see a new
object for the peer,
which actually corresponds
to the same Mac.
So this can lead to many issues
because iPhone doesn't know
that these two objects actually
correspond to the same device.
So in order to circumvent
that problem we recommend
that you reuse peer ID objects.
After you've created
a peer ID object
for the first time you can
store it in the user defaults,
so the next time you need it you
don't have to create a new one.
So if the Mac, when
it comes back,
reuses the first peer ID object,
the iPhone won't be confused
and it will only have one
object that represents the Mac.
Now let's see how you
guys can do this in code.
Once you've instantiated the
peer ID object you'll need
to store it in the
user defaults,
and to do so you'll first have
to serialize the peer ID
object using the archived data
with root object method.
Once the peer is serialized
into an NS data object you can
save it in the user defaults.
Later when you need to
de-serialize it and retrieve it
from the defaults
you'll first have
to de-serialize it
using an archived object
with data method, and then
when you have the original
peer ID object you can use it
in your application.
Next auto inviting, many of
you have made applications
that both advertise and
browse at the same time,
and when a browser sees an
advertiser it immediately sends
an invitation.
Basically, what you want to
achieve with this is you want
to abstract a way the connection
process from the user.
As soon as another user is
seen you want the devices
to connect to each other.
So let's assume we
have a Mac and a phone,
and both are browsing
and advertising.
So soon they will
discover each other,
and they will have a peer
ID object of the other peer.
But now the question
is who will be the one
to send an invitation?
And here's where many
of you get confused.
So in order to solve this
problem you can use a
deterministic algorithm
that will on both sides come
to the same result so that
only one peer will be the one
to send an invitation.
Now there are many ways you
can do that, and one of them is
to use peer ID hash
values or hash value
of the peer ID object.
Since both sides have access
to the same two peer ID
objects they will come
to the same determination as to
who has the higher hash value,
and only one invitation
will be sent out.
Next I want to talk about
discovery info a little bit.
Multipeer Connectivity
uses Bonjour underneath
for discovery, and you have the
option to set additional data
for advertisers when
you instantiate them.
Now this additional data
is passed to the framework
in the form of an NS dictionary
that we call Discovery Info,
and Discovery Info
is very useful
because it is made
available to the browsers
when they discover
an advertiser.
So first thing I want to advise
is to keep Discovery Info small,
this will make the discovery
experience much better
for your users.
Next both keys and values in
Discovery Info must be of type
and a string, if
any key or any value
in the Discovery Info
dictionary is not of type
and a string the framework will
complain and throw an exception.
Also, you should know
that each key value pair
in the Discovery Info dictionary
underneath gets formatted
in a Bonjour text record entry,
and each Bonjour text record
entry has a specific format,
which is shown in this slide.
First the key, followed by an
equal sign, and then the value.
Note that each text record
entry is limited to 256 bytes,
and if any key value
pair when formatted
as a text record exceeds
256 bytes the framework will
complain again and
throw an exception.
For more details
on Discovery Info
and Bonjour text records
I'd like to refer you
to the Bonjour RFC, which can
be obtained at the link quoted
at the bottom of this slide.
Okay, so now we're ready to
tackle on some advanced topics,
and I'd like to start
with custom discovery.
We've covered two approaches
to discovery so far.
The first one was UI based,
and it's really simple.
All you have to do is
instantiate an advertiser,
instantiate a browser,
and everything else is
entirely user driven.
Now this approach is
very simple to implement,
but the framework
gives you the UI,
so you don't have much
flexibility there.
If you want to design your
own framework you can use the
programmatic approach.
Now the programmatic
approach requires you
to do a little bit more work,
but you have much more
flexibility in terms
of how you define
the user experience.
So even given that we have
these two approaches we realize
that there may be some of
you who have the need to have
or to define the discovery
experience even more
or to customize it even more.
And for those we
offer a third way,
which we call the
custom approach.
Now the custom approach might
be useful for those users
that operate in environments
that is not Bonjour friendly,
for instance, or you
may have the need
to exchange large amounts of
data during the discovery phase
and that data cannot fit in
the Discovery Info dictionary.
So if you fit into one of those
categories you might find custom
discovery useful.
So let's go over custom
discovery in this section.
First, let me say that for
custom discovery you are
in full control of the discovery
process, so we will assume
that you will implement
a mechanism to discover
who is nearby and you will also
establish a one-to-one data link
between nearby peers.
So this will be your job.
Now the goal for nearby
peers will be to connect
into a Multipeer session
where they can exchange data
with other peers on
a many-to-many basis.
So let's see how
they can do that.
Assuming that we've
discovered nearby peers
and we've established
a one-to-one data link
between them, let's see
what you have to do in order
to connect them into a session.
First, each peer will need to
instantiate a peer ID object
and a session object, and
then it will have to --
they will both have to
complete a two-step process.
First, they will have to
exchange their peer ID objects
over the one-to-one data link.
So, in order to do that,
they will first have
to serialize their peer
ID object and pass them
over to the other peer.
Once the serialized ID object
is available they'll have
to de-serialize it, and at
that moment they'll
have the peer ID object
of the other peer.
Once the peer ID object
is available they'll have
to generate nearby
connection data
by calling nearby connection
data for peer method.
When nearby connection data
becomes available they will have
to exchange that object much
like before with the other peer,
so this is the second step
of the process, and when both
of these objects are available
on the other side
you can connect them
into a session using
connect peer
with connection data method.
When they are done
connecting, much like before,
you will be notified
with a delegate method,
peer did change state, and
the state will be specified
as connected.
Okay, so let's see how
we can do this in code.
Now serializing
and de-serializing can
be accomplished much
like we've described before
in the best practices section.
You can use, for serializing you
can use NS keyed archiver APIs,
and for de-serializing you can
use NS keyed unarchiver APIs.
So now that we've exchanged
the peer ID objects we have
to generate connection data,
and to generate nearby
connection data you can use
nearby connection data with
completion handler method.
The framework, when it's done,
will call the completion
handler, where it will pass
to you the object that
contains nearby connection data.
Then you will have to send that
object over to the other side
and when all peers have both
objects for the peer they want
to connect with they can do
so by calling connect peer
with nearby connection data.
In this method you also have the
opportunity to specify a timeout
in seconds, and this timeout
will let the framework know how
long you're willing to wait
until the peers successfully
connect in a session.
If for some reason you change
your mind during the connection
process you can cancel it
by calling cancel
connect peer method.
So in summary we've described
a fully customized discovery,
which you can use if you
can't use the UI based
or the programmatic
approach for your needs.
It consists of a
two-step process.
First, you need to exchange the
peer ID object, then you need
to exchange nearby connection
object, and when both
of these objects are available
for the other peer you can
connect it into a session.
Next up is authentication.
So some apps, for
instance, those that deal
with money transactions think
an app that enables people
to split a taxi cab
bill will have to rely
on properly implemented
security to provide safe
and trustworthy experience
to their users.
Multipeer Connectivity
gives you the option
of enabling encryption
and authentication
for providing security
to your users.
Now enabling encryption is
pretty easy, all you have
to do is set the flag when
you instantiate the session,
but in authentication it is
a little bit more involved.
So let's take a look
at how you can deal
with authentication
in this section.
If you want to provide
authentication
to your users you will have
to make sure that each one
of your users has
a digital identity,
and a digital identity consists
of a private key
and a certificate.
The users will use the private
key to sign their messages
and they will make their
certificate available
to other users so they can
verify if the signature is valid
and if they can trust
the sender.
In code a digital
identity is represented
by a set identity ref object.
The private key is represented
by a sec key ref object.
And the certificate
is represented
by a sec certificate ref object.
There are multiple ways how
you can distribute digital
identities to your users.
Perhaps the best way is to
make identities available
on a trusted web server so that
the users can download them
from that trusted web
server from within the app.
Other ways include
e-mail attachments
or via a mobile device
management server.
For more detailed information on
this topic I'd like to refer you
to the Tech QA 1745 and the
link for this is also provided
at the bottom of this slide.
Now let's see how you can import
a digital identity in your code.
Usually the digital
identity is stored
in a PKCS type 12 data file,
and these files are
password protected.
So the first thing you'll
need to do is get the password
for the file and store
it in a dictionary.
Next you will have to get
access to bytes in that file
by using data with
contents of URL method,
and once bytes are available you
can import the digital identity
by using sec PKCS
12 import method.
This method will import the
digital identity from the bytes
that we have from the file
and store it in an array.
So now you know what
a digital identity is,
how to distribute
it to your users,
and how to import
it in your apps.
Note that only certificate part
of your digital identity is
made available to other users,
and the other users can use
that certificate to verify
if you are really who
you claim you are,
and they can make a decision
if they want to trust you.
So let's look at how
they can verify this.
An end user certificate
can be issued
by a trusted root certificate
authority or it can be issued
by an untrusted intermediate
certificate authority whose
certificate was issued by a
trusted certificate authority.
This hierarchy of
certificates that starts
with the end user certificate
on the left and ends
with the trusted
root certificate
on the right is often referred
to as the chain of trust.
Roughly speaking, when we
evaluate the chain of trust,
the following step
wise procedure happens.
First, we inspect the
end user's certificate
and check if it's valid.
Let's assume it is, next,
we inspect the intermediate
certificate
and check if it's valid.
We also check if the end
user certificate was, indeed,
issued by the intermediate
certificate authority.
Say that checks out,
as well, finally,
we have to inspect
the root certificate,
and we check if it's valid.
We also check if the
intermediate certificate was,
indeed, issued by the
trusted certificate authority,
and if that checks out, as well,
then the chain of
trust is valid.
So in code when you
invaluate the chain
of trust the first
thing you'll have
to do is create a policy object.
This policy object will
govern how the chain
of trust is evaluated.
Then you will have to
create the chain of trust,
and once you have the chain
of trust you will
have to evaluate it.
So let's see how you
can do this in code.
First, we need to
create the policy,
and for our purposes we can use
sec policy create basic X509
API, which will create
a policy, an X509 policy
because we're dealing with
X509 type certificates.
Next, we have to
create the trust object
by using sec trust create
with certificates API,
and we also have to set
anchor certificates.
By anchor certificates we
mean the root certificates
that can be trusted
by the system,
so we have to let the system
know which certificates can be
at the end of the
chain of trust.
Once that is established, we
can evaluate the chain of trust
by calling the sec
trust evaluate method,
and the result will be stored
in the second parameter.
Now if the result equals
K sec trust unspecified,
that means that the
chain of trust is valid.
So, with that, let's see how
you can set up authentication
in a Multipeer Connectivity
session.
You'll have to use the
session initializer in it
with peer security identity
encryption preference method.