[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Good afternoon, everybody.
So, my name is Dan Kurtz.
Today, my colleague, Rhett
Dickson, and I will be talking
to you about What's New in
iOS Notifications and iOS 8.
So, before we get into all the
great new features of iOS 8,
let's lay down some foundation
about what notifications are
and how you have been
using them in iOS 7 today.
So, when I mention
notifications,
I'm actually talking
about two different types
of notifications, really.
We've got user notifications and
we've got silent notifications.
So let's start off with
user notifications.
What are these?
So, user notifications
are really just things
that the user can interact with,
see or hear on their device.
And they're coming
directly from your app.
So, for instance, with
the messages icon up here
on the top left-hand
corner of the screen,
let's say that the user happened
to receive a message from one
of their friends when the app is
currently not in the foreground.
Well, we've got three different
options for user notifications
that we could use
to let them know
that there's new information.
First one that we could
do is badge the app icon.
Having that little red
circle with the number 1
in there informs the user that
they've got one new message.
Now, for times that the user
happens to have that device
in their pocket and they might
not be able to see the screen,
we could instead play a sound
[sound plays] informing the user
that they've got a new message.
And lastly, we have alerts,
which tick down as that banner
from the top of the screen with
a little preview message of what
that message actually contains
so that the user doesn't even
have to tap on the messages icon
to check out what's there.
So we have badges, we have
sounds, we have alerts.
And for alerts, they
can actually appear
in different forms and in
different places as well.
Depending on how the user
happened to set their settings
for your app in the
notification center settings,
these alerts-instead of being
those banners that tick down
and then go away
automatically-they could appear
as modal alerts.
They'll stay up there on the
screen until the user happens
to interact with them.
And then we also have alerts
that they can be displayed
in the notification center drag
down as well as for the time
that the user happened to have
the device in their pocket
and the screen was off when they
happened to receive an alert.
Next time they turn it on,
it's waiting right there
for them in the lock screen.
So, where do these
notifications come from?
Well, for user notifications
they can come
from two different places.
First off, they can be coming
directly from your app.
That is, your app uses
UILocalNotification API
to present a notification
to the user.
Alternatively, you could
also have user notifications
that are triggered in response
to remote push payloads.
You've got an APNs server, the
app out there on the Internet.
In coordination with
the Apple Push Services,
you send a push payload
that defines, in this case,
an alert in it-oh,
sorry,-that results in an alert
that will appear
up on the screen.
Now, I go a little
bit over eager there.
We've also got another
type of notification.
I mentioned we have
user notifications
and silent notifications.
Silent notifications, they are
just push payloads that are sent
from your APNs server that,
instead of presenting a user
notification like an alert
or a sound or a badge on the
screen, iOS, when it receives
that push, will instead wake
up your app in the background
so that your app can do some
background image processing
or information processing.
In this case, your app is
fetching content from a server
so that the next time the user
happens to tap on your app icon
and bring it to the foreground,
that information is there
and ready so nobody has to
wait for a loading spinner
to complete and all
that other stuff.
So that's notifications
in iOS 7.
We've got user types,
we've got silent types.
User notifications can come
from locally on the app.
Remote notifications,
they can only be coming
from push payloads.
So let's talk about the new
features of iOS 8 notifications.
We're going to be talking about
four great new topics today.
First, I'm going to be talking
about user notifications,
what's changed about
them in iOS 8,
specifically with registration.
Then Rhett is going to come
up and he's going to talk
about a great new feature,
notification actions.
These are those interactive
notifications
to make your app interactive
even without it being there,
foreground on the screen.
Then we're going to
pass the baton again.
I'm going to come back to talk
about remote notifications,
some changes that we have
there for registering.
And then finally, we're going to
talk about one last new feature,
location-based notifications.
User notifications that
are triggered in response
to the user changing
their location.
So let's get on to the very
first topic, user notifications.
So, in iOS 8, regardless of
whether your app is going
to display remote
user notifications
or local user notifications,
your app must first register
to use those notifications.
And this is going to result
in an alert that is going
to be presented to the
user, asking them if it's OK
for your app to present
notifications to them.
So, what does this
code look like?
How do we register your app
in order to take advantage
of user notifications?
Well, the code is actually
pretty straightforward.
The very first thing you need
to do is declare the types
of user notifications
that you wish
to present from within your app.
In this case, this
app is actually going
to present all the
different types
of notifications
it possibly can.
It's going to be showing
badges on the icon.
It'll also be playing sounds
as well as displaying alerts.
Now, once we've decided the
types that we're actually going
to be presenting, we're going
to create a
UIUserNotificationSettings
object passing these types to
settingsForTypes categories.
Now, that second parameter,
the categories parameter,
you'll notice that
it's nil here.
Don't worry about it.
That has something to do
with notification actions.
Rhett's going to talk
about those later.
Finally, once we've
created the settings object,
we're just going to pass it to
the shared application instance
in registerUser
NotificationSettings.
And at that point, assuming this
is the very first time your app
has called this method,
the user is going
to be displayed an alert asking
them if it's OK for your app
to present user notifications
to them.
Now, they're either going
to say OK or maybe not now.
But no matter what they do, they
could always, at a later time,
background your app and change
their preferences and settings.
So this isn't the last time
that you have a chance in order
to present notifications
to the user.
So, once they've actually
replied to that alert,
your app delegate is
going to get a callback,
application didregisterUser
NotificationSettings.
That notification settings
object that we pass back
to you represents the
user's up-to-date,
most current preferences for
displaying notifications.
And at that point, all you
need to do is check what types
of notifications you're
allowed to present to the user.
So, again, like I mentioned
before, there is the possibility
that the user could
always background your app,
go into settings and
change their preferences.
And you need to stay
on top of this.
You don't want to be doing any
unnecessary processing for, say,
preparing a alert-type
notification
when you don't really need to.
So, we have API in UI
application as well.
This
currentUserNotificationSettings
method that is available
in the UI application
instance will give you the most
up-to-date user notification
preferences.
And from there you can make sure
that you're not doing any
unnecessary work to prepare
for notifications
that aren't going
to be displayed to
the user anyway.
So, that's user notifications.
Really, it's just a
registration method to state
that your app wishes to
use user notifications.
And to do this, you just need
to call registerUser
NotificationSettings
on the UIApplication
shared instance.
Any time you need to get the
most current user preferences,
you just have to call
currentNotificationSettings
on UIApplication.
And in order to create these
settings objects at the time
of registering, you just call
settingsForTypes: categories.
And recall, I said
the categories was nil
in the previous sample slide.
And that has something to do
with notification actions.
So, Rhett's going to
come up on stage and talk
about notification actions,
a great new feature in iOS 8
that I can't wait to see
you guys take advantage of.
Thanks.
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Thanks, Dan.
So, my name is Rhett Dickson.
And I'm going to talk
about notification actions,
a great new feature in iOS 8
that we're really excited about.
First, let's talk about
notification actions in iOS 7.
Whether on the lock screen,
notification center, banners
or modal alerts, you get one
default action when you swipe
or tap on the notification
that launches the
application in the foreground.
In iOS 8, in addition to that
default action, when you swipe
to the left on the lock
screen, you get two new actions.
Likewise, in notification
center, when you swipe
to the left, two new actions.
In banners, when you pull
down, two more actions.
And in modal alerts, when you
tap on the Options button,
you get up to four more actions.
So, to use notification
actions in your application,
you need to follow three steps.
You need to, first,
register your actions.
You need to, second, send a push
or schedule a local
notification.
And finally, once the user has
seen these actions and tapped
on one, you need to
handle the action.
To illustrate these steps,
I'm going to use the
calendar invite example
with three actions:
Accept, Maybe and Decline.
So let's first look at
registering actions.
You start off by
creating your action.
You then set the
identifier on your action.
The same identifier will
be passed back to you
when you handle the action.
You then set a title.
This is a localized string
that'll be shown to the user.
You then set the
activation mode.
This will determine if your
application is launched
in the foreground
or the background.
If you need to show UI, you
should choose foreground.
If you don't need to
interrupt the user,
you should instead
choose background.
If you do run in the background,
you'll have on the order
of seconds, not minutes, to run.
You then set whether the
action is destructive.
If this is Yes, the
action will be shown as red
on the lock screen and
in notification center.
Finally, you set whether
authentication is required.
If this is Yes, and the device
is locked, the user will have
to enter in their passcode
when they tap on the action.
If your action is a background
action, it's important to note
that the device does
not actually unlock.
So, if your application
accesses any files on disk,
you need to be sure
that they belong
in the correct data
protection class.
For more information
on data protection,
we'll point you toward
some more resources
at the end of this session.
So here's an example of
the accept invite action.
It doesn't need to show any UI,
so it can run in the background.
It's not destructive,
so it's shown in blue
in notification center
and on the lock screen.
And because accepting an
invite is relatively harmless,
you don't need to
require authentication.
On the other hand, if you
had a Trash Mail action,
it also doesn't need to show UI,
so it can run in the background.
It is destructive, so it will be
shown in red on the lock screen
and notification center.
And because you don't want
someone to be able to pick
up your phone and
delete all your email,
authentication is required.
Finally, we have a Reply action.
This does need to show
UI, so it will need
to run in the foreground.
Again, it's not destructive,
so it'll be shown as blue.
And because it's a foreground
action, if the device is locked,
the user will have to
enter in their passcode.
So, in this case,
the authentication required
property has no effect.
So, now that you've
defined your actions,
you need to group
them into a category.
A category is simply
a type of notification
with associated actions.
For example, you can have the
invite category, with Accept,
Maybe and Decline actions.
You could also have a New Mail
category with Mark as Read
and Trash, or a tagged category
of Like, Comment and Untag.
To start using the categories,
you first create one.
You then set the identifier.
You'll include this
identifier in your push payload
and your local notification.
You then set the actions on the
category for an action context.
There are two action contexts.
The first, the default
action context supports
up to four actions.
The second, the minimal
action context,
is used when there's only
room for two actions.
So, for example, if you set
these three actions, Accept,
Maybe and Decline, for the
default action context,
and if this notification
was then presented
on the lock screen, you would
see the first two actions,
Accept and Maybe.
If you wanted a different set
of actions, such as Accept
and Decline, you could set those
on the minimal action context.
Then when this notification is
presented on the lock screen,
you would see Accept
and Decline.
When this same notification
is presented as a modal alert,
because this is the
default action context,
you would see the
full three actions,
Accept, Maybe and Decline.
So, once you've defined
your categories,
you now need to register them.
You do this by first grouping
them together in a set,
providing them to your user
notification settings-this is
where Dan left us off-and then
registering those settings
with your shared
application instance.
So now we've registered
our actions.
The next thing to do is to
send a push notification
or schedule a local notification
to show those actions.
In the remote notification case,
you need to include the category
identifier in your push payload.
We'll use this to determine
what actions to show
when we present your
notification.
We're also very excited
to announce
that the previous size
limit of 256 bytes
for a push payload has now
been increased to 2 kilobytes.
[ Applause ]
So, in the local
notification case,
you create your notification
as normal.
You then set the category of
the actions you'd like shown.
Finally, you schedule the
notification as normal.
So, once you've sent
a push notification
or scheduled a local
notification
and the user has seen this
and tapped on an action,
you then need to
handle that action.
To handle the default action
when a user just swipes or taps
on the notification, launch your
application in the foreground
and call application:
didFinishLaunching WithOptions,
where we'll pass in
the local notification
or the remote notification.
In the remote notification case,
we'll also call application:
didReceiveRemote Notification:
fetchCompletionHandler.
If your application is
already in the foreground,
we won't actually
show the notification.
Instead, we'll either
call application:
didReceiveLocal Notification
or application:
didReceiveRemote Notification
with fetchCompletionHandler
if you've implemented that.
Otherwise, we'll
call the version
without the completion handler.
Finally, to handle the new
additional actions in iOS 8,
you need to implement at
least one of two new methods
on your application delegate.
In either case, we'll pass
you the action identifier.
You can use this to determine
what action was tapped on.
We'll also pass you either
the remote notification
or the local notification.
And you can use this to retrieve
any information you need
to handle that action.
Finally, we'll pass you
the completion handler,
which you must call when you
finish handling the action.
So, to summarize, to
use notification actions
in your application, you first
need to register your actions.
This involves defining
your actions, grouping them
into a category and then
registering those categories
with your user notification
settings.
You then need to send
a push notification
or schedule a local
notification,
including the category
identifier
of the actions you'd like shown.
You then need to handle the
action once the user has tapped
on it by implementing
one of the new methods
on your application delegate.
Notification actions are a great
new feature and we can't wait
to see what you're
going to do with them.
I'm now going to pass
it back to Dan to talk
about remote notifications.
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Hey. So, let's
talk about what's new
with remote notifications
in iOS 8.
So, recall we've got
two different types
of remote notifications.
We have user type
remote notifications.
That's when your APNs server
sends a push notification
to the device wherein the
payload we've got, in this case,
an alert, that results in a user
notification being presented
to the user as if it was coming
from the app that's running
or installed right
there on the device.
We've also got silent types
of remote notifications.
This is when your APNs server
is sending a push notification
with a content available
flag contained in it.
And then instead of us
presenting a user notification
on the device, instead iOS 8 is
going to come in, wake your app
up in the background,
then it can go
and fetch whatever
content it needs to
or do whatever info
processing is necessary so that
when the user next
launches the app,
all that info is right there
ready for them to ingest.
So, for user notifications
that are sourced
from remote payloads, just
like for local notifications,
you must make sure that your app
calls registerUserNotification
Settings before any
alerts or badges
or sounds are actually
going to be presented.
You will need to also
register for remote pushes.
And we'll show how to
get into that later.
Now, for silent notifications,
just like in iOS 7 and before,
you need to define in
your info.plist file a
UIBackgroundModes array.
And that array must
contain an entry
of remote notification in it.
So, user notifications,
silent notifications,
these are not mutually
exclusive.
Your app actually can use both.
Mix and match them to
whatever makes most sense
for your users and for your app.
So, for remote notifications,
you must make sure
that you are registering before
you can receive any pushes
from your APNs server.
Now, in iOS 7, when
you would register
for remote notifications,
we would ask the
user for permission.
But now, since we have separated
the concept of registering
for user notifications, which
does require permission,
from remote notifications
that could be user type
or silent type, we actually are
opting your apps into being able
to receive remote notifications
of any payload type by default.
However, keep in
mind-ah, OK, cool.
[ Applause ]
Thanks! Keep in mind,
however, that the user could
at any time go into
the settings app
and change their preferences.
So, how do we actually register
for remote notifications?
In iOS 7 and before,
we asked you
to call this method
here registerForRemote
NotificationTypes.
That's now deprecated.
Because we've change the way
we define user notifications
and remote notifications,
all you need to do is call
on UIApplication, register
for remote notifications.
Now again, this will allow your
app to receive remote payloads
that are coming from
your APNs server.
But if you want user
notifications to be presented
in response to those
payloads, if you've got, say,
an alert defined
in those payloads,
you also must make sure that you
call registerUserNotification
Settings, as I explained
earlier in the talk.
So, once you've called
registerForRemoteNotifications
as well as optionally
registerUserNotification
Settings, your app
delegate needs
to implement
applicationDidRegisterForRemote
NotificationsWithDeviceToken.
This actually isn't new API.
This is something that has
existed in iOS 7 and previously.
Just letting you know that you
still need to implement this
for handling remote
notifications.
And what this callback does
is it provides your app
with a device token, where once
you receive that token you need
to go and pass it off
to your APNs server.
Now recall, you need
to make sure
that you've always got the
most up-to-date device token
registered with your
APNs server.
Otherwise, pushes may not make
their way to the user's device.
So, in the case that the user
happened to disable your app
from using remote notifications,
or for any other failure case,
recall that the app
delegate also needs
to implement
applicationDidFailToRegister
ForvRemote
NotificationsWithError.
And at this point, all you need
to do is take that error object,
process it appropriately and
make sure you disable any logic
within your application
that's hinged off
of receiving remote
notifications.
You don't want to be doing
any unnecessary processing
within your app for
notifications
that aren't going
to be coming in.
Just gracefully degrade.
So, that's what's new with
remote notifications in iOS 8.
Again, just like before,
you do have to register
for remote notifications before
you can actually receive them.
However, now in iOS 8,
the user will be opted
into receiving remote
notifications.
And they could go into
settings later and disable this.
However, it does
still require you
to call this registration API.
As well as this API has changed.
We've simplified it,
and have named it
registerForRemoteNotifications.
You can call that on the
UIApplication shared instance.
Cool. So, let's get into
the last topic of today,
location-based notifications,
something we're very
excited about.
We've been working with the Core
Location Team for this feature.
Very happy to talk
about it today.
So, let's say that
you've got an app.
And you want to notify the
user when they happen to arrive
at some certain geographic
location.
So, the user is on their
device and they happen
to wander into that area.
And you want to show,
say, an alert.
Well you could do this
in iOS 7 and before,
but it required a lot
of hoops to jump through
and also could make
for a somewhat confusing
user experience.
In iOS 8, however, we
have streamlined this API.
All it is is simple
additions on top
of the UILocalNotification
API class.
And what you can do is define
core location region objects
and attach them to
this notification
so that the notification will
fire when the user happens
to come near, enter
or exit a region.
Now, you can make it so
that these notifications are
presented only the
very first time
that the user happens
to enter this region.
Or you could have it fire always
if that makes sense
for your app.
And, again, since this feature
is so tightly integrated
with core location, it
does require a little bit
of core location
registration on your part.
So, let's take a look at what
that registration
code is before we get
into how we can actually
schedule these notifications.
So, here we are.
What we need to do is create
a CLLocationManager instance.
Then we just need to set the
delegate on this manager.
The delegate is going to receive
callbacks notifying whether your
app is allowed to or not allowed
to track the user's location.
And then finally, in order
to enable these location-based
notifications,
on the location manager
instance you need
to call
requestWhenInUseAuthorization.
So, what does this mean?
WhenInUseAuthorization
-essentially,
if the user says OK,
will allow your app
to track the user's location or
know about the user's location
when your app is running
in the foreground.
However, recall these
notifications are going
to be appearing on the user's
device even if your app is
in the background or suspended.
And they might be able
to see these alerts.
Well, that's OK because even
if your app has been disabled
for core location, and even if
the user is seeing those alerts,
your app won't be
receiving any callbacks
until the user actually
interacts with that alert
and your app is still allowed
to track the user's location.
So we're requesting our
WhenInUseAuthorization
from CLLocationManager, assuming
this is the very first time
that your app has called
this code, the user is going
to be presented with
a permission alert,
just basically saying
is it OK for this app
to track your location when
it's running in the foreground.
Notice, however, in that alert,
we've got that usage text
down below in the smaller font.
This is actually something that
our app has defined on its own.
And you need to make sure
that your app defines
this usage text as well.
So to do that, in
your info.plist file,
hopefully this makes
it easier to read,
we've got NSLocationWhenvI
nUseUsageDescription.
You've just got to
define this key.
The value is going
to be a string.
And this is the actual
usage text that's going
to appear in that alert.
Recall, however, that
if your app is running
in different locales
in different languages,
you need to make sure that
this string is localized
appropriately for all
those other languages.
So, make sure that you
define values for this key
in your info.plist
strings file as well.
So, now we've asked the
user if it's OK for your app
to track their location when
it's running in the foreground.
Now we actually need
to handle the callback
from CLLocationManager.
And to do this, your
manager's delegate is going
to receive this callback
LocationManagerDid
hangeAuthorizationStatus.
At that point, all you need
to do is just make sure the
status is the When in Use status
if you are authorized
for tracking the user's
location when in use.
Then at that point you
can start scheduling these
location-based notifications.
So, how do we actually
schedule these
location-based notifications?
Let's take a look
at some sample code
of how we could schedule a
notification that triggers
in response to the
user entering a region.
Very first thing you need to do,
just like any other
UI local notification
that would otherwise be
triggered by a date or a time,
you've first got to create an
instance of UILocalNotification
and define what type
of notification this
is going to be.
In this case, we're just saying
this is going to be an alert.
When the user happens
to enter that region,
assuming the app isn't running
in the foreground, they're going
to get a little popup
saying: Hey, you have arrived.
Then, specific to region
type, core location type,
user UI local notifications,
we're stating here
that we only want
this notification
to trigger the very first
time the user happens
to enter or exit this region.
Now this is actually
the default behavior.
So, it's a little
bit superfluous here.
However, you could set this
to No if that makes sense
for your users and for your app.
Next, you just need to create
a CL region instance and set it
on the region property of
the UI local notification.
So, in this case, we're defining
a CLCircularRegion here,
and we're just giving it
some arbitrary coordinate
with some radius so that when
the user enters this circle,
this notification is
going to be triggered.
However, I did say that this
is a CL region property.
So, you could also use CL
beacon regions or any other type
of CL region subclass.
And if you want to find out more
about how you can
use Core Location,
especially in combination
with UILocalNotification,
I've got some resources
to point you towards
at the end of this talk.
Finally, on your UIApplication
shared instance, you just need
to call
scheduleLocalNotification,
passing this notification just
like you would any other
user-type local notification.
So, cool. Now we've actually
got this notification scheduled.
Assuming that your app is
running in the background
or suspended, rather, and
the user happens to enter
into that region, they're
going to be presented
with an alert saying: Hey,
you've arrived at
your destination.
And your app can handle
that local notification
in the applicationDidFinish
LaunchingWithOptions.
Alternatively, if your app
is running in the foreground
when the user happens to
enter into that region,
your app delegate is
going to be called back
with applicationDidReceive
LocalNotification.
So, the two different
methods here,
applicationDid FInishLaunching
versus applicationDidReceive
LocalNotification,
the logic is very, very similar.
So let's just take a look at the
latter step, or the latter part.
So, we've been informed that the
user has entered into a region,
or rather that the user has
received a local notification,
and we want to check
whether this is actually
region-based notification.
Well, UILocalNotification has
a region property now to see
if that region happens
to not be nil.
And if it isn't, we've got a
location-based notification.
And we can do whatever
makes sense.
Tell all the user's friends
where they've arrived.
So, that's location-based
notifications.
It's very, very simple
API that's added
onto UI LocalNotification.
And it's so simple because
we've integrated directly
with core location.
However, because
we've integrated this
with Core Location,
we do require some Core
Location registration logic.
Now, again, this is all as well
about keeping the user's
privacy first place in mind.
So, if the user happens to
have ever disabled your app
from being able to track their
location, even when your app is
in the foreground, you're not
going to be receiving callbacks
like applicationDidReceive
LocalNotification
for location-based
notifications.
The user might launch your
app in response to an alert
that was presented as a
location-based notification.
But still, your app
isn't going to know that.
And that was a lot of stuff
that we talked about today.
Biggest thing, we've
been talking
about notification actions.
Rhett came up here, talked
about this great new
feature for iOS 8.
So psyched to see
you guys use it,
making your apps interactive,
even when they're not running
in the foreground, in really
new and powerful ways.
Some simple changes behind user
and remote notification
registration.
Again, we've separated the
concept of having to register
for different remote
notification types
and instead ask you to register
for the user notification types
that your app is going to use.
And then we had location-based
notifications,
integrating tightly
with Core Location
to schedule user
notifications in response
to the user entering
or exiting regions.
So, that was a lot of stuff.
And we've got great resources
for you guys to check out.
Paul Danbold, he's our Core
OS Technologies Evangelist.
He is a great guy.
And you can send him
letters at danbold@apple.com.
We've also got documentation
at developer@apple.com
as well the dev forums.
Talk to like-minded developers.
Find out how other people are
using these great new features.
Ask your questions.
Get them answered.
But, but, but-this is WWDC.
And we've also got
other sessions.
Now, these sessions
happened previously.
What's New in Core
Location as well
as Taking Core Location
Indoors happened yesterday,
but these are available
online as well
as Protecting the User's Data.
Rhett hinted at that
data class protection.
Well, in 2012 we had a
session on these as well.
And you can check out
these videos online, too.
So, you guys have been great.
Thank you so much
for coming to WWDC.
Hope you have a great
rest of your week.
[ Applause ]