[ Silence ]
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Good afternoon.
My name is Katie
Skinner and I work
at Apple Product
Security and Privacy.
That means I work with teams
all across Apple on user privacy
and protecting our users.
This includes our
platforms like iOS, Siri,
and applications like iPhoto.
Today in this session, David
Stites and I are going to talk
about ways you can protect your
users' privacy and changes made
to the Apple ecosystem
to improve user privacy.
Thank you.
So, we're going to start
out talking about privacy
and reputation, identifiers
in iOS,
how to prompt your users well,
new classes for data isolation,
and some privacy best practices.
So, privacy and reputation.
Your users are so
important to you.
They're the key to your success,
so maintaining your relationship
with them is your
most important thing.
They're the people
who download your app,
tell their friends
how great it is,
don't think twice
before uploading photos,
or granting you access
to contents.
Or alternately, those
are the users
who will uninstall your
application or think twice
about using location with you.
So, privacy and how you protect
your users' data is a big part
of this.
Lately there's been an appetite
in the media for stories
about privacy, from
large stories
like Target to smaller ones.
But, they continue to
appear over and over again.
The best bet is to be
trustworthy with your users
because rebuilding
user trust is hard.
It's much more difficult than
maintaining your users' trust.
Now, I'm going to talk about the
identifiers available in iOS.
There are three purpose-scoped
identifiers.
The first one is the application
identifier, NSUUID UUID.
The second one is the
vendor identifier,
UIDevice currentDevice,
identifierForVendor.
The third one, advertising
identifier,
UIDevice currentDevice
identifierForAdvertising.
Now, I'm not going to talk about
these in a lot of detail today.
Last year we talked about
them, how to use them,
their behavior, lifetime.
So if you're new to the
platform, you should go and look
at "Protecting User's
Privacy" from last year's WWDC.
It's a great place to start.
Now, this is a great
reference slide to look
at when you're thinking
about which identifier to use
for a particular use-case.
I'm going to pull
out a couple points.
The application identifier
is used
to identify something
uniquely within a single app.
The vendor identifier
can be used
across multiple applications
and it's all in the same device
with the same team ID.
Now, the application identifier
you need to manage yourself,
but the vendor identifier
iOS will manage for you.
The advertising identifier
should be used
for all user tracking
for advertising,
or related to advertising.
Now, there's been a lot
of discussion about how
to use the advertising
identifier,
what are the supported
use-cases?
But, before we get into that
I want to allay one point
with you guys, is be
clear with your users
about how you advertise,
especially if you're using
their user data as part
of your advertising practices.
You should not cache the
advertising identifier.
You need to respect
a user's ability
to reset this identifier.
They can reset it under
Settings, Privacy,
Advertising using the Reset
Advertising ID button.
Also this year, for TestFlight
apps the advertising identifier
will be different each
time you call the API.
This is another reason
why you shouldn't count
on the advertising identifier
to be a stable value.
In iOS we've given users a
choice about how they want
to be served advertising
and that really comes
back to Limit Ad Tracking.
Before using the advertising
identifier you need
to check the value
of Limit Ad Tracking.
This is ASIdentifierManager
sharedManager
advertisingTrackingEnabled.
Note, this may be controlled --
this can be controlled
by restrictions,
and with Family Sharing this
year this may affect more
of your users.
Even if you, yourself,
are not writing the code
to handle the advertising
identifier
and you're using a third
party advertising library,
you need to ensure that that
library is also checking Limit
Ad Tracking before using
the advertising identifier.
When advertisingTracking
Enabled is set to No,
the advertising identifier
is not permitted to be used
to collect data for, or to
serve, targeted advertising.
You can use it only for
the purposes enumerated
in the iOS Program
License Agreement.
This includes frequency
capping, conversion events,
fraud detection for advertising,
and debugging for advertising.
Note, for fraud detection and
debugging this can only be used,
not for all fraud detection,
not for all debugging,
only debugging advertising
issues.
This year in iTunes Connect,
now you need to explain
and attribute why you're using
the advertising identifier
for which of these uses.
You should select one,
two, or three depending
on how you use the
advertising identifier.
The first one's pretty
clear; serve advertisements.
The second one, attribute
app installation,
now once a user installs
your application,
this means attributing
that installation
to an advertisement
they may have seen
in a different application.
The last one, attribute an
action, this could be Coins Bot
or any other in-app purchase.
Attribute that action taken to a
previously served advertisement,
either within your app
or another application.
Now, here's where you go
and make these choices
in iTunes Connect.
You can see the first thing that
you do is say, "Are you going
to use the advertising
identifier, or not?"
Then select which of the
three choices or more than one
that you'll be using the
advertising identifier for.
And then lastly, you must say
that you will check Limit
Ad Tracking before using the
advertising identifier.
Now, I'm going to talk about a
couple changes coming to iOS 8
and OS X Yosemite that
are privacy-related.
The first one's Family Sharing.
This means that this year
there'll be an increased number
of child accounts within
the Apple ecosystem.
There's a great talk by Chris
Espinoza [assumed spelling]
right after ours that will go
further into the implications
that you should be thinking
about as a result of this,
so I would encourage everyone
to stick around after our talk
to hear "Kids and Apps".
He'll talk a little bit
more about the relevant laws
like COPPA to be
thinking about for this,
for the additional number
of children on this system.
So, here's the talk,
right in here.
In iOS 8 the Mac address
during probe requests
and probe responses, as
well as region monitoring,
will be locally administrated
and random.
This means if you
interact or design a piece
of external hardware
you should not count
on a stable Mac address
until after authentication.
Go test some iOS state
and understand the impact
this may have for you.
This year in Safari
there's a new setting.
This will allow users to
block third party cookies
and it is available
both on iOS and OS X.
Now, I assume most of
you, if not all of you,
in the audience have
a web presence,
even if it's only a website
that points and has a link
to the App Store, you
have a web presence.
So, go on iOS, enable
this setting,
and visit your web presence.
Understand the impact that this
will have on you and ensure
that your users will still be
able to do the things they need
to do on your website; go to the
App Store, FAQ, whatever it is.
Here you can see where you
can go and find this setting.
On iOS it's under
Settings, Safari,
in the Privacy and
Security Section.
On OS X you can find this
under Safari Preferences
on the Privacy tab.
Note, this setting
is not on by default
but this is a choice
that users can make.
Also in iOS, we've now
given the ability for you
to utilize the people picker
without requesting
Contacts access
to the full address
book from your users.
This is a great win for apps
that don't need the
whole address book,
that maybe only you
need to send an invite
to one person you're
going to share every
so often with a single user.
But note, this will provide only
a static -- static information.
If the user then later
goes and decides to change
or update this contact
you will not receive any
of that information.
In a future seed, some of the
iOS 7 delegate methods are going
to be deprecated so you
need to update and migrate
if you're currently
using the people picker.
We have a great sample code
project for you to go and check
out and see how to
implement on iOS 8.
These are the delegate methods
that will be deprecated.
ABPeoplePicker
NavigationController Delegate
peoplePicker
NavigationController
shouldContinueAfterSelecting
Person
and shouldContinue
AfterSelectingPerson
:property:identifier.
And, we also have some new
properties and delegates
in iOS 8; ABPeoplePicker
NavigationController
.predicateForEnablingPerson,
predicateFor SelectionOfPerson,
and predicateFor
SelectionOfProperty.
And then new delegates
are ABPeoplePicker
NaviagionControllerDelegate
peoplePicker
NavigationController
:didSelectPerson
and didSelectPerson
:property :identifier.
So go and update,
and migrate early.
Now, I've gone through several
different privacy changes
and what I want to encourage
everyone here to do is
if they're not already
have a device on iOS 8
and OS X Yosemite, update now.
Understand the impact these
changes will have on you
because you have a great
experience for your users today,
and you don't want to mess it
up as they move and migrate
to iOS 8; keep a
consistent great experience.
Now, I'm going to
hand it over to David,
who's going to talk more
about the keys to prompting
with purpose and how to
be successful at that.
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Thank you and good afternoon.
As Katie mentioned, I'm
going to talk to you
about both prompting your users
with purpose and then dive
into data isolation and how
it works on both iOS and OS X.
Prompting with purpose means
designing the experience your
users will receive
when they're confronted
with a privacy dialog.
There are five core
principles that form the basis
for prompting with purpose;
consent, transparency, context,
clarity, and minimization,
and we'll talk
about all of those coming up.
The first principle is consent.
Consent is getting
your user's approval
to access their user data.
This should already
be familiar to you.
The model that Apple has
chosen to adopt is the Just
in Time model, meaning that
consent is only presented
to the user at the exact
time that the access occurs.
We think that Just in Time
access is a key differentiating
feature of our platform.
If the user decides
to allow access,
then you'll get data back.
And, if they decide not to allow
access, you won't get anything.
Transparency is the
second principle.
Transparency is complementary
to consent
in that it answers the question
of why an app needs
access to user data.
Apps are given a dedicated space
to tell users called
a purpose string.
And purpose strings
are as an apps chance
to explain the proposition
value of allowing that access.
If the user understands that
there might be more willing
to allow your application
access.
In this example, Calendar
wants to use Location
to estimate travel times and
improve location searches.
The third principle is context.
Context is making it clear
to your users what action led
to the consent dialog.
Consider this example.
Here we have the App Store.
And, when the user
goes to the Near Me tab
and taps the Show Popular and
Near Me link they're presented
with this dialog saying the app
would like to use their location
to find relevant apps near them.
Contrast this with a conga line
of alerts that are presented
to the user right when the
application first opens;
not a great user experience.
Conga lines don't work
because they're not presented
at the correct time so
make sure you choose
to present yours at
the correct time.
The fourth principle is clarity.
Clarity is distilling the
purpose of your request
down to its essence because it
helps users build clear mental
models about what you're going
to do with their user data.
You can think of this
as improving the why,
and when, and where.
Give the user a guide
of what they can expect
from your application.
Be concise, but include
sufficient detail.
In this example, Reminders
clearly states what it's using
Location for.
The last and fifth
principle is minimization,
and this one's super simple
because it's exactly
what it sounds like.
If you don't need access to that
data then you shouldn't ask.
Scared users are more
likely to tap Don't Allow.
All of the consent dialogs
support a purpose string,
and their use is
highly encouraged
because it makes what
you're going to do
with the user data
very transparent.
All of the data classes
support one purpose string,
except for Location Services
in iOS 8, which supports two,
and we'll talk about
that coming up.
You can set these
purpose strings
in your application's
info.plist.
And for those of you who
localize your applications,
you can set the localized
versions
in Localizeable.strings.
What you need to do is
you need to go to X code,
select your target,
select the info.plist,
and then fill out the strings.
You should look for the
privacy-data class keys.
Now, X code is simply a
frontend to the info.plist so,
if you want to, you can always
edit the info.plist manually.
In this example we see we have a
new application here that wants
to access Camera and Microphone
so that they can help you record
that new music video
for your album.
Now, there are several new
purpose string keys on iOS,
including Location, Camera,
HealthKit, and Motion Activity.
The reason Motion
Activity is listed here is
because it was announced
after WWDC last year.
You can always find the full
list of purpose string keys
in the Information Property
List Key Reference located
on the Apple Developer website.
When a user wants to go manage
their privacy settings on iOS,
they understand that they need
to look in the Settings app,
then Privacy, and then
look for the data class
that they want to manage.
Similarly, on OS X users will go
to System Preferences, Security
and Privacy, then Privacy.
This is what Apple and
developers have tried
to communicate with users.
However, users may want
to update their privacy
settings from time to time.
Perhaps your application
came out with a new feature
and they want to
take advantage of it,
or perhaps they've just simply
changed their mind on one
of their privacy settings.
We're excited to give you
a brand new ability today
to send users directly
to their privacy settings
so that they can manage them.
You can do that with
UIApplication sharedApplication
openURL and then pass it a URL
with a string UIApplication
OpenSettings URLString.
This is going to
drop them directly
into their settings bundle.
For each application
installed on iOS 8,
the device will now have
their own settings entries,
as well as full privacy
settings.
Users can go to these settings
and manage those settings.
If your application already
has a settings bundle,
then these entries
will be prepended to it
so you don't have to worry
about losing your settings.
All of the things
that we've talked
about so far form the
principles for data isolation.
For the developers
who are new out there,
data isolation is a technical
design where the OS intervenes
between an application
and the user's data
on behalf of the user.
This occurs outside the address
space of your process, however,
it's completely transparent
to your application.
Just simply calling the existing
APIs will help you gather
consent and inform the user.
If they decide to
allow the application
to access the data,
you'll get data back.
And, if they don't allow access,
then you will receive
nothing back.
There are several new data
classes and updated data classes
on iOS 8, including
Location, Contacts, Camera,
which is now worldwide, Motion
Activity, and HealthKit.
OS X Yosemite supports all the
same data classes that it did
in OS X Mavericks;
Location, Contacts, Calendars,
Reminders, and Social.
However, there were no
new additions or updates.
If you're already
shipping an application
on the App Store, that's great!
This data isolation applies to
your application from day-one.
You don't have to recompile
or resubmit your
application to the App Store.
However, certain changes
can help you improve the
user experience.
For example, if you
are accessing Camera,
new this year we've added
that to data isolation,
so additional UI might
be helpful to explain
to the user why they're
receiving a black screen,
or essentially all zeroes
in their video stream.
Also, adding purpose strings can
help clarify why you need access
to this data.
So, now that we know
what data isolation is,
let's briefly discuss what
that looks like on OS X.
On OS X, when an application
calls the purpose specific API,
the OS will handle that request
and present the dialog
to the user.
For example, if you call
ABAddressBook sharedAddressBook
ABPerson alloc init then
that will call the system
to pop up the dialog.
On OS X the calls
are synchronous.
So, you're going to want to
use Grand Central Dispatch
and wrap the invocation
in a block
to keep the UI responsive
while your user decides.
After the user has made
their initial decision,
the APIs will return
immediately.
As I said before, when the
user makes their decision,
if they decide to
grant you access,
then you will receive
populated objects.
And, if they decide
not to allow access,
then you will either receive
nil objects or no objects.
For applications that use system
services, such as Spotlight
or AppleScript, then
the OS will still prompt
on the user's behalf.
On OS X applications can
participate in the app Sandbox
and if you ship on the Mac App
Store then you are required
to participate.
For the new developers
out there,
the Sandbox is a security design
that isolates your process
from the other processes
on the system,
as well as the operating system.
Applications that are Sandboxed
typically have a tight set
of restrictions that
are imposed upon them.
So, if you're going to Sandbox
your application there's going
to be more work that
you'll have to do
to get these consent
dialogs to show up.
You'll need to add entitlements
to your entitlements plist,
which we'll talk about
here in a second.
An important note is that if
the permissions ever change
in the future while your
application is running,
the system will prompt the
user of whether they want
to terminate the app immediately
or wait until its next launch
to make the Sandbox consistent.
To add the entitlements to
the application all you have
to do is go to the
entitlements plist or use Xcode
to modify those entitlements.
What you would do
is you would go
to the targets My
Application Capabilities,
turn on the App Sandbox,
and then select the
entitlements that you want.
You should only build with the
entitlements that you need.
If you're interested in learning
more about the App Sandbox,
there's a reference at the end
of the talk to a practical guide
to the App Sandbox that
was presented in WWDC 2013.
So now that we've talked
about data isolation on OS X,
let's talk a little bit
about data isolation on iOS
and contrast it to that.
On iOS data isolation
is obligatory
because applications are built
on top of the App Sandbox.
However, you don't need
to add entitlements
to your application
as you did in OS X.
Also, access is asynchronous
so API calls will
return immediately,
and then data would be returned
via a block or a delegate call.
Unlike OS X, if the user decides
to change the permissions
of your application, then
you will receive a SIGKILL
signal immediately.
There is no chance to wait
or have the user
decide at a later time.
You need to be prepared
to handle changes
in permission status via change
notifications and, honestly,
this was a good idea anyway
because the user can change
their permissions at any time.
There's multiple ways to trigger
these data consent popups
and all you have to do
is simply call the API.
There's four new APIs in iOS
that will trigger these
consents; Location, Photos,
Camera, and HealthKit.
And, we're going to go over
some examples of that right now.
Location Services in iOS 8 now
supports two different modes
of updating device location;
when in use and always.
And the functionality
that is provided
in both sounds similar
to how they're named.
Also, depending on what
targets you want to support
with your binary, you may need
to conditionalize your logic
to call the appropriate methods.
When in Use is exactly
what it sounds like.
You're only able to access
the devices location while the
application is in
the foreground.
The API that you would call is
CLLocationManager requestWhenIn
UseAuthorization and
the info.plist key
that you would use
is NSLocationWhen
InUseUsage Description.
This is a more privacy-friendly
mode
because applications cannot
update location while they're
in the background.
Additionally, applications won't
have access to functionalities
such as Region Monitoring,
the Significant Location
Change API, or the Visits API.
Also, if your application
implements the UI Capability's
Background modes for
Location, in their plist,
then if you start updating
Location in the foreground,
and then serialize the
application to the background,
then the OS will implicate your
application as using Location
in the background by drawing
a double height status bar.
Here we can see that where
Fitness is using our Location
in the background.
Always authorization
is the second mode.
Its API is CLLocationManager
requestAlways Authorization
and the info.plist
key that you'll need
to implement is NSLocationAlways
UsageDescription.
You should only try and use
this mode when necessary
because it has an increased
privacy impact to the user
because applications can
start accessing Location data
in the background and
the app has access
to the significant Location
Change APIs, the Visits APIs,
as well as the Region
Monitoring APIs.
The default mode
for applications
that are not updated
to take advantage
of these new APIs will
be Always authorization.
And, if you use Always
authorization then the OS will
occasionally re-prompt the
user for access to Location.
You should only use this mode
if you think your users
will thank you for doing so.
So, previously on iOS 7 you
could implement this info.plist
key, NSLocation
UsageDescription.
That's now deprecated.
And, on iOS 8 there are
two new purpose strings,
NSLocationWhen
InUseUsageDescription
and NSLocationAlways
UsageDescription.
You must put one or two of these
plist keys in your info.plist.
Calling the APIs without
these keys will not work.
If you want to target
multiple operating systems
in a single binary then
you may need multiple keys.
So, let's take a look at what
a code example might look
like for this.
On iOS 7 you probably would have
had some code that looks similar
to this, CLLocationManager.
You get a shared manager object
and then you call
startUpdatingLocation.
This is what implicitly prompted
the user for access to location.
In iOS 8 we're changing that so
that you explicitly request
access to a user's Location
by calling requestWhenIn
UseAuthorization.
In this example we see we're
asking the Objective-C runtime,
"Do you respond to
the selector Request
When in Use Authorization?"
And if not, then we call
the old way of doing it.
Alternatively, you can
also call requestWhenInUse
or requestAlways Authorization.
Note that if you fail
a particular request,
either Request Always
or Request When in Use,
you can't request the
other mode, you're done.
You can't prompt up or down,
in terms of access rights.
So, we've talked a lot about
Location, and the changes
to Location, and what's new.
Here are the important
takeaway points.
There's two new modes
in iOS 8 versus iOS 7,
and there's two new
info.plist keys
that you'll have to implement.
While there is a
bunch of implications
to which modes you use, you
should check out what's right
for your application by
going to see "What's New
in Core Location"
that was presented
on Tuesday of this week.
The second example I would
like to talk about is Camera.
In iOS 8 Camera is a
data isolated data class.
Here, we create an
ABCapture Session,
and then we create
an ABCaptureDevice,
and simply calling the
API AVCapture DeviceInput
deviceInput WithDeviceError will
present the dialog to the user.
While the user decides, the
video stream will be all zeroes,
or essentially a black
screen, so you need to be able
to explain that to your user.
Then below, you can
either handle the failure
or the success as you choose.
The last code example I
want to show is HealthKit.
On this code example,
we're checking first to see
if HealthKit data is
available on this device.
Then, we're allocinitting
an HKHealthStore and asking
for access to the heart
rate type identifier.
This is an important
point because access
to HealthKit data types
is very, very granular.
And, you should only ask for
access to the data classes
that you're going
to actively use.
What you would do then is
call requestAuthorization
ToShareTypes completion
to prompt the user.
Now, you can't check
to see whether
or not the user gave you access
to read or if there, in fact,
is any data at all
of that data type.
That's part of the
privacy design.
So, the success variable
in the block actually indicates
whether the user was prompted
or not, not what the
response of the user was.
If the request was not
successful, then the error --
the NS error will be populated.
Writing is slightly different.
You can check to see if you
have authorization to write,
and you do that by calling
authorizationStatus ForDataType.
This will return you back
in authorization status,
which you then can then
conditionalize your logic on.
Also, applications can only
edit, or modify, or delete data
that they have written, not
other applications' data.
So, you should check your
authorization status first,
and then if you need to,
ask the user for permission.
Calling saveObject
and deleteObject will modify
those particular objects.
So, we've talked
about data isolation.
What are the differences
on the different platforms,
and that's a lot of information.
So, we need to be able to test
it and it's really easy to test.
All you need to do is
run your application.
You should already
be testing on-device,
however the simulator
does support a lot
of the data isolated classes.
Note that apps can only trigger
the prompt once, so if you need
to go back and retrigger it
on the iOS you need to go
to Settings, General, Reset,
Reset Location and Privacy,
or on OS X use tccutil.
Consider all of the different
test cases, and there's four
of them; permission
being sought and denied,
permission being
sought and granted,
permission previously denied,
and permission restricted.
You might even want to
consider building these
in to your unit tests so that
you don't ship any regressions.
I'd like to talk a little bit
about permission restricted,
as that's a special,
interesting case.
Restrictions can
prevent your users
from changing their privacy
settings even if they want to.
For example, enterprise
restriction
or on-device restrictions
can prevent the user
from changing their
privacy settings.
So, you should try to
send users to settings,
but your code should
be resilient
to the lack of data returned.
The OS can help you
fail gracefully.
Some of the picker classes
in iOS will actually show a lock
page indicating the user has
previously declined
access to that data type
so you shouldn't design dialogs
that say go flip the switch
in the case that
you're restricted
because users may not actually
be able to flip the switch.
It's easy to test
with restrictions.
All you have to do is go to
Settings, General Restrictions,
and then choose the
data type that you want
to test restrictions with.
So, we have some
great iOS sample code
out there for you today.
It's called "Checking
and Requesting Access
to Data Classes in Privacy
Settings" and it's available
on the iOS Developer Library.
You can use it directly
in your project
or just download it
and play with it.
So, that's data isolation
and prompting your
users with purpose.
I'm now going to give it back
to Katie so she can take you
through privacy best practices.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; Thanks, David.
So now, I'm going to finish
off talking about some things
that you can do and apply
in your application.
I'm going to talk about
transparency, data collection,
avoiding fingerprinting, and
how to protect your users' data.
So, David talked about
transparency already.
He talked about in terms of
consent and Just in Time alerts.
But, transparency is
important even wider.
This is all about insuring
that your users understand
what's happening to them
and what's happening
to their data.
Users should never be
surprised if you explain
to them how your code works or
what's happening to their data.
Think about what the
user expectations are.
This is what you should go
back to and think about.
What would users think
is happening here?
So, there's other ways
that we can be transparent.
Logging is one of those places.
For instance, both on iOS and
OS X, if the user has selected
to submit logs to
Apple via Diagnostics
and Usage the user can
go and look at these.
You can go in iOS under
Settings, Privacy, Diagnostics
and Usage, and look at all the
logs that will be sent to Apple.
You can also see them
via the console on OS X.
Another example of this on
OS X is for crash reports.
You can then expand
out and view the data
that would be sent to Apple.
I would also encourage
you to think about his
when you have a data
store of user data.
Figure out a way to
visualize this data
and let them see what
information you're storing.
Users like when they have
the control to be able to see
and understand what's happening.
Your Privacy Policy
is another way
that you can be transparent
to users.
It's a great tool.
Your Privacy Policy should
include what data you collect,
what you plan to do with
that data, and if you plan
to share it with any third
parties, who they are.
As a family's sharing, you may
need to include a kid section
of your Privacy Policy, as well.
There are four different areas
this year where we are going
to be requiring a Privacy Policy
if you're taking advantage
of this functionality.
The first one is apps that
link against HealthKit.
Second, HomeKit.
Third, third party keyboards.
And lastly, if you want your app
to show up in the kids' section
of the app store you will
also require a Privacy Policy.
We make it easy to submit a
link and you can do it right
in iTunes Connect, and
then this will be visible
in all of the App Stores.
So, here you can see
in iTunes Connect,
you probably know this page,
it's where you write
the description
of what your app
does, what it is.
And at the bottom, here's
where you add a link
to your Privacy Policy.
Then, in the App Store on
the first page, if you scroll
down you can see, and
users can go and click
on your Privacy Policy
and go read it.
Now this, users can see it
and read it before they
have downloaded this app,
so it gives them the ability
to understand what's happening
before it happens to their data.
Next, I'm going to talk
about data collection.
So, data collection is
a really powerful tool.
It's great to understand where
users are having problems,
where they're running
into issues or crashing,
where users are spending
the most time in your apps
so you can expand more
engineering resources there.
But, we believe that all data
collection does have privacy
impact, so you want a weigh
the benefits against the risks.
The thing that I work with teams
and talk to teams about is think
about the decision that
you're trying to achieve,
the decision you're trying to
make with the data collection,
and the question
you're trying to answer.
That's where you should
start with data collection.
And, if you can't think of
a question, you can't think
of anything that you're
going to do with the data,
the best question is -- because
I think it sounds interesting,
because I wondered,
then that's a good sign
that we shouldn't be
collecting that amount
of data and that data.
So, we've all heard
about and heard
in the industry about breaches.
And one thing to think about is,
unfortunately, if this happens
to you, you want to be able to
explain how you plan you use
and have a clear explanation
for all the data
that you're storing.
If you don't have a good
explanation and users want
to understand, this will
have more of an impact
to your reputation and
your company's reputation.
Now, this is true both for
applications and servers,
so you shouldn't think of just
this on the iOS or OS X side.
There is six data collection
techniques on this slide.
Now, last year we got
into depth about them,
we talked about, defined them.
We gave examples on
how to apply them.
So, if you're interested in
these, and they're great to use
to protect your users' privacy
when doing data collection,
go and watch last year's talk.
And, these are great techniques
to use to avoid fingerprinting.
That's really one
of their main uses.
So, what is fingerprinting?
I mean, we hear about
fingerprinting, but what is it?
This is when a large number
of fairly static
metrics are collected.
A configuration, collecting
configurations is a good example
of this, and then they
can be pieced together
to form a fairly stable
semi-persistent fingerprint.
So then, any other
data that is logged
with this information is then
associated to this device.
This can happen very easily,
it can happen accidentally,
and it can happen
without collecting any
personal information.
You may think, "Well, there's no
personal information in my logs,
in my logging, so
there's no privacy impact.
This is not true.
You should go back, look at
what you're logging to see
if you have accidentally been
fingerprinting your users.
Now, I'm going to take
us through an example
that helps illustrate
a little bit more
about how easy fingerprinting
can happen,
and how accidentally.
So, here we have an
initial user population.
All these dots, they're devices.
So, first we're going
to take all the devices
that have OS X Yosemite
installed,
then have a certain screen
resolution, a certain time zone,
Pacific Standard Time.
Do they have Java installed?
Are cookies enabled?
A certain version of Flash?
And, with a User-Agent string
of Safari OS X Yosemite,
we're down to a single
device, Alice.
So, this is where I encourage
all of you to go and look
at your data collection
and think
about if this is
happening to you.
And, this is where you
can easily apply some
of the data collection
techniques.
Maybe what you're doing,
it doesn't really matter what
screen resolution they have.
Bucketing it into high,
medium, and low maybe enough
for your use, but it'll
have more people fall
into each bucket.
We all are creating way
more data these days,
and users are sharing
it with us.
So, you need to be mindful
about how you're
protecting all this data
that users are entrusting
you with.
So, there are a bunch
of different tools,
in both iOS and OS X.
And, we have provided a
help and make it easier
to protect your users' data.
The first one is the keychain.
All application credentials
should be stored
in the keychain.
Think about whether they
need to be synchronized
or if they can be stored
only on a single device.
Also, think about Touch ID,
presence, APIs, can you use this
to help protect your
users' data?
All client-server communication
should be encrypted.
Also, for the data you
are storing on-disk,
use data protection.
This is great on iOS that we
have different data protection
classes so then you can pick out
data that may be most sensitive
and store it at the
highest level.
Now, we've talked about a
bunch of different changes,
new data classes for data
isolation, but the thing I want
to leave you with is a
couple of things you can do
and act on immediately.
Make sure if you don't have a
device that's upgraded to iOS 8
or OS X Yosemite
that you do today.
Test on them.
Understand the impact
this has to your users
to ensure there's not going
to be user impact on launch.
Prompt users well, and this
really means purpose strings.
If you don't have purpose
strings, go add them.
Look into the new data classes.
See if you can provide
a great experience
by taking advantage
of the new classes.
If you don't have a
Privacy Policy link,
go submit one to iTunes Connect.
And lastly, think about privacy
throughout the design process,
and this will help you
maintain your reputation
and a strong relationship
with your users.
Now, Paul is our Evangelist
and he is a great resource,
if you have any questions after
today, to go and reach out to.
Also, we have two pieces of
great sample code projects.
We have two sample
code projects.
The first one, privacy prompts,
this is a help start for how
to adopt data isolation,
and especially great to look
out for the new data
isolation classes.
Then, people picker,
this is good to look
at if you currently
use the people picker,
or are wanting to
adopt it in iOS 8.
We talked about, today,
a few best practices
for maintaining your
users' privacy,
but there are a lot more.
Go look at this documentation
and see
which other ones you can adopt.
Also, there's always great
information to be found
at the Apple Developers' Forums.
We mentioned several talks.
The first one is
"Kids and Apps".
It's happening right
here after ours
and I would encourage
you guys all to stay.
"What's New in Core Location",
and "Keychain Authentication
with Touch ID" already
happened this week,
but are great to go watch.
And then from last
year or previous years,
"Protecting your
User's Privacy",
"Protecting User's Data",
and "A Practical Guide
to the App Sandbox".
From David and I,
thank you very much.
[ Applause ]