&gt;&gt; Hi everybody.
I'm Chris Espinosa from Apple.
We're going to have
a lot of fun today.
We're talking about
kids and apps.
Going to cover a few things,
going to talk about the history
of Apple and kids, how
we got where we are.
Some recent regulatory
activity worldwide
and in the U.S. that's
going to affect you
if you're vending apps
that are addressed to kids;
some new programs we've had
in the last year for Apple IDs
for kids under 13, both the
Student Apple ID program
and Family Sharing that
was introduced on Monday;
talk about your responsibilities
if you're selling apps
that are directed at kids; some
best practices for doing that;
and then a brief view about what
to do about other countries.
But first of all
a little history:
Apple and kids go way back.
I personally know this,
because I was a kid
when I started working at
Apple on the Apple II in 1977.
One of our first programs
was called Kids Can't Wait.
We've been getting
computers in front of kids
for almost 40 years, from the
Apple II through the iMac.
We had a huge influx of
kids into the ecosystem
with the iPod, the most
popular music playback device
in the history of man.
And now we've got a huge
number of kids both in homes
and in the schools using
our mobile devices.
Now, it was great
when we started out,
because it was a
fairly simple model.
Parents would buy a device
that was pretty expensive.
They would buy some
software at a store.
They would put it
on their device,
and their kids would use it
in their home or classroom,
and that was pretty easy
and it was pretty safe,
but it's a different world now.
It's different for kids, and
it's different for parents, too.
Kids are beset by a
world on the Internet
where there are millions
of strangers
out there they can have
instantaneous contact with,
both other kids and grownups.
And there's also billions
of dollars of marketing
and merchandising that are aimed
at those kids, and that's why
around the world
people are working
on legislation to protect kids.
Now, we've been doing some
things gradually through OS X
and through iOS to give
parents and kids some protection
in the use of technology.
The parental controls that
have been in OS X forever
and the restrictions on iOS will
really help parents configure
the device to work the way they
want it to work with their kids,
and as app developers you're
kind of accustomed to this.
Sometimes, as in the
previous session,
when you go to use a
restricted data class,
it just won't be available,
because there's been a parental
control set on that device.
So, you're accustomed to dealing
with that as app developers.
And then when we start
putting networked capabilities
in the hands of users, we're
making some accommodations
to do things that are
specifically directed for kids,
Game Center for example.
We knew that a lot of kids
would be using Game Center
on their parent's devices,
and so we let them have
their own handles regardless
of their age.
They're more or less anonymous.
We don't collect
personal information.
We don't allow chat
for Game Center handles
for kids under 13.
There is no ads.
It's generic screen names.
There's no image sharing.
The chat messages they can
use are canned messages only,
not free-form chat.
So, we've created some, you
know, little cul-de-sacs
of functionality
for kids under 13.
There is a new kid's
category in the App Store
that you may have heard about.
You can go in the App
Store guidelines or go
to the App Store
sessions or labs
and learn a little
bit more about these.
If you're targeting your
apps to sell to the parents
of young kids who are going
to use them, there's a couple
of things you need to do
to get into that category.
You have to have a privacy
policy on your page,
and you've got to link to that
privacy policy on your app page.
You cannot have
behavioral-oriented advertising.
You can have contextual
advertising,
but not behavioral-oriented
advertising
that tracks your kid.
You can do no tracking
across sites or across apps.
The contextual ads must
be appropriate for kids,
and you've got to
have a parental gate
on your app before you
get out of the app to go
to In-App Purchases back to the
App Store or to any online site.
So again, little
cul-de-sacs of functionality
to accommodate kids
using our technology.
But there is a lot going on
in the world and a lot going
on in the United States about
what technology companies,
Internet companies in
general have to do about kids
to give parents the safety
and control they want.
Generally it's about
being sensitive
to the needs of parents
and kids.
But, some areas that
we've gotten scrutiny
and you may have
gotten scrutiny,
including not being clear
about the total cost of an app.
A free app that may
cost hundreds of dollars
in In-App Purchases in order
to have a good play
experience is going
to be considered a
little out of line.
You may need to look at that.
Aggressive exhortations to buy,
where you are constantly
bombarded with the urge
to spend money, that's not
going to be OK for some
of the regulatory
agencies, and you may have
to be careful about
some of these.
You're responsible for
local law compliance.
There are some principles
that you can follow.
The British government
has put some together.
There's a link on this website.
You can go back to
the tape and read it.
There's some general principles
about dealing with kids
in websites and in apps that are
really, really good to follow.
Now, at this point I want to
go off script a little bit.
I want you on a lot of these
slides to be thinking I'm going
to call my lawyer, OK?
So, we're going to take
a practice right now.
I want you to just
think to yourself,
I want to call my
lawyer, one, two, three.
&gt;&gt; I want to call my lawyer.
&gt;&gt; OK, that was good.
That wasn't just
thinking to yourself.
That was allowed.
I want to hear that.
Maybe we could up the volume
on that a little bit,
so one, two, three.
&gt;&gt; [group response] I
want to call my lawyer.
&gt;&gt; OK, that's pretty good.
Now, in the room next door I
have been told there's going
to be some loud music playing
that may disturb our session.
And my lawyer on this
project is in that room.
I want her to hear this, OK,
so loud enough for Russian Hill
to hear, one, two, three.
&gt;&gt; [group response] I
want to call my lawyer.
&gt;&gt; Aw, that's awesome people.
OK, thanks.
Remember that.
We're going to do that later.
The thing that's going
to affect you most
as developers is the Children's
Online Privacy Protection Act
of 2000, OK.
This was originally
written to focus
on websites and online services.
It applies to sites
that are directed at
or have actual knowledge of
use by kids under age 13,
and it restricts you
from collecting identifying
information
without parental consent.
Pretty straightforward as
it goes as it was in 2000,
but a lot has happened
since 2000.
The way the law was
originally written was
that you couldn't collect
the first or last name,
the email address or phone
number, any physical address,
street name or the name of a
city or a town, Social Security,
user identifier, any screen
name that would have a way
of contacting the kid, or
information that combines
with any of those above.
And it defined an
acceptable mechanism
to get parental consent.
Well, last year in 2013,
the Federal Trade Commission
in the United States revised
that act to clarify it,
expand it a little bit,
and these are the things you'll
really need to careful about.
They clarified that everything
that applied to websites
in 2000 applies to mobile, too.
So, all of your apps
are affected.
They expanded the definition
of personal information
that requires parental consent
according the new capabilities
of mobile devices.
So, any photo or video or sound
recording that your app makes
that could include the
child's own image is subject
to the COPPA regulations, OK,
very important for
you to know that.
Geolocation that can isolate
the kid's location to a city
or town - subject to COPPA
regulations, any screen name
or identifier that can
be used for contact,
that's pretty much the same,
or a persistent identifier
that identifies them
across sites or services.
If you're using this information
solely within your app
and solely for internal
functionality
to your app, that's OK.
But, if it goes up on a website,
if it goes outside your app,
if you're using it
for purposes other
than just making your app
work, then you're subject
to the requirements
of the Children's Online
Privacy Protection Act.
And there are some requirements
of that, and we're going
to go into that later.
Now, kids under 13
who are subject
to the COPPA law have Apple IDs.
They have it in two ways.
The first is an Apple
ID for Students Program,
and this is what we
rolled out last year.
It's a program that gets
verified parental consent
through the COPPA law
through schools, OK.
We've rolled it out in several
large school districts starting
last year and going
into this year,
and they're full-fledged Apple
IDs for iCloud and iTunes.
They're not these
Game Center accounts.
They're not kid accounts.
They're not junior accounts.
They really are full
accounts, OK.
There are a couple of little
things we've applied to them.
Students do not receive
marketing materials from Apple.
That box is implicitly checked
to not receive marketing
materials,
and the Limit Ad Tracking
switch is automatically set
for accounts for kids under 13.
Now, this is really
only for, you know,
a few tens of thousands
of kids now.
And of course, we're
going to expand
that in more school districts.
But, what we announced
Monday is much bigger,
and that's Family Sharing.
Family Sharing is a method to
get verifiable parental consent
under the COPPA law for any
family in the U.S., and in fact,
we're using the same
mechanism worldwide for parents
to create Apple IDs
for young kids.
It integrates with the Ask
To Buy feature that you saw
on Monday, so that
parents can see and approve
of purchases by their kids.
Once again, just
like the student IDs,
they're full-fledged Apple
IDs for iCloud and iTunes.
The same switches are set, no
marketing and no ad tracking,
and the verified
parental consent is set
up by a special mechanism.
So it's a way for us to get
the parents to create accounts
for kids under 13 and then
bring them into the family,
let them share existing
purchases
and make new purchases.
Let me walk you a little bit
through how the whole
Family Sharing program works
because that'll give you
a good background for it.
You start with the person
who has a payment method
and an Apple ID who decides
to be a family organizer.
And the family organizer can add
or invite other existing
accounts into the family
and share their payment method
and share their existing
purchases with them.
They can also create new
accounts for kids under 13
and create a family circle.
That can be up to
six accounts total.
And the requirement is
that during the life
of the family all
the accounts have
to use the family
organizer's payment method
or credit card, OK.
The way Purchase Sharing works
is that you have this bucket
of purchases that you've made,
and that is made available
to everybody in your family.
They can see all of your
movies, books and apps that -
and songs that you
have purchased.
They can pick one out of your
purchases and re-download it
to their device as if it was
in their purchase history.
It's not their title now.
It doesn't show up in
their purchase history.
It's still yours, and then
if you leave the family,
they lose the rights
to that title.
And then the Ask To Buy
capability is really cool.
If one of your family members
has the Ask To Buy switch turned
on and is shopping in any
of the stores and wants
to purchase something, at time
of purchase request a
notification is sent
to the organizer and other
parents in the family saying
that this person wants
to buy this product
with a link to the product page.
And the organizer
and the parents
or guardians get the option to
approve or deny that request.
And on approval, they
complete that purchase.
Now, this is going to affect the
way your In-App Purchases work,
because there may be a
long time between the time
when the user taps the
In-App Purchase Buy button
and when the parent
actually sees it, taps OK,
the request comes back
and they get to buy that.
Go back and look
at James Wilson's
"Optimizing StoreKit
Transaction" session.
There was one given yesterday
and he's reprising
it tomorrow morning.
See that. He's got some
great tips for how to deal
with that in your app.
So, given all of that,
what does this mean to you?
What does regulatory
environment mean to you?
What do the new under
13 accounts mean to you?
What is Ask To Buy and
Family Sharing mean to you?
And at this time
I want you to say-
&gt;&gt; [group response] I
want to call my lawyer.
&gt;&gt; Oh come on, come on, come on.
One, two, three.
&gt;&gt; [group response] I
want to call my lawyer.
&gt;&gt; Great. OK.
Only your lawyer can tell
you what this means to you
in the context of your
app and your company.
But, the thing you got
to know is that kids
under 13 may be buying,
selling, buying,
sharing and using your apps.
So, you've got to tell whether
your apps are directed at kids
under 13 or whether you have
specific knowledge that kids
under 13 are using your apps.
If you've got a general-purpose
app like a word processor
or a to-do list reminder,
you're not targeted at kids,
you're not in the kids
section of the store,
you don't ask their age
anywhere - you're probably OK
under the COPPA law, which only
affects things that are directed
at or you have actual
knowledge of the user's age.
Again, you have to consult
your lawyer in order
to know whether you do or do
not follow- fall under the law.
But, typically, if you
have a general-purpose app,
you don't market to kids,
you're not in the kids section,
you don't know the age,
then you don't have to worry
about COPPA conformance
specifically.
But, if your app is directed
at kids, which it probably is
if you're in this room, you
have some implementation choices
to either avoid requirements
for conformance with COPPA
or to conform with
the COPPA law.
And there three basic
approaches, and I'm going
to walk you through them now.
You can either avoid
doing the things
that subject you to
COPPA regulation.
Just stay out of it.
Do not collect personally
identifying information -
it's a great alternative.
Or you can choose to
collect the information
of how old the user is and
present a forked experience,
different experiences for
kids over 13 and under 13,
disable the personally
identifying information
experience for the
kids under 13.
That's a viable choice.
That's a good choice
for you to make.
Or, you can, if you're all about
that information, if you're all
about video, if you're all
about chat, if you're all
about sharing stuff, you really
need to address kids under 13
with the full features of your
application, then you have
to get verifiable parental
consent of the use -
from the user's parents before
you can proceed with the app,
and we'll lead you through
some steps to do that.
So, let's look at the first
alternative, avoid it.
This is pretty easy
for most apps.
Don't collect personally
identifying information.
Don't show behaviorally
targeted ads,
although contextual
ads are fine.
Don't support photos.
Don't support voice recording.
Don't support social networking.
Don't support finding
your location.
Don't support your
own push notifications
or any other COPPA-regulated
functionality.
You can go a long way
actually without doing those
if that's what your app is
about, if it's a simple game
or a general purpose
application.
Ask To Buy does not make
you COPPA compliant.
Getting the parental
permission to purchase
and download the game is
not COPPA compliant parental
notification and consent
to collect personally
identifying information.
So, just because the kid bought
your game through Ask To Buy,
that doesn't let
you off the hook.
If you limit yourself to
what Game Center does,
you're generally good, but
you got to check your app
and make sure that you're not
doing any of these things.
If you saw the previous
presentation, then you know
that there are some
protected data classes
in both platforms, iOS and OS X.
If you look at those
protected data classes,
this gives you a really good
idea of whether you're going
to be generally compliant
with COPPA or not.
If you're using location or
contacts or photos or microphone
or the worldwide or the
camera or social or HealthKit,
you are subject to COPPA
regulations, and you need
to be careful about that.
Even Bluetooth, because
Bluetooth has a persistent
identifier that can be
tracked across devices
and across locales,
and so even use
of Bluetooth makes
you subject to COPPA.
So, let me show you some demos
of some applications
that are PII-free.
This one is called
"Bonsai Slice."
It's a game where you
swack things with swords.
Again, you start it up.
There's not much to do
except tap to begin.
There's no particular login
or identification of yourself
or any setup, and you can just
go right into playing the game.
[ Game sounds ]
So, there we go.
I think that's enough
game demo for that.
So, that is the first approach,
which is just don't do
it and you'll be fine.
So, if you've got a
general purpose app
or you've got a kid oriented app
that doesn't collect any
personally identifying
information, you're fine.
You're in the clear.
The second approach is
to have an age screen
so you can tell whether
your user is under 13.
And then if they're over 13 you
can collect PII, and if they're
under 13 you just turn
off those features, OK.
It's pretty straightforward
to do.
One of the interesting
things is, well,
isn't their age personally
identifying information?
And the answer is no.
That's not.
You can ask their age, and
you can record their age
so you don't have
to ask every time.
If fact, we recommend that
what you do is you ask
on first launch.
You record the age
in per account iCloud
preferences store.
And so when that user
is logged into iCloud,
because your under-13 users are
all going to be iCloud users.
Anytime your app launches and
you read that recorded age
of over or under 13 from their
per app iCloud preferences,
you know whether this
user's under 13 or not,
and you don't have to ask
again, and you can continue
to tailor the preference -
continue to tailor
the experience
for that under-13 user.
If they're under 13,
you can't just exit.
That's not appropriate.
That is, have an app that
people can buy or download
and then have them
input their age
and then tell them,
oh you're too young.
Your app will be rejected
from the store if you do that.
If you have an age gate and
you have different behaviors
for above and under 13, you have
to have a pretty unified
valuable experience
for under 13.
You can't just quit, and
you can't have a really,
really crippled version
of the app.
It's got to be useful.
It's got to be fun.
But, you can omit
certain features like,
you know, like chat.
You can have chat in the over
13 and not have chat in the
under 13 as part of your
gameplay, for example.
Once again, you should be
thinking one, two, three.
&gt;&gt; [group response] I
want to call my lawyer.
&gt;&gt; Great, thank you.
And you might want to
have a parental gate too.
Parental gates are something
we recommend for applications
that are in the kids store,
where, you know, there is the
under 13s, where you
got to do one thing.
There's 13 through,
you know, grownups,
where you can anything.
And then over grownups
for terms and conditions
for buying additional stuff,
or if you're a parent,
you might want to have a
special control for that.
So, I'm going to go through
some of the apps that do that.
This is "Toca Town," another
great immersive environment
for kids.
You can tell from the start
that this is targeted at kids,
and it's likely to
have kids under 13.
So, it's the kind of thing
that would be subject.
And it's got a parental
age screen.
If you see the For Parents
way up here in the corner,
when you tap that they ask you
with a very simple challenge
what year were you born in.
And that's - this is asking
you for both under or over 13
or also for parental
information.
If you enter a date
that is old enough
to be a parent then you can
go to the license agreement.
You can go to additional
purchases.
You can go to off app websites.
This is the kind of thing
that is required to be
in the App Store in
the kids section.
And finally here's "Fraggle
Rock" from Jim Henson.
This is just another mechanism
that you can use to
ask the kid's age.
You start up, there's info.
It's the same kind of thing.
This is parental info,
yet they're asking
for the full parental -
full age information here,
month, day, year.
So, you can have
a just the year.
You can have it just the age, or
you can have a full birthdate.
Any one of those input
methods is sufficient
to ask whether the kid
is over or under 13.
Now, remember that that is only
for verifying whether
you can collect PII
or cannot collect PII.
Knowing the, knowing
that a parent has -
knowing that the age is
sufficiently old enough
to be a parent is
really not enough
for verified parental consent.
That's our third category.
You can - instead of having an
application that doesn't apply
or having an application where
you have forked behaviors,
you can have an application
that always uses the camera,
always uses the microphone,
always uses chat
and social networking,
uses location services,
goes the whole way.
You can do that for
kids of all ages
if you have verified
parental consent.
And that turns out to be kind of
hard to do, because parents have
to consent explicitly
for your app.
Parental consent that Apple
has received for the kids
to use the device, we
cannot delegate that to you,
because we don't know
what your app is doing.
You must ask the parent to
have an explicit consent to use
that app for that kit,
and that's a lot of
work on your part.
It's the same rule, you know
if you've got a website,
if you've been dealing
with this under the -
since 2000 on a website,
it's the same rules.
So, it's pretty easy if
you've already got a website.
In fact, many apps just simply
direct the kids to the website
to go through the COPPA
process before they can proceed.
There are several
ways to do this.
You can pick the one
that's right for you,
talk to your lawyer about it.
And a simple parental gate of
the kind that you need to be
in app - kids section of the App
Store, that is not sufficient
for COPPA verifiable
parental consent.
Once you get verifiable,
verified parental
consent, it's not over.
Some of the requirements of
collecting PII are that you have
to display that PII and
allow parents to review it
and delete it on demand.
You, the parents need to be able
to stop the collection
going forward.
You have to keep that
information reasonably secure
and be able to demonstrate
to the FTC
that you are keeping
it secure, and you need
to delete the information
when you no longer need it.
You can't amass vast databases
of private information
about kids.
Now I don't have a
lot of good examples
of what on-device verified
parental consent is mainly
because this is kind
of new, and not a lot
of apps are doing this.
The traditional way of doing it,
if you just look at a website
like Neopets, this is
the traditional way
of getting verified parental
consent is a webpage with a lot
of legal contract and then
a form that you print.
Please print legibly, and then
you fax it in to the company.
This is what websites
traditionally do before you
create an account.
And in the app world,
for example,
there is the great family
app called "Life360,"
which is a great way for parents
to communicate with their kids.
It sets up chat.
It sets up location services.
It is a fully featured family
management app, and it's going
to have kids under 13, and what
they do is you - they send you
to the app to create
accounts, and they send you
to the website to
create accounts.
And the website just has a
PDF that you fill in, you sign
and you mail or fax
in to the company,
because that's the
state of the art.
We can do better than this, and
we want to do better than this.
We really want to give
parents a great way
of delivering verifiable
parental consent
in a way that's acceptable to
the Federal Trade Commission.
Here's an example of
a good start at it.
Here's an app called "DIY."
When you start it takes you
through some setup
screens of what it does.
You pick an avatar, and
then it has an age slider,
and this is kind of like
the age slider that you saw
in the previous category for
deciding whether to turn on
or turn off capabilities.
And notice that if I'm
14, and I pick a nickname,
and then I can enter my email
and password to create
an account.
Very straightforward.
But, if I set an age under 13,
notice that interfaces change.
It doesn't ask me for
my password and email.
It asks for my parents' email,
and it sends my parents
an invitation
that they must approve before I
can go further with an account,
and that does the email,
that does the parental
consent process.
They have to review
the agreement.
They have to sign it.
They have to send it in.
That's what you need to do
under the COPPA law
in order to do that.
So, those are the ways
that you can get verified
parental consent.
Now this applies primarily in
the United States of America
and the territories that are
subject to the COPPA law.
That is not your whole market.
And the good news is
that in most of the rest
of the world there
aren't laws like COPPA.
But, they're coming, and many
of them will be modeled
on the U.S. law.
And the implementation
method we've chosen,
which is probably a good
idea for you to follow,
is what we're doing in the U.S.
we're going to deploy everywhere
because it shows
respect for kids.
It shows restraint on our
parts, and it makes us adaptable
and flexible for whatever
other countries may adopt.
The most important
thing for you is
that the ages I've been
talking about, 13 to be a kid,
and 18 to be able to
sign a legal contract -
don't take those as
hard coded values,
because they're different
worldwide.
The age that COPPA applies to
in the United States is 13.
But other countries
have ages where -
children's private
information is protected,
and that varies all
around the world from 13
up to 16 years of age.
Similarly the age at
which you can agree
to a legal contract is 18,
but in other countries
it may be 19, 20 or 21.
You should tailor these
on a per country basis.
Instead of hard coding 13 or
18, you can check your region
at runtime using StoreKit,
just use the ProductsResponse
to a products request with
your bundle identifier,
get the products response and
look at the priceLocale field.
And that will tell you
the locale of the store
from which your product
was bought.
And then if there are
regulations that apply
in that locale, you can make
decisions on what age is based
on that locale rather than hard
coding the numbers 13 or 18.
OK, I wonder what
you're thinking now.
Hmm, maybe it might be -
&gt;&gt; [group response] I
want to call my lawyer.
&gt;&gt; Very good.
It's an awesome opportunity.
These are families and parents
who are loyal Apple customers,
and they are going to love
being able to share apps
with their kids, to watch what
apps their kids are buying,
to let the kids shop in
the store by themselves
with some degree of safety;
they're going to
love this feature.
They are going - this is really,
really going to increase the use
of our devices among kids.
We want to make sure that
that's safe and that's legal.
If you're writing apps
for kids you should apply
to all applicable statutes
in all of the areas
where you sell your apps, and
that means you need a lawyer.
Don't collect personal
information, ID, pictures,
sounds or locations at
all if you can avoid it,
and then you'll avoid
a lot of hassle.
If that's what your
app is about,
then you can choose either to
have a forked experience based
on asking the kid's age,
and at that point you might
as well fork for younger kids,
older kids and parents in order
to be in the app store.
That's a really,
really good idea.
Or if you really
need kids under 13
and you need personally
identifiable information,
then what you need to do is
go the FTC codified verifiable
parental consent process.
Get the parent's
signature on a piece
of paper before you
can allow the kid,
before you can allow your app
to collect personally
identifying information
from the kid.
Do the same thing worldwide -
it'll be a lot more convenient
and it'll be a lot more
consistent and prepare you
for what's going to
happen in the future.
Here's some resources
that you can deal with.
There's a Safe Harbor Program,
where there are organizations
that you can go to, to
let them help you set
up accounts for kids.
Federal Trade Commission
has a whole list
of these safe harbor
organizations.
It's a really, really good
place to go to talk to people,
consult with them and use some
of their services
to be safe for kids.
Another good organization
is Moms with Apps.
Moms with Apps has a lot
of expertise in this area.
And you can go to the Moms
with Apps websites to see some
of examples of apps
that deal with kids
in a really, really
great manner.
There's always our Technology
Evangelist Paul Danbold,
and developer forums, lots
of developer forums
on apps for kids.
Related sessions, since
it's late in the week,
there aren't too many coming up.
The session right
before this on Security
and Privacy is a really good
one to go back to the films on.
Also to the "Designing a Great
In-App Purchase Experience"
that Rachel Roth gave.
That is a heck of
a presentation.
You ought to go to
the tape and see that.
And then "Optimizing
In-App Purchases,"
that's the one I mentioned with
James Wilson telling you how
to handle the scenario where a
kid asks for an In-App Purchase,
asks to buy his own, and
their parent is going
to be two hours before
they click the switch
and let the kid get those coins
that they needed in the game.
I really appreciate
you being here today.
I hope you develop
great apps for kids.
We want to have a lot of
apps for kids available
for Family Sharing when Family
Sharing opens up, when iOS 8
and OS X Yosemite are available.
And I really look forward
to seeing you in the store.
Thank you very much everybody.
[ Applause ]