[ Silence ]
>> And please welcome
your hosts,
Shaan Pruden and John Geleynse.
[ Applause ]
>> Good afternoon, and
thank you for joining us.
>> Yeah, thanks for coming
to spend time with us
at the end of this long day.
It's for many of you who
were out there last night
when I was leaving the
student event and putting
out your chairs, it got real
cool on the sidewalk, I'm sure,
and you spent a whole long
night waiting for this day,
and you've been here,
and now you've joined us
to celebrate some
excellent apps.
>> And we are here
to award excellence
in innovation on
both iOS and OS X.
And every year it gets
more and more difficult
to pick our design winners
because there are
so many great apps.
>> Yeah. So many of you, we
shared a statistic this morning
that 70 percent of
the audience here
at WWDC are new to the show.
And so many of you
have never been
to this show, the design awards.
And so we thought
we'd take a moment
to explain how we
pick the winners.
We judge the winning apps
using sort of three major --
we judge the winning apps
in three major areas.
The first is around design.
So for design, we look
at apps that are --
we're looking for apps
that are easy to use.
Apps that are familiar.
That are consistent within
themselves, but consistent
within the operating
system as well.
They have a great game loop,
so really excellent game play.
They're intuitive
and understandable
and immediately useable by the
people who they were built for.
And then we look at apps
in the technology --
we judge apps around technology.
So we're evaluating the
apps on their use of iOS
or OS X frameworks to
do really cool stuff
or to add really
valuable functionality.
Or we're also looking at whether
the app launches quickly.
Is it responsive?
Does it take, you know, does it
work the way you would expect it
to work?
And is there smooth scrolling?
We look at whether or not the
app runs on the latest OSs,
whether it takes advantage
of the newest hardware.
And takes advantage of
things like M7 or A7 on iOS
or multicore or other
technologies
and hardware technologies
on OS X.
And then thirdly, we're
looking at apps from the point
of view of innovation.
And innovation really is that
spark of brilliance, right,
that uniqueness, the clever
implementation of something
that you wouldn't have
expected in the first place,
but then when you see it,
you're blown away by it.
And there's just so many ways
to talk about innovation,
but really it comes down to
the implementation of something
that is just so fresh
and so compelling
and done in a unique way.
So those three areas are
how we judge the apps.
There's so many more things
we look at, but in a nutshell,
they're grouped in
those three areas.
>> So let's talk
about the prizes
that our award winners
will be given to take home.
It's pretty much one of every
piece of hardware that we make.
A Mac Pro with a cinema display.
A 27-inch iMac.
An Apple TV.
A MacBook Air.
A MacBook Pro.
An iPad. And an iPod touch.
>> Not a bad haul.
[ Applause ]
>> And, last but not least,
probably the most coveted
part of the award is:
>> Yeah, you get to take home
one of these 88 trophy cubes
and these are, you know,
statically they detect touch,
they're touch sensitive, so
you touch them, they light up,
on the top just like the
back of your MacBook Pro,
the Apple logo lights up.
And these are to die for,
must-have Apple products.
And a few of you are
going to get one tonight.
>> So without any further ado,
let us get to the winners.
We're going to start with
a few student winners.
Students have been part of
WWDC for many, many years.
In fact, we have got a
student scholarship program
where we awarded 200
students this year.
>> Yeah, 200 students.
If you're in the house
and you're a student
scholarship winner this week,
could you stand up for a moment?
We just want to award you
with some recognition.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you.
Please be seated.
You guys have done some great
work to get here, and the apps
that we looked at were
really impressive.
So you deserve to
be here this week,
and we hope that
you're going to continue
to produce some incredible apps
that put the more
veteran developers who are
in the audience, you know, give
them a run for the money, right?
>> Like these apps,
who have been.
>> Like some of these apps.
These were student
winners that we highlighted
in previous years, that
we demoed here on stage.
Some of them maybe have
changed names or what have you,
but they were great
apps written by students
over the past three years.
>> So let's move on
to our first winner.
Our first winner
is "PanoPerfect"
by HalfPeeled and TwoBros.
Winners, please come
up the stairs
on the front of the stage here.
[ Music and Applause ]
>> Congratulations.
"PanoPerfect" is a
fun and simple way
to share beautiful
panoramic photos.
These are two former high school
students that attended WWDC
in 2012 on student
scholarships and built this app
when they were inspired by our
'06 announcement of panoramics.
And John's going to show us now.
>> Yeah, it's a great story,
sitting in the keynote,
watching something, and then
deciding to write an app.
I think that's a great story.
So "PanoPerfect" is
this app that allows you
to view panoramic photos, and
it's there's just a community
of people who love panoramas
that are submitting
photos into the app.
So it's a familiar interface.
You're just scrolling
through this,
these guys are using UI kit
dynamics and image effects
for blurs on some of the UI,
which we'll get to in a moment.
So this is the explorer,
this is kind
of a curated set of panoramas.
If we go to nearby
they're using core location
to determine where you are.
And we're going to go in here,
hopefully, and load some panos.
Yeah, here's some
panos that are nearby.
A couple of them posted by
the creators of the app.
But let's just go into
this one: We double tap,
you can favorite it, you can
like it, you can comment on it.
And then you can double tap
and just go in and gesture
through the UI to go and
look at the entire panorama.
And they're doing low res
thumbnails in the feed
that you see here,
and then they're going
to the high res full
panoramas when you go and look
into the individual image.
So super cool app that
really was created
to address the experience that
at the time there was no support
for panoramic images in a lot
of social networking apps.
And so these guys stepped up
and made something really cool.
Congratulations.
[ Applause ]
All right, the next
app was created
because of the incredible
movement
and growth of iPad in education.
And, you know, people
are changing,
iPad has changed the way that
we're learning in the classroom.
Changing the way that adults are
learning and kids are learning.
And the mix of iPad in
education is really taking off
because of the incredible
new apps that are available,
interactive textbooks,
really tremendous content.
And the creators of this
next app saw all of that,
saw the growth that was going
on and also saw a specific need
that they wanted to
step up to and solve.
So our winner does that.
>> And they are "Addimal
Adventure" by Teachley.
[ Music and Applause ]
>> Congratulations.
>> Thank you.
>> You're welcome.
"Addimal Adventure" is
a fun and engaging app
that teaches single-digit
addition.
Why don't you come over here?
There we go.
It was created by grad students
from Columbia University
who were involved in
research and cognition,
the way kids learn,
and technology.
Sinister Professor Possum
has destroyed El Sumado
and is building a robot
that could ruin the world.
Join the animals
to win back blocks
and rebuild the golden
city to its former glory.
John.
>> Right, let's take
a look at this app.
So I'm not going to get into
sinister, you know, situation,
get into that whole game
play, but these folks worked
with folks from Sesame Workshop
and created some really
great artwork in the app.
The app is focused on teaching
children basic addition,
and for a lot of kids
this is a real struggle.
And so this developer set
out to solve this problem.
So we're going to
get into the app -
we'll skip over the narrative
at the beginning here.
This is pretty straightforward
stuff.
So most of you are going
to get the answers right
without even using the app.
But the key here is that the app
is teaching children addition,
and when you're first learning
addition, you just, you know,
the first thing you do is you
count on fingers, you just kind
of like 1, 2, 3, you count
them off individually.
And so the app lets you do that.
And so I can just tap,
you know, I got 5,
I got some feedback in the UI.
I move the slider bar with
the tactile fields to 5,
and I get confirmation that it's
the right answer, or I don't,
it was the wrong answer.
I can also do count on, which is
a second kind of addition tool.
So once the child has
learned to basically count
through the numbers,
you know, the numbers,
then they can start moving on
to different kinds of addition
where they're going
to take a big number
and add some smaller
numbers to it.
So in this case, the child's
going to start to learn
that you can start with 3 and
then do 1 more and get 4, right?
There we go.
And the app continues to
go on and teach all kinds
of other tools and techniques
for learning, addition.
Another one is doubles,
where you basically start off
with say, you know, 3 and 4 is
7, and so first it shows you
that you can cut the 4 into a
3 and you get 3, 3, and 1 is 7.
The app is full of these
kinds of techniques
that take advantage
of iOS technologies
to do a really great experience
with large text, great colors,
and an experience I think that
is really going to resonate
with little, little kids.
So congratulations.
Extremely well done.
>> Thank you very much.
[ Music and Applause ]
>> Can we get the
slides back, Chuck?
There we are.
>> All right, everybody loves
a great game, and there are
so many games on the App Store.
And we had a lot of fun
looking through the best games
and trying to figure out which
one was the one that needed
to be a winner, and there are
many that needed to be a winner.
Unfortunately we can only
award so many tonight.
But one of the types of gaming
- one of the types of games
on the App Store that is super
popular that everybody loves,
that originated in the
'80s, is the platformer.
And in the platformer
game, it's a genre,
what you're doing is you're
basically, you know, running
and jumping, moving and jumping,
to avoid obstacles and get coins
and save people and get
money, and you know,
whatever you're getting.
And the whole point is to not
fall off the platform, right?
And the way you fall off the
platform is you get, you know,
speared, or some
obstacle hits you,
or something falls
on you or whatever.
But the point is that the
platform is a pretty loose term,
but you're moving
across this thing,
and it just goes
on and on and on.
And our next winner
has created, I think,
one of the most incredible
platformer games today
on the App Store.
They're a recent arrival.
And we're thrilled to award
them with something today.
>> To "Leo's Fortune"
from 1337 & Senri.
[ Music and Applause ]
>> Congratulations.
You're welcome.
Congratulations.
In "Leo's Fortune,"
you hunt down a cunning
and mysterious gold thief.
Why don't you stand
over here, folks?
Sorry, a cunning and
mysterious gold thief traveling
through lush environments such
as mossy forests, arid deserts,
snow-capped mountains
and pirate cities
to uncover the truth
behind Leo's stolen fortune.
>> Great. Well, I'm not going
to go to the snow-capped peaks
or underwater or
anything like that.
I'm going to show you
the basic game play
so that you get a sense
for what's going on.
If I can get the volume brought
down a little bit,
that would be great.
All right, so "Leo's Fortune,"
you've got about 25 levels
or more that you can just swipe
through in a very
familiar user interface.
I'm going to start on level
1 because I want to point
out something that is such a
great example of their attention
to detail and the way
that they've done
things in this game.
So I'm going to start
the tutorial.
And this is really sort
of the onboarding
experience for the app.
And there are so many apps
nowadays that are needing
to do this, they want to get
you up, you know, into the app,
and help you understand
how to use the app.
And, you know, you don't
need something that's very,
you know, that's super intense.
But to do this well
takes a lot of design
and I think a lot of thinking.
And so I want to show you.
So the game starts
off like this,
and the first thing you're told
is where to place your thumbs.
And in order to do that,
you're immediately learning how
to hold the iPad
to play the game.
So I'm going to put my left
thumb here, my right thumb here,
and now the game starts to work,
and it's got these coach marks.
So I'm going to move the left
thumb, and we're going to start
to collect coins with Leo here.
Okay, so here's the
platformer experience, right?
You're driving along on this
so-called platform, and boom,
I'm stuck, I can't
get over this thing.
But this onboarding experience
has these ghosting images,
and they tell me that if
I move my right thumb up,
I can inflate Leo and
move him up and down.
And now I'm dealing with
an obstacle in this case.
Let's keep going.
I'm down there, no
problem, I can go back up.
I can inflate, nope, sorry.
Oh come on.
This is the problem
with these demos, right?
Okay, here we go, we land
on there, boom, ta-da,
here we are, we're
driving around.
And notice just the
effects in the background.
There's this perspective going
on, you've got petals flying
through the air, on other
levels there's rain falling,
there's all kinds of stuff
happening in the distance.
And here, you're dealing
with this obstacle,
and the game is full of
these kinds of obstacles,
where Leo has to solve - he
has to do something in one spot
to open a door or
some kind of a bridge.
In this case, if I landed
on top, I would die.
And so I'm just going to
inflate him, flip this around,
and then move along
and keep jumping.
And this is just a real
quick view of what's going
on in this game, but we
just thought they did
such a good job, for example,
with this kind of an S curve,
which is really hard to
get, you know, to do well.
You're going down through mines.
You're in rainstorms,
all kinds of stuff.
And then here again, this
onboarding experience,
but I'm actually playing it.
And you see that I'm supposed
to jump this guy, right, boom.
And then now I'm moving along.
And this is just
the first level.
But the game goes on, and
we just we love this game.
For that attention to detail
across all their levels,
for the great integration
with touch, for the leveraging
of iOS technologies and
graphics, for the sound system,
there's so much that these guys
did right, and we just want
to say congratulations.
This is an awesome app.
[ Music and Applause ]
>> All right, we all live busy
lives, and one of the things
that I've learned over time and
other people have learned is
that if you can capture some
of the things that are going on
and take a moment to record
an idea, a thought, a memory -
or something happens and it
triggers a thought and you want
to capture it - that that
exercise of writing things
down for a moment, to just
capturing these little bits
of information throughout
the day,
is actually a great
way to relieve stress.
It's actually a great
way to build memories
and kind of catalog your day.
It can also be an
idea incubator.
And so this is something,
it's a good discipline
for us all to get into.
And this developer, the
developer of the next app,
or the next winner, totally
understands this idea.
>> And they are Bloom
Built, who's made "Day One."
[ Music and Applause ]
>> Come this way.
Come this way.
Congratulations.
Here you go.
"Day One" lets you record
your life as you live it.
From everyday moments to
once in a lifetime events,
the elegant interface of
"Day One" makes journaling
your life a simple pleasure.
>> Right, so this is a Mac app,
it's also available
on iOS as well.
But we thought we'd award it
for the Mac and show it off
on the Mac, because so many of
us are so busy as developers,
on our Macs every day
- we're writing code,
we're spending time in Xcode
or we're doing, you know,
using various tools, you
could be in a spreadsheet,
you could be writing
some sort of a document.
But along the way,
something might happen -
you might get a phone
call, a thought pops
into mind, an email arrives.
And you might want
to record an idea
or put something quickly down,
which is a big part
of journaling.
Not sitting down to
write something huge -
it's just capturing
these little nuggets.
And so "Day One" just
builds a little menu extra
that you can type in and
put some sort of entry in,
and that'll go straight into the
blog and then into the journal,
and then you're back
to your work.
Or we could just go up here,
and we'll just launch the app,
and we can inside of the app,
immediately create
a journal entry.
So I can say, you know, here I
am at the Apple Design Awards,
sorry, the trophies are great,
want one of these soon, right?
There's my entry.
I can take - turns out I've
actually taken a trophy picture
earlier, so I can take this
picture, drop it into here,
and "Day One"'s going to either
take the date from the picture
or just say leave
it unchanged based
on the date I'm answering
this journal entry.
And then I say I'm done, I
can tag it with various tags
that are in the system,
I can add a location,
they've got maps integration,
so I could say use current
location if I'd like.
And I'm done, and there's the
entry in there, and I can look
at my journal over time
using the overall view
of all my journal entries.
And so here's just a sample
journal that we've got
in the app here where you can
take a look at all these entries
and go back in time and
see what's going on.
And really that is
the whole point
of journaling is capturing these
moments in time as they occur,
as they pop into your mind.
And we felt that "Day One"
did such a great job at this.
As well, they've got built-in
notifications so you can set
up reminders to put
things into your journal.
They've got inspirational
quotes that will pop
up when you're going to
create a journal entry
that can be inspiring
and get you writing.
And really that's the essence
of a great tool, right,
is that it gets the job done,
it doesn't get in the way,
and it's perfectly balanced.
And we selected this tool
for being super well designed
on OS X, and in being
exactly what it needs
to be and nothing more.
So congratulations
on a job well done.
[ Music and Applause ]
>> All right, our next winner
is just such a great example
of the principle of
minimalist design.
You know, design is all
about fit and finish.
It's all about the marriage
between form and function.
It's about, you know,
communicating clearly.
And iOS really helps
you to do this, right,
by helping you focus on
content, getting out of the way,
giving you a system that
allows you to draw, you know,
the UI from iOS 7 that
is minimalist in nature.
And, you know, it takes a lot
of attention and a lot of focus
and refinements to actually
end up with something that is
in its purest form,
that is something
that is exactly what you wanted
it to be and nothing more,
there's no extra adornments.
And our next winner did
that with their game.
>> And they are "Blek"
by kunabi brother.
[ Music and Applause ]
>> Congratulations.
The goal of this game is
to shape a line through all
of the colored circles while
avoiding black holes along
its route.
From delightfully simple to
exceptionally deep and complex,
it's a stroke of genius.
John.
>> Yeah, this app is awesome.
And if you've not
played this game,
you need to see it
from the start.
So the basic point of the game
is, you know, as Shaan said,
you gesture and you draw
this little line to knock
out the colored dots, and
when you get to a level
where there are black dots,
you want to avoid those.
But, you know, at
the first level,
you're just starting off
here with this gesture.
And you know, notice
as I'm playing here,
that there is nothing
extra onscreen,
it's just the dots,
it's just my gesture.
And the gesture, the rendering
of the gesture is almost
like calligraphy, I mean,
it has a flair to it,
it's representative of the speed
of my stroke, the exact timing,
the length and everything.
So let me get rid
of these three.
So those are easy levels.
Let me jump up to level 8 here
for a moment, which
is kind of fun.
So here I've got an
instance where I've got
to avoid the black dots
but get the white ones -
or get the colored ones.
And to do that I've got to
figure out what gesture to do
that will repeat
across the screen
to remove these colored dots.
Now, the other thing that's
super cool about this app is
that it leverages audio
for great feedback.
And so there's some very
fun, lightweight, you know,
sounds that come through
as you screw up, basically.
You know, so here
I'm messing up.
Let me try to do it right.
Not quite, not quite, not quite.
And the thing about this
game is it's like that.
You're like "Oh blast," and
the sound just gives you this
great feedback.
One last try.
No, come on, John.
Okay, I give up.
That's the problem
with these demos.
Yeah, we love this game
for the minimalist design,
the great integration with the
touch, you know, system of iOS,
just that expression of
just a great engagement,
this great expression of the
game in a very simplistic way
with no extra adornment.
And so congratulations
on an excellent job.
[ Music and Applause ]
>> Nice play there.
>> Right. So you know,
we're all, you know,
at the conference this
week, and we're crazy busy.
You've got 100 and what is
it, 10 sessions to attend,
and so this is just a great
example of how busy we are.
If we're not at a conference,
you guys are writing code,
you're going to school,
you're doing life.
And if you're anything like me,
you know that it's hard to keep
on top of all of the
things that are going
on in the world around us.
Whether it's in our industry,
whether it's not in our industry
but something that interests
us, whether it's sports
or world news or what have you.
And so, you know, it's not
for a lack of news sources,
it's just that there's so
much news coming at us.
And it's often hard to pick
a quality source of news.
It's hard to find one
that is, you know, curated
and that's going to give you
what you are really interested
in, in the length that
you want it to be in.
And more importantly,
it's even hard
to find time to read it all.
And the developer of our next
app the next app the winner has
set out to solve this dilemma
of getting information to people
in a timely manner in a way
that they can consume it easily.
>> And our winner is "Yahoo!
News Digest" by Yahoo!
[ Music and Applause ]
>> Congratulations,
sir, there you go.
Adam. Congratulations.
This app gets you in
the know in no time.
It delivers definitive
summaries of all the important
and need-to-know news of the
day in two beautiful digests.
Stories are both
hand curated as well
as algorithmically generated
to ensure high quality
and keep you informed of all
the key headlines of the day.
>> Let's take a quick
look at "Yahoo!
News Digest."
So what you get is these
two digests of news
with about eight stories in
them in the morning at 8 a.m.
and at 6 p.m. in the
evening, and that's it.
And so this is one of my
go-to news apps all the time.
I wait for these digests to
arrive, and once they arrive,
you can just scroll through
this really simple UI,
that lists the stories, the
top stories, of the day.
And what they've done really
well is they've, you know,
done this automatic collection
of information and aggregation
and all the work that they do
behind the scenes [inaudible],
but then they're doing human
curation of the content
in addition with their editors.
And so the content that you get,
the news stories are
extremely high quality.
So here we are, we're
moving through this list,
and you see a political story,
there's a U.S. news
story, technology, world.
Below each of these story
headlines you've got these
little atoms, these little
circles, and you can tap them
to get the legend of
what each of these mean,
but basically they're telling
you how much information there
is available for
one of the stories.
So let's go into the story
about Apple - hey, why not?
And you know, the first
time you use it, it says,
how to use the app, and so you
can swipe just right to left
around the stories, or
go back into a story
and read it in more detail.
And I find that these are,
you know, if I just take
about 10 minutes to plow
through this digest,
I've got some great information
about the latest headlines.
And so you get these great
call-outs, you're moving
through the stories,
that's pretty much it.
It's well laid out.
At the bottom you're getting
extra information like photos
that might be associated with
this story, that are coming
from really good sources.
There might be a
topic breakdown.
There might be a video that
loads very, very quickly
that it's a quick
summary of the story.
There's maps integration,
if it's appropriate.
And then you can go
through some top tweets
or other social networking
posts that apply to this story.
And so that's how each of
the stories is laid out,
and so you just flip through
them one by one, and read them,
some really great
visual effects and kind
of a playful UI in the app.
Another example of playful
UI is the share button.
These guys kind of pop up from
the bottom and then they kind
of bounce and go away.
So really great experience,
and then when you're done,
I love the -- what they've done.
This bear's having a good time.
I love what they've done at
the very end because you read
through this and the
news is really great,
but they've done a
great job of kind
of just gamifying this a little
bit by giving you feedback
on how many of the stories they
just sent you that you read.
And so while we just
swiped through them now,
it doesn't mean we read them,
but in theory you've read them,
and at the end you
just get told, hey,
you've read seven of nine.
And I just find that kind
of a cool bit of feedback.
Now, this digest
that we're looking
at right here has
a black background
because it's the
end of day digest.
But we can tap the
top right-hand corner,
see the next digest
is coming in 11 hours.
If I tap the center of
the screen, it says,
"Patience is a virtue."
I loved that the
first time I saw that.
And I can go back
across the last week
and pick one maybe a
digest that I hadn't read,
so I'll pick a morning digest,
and here the news comes in
and it's the white background.
So little bits of attention
to detail, little attention
to detail on things like
white background for day news,
black background for
nighttime news digest.
Very playful interface.
Really well integrated
with touch.
And, you know, beautiful
typography and layout.
And excellent quality news.
So really, really well
done, congratulations.
[ Music and Applause ]
We talk about great apps a
lot on the evangelism team.
We work with many of
you on Shaan's team.
She works with many,
many developers.
And we're always talking
with the developer community
about the need to create
something that is really great,
that is truly impactful
in people's lives.
And one of the ways to create a
really great game is of course
to use technology, have a
great game loop, have a great,
you know, game mechanic,
etcetera.
But more important
than any of that is
to add personality to a game.
That's what makes it engaging.
That's what makes a
connection with people.
And some of the you know,
some of the biggest names
that we all know, "Plants
Versus Zombies," "Cut the Rope,"
"Angry Birds," "Where's
My Water?"
by Disney, all of those games
had a great game experience,
but more importantly, they
had really great personality,
very unique to their game.
And this next game does
everything right in addition
to also adding personality
to the game.
And so we're pleased
to award an ADA to --
>> "Threes!"
by Sirvo.
[ Music and Applause ]
>> I'm totally addicted
to this game.
Congratulations.
I personally am addicted
to this game.
"Threes!" is a tiny puzzle
that will grow on you.
It's an engaging number-matching
puzzle that you'll learn
in a minute but play endlessly.
With an endearing
cast of characters
and an enchanting soundtrack,
it's been broadly
imitated but never equaled.
John.
>> Yeah, it's so true.
So, you know, most of you have
probably played this way more
than I have, by your
response when we awarded them.
But, you know, talk about
personality, you know,
this game has got
attitude, right.
So the longer I talk the more
annoyed they're going to get
because these tiles are
individual characters.
And we can find out
who they are.
This is Trin.
We can tap on Thumbert, right.
Each of these guys
has got character.
I love Treycee.
Hey. And you can see on
the front of these tiles
that they're, you know,
there's two eyes, there's a nose
or a mouth, the tiles
are constantly, you know,
they're blinking, they're
doing things with their face,
they're connecting
up with each other.
So the game is, you know,
you're doing ones and twos
to create threes and then you
can combine threes together.
So let's start to move here.
We've got to start playing here.
So we can combine one and
two with three, threes,
combining the sixes,
right, threes here, right.
And as you play, you get
this really great experience,
you know, these tiles talking
to you, and I love this.
And this is I think what
puts this game over the top
and helps it stand
out from the crowd.
I mean, it's not just
a tile sorting game -
the personality is this extra
layer, you know, brilliant layer
on top of the technology.
So this is why we picked
this game as a winner.
It's just great game play, very
engaging, great technology use
and excellent personality.
>> Thank you very much.
Congratulations.
[ Music and Applause ]
>> All right, so if you're
a creative professional,
the Mac has, you
know, the chances are,
the Mac has been
your tool of choice.
And, you know, across
all creative markets,
whether professional
or consumer, you know,
in the creative space, it's
pretty much always been the case
that the best apps are first
on the Mac or they're Mac only.
And our winner our next winner
stays in this tradition and we'd
like to award an
ADA tonight to --
>> "Cinemagraph Pro"
by Flixel Photos.
[ Music and Applause ]
>> Congratulations.
"Cinemagraph Pro" is
a professional tool
that allows you to
create living photos.
With its unique live masking
technology, it allows artists
to preview their
images in real time
and it creates ultrahigh
definition output
of your hybrid photos.
>> All right, so first
thing is, you know,
we all know how compelling video
is, and we see video on the Web
for advertisements or for,
you know, merchandising
or in catalogs or whatever,
for things that we might be
interested in that we want
to know about, and
video is really great.
But the problem with video is
it's hard to make and it's,
you know, got a big footprint,
it's got to be brought
down, it takes bandwidth.
And so, you know, there's
a better way to do this,
as far as these guys
are concerned,
they built this tool
that's optimized
to create something they're
calling Flixels or Cinemagraphs,
which are basically living
images that are a combination
of a photo and a video.
And they benefit from being
a whole lot more lightweight
than video and a lot more
interesting and compelling
than photos, just still photos.
So what I want to do
here is show you first
of all just an animated gif --
gif, sorry, animated gif that
I'm going to create in a moment,
and now this is sort of an
old file format on the Web,
but it's still prevalent.
And to create one of
these is difficult
to do what we're going
to do in a minute.
And so here's an animated gif.
And we're going to
end up with that,
and that started
with this raw video.
So this is just video taken
in a subway in New York.
And we're going to start
with that and quickly
in like three steps
create the animated gif
and create a Flixel.
So let me switch over
to "Cinemagraph Pro."
Now, what you do is you open up
the raw video that you've got,
and in this case we've got
somebody walking by on the left,
we've got the train
coming in here.
If you just look to the
left of the escalator,
you'll see as this loops,
the train's pulling in,
and there's the light,
and it stops, right.
So it's a very short clip.
But we don't want any of
those noise on the side,
we don't want any of the
reflection from the lights
and different things that are
in the station on the walls.
And so we start in the top
left corner we choose trim,
we pull in the trim, and
we figure out exactly,
you notice the lady on the left,
we decide where we want her
to freeze in the image
that we're going to create
or in the Cinemagraph that
we're going to create,
and we stop it there with
the left side of the trim.
The right side of the trim,
I'm just going to pull in here
and adjust just slightly
so I get the light
from the train coming
in to the left
of the escalator
there, you see that?
It's in there.
So that's just pulling
it in for the right side.
And then next is where
the magic happens.
I'm going to go to
the mask tool,
it's a little bit too big here,
so I'm going to adjust its size.
Go down and I'm going to
mask the portion of the image
that of the video
that I want to keep,
everything else now becomes
basically masked out.
And then I'm going to go to loop
and decide what kind of a loop,
I've got several types
of loops that I can do.
I'll just stick with repeat.
I'm going to, you know, leave
the speed the way it is.
Leave the lay the way it is.
And just increase crossfade.
Crossfade is what happens
when the video ends
and then it loops
back to the beginning.
So we'll just make
that smooth so it looks
like a continuous
movement of the escalator.
And lastly, we'll go to look
quickly at adjustments -
I can adjust all kinds of
the attributes on this video.
But I'll just go to the
canned effects that are here,
and you can see that you can
apply these super quickly
to this image.
And so let's grab black
and white cold sun,
and then we'll do a
render, and we can save it
out as [inaudible] or pro
res 422, so we'll do that,
save it to the desktop.
Let's call it demo.
And what it's creating now is
it's creating this Flixel file,
this cinemagraph that the folks
at "Cinemagraph Pro" sorry
at Flixel can host on
their servers for you,
and it's super lightweight,
comes down,
works with every browser, and
gives you that exact experience.
And so the end result is
basically this, you know,
you can see that the woman
on the left is frozen,
everything about
the scene is frozen,
except the one piece
that we want.
We did this in three
simple steps.
This app is brand new on the Mac
App Store, it's super gorgeous,
it's really streamlined.
It does one thing extremely
well, saving you 30 steps
in other tools, and they
have a really great model
for hosting these things and
serving them out to your site.
And we just love this app,
and it makes a Mac Pro sing.
So really well done
work, thank you.
[ Music and Applause ]
All right, we talked
about a moment ago
about how great apps
have personality,
and earlier on I talked
about how we judge
the apps for the ADA.
We talked about design.
We talk about technology or we
evaluate on technology adoption.
We evaluate on innovation.
And we all know that great
apps are also innovative.
And, you know, innovation is
hard to define, but it's sort
of that spark of brilliance.
It's that ingredient
that if an app has it,
it just makes your
jaw drop, right.
It's the kind of thing that
makes a category, you know,
appear out of nowhere, right.
They're category-defining
apps that are innovative.
They do something clever.
And, you know, you really
know it when you see it.
And we've all run
across innovative apps.
And we've run across one
for the ADA this year
that we thought was that was
just over the top in terms
of just approaching this game
situation in a very clever way.
Our next winner.
>> Is "Device 6" by Simogo.
[ Music and Applause ]
>> Look at this tie,
that's nice.
>> Nice tie.
"Device 6" plays
with the conventions
of games and literature.
It's a captivating thriller
in which the written
word is both your map
as well as your narrator.
Entwining story with puzzle and
blending puzzle with novella,
it draws the players into
an intriguing mystery
of neuroscience and technology.
>> Right, so I'm
in landscape mode.
Just bear with me here.
We're in landscape mode,
you're holding the iPad,
this is a narrative that
you're reading through,
it's a book that
you read through.
And we're starting
sort of halfway
through the first chapter.
But as you move here, you can
see this parallax effect behind
these images, yeah.
And that is pervasive
through the app.
But not only are the words
onscreen things that you read
to tell you the story, but
you're also going to get clues
about the puzzle that
you have to solve,
because fundamentally,
this is a game.
But it's a combination
novel game.
And so you're reading along,
you're looking at these photos,
they do really interesting
interactions,
and they have a great
sound system built in.
So sometimes you approach
sounds and, you know,
they'll become louder and
softer as you're near them.
Here we've run into
an interactive,
an interactive piece, which at
the moment doesn't do anything.
But we're going to need it at
some point to solve the puzzle.
And we move on here and
you'll see that, you know,
while I'm reading this text, the
text is actually doing all kinds
of interesting things.
So I'm moving along,
don't worry about the fact
that it's portrait up there
because we're going to go
in different directions
here in a moment.
And you see that I'm
just scrolling left
but the text is actually
moving things.
Here I get to the third
floor study, I keep going,
and here I've got a device I
can interact with, you know,
probably put a combo
in or something.
I keep going here and now
I've got a choice, I can go up
or down, I'm going to keep
going here a little bit.
And now we're starting
to get to a point
where we have to
rotate the device.
And now for you guys you'll be
able to read it, no problem.
Now I'm approaching
a source of sound.
[ App Sounds ]
And we'll leave that behind.
We go here, I have to turn
the device this way to read.
I've got to turn
the device this way-
of course it's screwing
up our projection.
There we pass that, and
now we're going here,
we're going this way,
we're reading the text.
Now we're going to
flip this way.
And essentially this
entire game is -
here we're moving
into a dining hall.
[ App Sounds ]
I've got to get authorization.
And what is so innovative
about this game is just this
combination of novel with game
with puzzle and just you're
constantly rotating your device,
tapping, pinching,
zooming, moving around,
reading this story,
trying to figure it out.
And we'd never seen
anything like this really.
And so great job,
congratulations.
[ Music and Applause ]
Talked a little bit before
about how we're so busy
that getting news in a
digestible format was a dilemma,
and the folks from "Yahoo!
News Digest" solved
that problem.
But, you know, there's
also something else
that we're all doing every day,
and that is sharing these
tidbits from our lives
with family, with
friends, with the world.
If you're here at WWDC
and telling the world
about what's going on.
But as interesting and
valuable as these tidbits are,
they don't I don't think
they replace the need
for sometimes telling
a much longer story,
a much more visual story,
that captures an emotion
and something much deeper than
any tweet or any, you know,
Facebook post or any other
social media post could do.
And our next winner
is an app that allows
for that type of
rich storytelling.
>> And it is "Storehouse
Visual Storytelling"
by Storehouse Media.
[ Music and Applause ]
>> Congratulations.
Instantly travel the
world, learn a new skill
or discover interesting people
as you explore the
stories created
by the Storehouse community.
Or you can simply put together
photos, videos and texts
to build your own stories.
And you don't have
to be a designer
to put together something
stunning.
>> All right, like all
of our winners tonight,
this app was designed, you
know, optimally designed
for the device it's running on,
for iPad, for iPhone, for OS X.
And this app is the storytelling
app that's built exclusively
for iPad.
And the stories are told
using photos and video.
And so what you do is -
and they're contributed
by the community of
Storehouse users.
So, you know, you create
an account with them
and then you can just use
this to push out your stories
to the world or to
a set of people
that you want to view them.
And so, you know, just some
really gorgeous animations here.
We can flip through these
books, these stories,
that have been pushed
out into the app.
They can contain
video and audio.
So let's go in here and take
a look at this one, Chicago.
I love this one.
So you just tap to go into this
story that someone published.
And we gesture through and
you get to see this, you know,
the great effect on text
that's happening here.
You can follow this publisher.
You can look at these photos.
You can apply effects
to the images.
You know, so this is
pretty gorgeous photography.
And it's just laid out in
such a really compelling way
that makes it really
digestible and easy to consume.
And then laying out text
on it is super easy.
Anyway, and so when
you're done with a story,
you can just pinch
to get out of it.
They're using, you know,
UI effects and UI dynamics
and stuff for the transitions.
Let me go into one
that's got some video,
so let's go into this story
by a photojournalist
who went to Rwanda.
And so this one's got, you
know, much larger photos,
a lot more texts, these
individual portraits.
And quickly here we're
going to get to a video,
just embedded right in,
you don't have to tap
to start playing the
video, it just does
as it pulls the majority
of it onscreen, right.
You keep reading.
Again, it's a much more
significant, deeper,
more emotional story that's
being told here, right.
And so these are being created
by chefs, by fashion designers,
by photojournalists
around the world,
and families are creating them,
individuals are creating them.
So one of the things about this
app is it lets you create one
of these books or these
stories sorry super easily.
So you just tap the
create button.
We're going to add
from the photo library.
Let's say we went to the lake,
we import these 14 images,
and immediately they're
laid out in the format
that the app provides.
So let's say, you know, trip
to the lake, great memories,
and we say done on that.
Okay, so now we're
down in the basic view,
which is thumbnail view, but
it's like I want to do more
than this, I want to
make something compelling
like the Chicago one
I saw a moment ago.
So you could say, well, you
know what, this image here
of the cyclist is pretty cool.
So we just tap and
drag, make that larger.
This one of her on the
tree stump is pretty cool,
so we can just tap
and drag that.
We can double tap and you know,
and crop it in the way we want.
Go around, make something
really big, like this,
everything else moves
out of the way.
Great feedback through
animation.
And you just go on and on,
and you can add the texts,
you can create the
breaks you want,
and then you can publish this
out to the Storehouse community.
And if people are following you,
they're going to see your story.
In this case I'm just going
to save it as a draft.
But this is just such a
compelling app, just to browse
through these stories and
see what people are posting.
And they are far more
significant and more meaningful
and more emotionally charged
than just something small
that we put out to the world
which is equally valuable
but very different.
So great adoption
of iOS technologies.
Thanks for making
something exclusive for iPad
that is so compelling.
[ Music and Applause ]
Now, people have been
captivated for, you know,
all of time pretty
much by the night sky.
I mean, who hasn't sat out,
you know, on a campground
with friends in the
back of a truck
on a country road
somewhere looking
up at the night sky watching,
you know, airplane lights,
watching satellites pass
over, identifying, you know,
constellations or trying to,
you know, pointing out things
that are known like the Big
Dipper or the North Star
or something like that.
We've all done that, and we've
all been captivated by that.
And it's certainly
a very humbling
and powerful experience
to see the night sky.
And the developer of our next
winner has created an app
that takes that to
a whole new level.
>> And it is "Sky Guide"
by Fifth Star Labs.
[ Music and Applause ]
Discovering what's in the
night sky is effortless
with "Sky Guide."
You can search for
thousands of celestial objects
and simply follow the arrow in
the sky above you to see them.
And "Sky Guide" works offline,
so you can take it
with you anywhere.
>> All right, let's
take a look at this app.
You know, first and foremost,
the app just does
everything right technically.
It is optimized, you
know, to the nth degree.
They're using OpenGL ES 3.
They're using Core Audio.
They're, you know, leveraging
all of the technologies
that are appropriate and
relevant for this app.
And the performance
is just stunning.
One of the first things
you'll notice in the app, too,
and you're hearing it now is
just this ambient music that's
playing in the background.
The composer of the
music was the same guy
who composed the
sounds for an ADA winner
of a couple years
ago called "Osmos."
Great game.
And this soundtrack here for
this game is just so compelling.
So as you're in this, you can
just, you know, tap around
and look at the night sky.
It automatically is showing
you the various constellations.
I can tap on stars, and
I'm going to stop talking
for a minute as I
tap on these stars,
small stars produce
a small sound,
larger stars produce
a large sound.
But just you tap around and you
can almost make your own music
as you're just experiencing
this.
[ App Sounds ]
You can lift it up, but
because of the shortness
of the cords I'm not
going to do that.
You can lift it up and
as soon as it detects
that you're looking at the
sky, it activates the compass
and gyroscope and so now
you can pan around the sky
above us and around us.
In this case I'm just going
to go search for something
that we all are familiar with,
which is the Space Station.
And you know, you saw it
pointing to where we're going,
and now you can see
the trajectory
of the Space Station,
which is pretty cool.
I can zoom in on stuff,
I won't be able to see it
in great detail because
it's, you know, pretty small.
But let's go back
out here and look
at the different part
of the night sky.
One of the things you can
do is you could just --
because of the light
pollution that's around us
when we're outside, you can
actually just tap two fingers
onscreen and drag up or
down to adjust the amount
of stars onscreen in "Sky Guide"
relative to what you're seeing,
you know, when you're
outside, so that's kind
of cool, so it's a good match.
You can also learn a
lot about the night sky
by leveraging a tool inside of
the app, and this is the loop.
So this lets you see different
spectra beyond what's visible
to the human eye.
And so you just bring
up this loop,
you can drag it around the sky.
But you could just take this
and move through, you know,
microwave, infrared, h-alpha,
and you can leave it there
and simply move around the night
sky and look at different things
that are going on that
you wouldn't know about
but might be behind one
of your most, you know,
most favorite constellations
or something.
If I tap on an individual
item, I get this little eye
on the side here, you'll see
it on the right side there.
It's blinking to say,
you know, look at me.
And I could read through
information about the object,
Sirius, in this case,
that I selected.
I can tap something like Canis
Minor, and it will go to that.
I can tap the name of another
star, and it'll go there.
I can tap the sun, and it
will rotate to the sun.
So, you know, and this is
just scratching the surface
of this app.
It's incredible the
attention to detail
that these guys put into it.
The optimization for iOS.
The soundtrack.
It's just a pleasure
to use this app.
And I think it sets a standard
that all of us should aspire
to in our particular
individual categories.
So thank you for great work.
[ Music and Applause ]
Now, speaking of great
work, we all aspire
to do great things
in our lives, right.
We've all got these great ideas.
All of you have got undoubtedly
ideas already coming to mind
for things you're going to do
with iOS 8 and OS X Yosemite.
And you know, when we've
got these great ideas,
we also have these
very high standards
for ourselves in many cases.
And when you've got
these high standards,
it's often difficult though
to actually realize them
for a variety of reasons
beyond our own control, right.
Life has a way of taking charge.
But and that's why some
of these great ideas are
such a big challenge.
But when you can pull
them off, it's amazing,
and it's definitely
something that's worth noting,
it's a definitely
notable moment.
And so our next winner
is just an incredible app
that was definitely a big
idea I think for them.
And they set out to do
something fantastic,
and I think they achieved that.
>> And our final award
this afternoon goes
to "Monument Valley"
by ustwo studio.
[ Music and Applause ]
"Monument Valley" is
a surreal exploration
through fantastical
architectures
and impossible geometry.
Guide the silent Princess Ida
through mysterious monuments,
uncovering hidden paths and
unfolding optical illusions
to outsmart the enigmatic
crow people.
>> This is such an awesome game.
And I don't know where
the idea came from,
we'll have to hear the
story someday, but it is -
they just set out to
do something so big
and the result is amazing.
So what you're doing is you're
taking this little Princess Ida
and you've got to get her to
the top of these, you know,
to the top of the scenes.
In this case the top
of the tower there.
But we're looking at this
very Escheresque 3-D model,
and a lot of things
don't line up.
Anyway, so we'll
figure it out as we go.
No. 1, you know, you can
interact with objects onscreen.
So this one's pretty
straightforward - let's just tap
and tell her where to go.
She's going to go up here,
we're going to put her up here.
But now, now what do we do?
But you get these hints onscreen
that so you can turn this
and so we'll walk around here,
we're going to walk her around,
flip this around, and now
she's got to go and step
on this special platform,
which is now going
to deconstruct things.
But you know, when you
look at this, okay,
now where's she going to go?
She can't climb that
center pole.
She can't you know,
what are we going to do?
But what's just so cool about
this app is that once you start
to interact with these objects,
you realize like look what's
going on here, you didn't think
that that top bar
was the same height
as the other walkway, right.
But as you start to
rotate it around,
they've just done this great job
of showing what you're doing.
[ Applause ]
You know, it's like that
you know, those stairs
that just never end, right,
it's exactly that experience.
So here you turn around,
now she's going to get
to the final destination, right.
And so she gets there, we
get this path that appears,
and now we get onto
this next level.
So she's going to
walk around here.
And this just goes
on and on and on.
And it's just so awesome,
because in this level here,
she suddenly learns to
walk sideways and walk
on different surfaces.
So here she's going up here.
We're going to walk
her around here.
And just listen to this
soundtrack that's going
on behind the scenes.
Now you're like what is
happening here, right?
But if we turn let's see -
can I remember how to do this?
Well, let's just end the
demo there because - oh,
I know what to do, I know
what to do, that's right.
I want to get to the backside of
this thing, no I can't do that.
I can't remember, it's okay,
you've got to play the game.
Awesome use of technology.
A great user experience.
Fabulous art that's
optimized for retina display.
And just such an
intriguing experience.
And you should just be
super proud of your work.
We really appreciate what
you've done for iPad, thank you.
[ Music and Applause ]
>> So that's it, those
are our 12 winners
for the Apple Design Awards in
2014; 12 incredible apps built
on and for iOS 7
and OS X Mavericks.
>> These are 12 incredible
developers who we'd love
to invite back on stage now.
So come on up, you guys.
[ Music and Applause ]
You know, these folks
have done such great work.
You've just seen, you
know, you've seen a little,
a few seconds of
each of their apps,
but already you get a glimpse of
why these apps are really great.
These guys have set a new
benchmark with these apps
for excellence, for creativity,
for technology adoption,
for innovation, for
so many things.
And really these
apps set a standard
that we're really saying to
you as a community, you know,
your work needs to be just
like these guys, it needs to be
of this quality or higher.
They've set the new bar.
And I think just for a
moment it would be great just
to give these people a hand.
They've worked so hard.
They're so creative.
[ Applause ]
So thank you for
all your hard work.
Keep doing it.
>> And we can't wait to see
what these developers and you do
with iOS 8 and OS X Yosemite.
Thank you very much.