>> OK. Hello everybody.
My name is Dave Wilson.
I'm on the iAd team, and
I'm here to talk to you
about optimizing your
earning power with iAd.
For those of you who
don't know somehow,
iAd is Apple's digital
advertising platform.
This is what's used -
you may have seen it
in other apps you've
used on iOS.
If you use iTunes Radio at
all, the ads that you see
in iTunes Radio are
driven by iAd.
So that's what iAd is.
There's two parts to
this presentation.
We're going to be talking
first about monetization:
how you can use iAd
inside your apps
to drive revenue for your apps.
And the second part is
promotion: how you can use iAd
to get more downloads of
your app to get more users
of your app - to get your app
out in everyone else's hands.
So let's start off
with monetization.
I'm going to start off
with a few different pieces
we're going to talk about here.
Talk about some developer
benefits,
what iAd can do for you.
Talk about some core concepts,
sort of an advertising 101.
We'll talk about improving
performance, how you can sort
of best use iAd and
get the most out of it.
We'll talk some details about
the actual code you have
to write to integrate
iAd inside your app,
which is fortunately
pretty simple.
We'll talk a little
bit about testing iAd
and making sure your integration
is actually working before you
get out in the App Store
and then just get bugs
So let's start off with
developer benefits.
First of all, iAd provides
rich, engaging ads.
This is a platform that
values great ads to go
into the great apps
that you create.
They're high production values.
There's rich media apps,
and there's rich media
ads involved here.
These are things
that involve video.
They involve animations.
They're immersive.
These are sometimes entire
games presented inside ads.
There was an Intel ad recently
that was literally a game
once the users tapped on it.
This is the other things
that your users are actually
interested in engaging on,
interested in tapping on,
which is great for you
as a potential advertising
publisher here.
These are award-winning ads.
These are not just fly by
night, you know, one off apps -
or ads with link tags
in them that are going
to annoy the heck
out of your users.
These are carefully crafted ads
that actually look good
as part of your app.
OK? In addition, Apple
is providing this SDK.
As a result, the same care
that Apple takes with respect
to privacy and power efficiency
on the rest of Apple's system,
Apple invests in iAd as well.
That means that we take
care of all of the power
and privacy considerations
for you
so you don't have
to worry about them.
You don't need to worry
about obeying the limit
ad tracking switch.
You don't need to obey
about - don't need to worry
about location permissions
or making sure
that your users' privacy
and personal data is
protected properly.
In addition, because this
is an Apple-provided SDK,
it's part of the iOS SDK.
Integration is simple.
There's nothing else to install.
There are no static
libraries to include.
There's no third-party
headers to drop
into your project to
clutter things up.
It's all there to begin with.
You can be up and
running with minimal code.
As we're going to see later,
it's about two lines of code
to get banners in your app.
In addition, along with the
rest of the code that other -
along with the rest of the
SDK that Apple provides,
there's great documentation
and great sample code available
to you on the websites.
iAd has global reach.
We're in 14 countries now.
We're constantly expanding.
This a larger list of countries
than we showed up
here last year.
And that means that you're
going to get ads in all
of those countries
inside your app.
So as soon as you get your
app in all those countries,
you're going to be
able to get revenue
in those countries as well.
Just like the actual
app purchase
and then In-App Purchases
as well, you're going
to get 70 percent of
the advertising revenue
from iAd inside your app.
Apple takes its 30 percent
share, and everything else goes
to you from whatever we
take in from the advertisers
who are producing these
ads to run inside your app.
It's very easy for you to
get into the iAd ecosystem.
There's an iAd contract on the
itunesconnect.apple.com site
that you have to sign.
That's pretty easy.
You integrate the iAd
framework; that's what the rest
of this talk is going
to be about.
And then, you submit
your app for review,
and that's really
all you have to do.
OK. So that's sort of
what iAd can do for you.
Let's talk about
some core concepts.
These are some fundamental
basics of advertising
and some terminology
that you're going to see,
especially on the iTunes Connect
website once you've integrated
iAd and are trying to track the
progress of you getting revenue
from iAd inside your app.
First of all, there's an ad
request, and you're going
to see this come up again.
Later, you'll see
this in metrics.
What is an ad request?
It's a network request.
It goes from the device,
through the iAd framework.
It's going to go out to the
iAd servers up in the cloud.
And hopefully, ads will
come back down to you,
assuming there are ads available
for your particular app
in the current situation
of the user.
You know, again, if the user
is in a country we're not in,
you're not going to be able to
get ads there, unfortunately.
Once you've started
getting ads from the -
if you get an ad request, you
want to look at your fill rate.
This is the ratio of ads
delivered by the ad server
to the number of requests that
you actually make to the server.
This is, again, going
to be determined
by where your users are located,
what type of app you have,
how well your app has
done with iAd in the past.
And we'll get to that in a
little bit - a little later,
as to how that can
be really important
in driving your fill rate.
Once you've gotten ads,
you've gotten your fill rate
and you've shown
ads to the user,
there's a constant called
the tap-through rate.
This is the number of the ads
that your user has
actually tapped on,
and this does not
count accidental taps.
So if the tap - if the user just
taps on it and then closes it
because they didn't really
mean it, that doesn't count.
This is the number of taps
that the user actually meant
to have happen relative
to the number
of ads you displayed
to that user.
This is something
you want to attempt
to maximize inside your app.
Again, though, accidental
taps don't count.
So trying to play games
is not a good idea.
Ad engagement.
Obviously, you need
to display the ad.
If you're not displaying
the ad to the user,
it doesn't matter how
many of them you request
from the server, you're not
going to get paid for them,
and you might as well
not have bothered.
Once you do that, make sure it's
actually fully visible as well.
The fact that it's onscreen and
only one pixel of it is showing
because you've got it covered
up with something else,
that doesn't really
count either.
You want to make sure
that the ad is visible
for as long as possible.
Leave it onscreen.
Again, if it shows
up and it flashes
for two seconds, no
one really saw it.
It doesn't matter.
You want to make sure
that ads are onscreen.
This is - has two benefits.
One, it's not distracting
to your user.
You're not annoying people
by flashing things on
and offscreen all the time that
people really don't want to see.
In addition, the user has
time to interact with it.
They have time to see it.
They have time to
see its message.
They have time to say, "Hey.
You know, I'd actually like to
tap on this and engage with it
and see what's going
on under the hood."
That leads into allow
interaction.
It's really easy to
put something onscreen
and accidentally cover it up,
especially accidentally
covering it up with something
that blocks user interaction.
If you put a banner onscreen,
you cover it up with something
that is, say, a transparent view
that does not allow user
interaction, the user can't tap
on the banner under the hood.
That's not a good
situation for the ad.
The user is going to
be trying to tap on it,
nothing's going to happen.
It's going to be
a bad experience.
In addition, again,
you're not going
to get the revenue you're hoping
for in this sort of situation
because the ad wasn't
really onscreen.
OK. So there's some
sort of core concepts.
Talk a little bit
about what you can do
to improve the performance
of iAd once you've actually
integrated it inside your app.
First of all, revenue
starts with your app.
If you don't have a great app,
it doesn't matter how
many banners you show,
many ads you show.
No one is using your app,
and you're not going
to make any money.
So the number one thing you
can do to drive revenue via ads
in your app is to start
off with a great app.
And that's what the rest of WWDC
is about, but a couple of sort
of small things we
can mention here.
First of all, app
engagement time.
If your - if you have an
app that's - you're trying
to drive revenue by showing
ads, you need to make sure
that your have sufficient
engagement time
for your users to
actually do this.
If it's a utility app that
the user is going to pull up,
it's going to be onscreen
for about three seconds,
and then they're going
to close your app again,
that's not enough time to
actually show ads to the users
and allow interaction and to get
interaction from those users.
So you need an app that
actually is going to be onscreen
and that people are actually
going to engage with.
Again, once you've done
that, you want to make sure
that the ad is placed
carefully within that app.
Think about what
the user is doing
on the various screens
of your app.
Make sure the ad is placed
appropriately within the app.
If you have a game,
for instance,
and the user is tapping and
swiping and slicing constantly,
maybe that's not a great place
for a banner where they're going
to be accidentally tapping.
The ad will pop up over
the top of everything.
You're going to be annoying
your users, and you're going
to be harming your app more than
you're helping it with the ads.
OK? Pulling back into app
engagement time: user loyalty.
You need to come - you need
your users to come back
to the app repeatedly.
That's how you get
more screen time,
that's how you get more ad
time for those particular -
for showing ads to those users.
In addition, user loyalty
is what drives ad -
or app engagement and
what drives app downloads.
The sort of network effects that
you may have heard of before.
The more people are using
your app, the more they want
to use it, the more they're
going to tell their friends
about using it, the more
downloads you're going to get.
Therefore, the more eyeballs
you're going to get looking
at ads within your app.
OK? I mentioned that
iAd is in 14 countries.
That means that your app should
be in 14 countries if you want
to get as most - the most
revenue from iAd as you can.
Market your app to the
countries where iAd actually is.
If you're - if you've spent
the time to integrate iAd
into your app, you want to make
sure that your app is in all
of the places that iAd is so you
have the largest reach possible
to potentially get the most
users possible for your app.
A big part of that is
localizing your app.
If the only thing you've done
is write your app in English,
and you're trying to get it
in all 14 of these countries,
you're going to have a
hard time in countries
where English has
a small presence.
Make sure you take the time to
localize your app appropriately
to drive users in
those countries.
And back into ad
placement a little bit,
because this is a piece I'm
going to keep coming back to.
Ad placement is extraordinarily
important within your app.
You will recognize high-use
areas inside your app,
and you want to make sure you
put banners inside those areas.
Those are the places where
users are going to be looking
at the screen for a
long period of time.
They're going to
have the opportunity
to see the app - the ad.
They're going to
have the opportunity
to engage with the ad.
At the same time,
as I mentioned,
avoid accidental taps.
Accidental taps are bad for your
user, and they're bad for you.
They're going to annoy
your user, and iAd doesn't
like accidental taps either.
So you want to make sure that
you are using the framework
in a way that does
not encourage them
because your app will ultimately
end up being penalized for this.
User context is really
important.
You want to take advantage of
different types of ads based
on what the user is
doing at any given time.
Say the user is on the
menu screen of your game.
Maybe that's a great
place to put a banner
at the bottom of the screen.
They're looking at the menu.
Maybe they notice the app
- or the ad at the bottom.
Maybe they tap on it
and engage with it.
At the same time, if they tap
to go into the first level
of your game, and you
immediately pop a full-fledged
ad and interrupt their
experience once they've done
their first action
inside the game,
that's just going to annoy them.
You're going to drive
users away.
Users aren't going to want
to engage with the ads.
That's what you want
to try to avoid.
So be very careful about
where you're putting the ads
within your app.
Once you've integrated iAd
and you can start looking
on the website, you'll
start getting reports
about your revenue.
One of the things
you're going to notice,
everyone always notices
this and brings this up,
is that revenue will fluctuate.
This is perfectly natural.
Consumer spending is seasonal.
Advertiser spending
is also seasonal
because consumer
spending is seasonal.
You need to be aware of
this and watch for it.
You can also take
advantage of this.
Market your app accordingly.
Start of summer, back to
school, holiday season -
these are the times
when users are going
out to get new devices, they're
going out to get new apps,
and advertisers are going out to
get eyeballs inside those apps.
So that's when you want to
try and get - try and put all
of your money into
pushing your app out there.
OK. We've talked about ads.
We've talked about impressions.
We've talked about tap-throughs.
We've talked about fill rate.
This is a virtuous cycle.
OK? You're going to
get ads to begin with.
They're going to
lead to impressions.
Impressions are going
to lead to tap-throughs.
The more tap-throughs you get,
the more ads you're going to get
from the ad server, the more
impressions you're going to get.
OK. So that's performance.
Now that we've done that, now we
can go into some actual details
about how you actually go about
integrating all of this stuff,
sort of the meat of this talk.
There's four ad formats.
There's banner, there's
interstitial,
there's medium rect, and
there's a pre-roll video ad.
We'll talk about each
of these four in turn.
As I mentioned earlier,
you're going to want
to choose the correct
ad for your app
in the various contexts
within your app.
So all four of these types
of ads are important
for many, many apps.
We'll start off with banner.
OK? So what is a banner?
It's a slim device width view.
It's placed at the
bottom of your content.
It continuously loads ads.
You may have used other iAd
SDKs or ad SDKs where you've got
to make a specific request.
This isn't that.
You create a view.
It's going to show up at
the bottom of the page
and will continuously
load ads over time
as new ads are downloaded
from the ad server.
There's nothing you have
to do to manage that.
Once the user taps on it, it's
going to go into some sort
of full-screen ad
experience - and supported
on both iPhone and iPad.
It has been since
the beginning of iAd.
Integrating banners
in your app is
about the simplest
thing that you could do.
There's three steps to this.
You're going to link
the iAd framework.
You're going to import
the iAd header,
which is the first
line that popped there.
And you're going to configure
your view controller,
which involves setting the
.canDisplayBannerAds property
to yes on your view controller.
That's it.
If you've done that, you've
got a banner inside your app.
OK? So what does that look like?
OK. Loading an ad.
You've got your view.
The moment you set the
.canDisplayBannerAds property
on it, we're going to do
something under the hood
to your view controller.
Your view is going to turn
into original content view.
We're going to move your view
over to original content view,
and we're going to take a
review on your view controller.
So it's very important
for you to remember
if you're subsequently
attempting to access your view
on that view controller.
We're then going to make a
request up the ad server.
It's going to come back
and hopefully a banner
is going to load.
And at that time, we're going
to move the banner onscreen
and we're going to resize
your original content view
appropriately and with
the appropriate animation
to move the thing onscreen
so the user can actually
look at it.
Once it's been onscreen
for a while,
hopefully the user is going
to go ahead and tap on it.
And at that point,
the full-screen ad
experience is going to pop up.
When that happens, there are a
couple of things you need to do.
First of which is to pause
activity in -viewWillDisappear:.
Your app is probably doing
things in the background while
that banner is onscreen.
When the user wants
to engage with the ad,
you want to get out of the way.
If you're playing music.
If you're running
a game simulation.
If you're doing anything else
that's potentially intensive
or distracting, you're
going to pause that activity
in -viewWillDisappear:
so that it gets
out of the way of the ad.
Eventually, the user will be
done interacting with the ad.
They'll dismiss it.
You'll get a -viewDidAppear:.
Resume all that activity.
Once the ad's gone, you want
to start the music up again.
You want to start your
game simulation, etcetera.
Eventually, say the user goes
out of network connectivity
or something, you may not
have an ad available anymore.
When that happens, the banner is
going to be moved off of screen.
The original content view will
resized and that - and you can,
you know, wait until it
hopefully reloads again.
In addition to waiting for
the network connectivity
to just move the banner
back off of screen,
you can control the banner
visibility whenever you
would like.
If something happens within
your app that you would
like to move the banner
offscreen temporarily,
you can go ahead and so.
Just go ahead and set
.canDisplayBannerAds to no.
Just don't forget to
set it back to yes
when you want to re-enable it.
Make sure you put the ad back
onscreen whenever you actually
need to.
OK. So that's banners.
Let's talk about interstitials
next, which is the sort
of second major type of
banner - type of ad here.
Very different than banners.
Rather than something
being permanently onscreen,
they're immediate
full-screen display.
They immediately take
over the entire screen
when you want to present them.
The user is immediately
able to interact with them.
OK? They've been on
iPad since iOS 4.3,
and they were introduced on
the phone in iOS 7 last year.
There's two major ways to handle
interstitial presentation.
The first is automatic
presentation.
Just like banners, it's pretty
simple to configure here.
Rather than setting
.canDisplayBannerAds,
you're going to set
.interstitialPresentationPolicy
to ADInterstitial
PresentationPolicyAutomatic.
What that does is tell
the iAd framework, hey,
this is a great view
controller to show ads on,
and whenever you, as the iAd
framework, think is a great time
to show ads, go ahead and do so.
At the moment, that means
that we're going to show ads
when this view controller first
moves onscreen, when it appears.
I'm going to take
that as an opportunity
to show an interstitial
ad if one is available.
So to do that, just take
your view controller,
push it onscreen, make it - push
it into your navigation stack,
or however you want
to put it onscreen.
That moves in, and we're going
to pop an ad up over top of it.
When the user is
done interacting
with it, it'll come back off.
In addition to automatic
presentation,
there's manual presentation.
Just set the presentation policy
to ADInterstitial
PresentationPolicyManual,
and instead of us automatically
presenting it whenever the view
moves onscreen, you can call -
request interstitial ad
presentation to attempt
to display it whenever you
think it's an appropriate time
for an ad to pop up over
top of your content.
Next, preparing for
presentation.
Because interstitials don't
have something onscreen,
something sitting
there requesting ads,
attempting to display
things at all times,
you want to notify the iAd
framework that you would
like to present interstitials
in the future so we can go ahead
and make an ad request and
have an interstitial waiting
for you when that time comes.
To do that, you're going to want
to call UIViewController
prepareInterstitialAds inside
something early in
your app's life cycle.
ApplicationDidFinish
LaunchingWithOptions is a good
opportunity here.
If you're doing a lot of
other work at that point,
maybe defer it a little bit.
But you want to call this
prior to your attempt
to present an interstitial
for the first time.
That gives the iAd
framework enough time to go
out to the network, request an
ad, and have everything ready
to present by the time you
want one to be presented.
That will prevent you from
missing ad opportunities.
OK. So that's banners
and interstitials.
We're going to go from
here into a quick demo just
of the APIs I just went over.
So we'll switch over to
my demo machine here.
What I'm going to start off
with here, I'll just draw
up my little app, is a very
simple master detail app here.
Just shows some news articles.
I can click on one of these
news articles and bring it up.
And what we'd like to do is
take this app and add some ads
to it, monetize it with iAd.
So if I can quit the
simulator again here.
What do we want to
do here first?
The first thing we're going to
do is add a banner to the bottom
of the MasterViewController,
the bottom of that article list.
So inside our
MasterViewController here,
we're going to import
the iAd header.
Do that like this.
And then, inside, awakeFromNib,
all we're going to do is call -
set self.canDisplayBannerAds
to yes,
and that's really
all we have to do.
Oh, one more thing.
We need to go in here,
development phases,
and ensure that we link
against the iAd framework.
Make sure the APIs are actually
available to us, so we go back
to MasterViewController here.
Go ahead and run.
And we'll see that with two
lines of code and one link,
we have banners at the
bottom of our screen
that are automatically in
line with our view controller.
Now, we only set that on
the MasterViewController.
That means that when we go into
an article, there's no ad there,
which is a little
bit unfortunate.
So the next thing we want
to do is take advantage
of the other type of ad that
we talked about, interstitials,
to present an ad
to the user prior
to them actually being
able to read the article.
So once they've tapped
on the article title,
we want to add the
popup over the top
of the screen before they
can actually see the article.
So let's go ahead
and quit this again.
And this time, we're
going to, down here,
inside our prepareForSegue
function, we're just going
to set up the
DetailViewController
that shows the actual article.
We're going to grab this
destination.interstitial
PresentationPolicy
ADinterstitial
PresentationPolicyAutomatic
so that we can say
that on this
DetailViewController,
the thing that's
showing the article,
we want the iAd framework
to manage presentation
of interstitial ads over
top of this view controller.
Once we've done that, that's
going to get interstitials shown
over that view controller.
However, we want to make sure
that the iAd framework knows
to go out and look
for interstitials
before the user taps
on an article for
the first time.
So to do that, we're
going to go over here.
We're going to get to
our AppDelegate here,
and we're just going to
grab UIViewController
prepareInterstitialAds.
Make sure we import
the header as well.
That tells iAd, hey, go
prepare interstitial ads
so they're ready
for our user here.
So I'll go ahead and save this.
Run our demo again.
Once again, we've got
the article view here.
We've got a banner loaded
at the bottom that happened.
Now, once the user taps on this,
the interstitial ad is going
to pop up over top
of the article.
Once the appropriate
time is expired,
the user is done interacting
with this, they can go ahead
and close that, and the article
is behind, and they can go ahead
and start reading their article.
So that's basically how easy
it is to integrate banners
and interstitials to your app.
So we'll go back to the slides.
OK. So that's banners
and interstitials,
which are the first two
major types of ads for iAd.
They were also the first two
types of ads that iAd had.
Those were the ones that were
sort of available pretty much
from the beginning of iAd.
There are a couple of
newer types that we've got.
The first new type, it's
- talking about banners
and interstitial a
little bit more, sorry.
First of all, use
.canDisplayBannerAds
and
.interstitialPresentationPolicy
on your controllers
as much as possible.
We talked about ad engagement.
We talked about the user having
the opportunity to see the ads,
leaving them onscreen, the
user having the opportunity
to engage with the ads.
Setting these properties
is a big part of that.
In addition, remember to
use .originalContentView
when you actually use
.canDisplayBannerAds.
It's very important that once
you set .canDisplayBannerAds,
you realize that you have
given over control of view
to the iAd framework,
and .originalContentView
is yours to continue using.
Pick the right transitions
for interstitials.
Think about what your user
is doing at any given time
when they're transitioning
from view controller
to view controller.
And make sure
that .interstitialPresentation
PolicyAutomatic is set
on the appropriate view
controllers for an ad to show
up when they first pop up.
For instance, in the news
demo that we just showed you,
having that show up on the
main article list is probably
not appropriate.
That would just be distracting
and annoying to users.
Having it on the article view
controller, on the other hand,
just gives a gating
function to allowing the user
to actually use your content.
That's sort of the appropriate
use for the interstitial.
Be consistent throughout
your navigation stack
in your use of these.
This is particularly important
for navigation controllers,
in particular deep
navigation controllers.
What I mean by this
is, in particular
with .canDisplayBannerAds,
if you have a deep navigation
hierarchy, you want to attempt
to set .canDisplayBannerAds on
as many of the view controllers
that you're going to be pushing
into that hierarchy as possible
to ensure that the
ad remains onscreen
as the user navigates
throughout that hierarchy.
Otherwise, you have the
possibility of the ad popping
up onscreen for a second.
The user taps on something;
the ad goes back away.
They tapped to something else.
Maybe the ad comes back.
That's distracting to your user.
At the same time, it
doesn't allow the ad
to stay onscreen long
enough for the user
to actually engage with that ad.
OK. So now, we're done talking
with banners and interstitials.
Let's talk about medium rect,
which is then next major type
of ad that iAd provides to you.
What is a medium rect?
It is an International
Advertising Bureau medium
rectangle; it's a
standard ad type.
It's positioned inline
with your content.
It's a standardized size;
this is the same size
that you may have seen when
you're browsing the web.
You see this sort of square
or rectangular ads positioned
inline with the web content.
This is the same type
of ad that we've got.
Just like banners, they
automatically cycle over time.
So you put them onscreen,
new ads will be loaded
out of the iAd framework
- feels appropriate -
and will automatically
manage making a request
and putting ads in here for you.
And just like banners, there's
a full-screen ad experience once
the user taps on and
engages with this banner.
They were introduced in iOS 6
on iPads and happy to announce
that in iOS 8, we're adding
this to phone as well.
OK. So what's the medium
rectangle life cycle look like?
Because these banners are not
managed by the iAd framework,
you have to do a little bit
more work to put these onscreen.
OK? You need to create the
banner explicitly rather
than just setting a property
on your view controller.
You need to configure a
delegate, which is going
to allow us to tell you
when certain things happen,
and we're going to get into the
code for this in the next slide.
Implement the delegate protocol
so you can actually take notice
of these events and move
the thing on and offscreen
as the banner loads and unloads.
You're going to show the banner
when you receive the
-bannerViewDidLoadAd:
property - or delegate callback.
You're going to pause activity
in -bannerViewActionShould
Begin:willLeaveApplication:.
This is analogous to getting
the view will disappear message
from interstitials or banners.
And you want to resume activity
in -bannerViewActionDidFinish:,
analogous to view will appear.
You're going to hide the
banner in -bannerView:
didFailTo ReceiveAdWithError:.
This is important.
This indicates that your banner
no longer has an ad loaded
and it should no longer be
taking up space onscreen.
So what does this look like?
First of all, creating a banner.
You're going to import
the iAd header at the top.
You're going to implement
ADBannerViewDelegate
on whatever object you would
like to actually be managing
this particular banner.
Then you're going to
create the banner view.
You can do that with
initWithAdType:
ADAdTypeMediumRectangle,
and then you're going
to set the delegate
to the object that's
implementing the
delegate protocol.
So what does that delegate
protocol look like?
Well, first how does a medium
rect actually load and unload?
It's going to start
out unloaded.
When you first create it
there's nothing in there.
We haven't made an ad request.
There's nothing to
put onscreen yet.
So don't put it onscreen
when you first create it.
It's just going to
be a blank slide,
and we're going to
send you an error.
Once you get a
-bannerViewDidLoadAd:,
that's your cue that there is an
ad available inside your medium
rect, and you should
move it onscreen.
You're going to leave
the banner onscreen
as long as it has an ad.
Remember, too, that this is
something that's supposed
to be positioned inline
with your content.
When you move it onscreen,
when you leave it onscreen,
make sure that it's within
the rest of your content.
If you have an article and you
put the medium rect onscreen
with the article, text
should flow around it.
It should be inside a
scroll view and scroll
with the rest of your content.
That's what this type
of ad is intended for.
You're going to move the
banner back offscreen
in bannerView:didFail
ToReceiveAdWithError.
Again, once you move
it offscreen,
it's your responsibility
to reflow your content
to fill the hole that
was just left by the ad.
At that time, it's
going to move offscreen.
You reflow up your content.
This is what banner loading and
unloading is going to look like.
You're going - there's
two important delegate
callbacks here.
BannerViewDidLoadAd, in
which case you're just going
to put the banner onscreen,
rehandle all of your layout.
And bannerView
didFailToReceiveAdWithError,
you're going to remove
it from the super view.
You're going to do the converse.
You're going to, again,
layout, reflowing your content
around the hole that was
left by the banner view.
So some best practices
for medium rectangle.
Again, this is great
for reflowable content.
This is the sort of
thing that you're going
to put inside a scroll view,
within the rest of your content
that may scroll up and
down along the device,
may go on- and offscreen.
It's sort of static with
the rest of your content -
flows around it, fills a hole
with inside the space
on the screen.
It's got a full-screen
ad on tap, remember that.
Pay attention to the delegate
callbacks for willBeginAction,
didFinishAction so that you
can pause and resume activity.
Pause it in
bannerViewActionShouldBegin.
And resume activity in
bannerViewActionDidFinish.
So that's medium rectangle.
A little bit more complicated
than the banner because you have
to manage positioning yourself,
but still fairly
simple to implement.
OK, the fourth type of ad
that we're going to talk
about here is the pre-roll.
What is a pre-roll?
The video pre-roll is a short
video that plays between -
before your own media content.
It's full-screen ad on tap, just
like the other banner types.
It was added in iOS 7.
And in iOS 7 we added it
on MPMoviePlayerController.
And new in iOS 8
we're also adding it
on AVPlayerViewController,
new AV kit APIs
that are introduced
here at WWDC.
This is available on both
iPhone and iPad and has been
since the initial introduction.
I want to sort of circle back
to the very first bullet here,
the short video plays
before content.
This is really important.
This is not an
interstitial-style ad.
This is something to be
played before your content,
so you need to make sure
that you actually have a
video to play after it.
We don't want - it's not
supported for you to attempt
to use this just to play a
random ad at a random time.
Make sure that you have
content to follow it;
that's what the API
is designed for.
So setting up and playback,
also fairly straightforward.
You're going to start off
by linking the MediaPlayer
and iAd frameworks.
Import Media and iAd headers.
You're going to create a player.
You're going to tell it to
play the pre-roll video,
and then you'll play
your content video.
Very straightforward.
Basically almost all
those except the iAd vids
and the play pre-roll
you already have to do
if you've got your own content.
This is just a few
tiny additional lines.
So what does that look like?
First import MediaPlayer
and import iAd.
You're going to create your
MPMoviePlayerController.
You're going
to initWithContentURL
as you already would.
You're going to add
that MoviePlayer
into your view hierarchy
so that it's onscreen.
Call layouts, you
redo your layout
for it once it's there as well.
And then you're going to
call playPrerollAdWith
CompletionHandler.
You're going to call
this instead
of immediately calling Play.
This tells iAd, "Hey, try
to put a pre-roll video
in there if you've got one.
Play that first."
This takes a completion handler.
It's going to return
an error possibly
if something went wrong.
Inside the completion handler is
your cue to start your content.
You want to make sure you don't
automatically play your content.
You want to pause your content
until this actually
begins playing,
or until the pre-roll
finishes playing and you want
to begin your own content then.
For AVKit it's almost identical.
You're going to create an
AVPlayerViewController instead.
You're going to import
the AVKit headers.
And you're going to call, again,
playPrerollAdWith
CompletionHandler.
It has identical semantics
to the MPMediaPlayerController
ones.
Inside the completion handler,
you're going to call player play
to start your own video
content afterward.
This is new in iOS 8.
Just like interstitials, because
this is something that is going
to happen at some point and
you want to have iAd prepare it
for it you need to tell
the iAd framework, "Hey,
I'm going to want to play
pre-rolls in the future."
That allows us to have
the opportunity to go
out to the ad server, grab ads,
and be ready for your request
to play pre-rolls so that
we can actually play one
when the user does
something that requires it.
To do that, just like
interstitials you don't want
to miss these early impressions,
so you're going to want
to start ad requests early
by calling
MPMoviePlayerController
preparePrerollAds.
Again, probably an
application did finish launching
with options or some other early
in your app's life cycle period,
so we haven't had an
opportunity to go get ads
for you before you
call the APIs.
If you're using AVKit
it's almost identical,
AVPlayerController
preparePrerollAds instead.
Going with best practices for
video then: Don't play content
until the ad completes.
If you've called playPrerollAd,
and then half a second later you
call play before we've called
your completion handler,
we're going to interrupt it.
You know, notification handling
is a very common case for this.
This is going to interrupt
playing of the pre-roll ad.
It's going to immediately skip.
It's going to go
to your content.
And it's like the ad
never played except
that it's a poor user
experience for your user.
You'd like to try to
avoid this when possible.
So make sure that you wait
until our completion handler
is called to call play.
For notifications,
this frequently means
just recording the fact
that your content is ready.
If you're already calling
play in these notifications,
instead of just calling
play, record that fact,
and inside the completion
handler check
for that fact, and
then call play.
Similarly, defer
UI customization.
Many of you may be doing
UI customization on top
of the MediaPlayer controller
to present custom controls
or present custom UI around it.
Wait to do that until
after we've called your
completion handler.
The pre-roll already has
custom UI, and you don't want
to interfere with that custom
UI with your own customization.
That's, again, going to
provide a very poor experience
for your users.
OK, so now that we've
got that, let's go back
to our demo machine here.
I've got a quick demo
setting that up as well.
Let's close - yep - that.
I can pull up quick little
demo of this as well.
Can run this.
This is a very simple
little app,
just provides a few quick
little video clips here.
I can click on one of these
and we've got a quick video.
Now what I'd like to do is, now
that I've got this video content
that my user would
like to engage with,
I'd like to monetize this by
playing a pre-roll ad prior
to the user actually being
able to view my clips.
So let's go ahead and quit
this and see what we have
to do to get that done.
We can start off here - the very
first thing we need to do is,
as for interstitials, we want
to make sure that we tell iAd,
"Hey, I'm going to be
playing pre-roll ads,
go fetch them early."
We'll start off in
our app delegate here,
and we will import iAd, and
we'll import the MediaPlayer
so we have the appropriate
classes for our APIs.
And we'll go ahead and
call preparePrerollAds
on MPMoviePlayerController.
Once we've done that, we
need to actually go ahead
and call preparePrerollAds,
so we'll go to our
View Controller here,
which is doing the actual
display, and we're going
to scroll down to -
at the bottom here,
collectionView
didSelectItemAtIndexPath.
This is what happens when
the user actually taps on it.
At the moment, all
we're doing is creating
MPMoviePlayerViewController,
setting the content URL,
and then calling
presentMoviePlayer
to have it start
playing automatically.
We want to sort of
interrupt that briefly,
and instead we're
going to go ahead
and call playPrerollAdWith
CompletionHandler.
And again, inside the
completion handler to that,
that's where we're going to call
mpvController.moviePlayer play.
Go back up to the top here, and
ensure that we are importing iAd
as well, so we get the
iAd APIs available.
Go ahead and save that.
We can run again.
No. This is what I
knew I was going to do.
Once again, we got
to go in here,
make sure that the iAd
framework is linked.
Now we can run it.
OK, and we got our ad up
- our app up here again,
same quick little videos.
We can go ahead and click
on one of these now.
And before the video content
actually plays you see
that we've got an iAd workbench
ad that comes up instead.
The user can view
this ad content.
Once they're done with it
they can decide to go ahead
and skip ahead of it, and
we go immediately back
to the video content
for the app itself.
And that's pretty much
all that's involved
in implementing pre-rolls once
you've already got MediaPlayer
content for that pre-roll
to play in front of.
OK, so those are the four
different types of ads
that we have for integration
with iAd inside your app.
Once you've started using them,
let's talk a little
bit about testing.
First of all, there are a
couple of things we add -
we've added to the developer
settings on the phone
to help you test the integration
of iAd within your app.
First, you can adjust
the fill rate.
This is inside the apps that you
have when you're testing them
on the device - you can adjust
how frequently you're going
to get ads.
This allows you to
test error conditions.
It allows you to test always
working conditions and make sure
that your app handles those
conditions appropriately.
In addition you can adjust
the refresh rate for things
like banners and medium rects.
This is going to
adjust the frequency
with which new ads come in.
In addition, in combination with
the fill rate this allows you
to rapidly test error
and nonerror conditions moving
things on- and offscreen.
Most importantly there's
a switch called Highlight
Clipped Banners.
If you're using the
.canDisplayBannerAds,
this isn't going to
affect banners very much,
but this is very
important for medium rect.
It's very easy to accidently
occlude part of the medium rect
with some other UI element.
If you do that, that's a
part of the medium rect
that may not be seen
by your user.
It's a part of the
medium rect that you -
that the user may not be able
to tap on and interact with.
This will detect that.
You turn on the Highlight
Clipped Banners button.
We're going to provide
a green or a red overlay
over your medium rect, or
banners, or instructions
for that matter, that will show
when the user can actually tap
on all parts of this banner,
when it is officially
onscreen and visible.
You want to make
sure that any banners
that you show inside your
app are always green.
Remember this only affects your
apps, your developer-mode apps
that you have run from Xcode
and deployed onto your device.
So no, you can't just
fill right to zero
for all the other iAd-using
apps on your device.
This only affects
developer-mode apps.
OK, so that's monetization.
That was sort of the first
major portion of the talk.
Let's talk next a little
bit about promotion.
This is the other half
of the iAd ecosystem.
This is how you can use iAd to
drive downloads of your own app.
So there's three major parts
that we're going
to talk about here.
First I'm going to do a really
quick intro to iAd Workbench.
There's another session
on that tomorrow
if you get more in detail.
So this is just a
quick overview.
And then there are two new APIs
that we're introducing in iOS 8,
one for app attribution and one
for app audience retargeting.
And we'll talk a little
bit about those new APIs.
Let's start off with
iAd Workbench.
What is iAd Workbench?
iAd Workbench is
iAd's self-servicing
advertising platform.
It's basically a web
app on the apple.com,
iadworkbench.apple.com.
This is how you can manage
being an advertiser on iAd.
OK? You can create mobile ads.
You can upload your own banners.
You can use built-in templates.
You can also use iProducer to
create your own iAd assets.
Once you've done that, you can
use this to reach the users
who are most likely to
actually download your app.
iAd is an iOS advertising
platform.
You're going to reach a whole
bunch of users who are on iOS
who are already using apps on
iOS and who are, therefore,
highly likely to engage with the
ad that is advertising your app
and download your app.
You can also manage your
campaign performance here.
This is where you're going
to see how many people
have seen your ad,
how the campaign is doing,
tap-through rates, etcetera,
for your particular
advertising campaign.
So that's Workbench.
Again, there's going
to be another session tomorrow
going into more detail.
Next important part to
talk about is some new APIs
that we've got for
app attribution.
OK, what is app attribution?
App attribution allows you to
track app downloads of your app
that originated from iAd.
OK? This is going to let you
measure the effectiveness
of your campaigns that you've
created in iAd Workbench
that you're running to
actually promote your app.
OK, the APIs were available
in iOS 7 - or iOS 7.1, rather.
And we've enhanced them a
little bit in iOS 8 as well.
So there's a new one in iOS 8.
So what does the API
actually look like?
It's very simple.
Again, you're going
to include iAd/iAd.h,
as everything starts
with for iAd.
And then you're going to
call ADClient sharedClient.
And on that you're going to
call lookupAdConversionDetails.
OK? Inside that you can use
the two dates that are provided
with completion handler
to determine whether
or not this particular
installation
of the app was due to iAd.
OK? These dates are going
to give you two things.
The first is the
app purchase date -
the date at which the user
actually made the purchase
of this app.
And then the date
of the impression,
the date that the user saw and
interacted with the ad prior
to them purchasing the app.
OK? If both of these dates are
there and true, that's going
to indicate to you that as far
as iAd is concerned
this was a installation
of your app directly
attributable
to the user interacting with
and seeing an iAd
promoting your app.
It's very important to remember
that these dates are going
to be nil if they are
not attributed to iAd.
They'll also be nil if the user
has Limit Ad Tracking enabled.
So regardless of whether
or not this is an
iAd-driven installation,
the user has Limit
Ad Tracking enabled;
they don't want their ad
browsing data to be tracked
or shown to various apps.
These are going to be nil.
We're not going to give you
this information in those cases.
So you should be aware of that
if you're trying to use this
for any sort of analytics.
In addition, you
want to avoid lookups
of this data on every launch.
It's probably very
tempting to add this
to appDidFinishLaunching,
lookup your conversion details,
set some state flag,
and do something
on every single launch
on the app.
Try to avoid doing that.
There is some cost to
actually doing this lookup.
You want to defer doing this
lookup until you actually need
to and then cache
the data afterward.
OK, so that's app attribution.
The next thing we can talk
about is the app
audience retargeting APIs.
These are new APIs in iOS 8.
So what is app audience
retargeting to begin with?
Audience retargeting allows you
to group the users of your app,
that particular audience, into
various categories depending
on their activity within your
app or things that you know
about them from their
use of your app.
This might be frequent
in-app purchases.
It might be a very high
usage rate relative
to other users within your app.
It might be dormant users, users
who used your app a while ago
but you haven't seen in a while.
You can then use this
information to target new ads
in iAd Workbench directly at
specific subgroups of your users
to reach specific audiences
within the users of your app.
Each group defines
what we call a segment.
That's terminology
that's going to come
up in the next couple of slides.
That's important to know.
A specific group of
your users is a -
with a specific name
is a segment.
So why would you
want to use this?
Let's say you're a
game app developer.
You want to promote the
new iAd version of your app
to all your iPhone users.
You want to go back and reach
those specific users and say,
"Hey, I've got a great
new iPad version of it.
Come try it again.
Come back to this app,
maybe redownload it."
If there's new features
that affect specific subsets
of your app, you can use this
to reach those specific users.
That's going to ensure that
the ads you create are going
to reach precisely the
audience you're attempting
to target with those ads.
Similarly you can
reengage dormant users.
If you've got users
that you haven't seen
in a while you can craft a
message specifically designed
to try to pull those
people back into your app
to reengage those users who
may not have used your app
in some time.
If you're a retail app instead,
there's similar reasons
to use this.
It can remind users who may
have abandoned a shopping cart
in your app, segment those into
something, send them a message,
"Hey, you abandoned
your shopping cart.
Maybe you should come back
and reengage with this app.
Maybe you still want to
purchase those things."
If you've got loyal
customers, maybe you want
to send them a special offer.
Maybe you want to send them a
gift for being a loyal customer.
You can do that with
an ad as well.
You can retarget specific ads to
specific segments of your users.
If they've - you
can group customers
into specific categories based
on their previous purchases.
You can promote sales based
All these are done by segmenting
those users into specific groups
and recording that so
that you can reengage
with those users
with specific ads.
So how does this actually work?
First thing you're going
to do is you're going to go
on iAd Workbench, and you're
going to create segments.
And you're going to tell
iAd Workbench, "Hey,
I'm going to group these people
into 10 different segments.
Please give me some segment
identifiers to use for that."
It's important to notice that
you do not create segment -
specific segment identifiers;
iAd Workbench does instead,
and this is partially
for privacy reasons.
We manage the specific
segment identifiers.
Once you've done that,
you're going to go ahead
and update your app and take
advantage of the new APIs,
so you can actually
associate specific segments
with specific users.
And that goes up to the server
so we can actually
record that information.
Once that's done, you go
back to iAd Workbench,
and you create your
new Workbench campaign
to retarget those customers
with some specific ad message.
OK, so how do you
actually do this?
Actually very simple
on the client side.
You're going to include iAd.
You're going to create
an array of segments,
and these are segments -
the segment identifiers are
what you've already gotten
from Workbench.
If you attempt to send random
segment identifiers up to iAd,
we're just going to ignore them,
so you want to make sure
you're using the ones
that you've already created
and set up inside Workbench.
So maybe you decided you know
Segment A is loyal users,
Segment B is frequent
purchases, and you want
to associate the current
user with those two segments.
And you go ahead and
create a segment array
with those segments in it.
And you're going to call
ADClient sharedClient,
addClientToSegments,
replaceExisting.
This is by default with
replaceExisting:NO going
to add these segments
to the current user.
If instead you'd like to
say, "Hey, these are all
of the segments I'd like
to associate the user,"
which might also allow
you to remove old segments
from the user, you can just
update that replaceExisting
to yes to just completely
replace the old set
with the new set.
OK, so that's basically iAd
for promotion, the new APIs
that we've added in iOS 8.
So what did we learn?
First of all, there's some
best practices for using iAd.
There are four different types
of banners that we've talked -
four different types of ads
that we've talked about.
There's a banner.
There's an interstitial.
There's a medium rect.
And there's a pre-roll, and
they all have their place.
You want to take advantage
of the different ad formats
that we've given to you,
think about where they belong
in your app, and make sure
you use the appropriate ad
for the appropriate context.
As part of that, consider the
user when you're placing ads.
Yes, ads are very valuable
for generating revenue
from your app, and iAd can
help a lot with doing that.
But great revenue and great apps
start with great users as well.
If you're going to
alienate all of your users
by poor ad placement,
by poor ad choice,
you're not actually going
to have a net win here.
You want to really make sure
you have a user-centric focus
to where you're picking
to put ads
and which type you're
choosing to put there.
In addition, there's
a cycle here
between monetization
and promotion.
OK? Optimize your ad's
performance to begin -
your app's ad performance
to begin with, that's going
to generate revenue from it.
But don't forget to take
advantage of iAd Workbench
and repromote your app.
It's important to continue
to get new users for your app
if you want to continue to
get revenue from your app.
The two feed into each other.
You want to generate revenue;
you want to spend some
of your revenue to readvertise
your app and acquire new users.
OK? So those are some sort
of best practices for iAd.
For more information
beyond this,
we've got Mark Malone is our
iAd Technologies Evangelist.
You can reach him at
the email address above.
There's an iAd Programming
Guide online along
with the iOS STK
developer information.
There's some Apple developer
forums that we monitor.
If you've got questions,
you and other developers,
and us will be monitoring
those to answer questions,
hopefully help you out.
There are a couple related
sessions here at WWDC.
Unfortunately you already
missed "The New iTunes Connect,"
which talked a little
bit about iAd.
That was yesterday.
You can watch the video.
Tomorrow morning at 9:00 in
Nob Hill there's "What's New
in iAd Workbench,"
which is going to go
into a little bit more detail
about the app attribution
and the audience segment
retargeting that I talked
about at the end of
this presentation.
And that's it.
Thank you very much.
[ Applause ]