[ Silence ]
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you.
I'm Mike Hess.
I'm a software engineer on the
iOS Apps and Frameworks team,
and I'm here with Johannes
Fortmann to talk to you
about building great cloud
documents-based applications.
So here we go.
We've made some important
changes to iCloud.
First, the iCloud daemon has
been completely rewritten
on top of CloudKit.
We're calling it iCloud Drive.
If you're interested in
learning more about CloudKit,
I encourage you to attend
their sessions and labs.
Second, we've added
Windows support to iCloud.
Now your users with
Windows devices can access
and modify their documents
on their Windows devices.
Third, we've added an
iCloud folder into Finder.
Now your users can add
whatever documents they want
into their iCloud
folder in Finder
and organize them
however they see fit.
Fourth, we've added access
to this iCloud folder
from within your iOS apps.
We'll get into this
a little more later.
So, what are we going
to cover here today?
We're going to start off
by talking about some
of the best practices
of accessing your
documents in the cloud.
Then we're going to move on to
talking about how to discover
and list your documents
in the cloud.
Next, we're going to talk about
displaying thumbnails in your UI
when you're listing your
documents in the cloud.
Then, we're going to talk about
accessing documents from outside
of your apps container such
as the shared iCloud folder.
And finally, we're going to talk
about providing document storage
to other applications
from within your app.
So, what is a document anyways?
We're going to define
a document here
as a single standalone entity,
and it's understood by the user
as a single standalone entity.
A user might want to modify it,
or give it a name that's
meaningful to them,
or send it via email to one of
their friends or colleagues.
There are some documents
which we all sort
of understand are
documents: a keynote document
or a numbers document or a pages
document are clearly documents.
But we're also going to consider
something like a chess game
to be a document, for
this presentation.
A user might want to
save the current state
of their chess game and email
it to one of their friends
so they can pick up
where they left off
against some hard AI level.
So, we're going to consider a
chess game to be a document.
Now, let's talk about dealing
with your documents
in the cloud.
So, it's important, when you're
dealing with your documents
in the cloud, to use
file coordination.
There are several
reasons for this,
but one of the main ones
is to avoid data loss.
You may have the simplest
single-threaded application
in the world, and you may think
that you're the only one reading
from or writing to
your documents,
but once you add the
iCloud daemon into the mix,
that's no longer the case,
so use file coordination.
Let's take a quick
example of this.
Say your app is doing
proper file coordination.
You'll write your
changes to disk,
the iCloud Drive daemon
will pick up those changes
and push them up to
the cloud and down
to all the other users' devices.
Everything's working
properly here.
That's what you want
to have happen.
Now let's say you're not using
proper file coordination.
You may be writing
your changes to disk,
but iCloud Drive may also be
writing changes at the same time
for that same document.
This could result in
a corrupt document
which the iCloud Drive daemon
will again push up to the cloud
and down to the other
users' devices which results
in data loss everywhere,
so use file coordination;
it's very important.
There's good news though.
UIDocument makes things simple.
UIDocument and NSDocument,
on OS X,
does all the heavy
lifting for you.
It takes care of
file coordination.
It also uses background queues
to prevent the file coordination
from blocking your apps UI,
and UIDocument provides you
with several high-level APIs
for whatever use
case you might have.
Let's take a quick example
like reading a document
from disk with UIDocument.
So, at the highest-level
UIDocument does all
of the file coordination
for you,
and in addition reads
your document from disk.
If your document is a file
you'll get an NSData object,
which is the contents
of your file on disk,
and if the document
is a package,
you'll get an NSFileWrapper
object,
which represents
your package on disk.
You just have to override the
LoadFromContentsofType method
and then display the contents
of the document to your users.
At a slightly lower level
UIDocument still does all
of the file coordination
for you,
but this time you would an
NSURL back which is the location
of your document on disk.
You then just have
to read the document
and display it to your users.
At the lowest level we have an
option that's really provided
only for hooking.
If you override the
openWithCompletionHandler
method, you should really
invoke super, and implement one
of the other two methods.
You can override
this method though
if you want some custom
application behavior
when UIDocument would be
doing the file coordination
to read the document from disk.
New in IOS 8, we have
some asynchronous file
coordination APIs.
So, the existing file
coordination APIs were
completely synchronous.
That means you would have to
do your own background queuing
to prevent file coordination
from blocking your app.
That can be a little
bit tricky to do.
So, we have some new
file coordinator APIs
for asynchronous
file coordination,
which is the coordinateAccess
WithIntents method.
We also have a new
corresponding class
which is the NSFileAccessIntent
class
which essentially just
contains a URL and some options
for your intent of coordination.
You pass these in an array
to the
coordinateAccessWithIntents
method to do your file
coordination operations.
Let's take a quick look at
that in some simple code.
So, this code might be if
I want to copy a document
from one location to another.
As you can see I
allocate a source intent
to read the document where
it currently exists on disk.
I then, allocate a destination
intent for the location
that I want to copy
the document to.
I pass these to the
file coordinator method
of coordinateAccess
WithIntents, and at some point
in the future my accessor
block will be called
on the queue I provide.
I then just have to do my
operation in my accessor block.
Now, it's important when
you do your operation
in your accessor block to use
the URLs that are attached
to the NSFileAccessIntents
because they may have
changed while you were waiting
for your coordination.
Now let's move on to discovering
and listing your
documents in the cloud.
So, the way to discover and list
your documents in the cloud is
through the existing
NSMetadataQuery APIs.
Now, in previous versions of iOS
NSMetadataQuery has been slow
to pick up your local
changes like creates, deletes
and renames; let's take
a quick look at this.
So, let's say you have your app,
you have a couple of documents
in your apps container,
you also have a couple
of NSMetadata items from your
NSMetadataQuery which correspond
to those documents on disk.
Now let's say your app
creates a new document on disk.
There might be a long delay
before NSMetadataQuery updates
and gives you a new
NSMetadata item corresponding
to that newly created
local document.
New in iOS 8 NSMetadataQuery
is easier
to use directly with stitching.
Let's take a look at that.
Now let's say your app creates
this new document on disk,
and is using proper
file coordination.
This only works if you create
the document using proper
file coordination.
We actually have a hook in
your file coordination access
which will update the
NSMetadataQuery quickly
and automatically to
create a new NSMetadata item
to update your app.
That means that you no
longer need two data sources
to show your app's UI,
one from local changes
and one for cloud changes.
You just need NSMetadataQuery.
[applause] Thank you.
Also, NSMetadataQuery can
list non-local documents.
You may want to display
some file system attributes
about those documents
though, to display in your UI
when you're listing
your documents.
We have a new NSURL API for you,
which will let you get
file system attributes
about those documents, which may
or may not have their
content available locally.
The way to do this is
with the NSURL method,
getPromisedItem
ResourceValue:forKey.
If you want more than one file
system attribute we also have a
bulk method, which is
the promisedItemResource
ValuesForKeys.
You don't need to be
under file coordination
when using these methods
for listing your documents.
Also, if you are under
file coordination,
we have some new file
coordinator flags
for dealing with metadata.
The key difference with these
methods is that the content
with these flags that you pass
through your file coordinator is
that the content of the
documents does not need
to be available locally when
you are doing file coordination
using these flags.
Now let's move onto
document thumbnails.
So, we think the
best user experience
when you're listing your
documents in your app is
to show document previews.
This gives your user
more context
so that they can
quickly identify
which document is meaningful
to them at that point in time.
As you can see in this pages
app, we have document previews,
which lets your user
quickly identify
which document is which.
Now it was possible to show
document previews previously,
but it required a
custom implementation.
New in iOS 8 we have some new
file system attribute keys
for you to display
thumbnails in your app.
The main way to do this is
with the NSURLThumbnail
DictionaryKey.
If you call this on
your document using the
getPromisedItem ResourceValue
:forKey method you'll get a
dictionary which
contains your thumbnails,
which you can display
on your UI.
The only key in this dictionary
right now is the NSThumbnail
2024x1024SizeKey, which
corresponds to the UIImage
or NSImage which you can
then just display in your UI.
Now onto saving document
thumbnails.
So, the easiest way
to save thumbnails is
through UIDocument.
If you override the
fileAttributesTo WriteToURL
:forSaveOperation method and
have it generate a UIImage
which is your thumbnail
and return it,
UIDocument will automatically
write the thumbnail to disk
for you, and then the iCloud
daemon will go ahead and pick
up those changes and push
them up to the cloud.
Alternatively, if you're not
using UIDocument you can save
your thumbnails manually using
the existing NSURLsetResource
Value:forKey method,
but you should really be
under file coordination
when you invoke this method.
On OS X thumbnails are actually
generated for you automatically.
However, if you have a custom
document format you'll need
to let Quick Look know
how to display thumbnails
for your documents, so you'll
need a Quick Look plug-in
to generate your thumbnails.
Now let's move onto to
discovery documents outside
of your apps container.
Now, in previous version of
the OS, it's been difficult
for your users to
access documents outside
of your apps container
from within your app.
Let's take a look at how they
might do this previously.
So, let's say you have your
app, you have direct access
to all the documents in
your app's container;
there's no problem there.
But let's say your user wants
to open say document three
from within your app.
How might they go
about doing this?
Well, one way they might
do this is they would have
to launch the other app,
then using the UIDocument
interaction controller make a
copy of the document from
the other apps container
into your app's local container.
Only then could they read the
document from within your app.
We think a better
user experience is
if your app can just
access those documents
in the other apps
container directly.
So, if you have your app again,
if you can just open
those documents directly,
the user is happy.
So, we think that's a
better user experience.
New in iOS 8 there's
a way to do this
with a UIDocumentPicker
ViewController.
This allows your users to
discover documents outside
of your app's sandbox and
lets your users grant your app
permission to access
and modify the documents
that they have chosen.
Now, to have your
apps container show
up in the document
picker you have to opt-in
by marking your container
with a NSUbiquitousContainer
IsDocumjentScopePublic to be
"yes" in your info plist.
I have a great new UI -- we
have a great new UI here,
which you can display in
your app for your users
to choose documents,
and I'd like to show you
that now with a quick demo.
Okay. Let's go ahead
and launch my app.
Yeah, the app I've written.
It's a simple text-editing app.
So, as you can see, I'm
using NSMetadataQuery
to list only one document
in my container right now,
but I'm using NSMetadataQuery
without file coordination
to list my documents and
display a quick simple preview
of the documents.
Now let's go ahead and launch
up the document picker.
So, this is our new
document picker UI.
As you can see there are
several containers listed here
but I also have a document which
lives in the shared icon folder
which is listed alongside
my containers.
Now I can switch to list
view here; there's a bunch
of stuff I can do, sort by
name, tag, state, etc. Now,
let's go ahead and like drill
down into this text edit
container, and select a document
from the text edit container.
So, now I have opened the
document which actually lives
in the text edit container.
I have not made a
copy of this document.
This document still exists in
the text edit container but now
that I, as the user,
have granted my access
to it I can edit and access
it in the text edit container.
Let's go ahead and
X out of this.
As you can see, now that
I've granted my app access
to this document it has now
updated in the NSMetadataQuery
and I can list it alongside
the other documents in my app.
I've also annotated it, if you
can see with a text edit name,
just to tell my user
that it lives
in the text edit container.
Let's take a quick
look at this in code.
So this is basically all
the code I had to write
to display the document picker.
All I have to do is allocate the
document menu view controller
and pass it on array
of the document types
that I'm interested in.
I have a simple text-editing
app,
so I only pass the plain
text UTI as the documents
that my app can access.
I then just present
the view controller
and then implement these
two simple delicate methods,
and finally when the document --
when the user picks a document
of a given URL I just load it
and display it to my users.
It's super simple.
Now if you noticed my
app did not actually show
up in the document picker.
That's because I
haven't set my container
to be a public container, yet.
Let's take just a quick
look at how to do that.
So, if I open up my info plist
here, drill down into this.
As you can see my document
scope is set to be not public.
All I have to do is
set this to "yes"
and then bump the
bundled version
so that the document picker
knows that I have made a change
to my info plist, and then
my app will be displayed
in the document picker so
that other apps can get access
to my documents.
All right, so quick summary.
We've just shown
you how easy it is
to display the Document
Picker inside your app,
and how easy it is for users
to grant your app access
to documents in other
apps' containers
such as the shared
iCloud folder.
We've also shown you how easy it
is to make your container show
up in the UIDocumentPicker just
by setting a flag to be yes
and then bumping
your bundled version.
With that I would like to
Johannes Fortmann to the stage,
who is going to talk
to you about some
of the key principals
behind the Document Picker.
Please welcome Johannes
to the stage [applause].
>> Thank you, Mike.
Hi, I'm Johannes from the UIKit
team, and I would like to talk
to you about some of
the main differences
between external
documents and documents
that may live in your container.
As you know, your application
right now has access
to its own container only.
So, you're able to read
and write the documents
inside your own container.
And as you have seen
in Mike's demonstration
for other documents what we do
is once the user has chosen this
document we save a
so-called document reference
into your container.
This document reference
will then go and point
to your external document.
To ease this new concept
into your application we
provide a few new features
and attributes on
the NSMetadataQuery.
You are probably using
the NSMetaDataQuery
with the UbiquitousDocuments
Scope right now
to list the documents that are
inside your container, locally.
And even if the user has
granted your application access
to a document outside
of your container --
even if the user has gotten
your application access
to document outside
of your container,
we will still continue to
merely list the documents
that are local to
your container as long
as you don't pass a new scope
which is the UbiquitousExternal
DocumentScope.
The UbiquitousExternal
DocumentScope ensures
that you've got an NSMetadata
item that corresponds
to the file references
that the user has extended
to your application container.
Now, these new NSMetadata
items are effectively just
like the old ones.
They also have an
NSMetadata item URL key
and this NSMetadata item URL
key will point to this --
NSMetadata item URL key
will point to the URL
that your document is
actually located at.
That means that if your app is
using the NSMetadata item URL
key right now to
access the file directly
that will still work even
with the document reference.
You can pass the return value
of getting this key directly to,
for example a UIDocument,
and use that URL
to directly access
the external document.
Now, of course sometimes that
is not actually what you want
to do.
Sometimes, what you're
interested
in is not the actual document
backing this reference,
but rather the reference itself.
For example, you may want
to display the reference
inside a folder
in your application's
container, in your UI,
or you might even
want to allow the user
to move these references
around inside their folder.
For that we provide a new key,
and this one is actually new
on iOS 8, the UbiquitousItemURL
InLocalContainerKey.
This key points to the
actual reference inside your
applicant's container, so the
user can use the file that is
at this location
to move it around.
Now, there are a few other keys.
It may be useful for you
to know whether a file
that has been returned
by the NSMetadataQuery
is actually external
to your application or not --
sorry, to your application's
container.
And for that we provide
the IsExternalDocumentKey,
which will return "no" for
local documents and "yes"
for external documents.
And as you've seen in Mike's
demo he showed a little badge
or text a label to inform
the user that the document
that he's shown that popped
in there was actually not
from the local container
but rather from Text Edit,
and to enable you to do that we
have the container display name
key, the container display
name key is a localized key
that is fit for display
DOS and for example would
if you extended a document
from Text Edit would
show Text Edit's name.
All right, so, we've got
these document references,
but why do you even need these?
So, the main reason
is for security.
We do not generally
allow any app
to access any other
app's container.
Only the Document
Picker can do that.
The Document Picker is running
out-of-process, so it's not --
it is able and has the
sufficient entitlements
to be able to list all of
the document containers.
And the only way to
get a document inside
of your application is to
use the Document Picker.
To that -- for that purpose,
we return a so-called
security scoped URL
and if you've used the
sandboxing mechanism
on OS X you may already
know this concept
of a security scoped URL.
You get a NSURL, which has a
tiny bit of information attached
to it, that informs the kernel,
and of course the owning app,
that in fact the owning app is
allowed to access this document,
and is allowed to for
example modify it as well.
Now importantly, if you
naively were to save this URL,
for example you would
serialize it into a string
and then de-serialize
it out of the string,
you would lose this
security scope.
And that is not something
you want to happen
because of course the
security scope is what you use
to access this URL.
Of course, you need a way to
get back to the scoped URL,
and the document references
feature is providing one
of the ways to get
back to these URLs.
If you get a NSURL from the
document reference this NSURL
already has the security scope
attached, so you can use it
with your document or
with the start accessing
and stop accessing security
scoped resource methods
on NSURL - but I strongly
suggest that you use UIDocument
because that does all of
this for you; for example,
load the contents off of
the file backed by this URL.
Now, sometimes enumerating your
documents is not actually what
you want to get back
to the document.
For example, one thing you might
be using is state restoration,
and in state restoration
of course what you want
to do is pop the user back into
the UI that they saw before.
So, you instead of
enumerating files
that the user had access
previously, what you want
to do is access a
very specific file.
We offer a mechanism to do that
for you, which is a bookmark.
The bookmark is also possibly
known to you if you've used it
with the sandbox on
OS X, and the bookmark
and codes the security
scope alongside the URL
so you can use the
bookmark to get back
to the security scoped URL.
We offer API, which
already exists.
The bookmarkDataWithOptions
API is used for, by you,
on a NSURL instance to create a
bookmark that you can then save.
It's basically opaque NSData
blob that you can then save
into a state restoration
archive, for example.
And of course its counter-part
is a class method on NSURL.
The URL by resolving bookmark
data which we can then use
to resolve this bookmark
into a NSURL
that has the scope attached.
All right.
Now, Mike showed you the
UIDocument picker view
controller in the
so-called open mode.
In open mode what we will do
is indeed create a bookmark
and a corresponding
security scope URL,
hand you back the
security scope URL
and of course place
the bookmark,
the reference document
inside your app's container.
Now, sometimes that is not
what you want to do, actually.
For example, you may
have an application
that does not instead of
opening specific documents,
may also aggregate
documents, Keynote,
for example would be one
of these applications,
in which you, for example,
might want to open an image
from an application to insert
it into your presentation.
You don't want to maintain
a persistent reference
to that image, but instead
want to copy this image
into your presentation
as one piece.
And we also support
a mode for that,
it's the so-called import mode.
In import mode will
not create a bookmark,
but instead we'll copy the
file to a temporary location.
You will of course
still be granted access
to this temporary location,
but the file is not persistently
referenced by your application.
After your application
terminates
for any reason we will clean
out the temporary location
and you will no longer
have access,
so you have to make a copy soon
after you get your
delegate call back
to actually hang
onto the document.
All right.
This is reading documents
and it is
of course a very important part,
but equally as important is
of course writing document
and creating new documents.
Now, as I've mentioned you
will not have general access
to containers outside of
your app's own container.
But of course you can write
into that container, so --
or possibly into a
temporary location.
So, to create a new
UIDocument that is --
sorry, a new document on disk
that is exactly what
you want to do.
You can then use a special
document picker mode to move
that document outside
of your app's container,
but again the user chooses
where to move the document.
Let's have a quick
look at how that works.
You would, of course, you
already have a document,
Doc 3 in this case, and you
use the initWithURL method
on your document picker with the
URL of your existing document
to allow the user to
choose a new location.
The user now chooses a new
location, and we move the file
into the new location.
We will return a
document reference to you,
so you still maintain
access to the document.
And this URL is effectively
exactly like one
that has been returned to
you by the open mechanism,
so you can enumerate this
new document preference
in your NSMetadataQuery.
Now of course sometimes that
is exactly not what you want.
You don't want the reference.
So, we also have an expert
mode, which allows you
to forego the entire
reference thing.
In that case we will make
a copy of your document
into another app's container
and that is basically it.
Okay. Let me give a
quick summary of how
to use document management here.
We've seen that you can use the
document reference mechanism
to enumerate documents that
have been previously used by,
or granted access by the user.
We've also seen that you can use
bookmarks for state restoration
and we've also shown you quickly
how to use the import open
and export and move modes.
And all of these of course play
together to enable your user
to access all of their iCloud
documents, not merely those
that are inside your folder.
But you noticed I said all of
your iCloud documents here, and,
of course, your users may
have different locations
for storing their documents.
For example, you may be
part of an enterprise
that has their own storage
management system, and,
of course, it would be grand
if you could grant
your users access
to those documents as well.
And for that we are
introducing a new feature,
the so-called Document
Provider Extensions.
Now, what is a Document
Provider Extension?
A Document Provider Extension
is an alternate way for you,
or a third party, to
provide document storage.
From the host application's
perspective this works exactly
the same way as the pre-existing
iCloud storage location.
The user is able to select
one of these storage locations
from the Document Picker,
and they can use these storage
locations in the exact same mode
so they can open documents
and move out documents
to the storage locations.
We implement these using two
different, separate extensions,
the first of which is the
so-called Document Picker
Extension, which provides
a UI view control subclass
that is effectively free
form; that the user can use
to choose a document from your
storage location, or from,
of course, from someone
at the storage locations.
This UR Document Picker
subclass is displayed as part
of the document picker
view controller,
so it's effectively
contained inside one
of these view controllers just
like the iCloud Picker is.
There is also a separate
second extension,
which is the so-called
File Provider Extension.
The File Provider Extension
is a non-UI extension,
which deals with actually
providing the files.
The usual use cases where you
want to provide files would be,
for example, ensuring that
a file on disk is current,
uploading a file that has
been changed by the user,
or enabling us to identify a
file, so the user can save,
or the user's app can save a
bookmark for state restoration.
The file provider extension --
access to the file provider
extension is modulated
through file coordination, which
means that all accesses that go
through file coordination will
automatically do the right thing
with regards to providing
access to the file.
This is another important case
where you absolutely must
use file coordination
or everything else --
everything will just not work.
All right.
Let's have a quick look
at how the data flow works
with a File Provider
Extension, specifically
when reading a file from disk.
Let's say you have a host
app and this host app is used
by the user who is trying
to actually open a
document, in this case.
So, the host app,
through some UI action,
is calling the
initWithDocumentTypes inMode
method on the
UIDocumentPickerViewController,
and now the Document Picker --
well, the user inside the
Document Picker selects a
third-party Document
Picker extension: yours.
We instantiate your
UIDocument Picker Extension
and send it prepare for
presentation in mode call.
Now, this method is
called with the mode
that the user has
actually selected,
and at this point you want
to probably display a View
Controller that corresponds
to the mode that
the user has chosen.
For example, for the
open mode you would want
to display a view controller
that allows the user
to pick a specific document,
and of course for the move
out mode you will want to
display a view controller
that allows them to select a
location instead of a document.
All right.
The user now goes ahead and uses
your UI to select a document
at which point, after the user
has confirmed their intentions,
you have to determine
which location
in the file system you want
to store this document in.
You can then call the
dismiss grant access --
the granting access to
URL method on self, well,
that is your Document Picker
View Controller Subclass,
and thereby inform us
about your intention
to actually the user
to access this URL.
The document picker will
then call the document picker
didPickDocument AtURL
method on its delegate
to inform the user app that
the user has just picked
this document.
Now what the user is
probably wanting to do is
to read the document
at this location.
It will use the
NSFileCoordinator methods,
for example, coordinateReading
ItemAtURL
and its file coordinator
that it should ensure
that the document
is actually present.
NSFileCoordinator will call out
to your file provider extension,
that's your tiny
non-UI extension,
with the startProvidingItemAtURL
method.
This method takes a
completion call back
which you can call once
you're sure that the item
at this specific location
is actually current.
So, once you call
that completion call
back on -- sorry.
Once you call that completion
call back the file coordinator
will know that it is now
able to unlock the file
and it itself can call
its accessorBlock.
And now inside your
accessorBlock the user
application can use this UR
document like it sees fit,
for example, using data
with contents of URL
to be able to read the file.
Let's take a quick
look at how security
and persistent file access
works for document providers.
Unlike the iCloud
document provider,
which saves the special document
reference inside an iCloud
container the document provider
extensions don't take part
in the document reference
mechanism.
This is because, of course,
in this let's say we're
in an enterprise setting,
our enterprise administration
has decided
that they do not
want to use iCloud,
but of course we still want
this document provider extension
mechanism to still work because
our enterprise has given us an
application that can be
used to access the files
on the enterprise's file server.
So, it's no good to use iCloud
in this case, of course,
to get back to your
document preferences.
But, of course, the bookmark
mechanism will still work.
To that end, the file provider
is able, or has to be able,
to resolve or resolve
into a file URL
and the other way around.
Now for security purposes
we have an isolation layer
that saves the state information
about which application
has been granted access
to which identifier --
inside which file provider,
and this is also something that
we use these identifiers for.
Let's have a quick look at how a
bookmark is created and resolved
by a Document Provider
Extension.
Let's say we have our host
app and the host app is,
for some reason, going into
the background and just wants
to save its state, it will call
the bookmarkData WithOptions
method on NSURL, and NSURL
will call the persistent
IdentifierForItemAtURL method
on your file provider extension,
which can then return
a persistentdentifier.
This might be a database key
or it might be something
much simpler;
it depends on the actual way
that your file provider is
actually accessing files.
Now, at some point it will
return the Personal Identifier,
which is just a freeform
NS string to the NSURL,
and NSURL will package
that up and return it
as the opaque data blob,
that has the bookmark data.
At this point our user app can
go and save its state, and,
for example, get terminated
in some way, for example,
the user reboots their device.
Now, at some point later the
user is reopening their app,
the user app is doing state
restoration, and in the process
of doing this is calling the URL
by resulting bookmark
data on NSURL.
We hand the identifier back to
your file provider which can
in the URLForItemWith
PersistentIdentifier method
and it can then resolve this
identifier into a NSURL on disk.
Now, soon after, we call the
providePlaceholder AtURL method
which you can use to
provide a small placeholder
that can be used
in correspondence
with the previously discussed
getPromisedItem ResourceValueby
theUser app to merely get
Metadata on this file.
But what it can also do at this
point eagerly download the file.
We will at least ensure
that you are providing a
placeholder though.
You pass the NSURL off
the file on disk back.
The NSURL method can
now return this NSURL
and the host app can use the
getPromisedItem ResourceValue
to merely read metadata
or use FileCoordinator AP
on the NSURL to access the file.
Well, no matter what you
have chosen that we will
at least call you to ensure if
the user uses file coordination
in this case to load the
actual data from this document
to ensure that the file
on disk is current.
All right.
We've seen how reading
works and how getting back
to your documents works.
Let's have a quick look at
how writing files works.
In this case, the user is using,
or the host app is using
the file coordination API
to actually write data to disk.
So, it would do a
coordinated write
to the file inside your
storage apps folder.
The file is now changed inside
your storage apps folder.
At some point very soon after,
but importantly to note not
in a blocking way, so the file
coordination will have succeeded
by this point, we will
call itemChanged AtURL
on your file provider.
At this point your
file provider can go
and for example initiate
an upload of this file,
or at the very least mark it as
being dirty and needing upload,
so you don't accidently
overwrite it at a later point.
All right.
Let's have a quick
look at how that works.
What I've done is I've built a
very small sample project using
the template that comes with
xcode, which is very nice,
because it provides you
with almost everything
you need at the start.
We can use the target here
and use the application
and get extension template
for the Document Picker,
and basically choose a
name here and it'll set
up the two different extensions.
Inside my project I just have
the two different extensions,
one folder here for
the actual picker.
I'm doing a text
snippet picker to go
with the text display
app that Mike showed.
And inside this I have
a whole bunch of files
which are basically, well,
classes to display some sort
of picking UI, but the
important part is my subclass
of UIDocumentPicker
ExtensionViewController here.
And inside this subclass
the important parts are the
prepareForPresentationinMode
method - let me make this big
so you can see this -
and in this PresentationinMode
method what I want
to do is basically
display a specific,
in this case I'm using a
collection view controller
to display a list of documents,
and I'm displaying this.
And all of my picking
actually is not handled
by my DocumentPicker
ViewController,
but by a subclass.
Of course, I use a
delegate pattern to get back
to my main class once the
user has picked a document
and we'll call this method here
and inside this method
all I have
to do is call the
dismissGrantingAccesstoURL
with the file URL that I've
previously written out.
Now, the document file
provider here is very simple
in this case.
The interesting method for this
demo is the startProvidingItem
withURL method, which
I implement to ensure
that the snippet at
this URL is current,
and then call the
Completion Handler.
Let's have a quick look at
how that looks on the machine.
All right.
I've got my demo app here, which
is basically, since I started
from the template,
just an empty app.
So, instead I'm going to
pop off the Document Picker
and you notice I don't
even have any documents
in my iCloud account,
but when I pop
up this Document
Picker menu here,
I see a list including
the iCloud document picker
and my SnippetPicker.
And if I pop
up the SnippetPicker what is
displayed is my SnippetPicker
View Controller and I
can use that to pick any
of these documents
or Snippets in here.
So, when I pick these with
the exact same sample app
that Mike showed you I'm
able to access these Snippets
from my little document
picker app.
Now, when you use the
seed one to try this out,
note that this Snippet that the
document picker you will create
will not show up by default,
so you can use the
little locations button
in the navigation bar of
the iCloud Document Picker.
It has a little more pop
out where you can enable
the Snippet Picker.
All right.
Now let's switch back to slides.
Cool. To summarize the demo,
we've got an Xcode template
to get you started with the
document picker mechanism.
The Document Picker, or a
Document Provider will show
up right next to
the iCloud picker
if the user installs them.
And we also have
sample code available
on the Session Home Page,
that will enable you
to quickly test this out.
The sample code is basically a
little test app that we wrote
to be able to display each
of the document picker modes.
Cool. So that's Document
Providers,
and that almost concludes the
session, but I have a little bit
of information for you --
to inform you how since we have
this new Cloud Drive mechanism,
how the migration
story is for that.
On iOS 8 the users can either
choose to, once it comes out,
choose to use the old
iCloud Documents mechanism,
or to migrate to iCloud Drive.
On OS X Yosemite we do
not provide the backwards
compatibility for the old
iCloud documents mechanism,
so the user has to either
choose to migrate to Cloud Drive
or they will no longer
receive the updates
across their devices.
Of course, they can choose
to migrate at a later point,
at which point the
upgrades resume.
And of course after
an account is migrated
to iCloud Drive only the devices
that are actually using iCloud
Drive will propagate changes
between each other.
For US developers this
is important to know
because even though the
current Seed Build that you have
in your hands right now is
automatically using iCloud
Drive, the actual new features -
and thus you can easily test all
of this out - the new
features that we've presented
in today's presentation
will only be available
if your user is using
iCloud Drive.
So you have to be aware
of this possibility
in case they have not
actually chosen to migrate.
All right.
To summarize, if you're
just taking one thing away
from today's session it would be
that you should use
file coordination
for document access.
Without using file coordination,
none of these mechanisms can
work, and you will probably be
at some point experiencing
data loss on the machines
of your users; which of
course is extremely bad.
We've seen how to discover
and display files not only
in your own container, but
also using the UIDocumentPicker
which allows you to
access files outside
of your applications'
containers.
We've given a quick
overview on how
to use document provider
extensions to be able
to integrate your own
company's storage system
into the whole document
access mechanism.
For more information I
would like to guide you
to Dave DeLong, our App
Frameworks Evangelist
and also Jake Behrens
who is the UIKit specific
Frameworks Evangelist.
We have some neat
documentation out.
There is a brand new
iCloud for Developers guide
and we also have guides
for the Document Picker,
and of course also guides for
the extensions mechanisms.
We also have the Apple Developer
Forums where our developers hang
out and will answer questions.
Related sessions: there
was a very nice session
on introducing CloudKit.
If you're interested
in the technology behind the
new iCloud Drive mechanism
that powers all of this.
This session is of course
not entirely necessary
if you merely want to
store your documents
because the CloudKit mechanism
is entirely transparent
from the document
storage perspective.
We also have had sessions on
creating extensions for iOS
and OS X, and with that
thank you for your time
and I wish you pleasant rest
of the week and a nice bash.
[ Applause ]