[ Silence ]
>> Alright.
Hello and welcome to
the Advanced Graphics
and Animations for
iOS Apps talk.
I'm Axel. Mike is over there.
He will take over in
the middle of the talk.
And with today's
talk we're going
to cover the following topics.
The first part we'll be talking
about the Core Animation
pipeline
and how it interacts
with the application.
After this I'll introduce
a few rendering concepts
that are required to
understand our new two classes,
UIBlurEffect and
UIVibrancyEffect
and after this Mike will
take over and walk you
through existing Profiling Tools
and demonstrate a
few case studies.
To iterate the frameworks
that we'll be looking
at in this talk, in the first
part of the talk we're looking
at Core Animation and how
it interacts with OpenGL
or some hardware with metal,
the graphics hardware.
And then in the second
half of my part I will talk
about the UIBlurEffect
and UIVibrancyEffect
that are a part of UIKit.
So let's get started with
the Core Animation pipeline.
So it all starts
in the application.
The application builds
a view hierarchy.
These are indirectly with UIKit
or directly with Core Animation.
One thing worth noticing now is
that the application process is
actually not doing the actual
rendering work for
Core Animation.
Instead this view hierarchy is
committed to the render server
which is a separate process
and this render server
has a server side version
of Core Animation that
receives this view hierarchy.
The view hierarchy is then
rendered with Core Animation
with OpenGL or metal,
that's the GPU.
It's GPU accelerated.
And then once the view hierarchy
is being rendered we can finally
display it to the user.
So the interesting part
is now how does this look
like time wise within
the application?
So, therefore, I would like to
introduce the following grid.
The vertical lines represent
particular blanking interrupts
and since you're rendering at
60 hertz of UI the distance
between those vertical
lines is 16.67ms.
So, the first thing that
happens in the application,
you receive an event
probably because of a touch,
and therefore, the usual case,
I mean to handling this case is
that we want to update
a view hierarchy.
And this happens in a phase
that we call the commit
transaction phase.
It is in our application.
At the end of this phase the
view hierarchy is then encoded
and sent to the render server.
The first thing that the
render server then asks is
to decode this view hierarchy.
The render server then has
to wait for the next resync
in order to wait for buffers
to get back from a display
that they can actually render to
and then it finally starts
issuing draw calls for the GPU,
this OpenGL or metal again.
Then once this is
completed hopefully
with the review sources now
available it can finally start
rendering and so the GPU starts
doing its rendering work.
Hopefully this rendering work
finishes before the next resync
because then we can
swap in the frame buffer
and show the view
hierarchy to the user.
As you can these various steps
span over multiple frames.
In this case it's three frames
and let's say we
would now continue
with the next handler event
and Commit Transaction
after the display then we would
only be able to render 20 hertz.
I know that's 60 hertz.
So, therefore, what we're
doing is we are overlaying
these stages.
So in parallel with
the draw codes
that you can see here we will
do the next handler event,
handler event and commit
transaction and so at the end
of this flowing step diagram.
In the next few slides
I would like to focus
on the commit transaction stage
because that's what affects
application developers the most.
So let's take a look
at commit transaction.
Commit transaction itself
consists of four phases.
The first phase is
the layout phase.
This is where we
set up the views.
Then the next phase
is the display phase.
This is where we draw the views.
The third phase is the
prepare commit phase
where we do some additional
Core Animation work
and the last phase is where we
actually package up the layers
and send them to the
render server in the commit.
So let's look in detail
at those four phases.
First the layout phase.
In the Layout phase the
layoutSubviews overrides
are invoked.
This is where view
creation happens.
This is where we add
layers to the view hierarchy
with addSubview and this
is where populate content
and do some lightweight
database lookups.
And I'm saying lightweight
because we don't want
to stall here too long.
The lightweights could be,
for example, localized strings
because we need them
at this point in order
to do our label layout.
Because of this, this phase is
usually CPU bound or I/O bound.
The second phase is
the Display phase.
This is where the draw
contents this drawRect
if it's overridden
or do string drawing.
One thing worth noting here is
that this phase is actually CPU
or memory bound, because the
rendering is [inaudible].
We use here the core
graphics for this rendering.
And so we usually do this
rendering with CG context.
So the point is here that
we want to minimize the work
that we do with core graphics
to avoid a large
performance set in this stage.
The next phase is
the Prepare phase.
This is where image decoding
and image conversion happens.
Image decoding should
be straightforward.
This happens if you
have any images
and in your view
hierarchy and these JPEGs
or PNGs are getting
decoded at this point.
Image conversation is not
quite so straightforward.
What happens here is
that we might have images
that are not supported
by the GPU.
And, therefore, we need
to convert these images.
A good example for this could
be index bitmap so you want
to avoid certain image formats.
In the last phase the Commit
phase, we package up the layers
and send them to
the render server.
This process is recursive.
You have to reiterate
over the whole layer tree
and this is expensive.
The layer tree is complex.
So this is why we want to
keep the layer tree as flat
as possible to make sure
that this part of the phase
and as efficient as it can be.
So let's take a look with how
this works with animation.
Animations themselves are
a three stage process.
Two of those happen
inside the application
and the last stage happens
on the render server.
The first stage is where
we create the animation,
update view hierarchy.
This happens usually with
the animate restoration
animations method.
Then the second stage
is where we prepare
and commit your animation.
This is where layoutSubview
is being called drawRect
and that probably
sounds familiar.
And it is, because these are
the four phases we were just
looking at.
The only difference here is
that with the commit
we don't just commit
to the view hierarchy.
We commit as well the animation.
And that's for a
reason, because we would
like to handle the animation
work to render server
so that we can continue
to update your animation
without using interprocess
communication to talk back
to the application or force
them back to the application.
So that's for efficiency
reasons.
So, let's take a look at a few
rendering concepts that require
to understand the
new visual effects
that we are providing
you with in iOS 8.
So in this part of the talk
I'm covering three areas;
first tile based rendering
is how all GPUs work.
Then I'm going to introduce
the concept of render passes
because our new effects
they use render passes.
And then I'm doing
a first example
by showing you how masking
works with render passes.
So let's take a look at
tile based rendering.
With tile based rendering,
the screen is split
into tiles of NxN pixels.
I've put here a screenshot
together and overlaid it
with a grid where you can see
actually what a tile size would
be like.
The tile size is chosen so that
it fits into the SoC cache.
And the idea here is that
the geometry is split
into tile buckets.
And I would like
to demonstrate this
by using the phone
icon as an example.
As you can see the phone
icon spans multiple tiles
and the phone icon itself
is rendered as a CA layer.
And the CA layer in
CA is two triangles.
And if you look at the two
triangles they are still
spanning multiple
triangles, multiple tiles.
And so what a GP will do now,
it will now start splitting
up those triangles, where
we committed the tile
so that each tile can be
rendered individually.
The idea is here that
we do this process now
for the hue geometries so at
some point we have the geometry
for each tile collected and
then we can make decisions
on what pixels are visible
and then decide what
pixel shade to run.
So we run each pixel
shade only once per pixel.
Obviously if you do blending
this doesn't quite work.
Then we still have the
problem of overdraw.
So, let's take a look at what
type of rendering passes are.
So let's assume application
has built a view hierarchy
with Core Animation.
It's committed to render server
and Core Animation has decoded
it and now it needs to render it
and it will use OpenGL or metal.
In the slide I'm
just saying metal
for simplicity to render it.
And it will generate
with OpenGL command
but it is then submitted
to a GPU.
And the GPU will receive
this command buffer
and then start doing its work.
The first thing that GPU will
do is vertex processing is
where the vertex shader runs.
And the idea here is that
you transform all of vertices
into screen space at this stage
so that we can then
do the second stage,
which is the actual tiling.
Where we actually tile the
geometry for our tile buckets.
And this part of the stage
is called the tiler stage.
You will be able to find
this in the instruments,
in the OpenGL ES
driver instrument
and the tiler utilization.
The output of this
stage is written
in something called
the parameter buffer
and the next stage is
not starting immediately.
Instead we wait now until all
geometry is processed and sits
in the parameter buffer or until
the parameter buffer is full.
Because the problem is
if the parameter buffer is
full we have to flush it.
And that's actually performance
it because then we need to start
at the vertex processing and get
and frontload pixel
share at work.
And next stage is as I said
the pixel shader stage.
This stage is actually
called the renderer stage
and you can find this again
in the instruments
OpenGL ES driver tool
under the name renderer
utilization.
And the output of
this stage is written
to something called
the render buffer.
Okay, so next let's take a
look at a practical example
by looking at masking.
So let's assume our view
hierarchy is ready to go.
The command buffer is
sitting with the GPU
and we can stop processing.
So the first thing happens
in the first pass is
that we render the
layer mask to a texture.
In this case it's
this camera icon.
Then in the second pass if
you render the layer content
to a texture and in this case
it's this kind of blue material.
And then in the last pass
that we call the compositing
pass we apply the mass
to the content texture and
composite to the reside
to screen and end up with
this light blue camera icon.
So let's take a look
at UIBlurEffect.
For those that don't know
UIBlurEffect can be used
with UIVisualEffect view
and this now a public API.
Since iOS 8, it basically
allows you to use the Blurs
that we introduced as iOS 7.
And if we are providing you
with three different Blur styles
that I want to demonstrate here.
I took this regular
iOS wallpaper
and applied three
different BlurEffects to it,
extra light, light and dark.
So let's take a look how
this looks performance wise.
I'm using here the dark
style as an example
for the rendering passes.
The dark style is actually
using the lowest amount
of render passes.
And you also need to keep in
mind this render pass depends
on the fact that we did
certain optimizations
for certain passer hardware.
So in the first pass
we render the content
that is going to be blurred.
Then in the second pass
we captured the content
and downscale it.
The downscale depends
on the hardware
so in this slide I kept
it at a certain size
so it's still readable.
Then in the next two passes
we applied the actual blur
algorithm, which is separated so
we do first the horizontal blur
and then the vertical blur.
There's actually a
common blur optimization.
We could do this
in a single pass
but let's assume our blur
corner would be 11x11.
This would mean we would
need 121 samples per pixel
and by separating we only need
to read 11 samples per
pixel in each pass.
So after the fourth pass
we have this horizontally
and vertically blurred
small tiny area.
And so what's left in the
last pass is that we need
to upscale this blur
and tint it.
In this case we end up
then with our dark blur.
So that looks fine, but let's
take a look how this looks
like performance wise.
So what I did as I test, I
created a fullscreen layer
and applied the UIBlurEffect to
it and measured the performance.
In this diagram you
can see three rows.
The first row represents
a tile activity,
the second row a render
activity and the last row I put
in the VBlank interrupt
and we can actually see what
our frame boundaries are.
And again, we are
running at 60 hertz UI.
So, the time you
have is 16.67ms.
So let's focus on
a single frame.
As you can see as a first look
here the first tiler pass is
happening before the first
render pass and that's
because the tiler needs to
pull this whole geometry,
so it's emphasized in what we
just saw on previous slides.
So let's go quickly
over the passes again.
So the first pass
is the content pass.
The time for this really
depends on the view hierarchy.
In this case it's
just a simple image
so it might take longer
if we involve the UI.
Then in the second
pass we downscale
and capture the content.
It's actually fairly fast.
This is pretty much
constant cost.
Then the subpass is
the horizontal blur.
Again it's constant cost
which is pretty fast
because we only apply
it on a very small area.
And then in the fourth pass
we do the vertical Blur,
again very fast and we end
up with our blurred region.
And then in the last pass we
upscale and tint the blur.
So one thing you will
notice now are those gaps
between those passes.
I've marked them here in orange.
And those gaps are actually
[inaudible] and they happen
because we do here run a
contact switch on the GPU.
And this can actually
add up quite quickly
because the time spent here
in idle time is passable
at 0.1 to 0.2ms.
So in this case with four passes
we have about idle time of 0.4
to 0.8ms, which is a
good significant chunk
of our 16.67ms.
So let's take a look
how the blur performs
on the various devices.
So again this is the fullscreen
blur that I used before
and I met it as well on
iPad 3, 3rd generation.
And as you can see the iPad 3rd
generation performs much worse
than the iPad Air.
In the case of the extra light
blur the timing is 18.15ms,
so we can't render at 60 hertz
this type of blur on iPad Air.
And for light and dark we are
around 14.5ms, which leaves us
about 2ms for UI, which
is not really enough
for rendering any compelling UI.
So the decision we
made on iOS 7 RA was
that we would disable the
blur on certain devices
and the iPad 3rd generation
is one of these devices.
And this -- the performance
on the iPad 3rd generation
changes to this.
You basically just apply
a tint layer on top
so that we can make sure
that legibility is the same
as without the BlurEffect.
So, and to reiterate on
what devices we don't blur
and that we only do the
tinting on the iPad 2
and iPad 3rd generation,
we just apply the tint
and we skip the blur steps.
On iPad 4th generation,
iPad Air, iPad Mini,
iPad Mini with retina
display, iPhones
and the iPod touch we do both
the blur and the tinting.
So, in summary for
the UIVisualEffectView
with UIBlurEffect, UIBlurEffect
have multiple onscreen passes
depending on the style.
Only dirty regions are redrawn.
So it's actually fine if
you have a large blur area
and you don't have
the content behind it,
because we only applied
the blur once.
The effect is very costly so
UI can be easily GPU bound.
So, therefore, you
should keep the bounds
of the view as small
as possible.
And, therefore, as well
you should make sure
to budget for effect.
So, next let's take a look
at the UIVibrancyEffect.
UIVibrancyEffect is an
effect that's used on the top
of the blur and it's meant
to be used for contents
which can make sure
that content stands out
and doesn't go under
with the blurs.
So, let's take a look
how this looks like.
This is our three
blur styles again.
And let's assume we want
to render the camera icon
from our masking example
from before on top.
And this could look like this
if you don't use
any VibrancyEffect.
And as you can see with the
light style there might be some
legibility issues because
the gray starts bleeding out.
So, what we decided is that
we edit some VibrancyEffect
and VibrancyEffect is a punch
through and then you end
up with this nice vibrant look.
So, let's take a look how
this affects performance.
So, back to our render
pass diagram.
The first five passes
are in this case
for the dark blur,
the blur cost.
And then in a sixth pass
we render the layer content
to a texture.
And then in the final
compositing pass we take the
layer content and apply filter
and composite it
on top of the blur.
Don't be fooled here.
The filter content is actually
quite expensive and I want
to show this in the
next couple of slides.
So this is our diagram
from before.
This is the steps for the blur
and let's add on now the steps
for the VibrancyEffect.
So, in pass six I'm adding
in here some content,
you saw a camera icon.
And then obviously the
cost for this pass depends
on what you're rendering there,
what view hierarchy looks like.
And then the last pass
we apply the filter.
And as you can see the filter
cost is actually very expensive.
It's actually the most
expensive pass we have here.
One thing to keep
in mind here is
that I apply the VibrancyEffect
to a fullscreen area.
The recommendation is to
not apply the VibrancyEffect
to a fullscreen area,
instead to only apply it
to small content areas to avoid
this huge performance penalty.
As well to emphasize -- we
have now is way more gaps
because we have more
render passes.
So, the GPU idle time
has increased as well.
We have now six gaps and this
can add up to 0.6 to 1.2ms
of idle time in our GPU.
So, let's take a
look how this looks
on iPad 3rd generation
and iPad Air.
There is the base cost
from before, 4.59ms.
For the iPad 3rd generation we
don't blur and different times
for the iPad Air
depending on the blur style.
So, let's add this on
and what we can see is
for the fullscreen effect
is that we are spending
on iPad 3rd generation
about 27 to 26ms just
for applying the VibrancyEffect.
On the iPad Air we
spend about 17.48ms
for the extra light style and
around 14ms for light and dark.
So you don't have a lot of
time left there on the GPU
to do any other rendering.
I mean 2ms is the
best case here.
So to emphasize again, we
should really restrict the
VibrancyEffect on a small area
to avoid this huge GPU overhead.
So, in summary, UIVibrancyEffect
adds two offscreen passes.
UIVibrancyEffect uses expensive,
uses expensive compositing
filter for content.
So, therefore, you should
only use the UIVibrancyEffect
on small regions.
Again likeness to blur only
dirty regions are redrawn
and the UIVibrancyEffect is
very costly on all devices.
So with the blurs UI can easily
be GPU bound, keep the bounds
of the view as small as
possible and make sure
to budget for the effects.
So, next I would
like to give a couple
of automization techniques
on the way.
One is rasterization.
Rasterization can
be used to composite
to image once with the GPU.
This can be enabled
with shouldRasterize
property on a CAlayer.
And there are a few things to
keep in mind when doing this.
First extra offscreen
passes are created
when we update the contents.
We should only use this
for static content.
Secondly you should not overuse
it because the cache size
for rasterization is limited to
25.5 times of the screen size.
So if you start setting
the rasterize property
of the last part of your view
hierarchy you might blow the
cache flow over and over and end
up as a lot of offscreen passes.
Last the rasterized images
are evicted from the cache
if they are unused
for more than 100ms.
So you want to make sure that
you use this only for images
that are consistently used and
not for infrequently used images
because then you will incur
every time an onscreen pass.
So typically use cases are
to avoid redrawing expensive
effects for static content
so you could rasterize,
for example, a blur.
And the other thing
is the redrawing
of complex view hierarchies
so we could rasterize
for view hierarchy
and composite on top
of a blur or under a blur.
So the last thing I have
here is group opacity.
Group opacity can be disabled
because it allows GroupOpacity
property on a CALayer.
Group Opacity will actually
introduce offscreen passes
if a layer is not opaque.
So this means the opacity
property is not equal to 1.0.
And if a layer has
nontrivial content
that means it has child
layers or a background image.
And what this means in turn is
that sub view hierarchy needs
to be composited before
its being blended.
Therefore my recommendation is
to always turn it off
if it's not needed.
Be very careful with this.
And with this I would
like to turn it
over to Mike for the Tools.
[ Applause ]
>> So, I am Mike Ingrassia.
I am a software engineer
in the iOS performance team
and the first thing I want
to talk about are Tools.
So before I get into
Tools though,
I do want to mention
the performance
investigation mindset.
So basically, what are
the questions running
through my head when I encounter
a performance issue and want
to start tracking down
the source of that?
So, first thing I want to know
is what is the frame rate?
You know it's always
good to know
where you're starting
performance wise
so that you can gauge how
the changes you make are
affecting performance.
So our goal is always 60 fps.
We want to ensure that
we have smooth scrolling
and nice smooth animations to
provide a good user experience.
So, our target should
always be 60 fps.
Next up I want to know
are we CPU or GPU bound?
You know obviously the lower
the utilization the better
because it will let us hit
our performance targets
and also give us
better battery life.
Next thing you want to know,
are there any unnecessary,
is there any unnecessary
CPU rendering?
So basically are we
overriding drawRect somewhere
where we really shouldn't
be you know and kind
of understanding
what we're rendering
and how we're rendering it.
We want the GPU to do as
much of this as makes sense.
Next thing I want to know
is do we have too many
offscreen passes?
As Axel pointed out previously
offscreen passes basically give
the GPU idle time because it
has to do contact switches
so we want to have
fewer offscreen passes,
you know the fewer the better.
Next up I want to know is there
too much blending in the UI?
We obviously want
to do less blending
because blending is more
expensive for the GPU
to than rendering just
a normal opaque player.
So, less blending is better.
Next I want to know is are
there any strange image formats
or sizes?
Basically we want to avoid
on the fly conversion
of image formats.
As Axel pointed out previously
if you are rendering an image
that is not, in a color
format that is not supported
by the GPU then it has to
be converted by the CPU.
And so we want to try and avoid
anything on-the-fly like that.
Next up I want to know are there
any expensive views or effects?
Blur and Vibrancy are
awesome but we want
to make sure we're using
them sparingly in a way
that will give us the scrolling
performance that we want.
And lastly, I want to know
is there anything unexpected
in the view hierarchy?
You know if you have a situation
where you're constantly adding
or removing views you know
you could introduce a bug
accidentally that say you know
inserts animation and forgets
to remove them or you
know you're adding views
to your hierarchy and
forgetting to remove them.
You know you want to make sure
that you only have the views
that you really need you know in
your hierarchy because you want
to avoid excessive CPU
use of backboard D.
So, now let's get
into some of the tools
that will give us the
answers to these questions.
So first off I want to
talk about instruments
and particularly we'll talk
about the Core Animation
instrument
and the OpenGL ES
Driver instrument.
Then I will say a few
things about the simulator
that you can do with
color debug options
and then I will briefly talk
about a new feature in Xcode
for live view debugging
on device.
So first up, if you
launch instruments
and select the Core
Animation template
that will give you a document
that contains a Core
Animation instrument
and a time profiler instrument.
If you select the Core Animation
instrument you can then choose
which statistics
you want to show.
In this case it's only fps.
So we'll choose that and then
when you take a trace it will
show you your frame rate.
So you can see in the column
here it shows you the fps
for each interval that
this trace was running.
So you see this in
sample intervals.
Likewise if you want to see what
the CPU is doing you can select
the time profiler instrument.
And so you select it and then
you can then see an aggregated
call stack of what the CPU is
doing while you were taking
your trace.
So this is where you would look
for you know am I
overriding drawRect?
Am I spending too much time
in main thread doing
things that I shouldn't be?
Next up let's talk about some
of the color debug options
that are part of the Core
Animation Instrument.
So if you select the Core
Animation Instrument you can see
the color debug options
over here on the right.
So let's go through
what those are.
First up we have
color blended layers
and so this will tint
layers green that are opaque
and tint layers red
that have to be blended.
As we said previously,
you know layers that have
to be blended is more
work for the GPU.
And so you ideally want to see
less red you know and more green
but there are going to be
cases where you can avoid it.
For example, in this particular
case we have a white table view
with white table view
cells and we notice
that our labels are you know
having to be blended here.
So if we made our labels in this
case opaque then we wouldn't
have to worry about
doing the blending
so that would be one
optimization we could make
in this particular case.
Next up color hit
screens and misses red.
This shows you how you're using
or abusing the should
rasterize property on CALayer.
So what this will do is it
will tint cache hit screen
and cache misses red.
So as Axel pointed out
previously keep in mind
that your cache size is only
two and a half times the size
of the screen and items
are evicted from the cache
if they're not used
within 100ms.
So, you know it's good
to use this particular
coloring debug option
to see how you're
utilizing the cache
with you know what you have
set should rasterized on.
When you first launch your
app you're going to see a lot
of flashing red because
you obviously have
to render it once
before it can be cached.
But after that you don't want
to see a whole lot of flashes
of red because you know
as we said previously,
you know anything
you're doing is going
to incur offscreen passes
when you have to render it
and then stick it in the cache.
So, next item is
color copied images.
As we said before if an
image is in a format,
is in the color format that
the GPU can't work directly
with it will have to be
converted by the CPU.
So in this particular example
you know this is just a simple
photo browsing app.
We're just getting images
from an online source.
We're not really checking their
size or their color format.
So in this particular
case we're getting images
that are 16 bits per component.
And so you can see that
they are tinted cyan here.
That is telling us that these
images had to be converted
by the CPU in the commit phase
before they could actually
be rendered.
So, you know for this particular
case we don't want to do this
on the fly because it will
affect scrolling performance.
So you can beforehand you know
convert your images to the size
and the color format
that you're expecting.
And it's best to do this in,
you know in the background
so you're not eating up time
on the main thread while
you're trying to scroll
or doing other things.
So the next option is
color misaligned images.
This will tint images
yellow that are being scaled
and tint images purple
that are not pixel aligned.
You know as I said previously
it's always good to make sure
that images are in the
color format and the size
that you want because
the last thing you want
to be doing is you know
doing conversions in scaling
on the fly while
you're scrolling.
So the same principles
we applied
in the previous slide we would
also apply here to get rid
of the scaling on-the-fly.
So, next up is color
offscreen yellow.
So this will tint layers
yellow based on the number
of offscreen passes
that each layer occurs.
So, the more yellow you see the
more offscreen passes we have.
If you notice the nav bar and
the tool bar are tinted yellow,
that's because there are
blurs with these layers
that are actually blurring
the content behind it.
So we expect those, but
I do find it curious
that the images are
having offscreen passes.
So we'll take a look at that
later on in the presentation
and see how to work
around this issue.
So next is color
OpenGL fast path blue.
And so what this will do is
this will tint layers blue
that are being blended
by the display hardware.
This is actually a good
thing you want to see
because if we have content
that's being blended
by the display hardware
then that's less work
for the GPU to have to do.
So in this case if
you see something show
up in blue that's a good thing.
Last option is flash
updated regions.
And so what this will do
is it will flash parts
of the screen yellow
that are being updated.
This particular example is
with the clocks app
that shifts in iOS.
You notice that the
yellow regions here are the
second hand.
Ideally you only want to see
parts of the screen flash yellow
that you're actually updating.
Again because this means
less work for this GPU
and less work for the CPU.
So, if you turn this on
you don't want to see a lot
of flashing yellow unless
you actually are updating
that much of the screen.
So, in summary some
of the questions
that the Core Animation
Instrument will help you get to,
it will help you figure
out what the frame rate is,
is there any unnecessary
CPU rendering
because it does include the
time profiler instrument.
And also with the color debug
options you can see things
like are there too
many offscreen passes?
How much blending is going on?
And do you have any strange
image formats or sizes
that you're not expecting?
And so one additional point
on the coloring options some
of the coloring options are
available in the iOS simulator
so you can see the example here.
A few things to point
out with this,
the colors might be slightly
different because the version
of CA that's running inside the
simulator is actually a version
of CA that's on OS
X, not on iOS.
So if you see any discrepancies
always trust what you see
on device, because that's what
your customer is actually going
to be using.
So, this is a good future
because you can have
like say your testing team go
off and hook around your app
and see if you have any
unexpected offscreen passes
or any conversion or anything
that looks suspicious.
So next topic, I want to talk
about the OpenGL ES
driver instrument.
So if you launch instruments
and select the OpenGL
ES driver template
that will give you a document
that contains the OpenGL
ES driver instrument
and a time profiler instrument.
So if you select the OpenGL ES
driver instrument you can choose
from which statistics you
want to actually collect.
When I'm investigating
things I tend to go
for device utilization,
which will show you how much the
GPU is in use during the trace.
Render and tiler utilization,
those correspond to the renderer
and tiler phases that Axel
was talking about previously.
And then, of course, the Core
Animation fps because I want
to know what the actual frame
rate is that we're seeing.
So, if you take a trace
and then select the core,
the OpenGL ES driver
instrument you can then look
at the statistics and see,
for example in this case,
we are hitting 60 fps and
our device utilization is
in like the mid lower 70s.
So, you know it depends
on while you're rendering
so you know you may want
to investigate this,
like if it all boils down to
what you're actually rendering
for this case.
And likewise since we have the
time profiler instrument here
you can see what
the CPU is doing.
So, if you select that
you can then again look
at aggregated call
stacks of what was going
on in the CPU during this time.
So this is always useful because
you can highlight certain
regions you know if you notice
that you're dropping frames
or you notice a lot of
activity you can zoom in
and see what the CPU is doing
during that particular time.
So in summary, with OpenGL ES
driver instrument you know this
will give you answers
to questions
like what is your frame rate?
You can see what the
CPU and CPU are doing
and you can also use the
time profiler instrument
to see are there any unnecessary
CPU rendering going on?
So next up is a really cool
feature that was added in Xcode
for live view debugging
on device.
So if you open your object
in Xcode and then run it
and then click this little
button on the bottom here,
what it will actually do is it
will grab the view hierarchy off
the device and you
can then go poking
around in your view hierarchy
and see what exact
views are in your UI.
So this is always good because
you can inspect to see as I said
if there's anything unexpected
there you know maybe something
is building up or you have
a leak of say animations
or something or constraints.
So this is good to actually
see what the view hierarchy is
on your device versus say what
you conceptually think it is
when you're writing your code.
If you select an individual item
or an individual view you can
look at the properties for it.
So in this case we selected a
UI view and you can see details
about what property and what
image is currently being
rendered by that view.
So summary for Xcode view
debugging this will let you poke
around in your view hierarchy
to see what's actually
being rendered on device,
you know which is helpful
because you can see
if you have any expensive views.
You know looking at their
properties you know seeing what
your bounds are and whatnot.
Also good to see if you
have anything building
up unexpectedly in
your view hierarchy.
So next up let's talk
about some case studies.
So what I want to do with this
is I want to talk about a couple
of different scenarios
and measure performance
across different devices.
And then we'll figure
out how we can work
around these performance
problems
and keep the same
visual appearance,
but you know get the
performance gain that we want.
So first up, let's talk about
a fictitious photo application.
So this is just a simple
application with a table view
where each table view cell has
an image and a couple of lines
of text and there's also a
small shadow behind each image.
So, if we take this and
we measure the performance
on an iPhone 5s using the
OpenGL ES driver instrument.
You know we can see that
we're hitting 60 fps.
So, that's good; 60
fps is our target.
So, awesome, ship it.
Not just yet.
We you know actually love all
of our customers and we want
to make sure everybody has a
good user experience regardless
of what device they're on.
So, let's take a look at
some of the other devices
that we support in iOS 8 to see
how the performance stacks up.
So, first off let's
look at the iPod touch.
So I'm curious what scrolling
feels like on an iPod touch.
So, you know again we'll
take our iPod touch
and we'll use the OpenGL
ES driver instrument
and you know sure enough
we notice our frame rate is
in the mid 30s, which is
nowhere near our target.
So that would be a lousy
scrolling experience.
And if we look at the
device utilization we see
that you know this is
like mid to high 70s.
This strikes me as
really kind of odd
because all we're doing is
just scrolling around a couple
of image thumbnails
and some text.
So I don't really expect
this much GPU activity.
So let's see if we can figure
out what's going on here.
So, first thing I want to
know is you know what's
in my view hierarchy.
Is there anything
unexpected here?
So we use the Xcode
debugging feature.
We grab the view hierarchy.
I don't really see
anything surprising here
so we've got you know table
view cell with an image view
and two labels, nothing
out of the ordinary here.
So, let's see if we can
figure out something else.
So if we use the Core Animation
instrument you know remembering
that offscreen passes
are expensive,
let's see if we have
any offscreen passes
that are unexpected.
And sure enough this
is the slide
that I referenced previously.
So you know we have offscreen
passes for the images,
which again strikes
me as curious.
Let's just take a look at the
code and see what we're doing,
how are we setting this up.
So, as I said each image
thumbnail has a shadow.
How are we generating
that shadow?
So in this case we are
asking Core Animation
to generate the shadow for us.
And we're doing that just
by setting shadowRadius,
shadowOffset you know
and other properties.
Basically when we're doing this
Core Animation has to figure
out what the shape of
the shadow looks like.
And when it does this it
has to take offscreen passes
to render the content and
then look at the alpha channel
of what it just rendered
to figure
out where the shadow
belongs and then go
through all the extra work
of doing the shadow itself.
Is there a better way?
Is there something that
we can do to avoid this
and it turns out there is.
If we add the following line,
so there is the shadowPath
property you know we're only
scrolling image thumbnail,
so just basically
Rects of various sizes.
We can easily figure out
you know what the shape
of the shadow needs to
look like because again,
they're all just
various sized rectangles.
So if we take advantage of the
shadow path property and add
that to our code then Core
Animation doesn't have to eat
up any offscreen passes to
actually generate these shadows.
So, let's-- you know
let's make this change.
We'll add this line
and let's take a look
with the Core Animation
instrument to see
if this really did get rid
of our offscreen passes
and sure enough it did.
So, this is great.
Less offscreen passes means you
know less idle time on the GPU.
So, let's take a trace and see
what our scrolling performance
looks like.
So, again looking at an iPod
touch we'll use the OpenGL ES
driver instrument and we notice
that we are indeed
hitting 60 fps.
That's great.
And check out the device
utilization, you know we are now
in like the mid 30s as opposed
to you know the mid 70s before.
So this is great, you know less
GPU work means we are hitting
our performance targets and it
also means better battery life.
So, that's a good thing.
So, awesome, can we ship it now?
Well not just yet; we still
have one more device we should
look at.
So, let's take a
look at an iPhone 4s
and see how scrolling is
with our new changes now.
So, we are in fact
hitting 60 fps.
That's good and again device
utilization seems same.
You know 30 percent is a
lot better than mid 70s.
So, to summarize when we
had Core Animation doing
and figuring out
rendering the shadow
for us you notice
there's a drop off
when you look at older devices.
So the iPhone 5s can
handle this no problem.
But as you look at the iPhone
5, the iPhone 4s and the iPhone,
iPod touch you notice
that performance drops off
because again, older devices
can't handle the amount
of offscreen passes
that newer devices can.
And when we make this
change and take advantage
of the shadowPath property you
know notice we're hitting our
targets everywhere for 60 fps.
So, this is good.
We can ship this and
have happy customers.
So, awesome we can
finally ship it.
So, in summary, offscreen
passes are expensive.
You know you always want to
use Core Animation instruments
to find out if you have any
unnecessary offscreen passes
and know the APIs and view
hierarchy that you're using
to understand if there's
things you can do to avoid it.
In this case it was
using shadowPath.
And as always you know
measure your performance
across multiple devices.
You know you can see what the
GPU utilization is by looking
at the openGL ES
driver instrument
and you can see what
the CPU is up to
by using the time
profiler instrument.
And as always you know,
know your view hierarchy,
know if there's any hidden
costs for what you're,
for what you're trying
to render.
And this is especially true
for things that we have inside
of table view cells
because we want to ensure
that we have smooth scrolling.
So it's particularly important
with a view hierarchy you build
up in a table view cell.
So, next case study
I want to look
at is a fictitious
contacts application.
So, again this is just
a simple table view.
We have you know
a round thumbnail
and we have a line of text.
So, not a whole lot
going on here.
So, if we look at performance
across different devices.
We notice that you
know the iPhone 5s
and the iPhone 5 are
hitting 60 fps that's good.
But the iPhone 4s and the
iPod touch aren't quite there.
So you know again,
we want everybody
to have good user
experience regardless
of the hardware that
they're using.
So let's take a look at this
and see why we're not getting
with the target frame
rate on these devices.
So, the first thing I want
to do is take an OpenGL,
use the OpenGL ES driver
instrument and take a trace.
You know it's always good to
know where you're starting
so you understand how
the changes you make are
affecting performance.
So take a trace.
Notice that our scrolling
is you know only
in the mid 40s; it's not good.
And look at the device
utilization.
The device utilization
is really high here.
That's rather interesting again
because we're just
rendering a couple
of those you know
images and some text.
So that looks suspicious to me.
So let's take a closer look.
Again you know we'll use the
Core Animation instrument
and see if there's
any unnecessary
or unexpected offscreen passes.
So you know we notice the
images here are incurring
offscreen passes.
So, just kind of curious.
Let's take a look at how we are
rendering and how we are setting
up these round thumbnails.
So, basically what we're
doing is we're starting off
with this particular case.
We're starting off
with square thumbnails
and we are on-the-fly
asking Core Animation
to round them off for us.
And we're doing this by using
cornerRadius and masking.
So this is where the offscreen
passes are coming from.
So, you know again
anything that we can do
to avoid offscreen passes you
know will improve performance
across all devices.
So, is there a better
way to do this?
Ideally if you can pregenerate
your thumbnails round then
that would be great, because
then you'd just be rendering
images and you wouldn't be
trying to do all of this masking
and having all these
offscreen passes on-the-fly.
So, you know if you can
pregenerate them that's great.
If you can't then another trick
you could do is remember this UI
was just a white table view
with white table view cells
and just you know
white background.
So we could fake
it in this case.
You know we could
render the square content
or the square thumbnail and then
render a white inverted circle
on top of it to kind of you know
in essence cut away
the rest of the image.
This would be reducing
our offscreen passes
but increasing the
amount of blending.
You know but this still turns
out to be a net performance win
because the GPU can
blend a lot faster
than it can do offscreen passes.
So, let's make this change
of just doing the, you know,
faking it and see how
that affects performance.
So, we'll take an
OpenGL ES driver.
We'll take a trace using the
OpenGL ES driver instrument
and see what our frame rate is
and sure enough we're
hitting 60 fps.
And notice how much less
the device utilization is.
So again, we're 30 percent
versus mid to upper 80s.
One quick word on this,
you notice before we
were actually GPU bound
but we weren't actually at
100 percent for GPU time.
That's because you know when you
have offscreen passes there is
that idle time when the GPU has
to change contacts
or switch contacts.
So, you know you still
might be GPU bound,
but not quite hitting
100 percent GPU usage
because of the situation
with offscreen passes,
so that's something
to keep in mind.
So, if we summarize performance
across all the devices you
know before we were just using
masking we noticed that there
was a performance drop off
on older devices.
After we made this change and
we made the tradeoff of doing,
having more blending for less
offscreen passes we are now
hitting 60 fps everywhere
which is good.
This is what we want.
So, in summary, notice
there's a theme here.
Offscreen passes are expensive,
so again you can use
Core Animation to find
where you have any
unexpected offscreen passes
and you know it's always
good to know you're API
and what user you're using
if there's anything you
can do to avoid them.
And, of course, always
measure your performance
across different devices,
you know OpenGL ES,
OpenGL ES driver instrument
will give you GPU activity
and time profiler instrument
will show you CPU activity.
And again always know what
view hierarchy is you know
if you have any kind of strange
or bizarre looking
performance issues.
So overall summary, you
know what were the question,
our original questions and
what tools have we used
to actually find these answers?
So here's a nice little table
that shows what we actually used
to get down to the questions.
So, this is always a good
starting point for figuring
out before you start
digging in your code to try
to figure out what's going on.
It's good to see what's
actually happening on device.
So overall summary, Axel talked
about the Core Animation
pipeline and talked
about some rendering
concepts and then talked
about some new UIKit features
for Blur and Vibrancy effects.
And then I went over
profiling tools
and then did some
example case studies.
So if you have any
questions feel free
to contact either the
Apps Frameworks Evangelist
or the Developer
Tools Evangelist.
So feel free to contact
Jake or Dave.
If you're curious about Core
Animation documentation that's
available online as well
as the Developer Forums
is a great resource.
And other related
sessions that are happening
at WWDC you now you might
find these interesting.
So these might be
worth checking out.
So thanks and have
a wonderful WWDC.
[ Applause ]