[ Silence ]
[ Applause ]
>> Hi everyone.
Thanks for coming today.
My name is David Eldred.
This is session 513
and we're going to talk
about Video Encoders
and Decoders today.
All right.
We want to make sure that
no matter what you're doing
with the video in your
application, you have access
to hardware encoders
and decoders.
This will help users.
This will improve user
experience in a number of ways.
Obviously, they'll
get better performance
and they will be far more
efficient, but most importantly,
this will extend battery life.
Users will really appreciate it
if their OS X, their portables,
as well as their iOS devices
have improved battery life.
And as an added bonus, people
with portables will love it
if their fans don't kick
in every time they're
doing video processing.
So today, we're going
to break this --
first, we're going to break this
down into a few case studies.
We're going to look at
some common user scenarios.
The first scenario we're going
to talk about is the case
where you have a stream of H.264
data coming in over the network
and you want to display
that inside
of a layer in your application.
The next one we're going
to talk about is the case
where you have a stream of H.264
data coming in over the network,
but you don't just
want to display
that in your application, but
you want to actually get access
to those decoded
CV pixel buffers.
Next, we'll be talking
about when the case
where you have a sequence of
images coming in from the camera
or someplace else and you'd
like to compress those
directly into a movie file.
And accompanying that, there's
the case where you have a stream
of images coming in from
the camera or someplace else
and you'd like to compress
those but get direct access
to those compressed
sample buffers
so that you can send
them out over the network
or do whatever you
like with them.
And then finally, we're
going to give you an intro
to our new multi-pass APIs
that we're introducing
in iOS8 and Yosemite.
All right, let's
do a quick overview
of our media interface stack.
You've seen stuff like
this earlier this week,
but we'll do it once more, and
there's a little focus on video
in my view of this, because
we're talking about video.
So at the top we have AVKit.
AVKit provides very
easy-to-use high level - ah,
view level interfaces
for dealing with media.
Below that, we have
AVFoundation.
AVFoundation provides an
easy-to-use Objective-C
interface for a wide
range of media tasks.
And below that, we
have Video Toolbox.
Video Toolbox has been
there on OS X for a while,
but now it's finally
populated with headers on iOS.
This provides direct access
to encoders and decoders.
[applause] And below that we
have Core Media and Core Video.
These frameworks provide
many of the necessary types
that you'll see throughout
the --
in the interfaces in
the rest of the stack.
So today, we're going
to focus on AVFoundation
and the Video Toolbox.
In AVFoundation, we'll be
looking at some interfaces
that allow you to decode
video directly into a layer
in your application or compress
frames directly into a file.
And the Video Toolbox -- we'll
be looking at these interfaces
to give you more direct access
to encoders and decoders
so you can decompress
directly to CV pixel buffers
or compress directly
to CM sample buffers.
So a quick note on
using these frameworks.
A lot of people think they have
to dive down to the lowest level
and use the Video
Toolbox in order
to get hardware acceleration,
but that's really not true.
On iOS, AVKit, AVFoundation
and Video Toolbox will
all use hardware codecs.
On OS X, AVKit and AVFoundation
will use hardware codecs
when they're available on
the system and when you --
when it's appropriate.
And Video Toolbox will
use hardware codecs
when it's available on system
and when you request it.
All right.
So before we dive into
more stuff, we're going --
I'm going to do a quick look
at this cast of characters.
These are some of
the common types
that you'll encounter
in these interfaces.
First off, there's
CVPixelBuffer.
CVPixelBuffer contains a block
of image data and wrapping
that buffer of data is the
CVPixelBuffer wrapping.
And the CVPixelBuffer
wrapping tells you how
to access that data.
It's got the dimensions,
the width and the height.
It's got the pixel format,
everything you need in order
to correctly interpret
the pixel data.
Next, we've got the
CVPixelBufferPool.
The CVPixelBufferPool allows you
to efficiently recycle
CVPixelBuffer back ends.
Those data buffers can be very
expensive to constantly allocate
and de-allocate,
so PixelBufferPool allows
you to recycle them.
The way a PixelBufferPool works
is you allocate a CVPixelBuffer
from the pool and the
CVPixelBuffer is a ref
counted object.
When everyone releases
that CVPixelBuffer,
the data back end goes back
into the pool and it's available
for reuse next time you allocate
a pixel buffer from that pool.
Next thing is
pixelBufferAttributes.
This isn't actually a type,
like the rest of the things
in this list, but it's a
common object you'll see listed
in our interfaces.
You'll see requests
for pixelBufferAttributes
dictionaries.
pixelBufferAttributes are a
CF dictionary containing a set
of requirements for
either a CVPixelBuffer
or a PixelBufferPool.
This includes the, you can --
this can include several things.
This can include dimensions
that you're requesting,
the width and height.
This can include a specific
pixel format or a list
of pixel formats that
you'd like to receive.
And you can include specific
compatibility flags requesting
compatibility with specific
display technologies
such as OpenGL, OpenGL
ES or Core Animation.
All right.
Next, we've got CMTime.
CMTime is the basic
description of time
that you'll see in
your interfaces.
This is a rational
representation of a time value.
It contains a 64-bit time
value that's the numerator,
and a 32-bit time scale,
which is the denominator.
We use this sort of
rational representation
so that these time values can
be passed throughout your media
pipeline and you won't have to
do any sort of rounding on them.
All right.
Next, CMVideoFormatDescription.
You'll see this in a
bunch of our interfaces,
and a CMVideoFormatDescription
is basically a description
of video data.
This contains the dimensions.
This includes the pixel format
and there's a set of extensions
that go along with the
CMVideoFormatDescription.
These extensions can
include information to --
information used for
displaying that video data,
such as pixel aspect ratio,
and it can include
color space information.
And in the case of H.264 data,
the parameter sets are included
in these extensions
and we'll talk
about that more a
little bit later.
All right, next is
CMBlockBuffer.
CMBlockBuffer is the basic way
that we wrap arbitrary blocks
of data in Core Media.
In general, when you
encounter video data,
compressed video
data in our pipeline,
it will be wrapped
in a CMBlockBuffer.
All right, now we
have CMSampleBuffer.
You'll see CMSampleBuffer show
up a lot in our interfaces.
These wrap samples of data.
In the case of video,
CMSampleBuffers can wrap
either compressed video frames
or uncompressed video frames and
CMSampleBuffers build on several
of the types that we've
talked about here.
They contain a CMTime.
This is the presentation
time for the sample.
They contain a
CMVideoFormatDescription.
This describes the data
inside of the CMSampleBuffer.
And finally, in the case
of compressed video,
they contain a CMBlockBuffer
and the CMBlockBuffer has
the compressed video data.
And if it's an uncompressed
image in the CMSampleBuffer,
the uncompressed image
may be in a CVPixelBuffer
or it may be in a CMBlockBuffer.
All right.
Next, we've got CMClock.
CMClock is the Core Media
wrapper around a source
of time and, like the
clock on a wall --
there's no clocks on
the wall here, but --
like a clock on the wall,
time is always moving
and it's always increasing
on a CMClock.
One of the common clocks
that you'll see used
is the HostTimeClock.
So CMClockgetHostTimeClock will
return a clock which is based
on mach-absolute-time.
So CMClocks are hard to control.
You can't really control them.
As I mentioned, they're
always moving
and always at a constant rate.
So CMTimebase provides a more
controlled view onto a CMClock.
So if we go ahead and
create a CMClock based --
CMTimebase based on
the hostTime clock,
we could then set the time
to time zero on our timebase.
Now, time zero on our timebase
maps to the current time
on the CMClock, and you
can control the rate
of your timebase.
So if you were then to go and
set your timebase rate to one,
time will begin advancing on
your timebase at the same rate
at which the clock is advancing.
And CMTimebases can be
created based on CMClocks
or they can be created
based on other CMTimebases.
All right.
Let's hop into our
first use case.
This is the case where you
have a stream of data coming
in over the network and
since its video data coming
over the network, we can
safely assume it's a cat video
[applause] and so we've got
AVSampleBufferDisplayLayer,
which takes -- which can take
a sequence of compressed frames
and display it in a layer
inside of your application.
AVSampleBufferDisplayLayer
shipped
in Mavericks, and
it's new in iOS8.
So let's take a look inside
AVSampleBufferDisplayLayer.
As I mentioned, it takes
a -- a CM sample --
a sequence of compressed
frames as input and these need
to be in CMSampleBuffers.
Internally, it's going
to have a video decoder
and it will decode the
frames into CVPixelBuffers
and it will have a sequence
of CVPixelBuffers queued up,
ready to display
in your application
at the appropriate time.
But, I mentioned we were getting
our data off of the network.
A lot of times, when
you're getting a stream
of compressed video off the
network, it's going to be
in the form of an
elementary stream.
And I mentioned that CMSample --
uh, AVSampleBufferDisplayLayer
wants CMSampleBuffers
as its input.
Well, there's a little bit of
work that has to happen here
to convert your elementary
stream data
into CMSampleBuffers.
So let's talk about this.
H.264 defines a couple
of ways of packaging --
the H.264 spec defines a couple
of ways of packaging H.264 data.
The first one I'm going to refer
to as Elementary
Stream packaging.
This is used in elementary
streams, transport streams,
a lot of things with
streams in their name.
Next, is MPEG-4 packaging.
This is used in movie
files and MP4 files.
And in our interfaces that deal
with CMSampleBuffers, Core Media
and AVFoundation exclusively
want the data packaged
in MPEG-4 packaging.
So let's look closer
at an H.264 stream.
An H.264 stream consists
of a sequence of blocks
of data packaged in NAL Units.
These NAL Units can
contain several --
so this is the network
abstraction layer,
and these are Network
Abstraction Layer units.
These can contain a
few different things.
First off, they can
contain sample data.
So you could have -- a single
frame of video could be packaged
in one NAL Unit, or a frame
of video could be spread
across several NAL Units.
The other thing that NAL Units
can contain is parameter sets.
The parameter sets, the
Sequence Parameter Set
and Picture Parameter
Set, are chunks of data
which the decoder holds
on to and these apply
to all subsequent frames; well,
until a new parameter
set arrives.
So let's look at
Elementary Stream packaging.
Elementary Stream packaging,
in Elementary Stream packaging,
the parameter sets are included
in NAL Units right
inside the stream.
This is great if you're
doing sequential playback.
You read in your parameter
sets and they apply
to all subsequent frames until
a new frame or sets arrive.
MPEG-4 packaging has the NAL
Units pulled out and it's
in a separate block of data,
and this block of data is stored
in the CMVideoFormatDescription.
So as I mentioned,
each CMSampleBuffer references
this CMVideoFormatDescription.
That means each frame
of data has access
to the parameter sets.
This sort of packaging
is superior
for random access in a file.
It allows you to jump anywhere
and begin decoding
at an I frame.
So what do you have to do
if you have an Elementary
Stream coming in?
Well, we've got --
you've got a couple --
you've got your parameter sets
and NAL Units and you're going
to have to package those in
a CMVideoFormatDescription.
Well, we provide a handy
utility that does this for you;
CMVideoFormatDescription
CreatefromH264ParameterSets.
[ Applause ]
[ Laughs ]
All right, so the next
difference that we're going
to talk about between
an Elementary Stream
and MPEG-4 packaging
is in NAL Unit headers.
So each NAL Unit
in an the stream --
Elementary Stream will have a
three or four bytes start code
as the header and
in MPEG-4 packaging,
we have a length code.
So for each NAL Unit in your
stream, they're going --
you have to strip
off that start code
and replace it with
the length code.
That's the length
of the NAL Unit.
It's not that hard.
So let's talk about
building a CMSampleBuffer
from your Elementary Stream.
First thing you're going to have
to do is take your NAL Unit,
or NAL Units, and replace the
start code with a length code.
And you'll wrap that NAL
Unit in a CMBlockBuffer.
One note here, for simplicity,
I'm showing a single NAL Unit
but if you have a frame that
consists of several NAL Units,
you need to include
all of the NAL Units
in your CMSampleBuffer.
So you have a CMBlockBuffer.
You have your
CMVideoFormatDescription
that you created
from your initial --
from your parameter sets,
and throw in a CMTime value,
that's the presentation
time of your frame,
and you have everything
you need in order
to create a CMSampleBuffer
using CMSampleBufferCreate.
All right, let's talk
about AVSampleBufferDisplayLayer
and Time.
So as we saw,
all CMSampleBuffers have an
associated presentation time
stamp, and our video
decoder's going to be spitting
out CVPixelBuffers each with
an associated presentation
time stamp.
Well, how does it know when
to display these frames?
By default, it will be driven
off of the hostTime clock.
Well, that can be a
little bit hard to manage;
the hostTime clock isn't
really under your control.
So we allow you to
replace the hostTime clock
with your own timebase.
To do this you set the time -
y'know, in the example here,
we're creating a timebase
based on the hostTime clock
and we're setting that
as the control timebase
on our
AVSampleBufferDisplayLayer.
Here, we're setting the
timebase time to five,
which would mean our frame
whose time stamp is five will be
displayed in our layer,
and then we go ahead
and set the timebase
rate to one,
and now our timebase begins
moving at the same rate
as the hostTime clock,
and subsequent frames
will be displayed
at the appropriate time.
All right.
So providing the
CMSampleBuffers,
the SampleBufferDisplayLayer,
there's really two
major scenarios
that can describe this.
First off, there's
the periodic source.
This is the case where
you're getting frames
in at basically the same rate
at which they're being displayed
in the
AVSampleBufferDisplayLayer.
This would be the case
for a live streaming app
or live streaming
app with low latency
or video conferencing scenario.
The next case is the
unconstrained source.
This is the case where you have
a large set of CMSampleBuffers
at your disposal ready to feed
into the
AVSampleBufferDisplayLayer
at one time.
This would be the case
if you have a large cache
of buffered network data
or if you're reading the
CMSampleBuffers from a file.
All right, let's talk
about the first case.
This is really simple.
Frames are coming
in at the same rate
at which they're
being displayed.
You can go ahead and just
enqueue the sample buffers
with your
AVSampleBufferDisplayLayer
as they arrive.
You use the enqueueSampleBuffer
column.
All right.
The unconstrained source is a
little bit more complicated.
You don't want to just shove
all of those CMSampleBuffers
into the
AVSampleBufferDisplayLayer
at once.
No one will be happy with that.
What you want to do,
the AVSampleBufferDisplayLayer
can tell you when it's buffers -
it's internal buffers are
low and it needs more data
and you can ask it when
it has enough data.
The way you do this is
using the requestMediaData
WhenReadyOnQueue.
You provide a block
in this interface
and AVSampleBufferDisplayLayer
will call your block every time
its internal queues are
low and it needs more data.
Inside of that block,
you can go ahead
and loop while you're asking
whether it has enough data.
You use isReadyForMoreMediaData
column.
If it returns true, that means
it wants more SampleBuffers,
so you keep on feeding
SampleBuffers in.
As soon as it returns false,
that means it has
enough and you can stop.
So it's a pretty
simple loop to write.
All right.
Let's do a quick
summary of what we talked
about with
AVSampleBufferDisplayLayer.
At this point, you
should be able
to create an
AVSampleBufferDisplayLayer.
You've learned how to convert
your Elementary Stream H.264
data into CMSampleBuffers that
will happily be decompressed
by your
AVSampleBufferDisplayLayer.
We've talked about a
couple of scenarios
about how you would provide
these CMSampleBuffers
to your layer,
AVSampleBufferDisplayLayer.
And finally, we talked about
using a custom CMTimebase
with the
AVSampleBufferDisplayLayer.
All right.
So let's dive into
our second case.
This is the case where you have
a stream of H.264 data coming
in over the network, but you
don't want to just display it
in your application; you want
to actually decode those frames
and get the decompressed
pixel buffers.
So what we had
in AVSampleBufferDisplayLayer
contains a lot
of the pieces we need.
But instead of accessing
the video decoder
through the
AVSampleBufferDisplayLayer,
we'll access it through
the VTDecompressionSession.
Like the
AVSampleBufferDisplayLayer,
VTDecompressionSession wants
CMSampleBuffers as its input.
And it will decode
the CMSampleBuffers
to CVPixelBuffers
and receive those
in the OutputCallback
that you implement.
So in order to create a
VTDecompressionSession,
you'll need a few things.
First, you need to
provide a description
of the source buffers that
you'll be decompressing.
This is a
CMVideoFormatDescription.
If you're decompressing
from an Elementary Stream,
you've created this from
your parameter sets,
if you just have a
CMSampleBuffer that you want
to decompress you can pull it
straight off the CMSampleBuffer.
Next, you need to
describe your requirements
for your output pixelBuffers.
You use a pixelBufferAttributes
dictionary for this.
And finally, you need
to implement a
VTDecompressionOutputCallback.
All right.
Let's talk about
describing your requirements
for the output pixelBuffers.
Here, you need to create
a PixelBufferAttributes
dictionary.
So let's look at a
scenario where we want
to use the Output CVPixelBuffers
in an open GLS ES
render pipeline.
Really, the only
requirement here that we have
for our Output PixelBuffers is
that they be OpenGL
ES compatible.
So we can go ahead and
just create a CFDictionary
or NSDictionary specifying
the kCVPixelBufferOpen
GLESCompatibilityKey
and set it to true.
So it can be very tempting to,
when you're creating these
PixelBufferAttributes
dictionaries, to
be very specific.
That way, there's no
surprises about what you get
out of the
VTDecompressionSession,
but there's some pitfalls here.
So let's look at this case
where we had kCVPixelBufferOpen
GLESCompatibilityKey set
to true.
Here, our decompression
session --
the decoder inside of our
decompression session is going
to be decoding the frames and
outputting YUV CVPixelBuffers.
In the VTDecompressionSession
we'll then ask, is this --
well, it'll ask itself, "is
this PixelBuffer compatible
with those requested
attributes?"
And the answer is yes.
That YUV frame is OpenGL ES
compatible so it can return
that directly to your callback.
But let's say you were
possessed to add BGRA request
to your PixelBufferAttributes.
So just like before,
the decoder inside
of our VTDecompressionSession
will decode to a YUV format
and will ask whether this
CVPixelBuffer is compatible
with the requested
output requirements.
And it is OpenGL ES compatible,
but it's certainly not BGRA.
So it will need to do an
extra buffer copy to convert
that YUV data to BGRA data.
So extra buffer copies are bad.
They decrease efficiency
and they can lead
to decreased battery life.
So the moral story here is --
be, uh -- don't over specify.
All right, let's talk
about your Output Callback.
So the Output Callback is
where you'll receive the
decoded CVPixelBuffers
and CVPixelBuffers don't
have a built in time stamp,
so you'll receive the
presentation time stamp
for that PixelBuffer here.
And if there are errors or the
frame is dropped for any reason,
you'll receive that information
in the Output Callback.
And it's important to note
that the Output Callback will
be called for every single frame
that you push into the
VTDecompressionSession even
if there's an error,
even if it's dropped.
All right, let's talk
about providing frames
to your VTDecompressionSession.
To do that, you call
VTDecompression
SessionDecodeFrame.
Just like
AVSampleBufferDisplayLayer,
you need to provide these as
CMSampleBuffers, and you need
to provide these
frames in decode order.
And by default,
VTDecompressionSession
DecodeFrame will
operate synchronously.
This means that your
OutputCallback will be called
before VTDecompression
SessionDecodeFrame returns.
If you want asynchronous
operation, you can pass
in the flag requesting
EnableAsynchronous
Decompression.
All right, let's talk about
asynchronous decompression then.
With ASynchronousDecompression,
the call
to VTDecompressionSession
DecodeFrame returns as soon
as it hands the frame
off to the decoder.
But decoders often have limited
pipelines for decoding frames.
So when the decoder's
internal pipeline is full,
the call to VTDecompression
SessionDecodeFrame will block
until space opens up in
the decoders pipeline.
We call this decoder
back pressure.
So what this means is that
even though you're calling
VTDecompressionSession
DecodeFrame
and requesting Asynchronous
Decompression,
we will be doing the
decompression asynchronously
but the call can still
block (in some cases).
So be aware of that.
You're doing
AsynchronousDecompression
but the call can block, so don't
perform UI tasks on that thread.
All right, if you find yourself
in a situation where you want
to ensure that all asynchronous
frames have been cleared
out of the decoder, you can
call VTDecompressionSession
and WaitForAsynchronousFrames.
This call will not return until
all frames have been omitted
from the decompression session.
So, sometimes, while
decoding a sequence
of video frames there
will be a change
in the CMVideoFormatDescription.
So let's look at the case
where we had a sequence
of an Elementary Stream
and we created the
first format description
out of the first parameter
sets that we encountered.
So now we have format
description one
with our first SPS and PPS.
We can go ahead and create
our VTDecompressionSession
with that format description and
decode all the subsequent frames
with that format description
attached to the CMSampleBuffer
until we encounter a new
SPS and PPS in the stream.
Then, we need to create
a new format description
with that new -- the new SPS
and PPS and we have to make sure
that the decompression
session can switch
between these format
descriptions.
So to do that, you call
VTDecompressionSession
CanAcceptFormatDescription.
This will ensure -- ask the
decoder whether it's able
to transition from
FormatDescription one
to FormatDescription two.
If the answer is true (yes,
it can handle the new
accepted FormatDescription)
that means you can
pass subsequent samples
with that new FormatDescription
attached to them
into the Decompression Session
and everything will work fine.
If it returns false, that
means the decompressor cannot
transition from that
first format description
to the second format
description, and you'll need
to create a new
VTDecompressionSession
and be sure to -- and pass
the new frames into that one.
And be sure to release that
old VTDecompressionSession
when you're no longer using it.
All right.
Quick summary of what we talked
about with
VTDecompressionSession.
We talked about creating the
VTDecompressionSession and how
to make optimal decisions when
creating your PixelBuffer--
ah, your PixelBufferAttributes
dictionary
for specifying your
output requirements.
We talked about running your
decompression session both
synchronously and
asynchronously and we talked
about handing changes in
CMVideo FormatDescription.
So. With that, let's
hop into case three.
This is the case where you
have a stream of CVPixelBuffers
or frames coming in from a
camera or another source,
and you want to compress those
directly into a movie file.
Well, for this -- you may be
familiar with this already --
we have AVAssetWriter.
AVAssetWriter has an encoder
internally, and it's going
to be encoding those
frames into CMSampleBuffers
and it's got some
file writing smarts,
so it can write these
optimally into a movie file.
We're not actually going to
talk more, at this point,
about AVAssetWriter, but
it's an important concept
and an important thing to bring
up in the context of this talk,
so if you want more information
on the AVAssetWriter,
you can go back to WWDC 2013
and the talk "Moving to AVKit
and AVFoundation" or 2011,
"Working with Media
and AVFoundation."
All right.
Let's just hop straight
into case four.
This is the case where you
have that stream of data coming
in from your camera and
you want to compress it,
but you don't want to
write into a movie file.
You want direct access to
those compressed SampleBuffers.
So we want to approach
our video encoder
through a VTCompressionSession
rather
than through the AVAssetWriter.
So just like the AVAssetWriter,
VTCompressionSession takes
CVPixelBuffers as its input,
and it's going to compress those
and return CMSampleBuffers,
and we can go ahead and send
that compressed data
out over the network.
So to create a
VTCompressionSession,
you'll need a few things,
and this is really simple.
You just need to specify
the dimensions you want
for your compressed output.
You need to tell us what
format you want to compress to,
such as kCMVideoCodec
Type-H.264,
and you can optionally
provide a set
of PixelBufferAttributes
describing your source
CVPixelBuffers that
you'll be sending
to the VTCompressionSession.
And finally, you need
to implement a VTCompression
OutputCallback.
So you've created a
VTCompressionSession.
Now you want to configure it.
You configure a
VTCompressionSession
using VTSessionSetProperty.
In fact, you can
have a whole sequence
of VTSessionSetProperty calls.
So I'm going to go through a few
common properties here and, but,
this is not an exhaustive list.
The first one I'm going to
mention is AllowFrameReordering.
By default, H.264 encoder will
allow frames to be reordered.
That means the presentation
time stamp that you pass them
in will not necessarily
equal the decode order
in which they're emitted.
If you want to disable this
behavior, you can pass false
to allow frame reordering.
Next one: AverageBitRate.
This is how you set a target
bit rate for the compressor.
H264EntropyMode -- using this,
you can specify CAVLC
compression or kVTH compression
for your H.264 encoder.
All right, and then there's
the RealTime property.
The RealTime property allows
you to tell the encoder
that this is a real-time
encoding operation (such
as in a live streaming case,
conferencing case) as opposed
to more of a background activity
(like a transcode operation).
And the final one I'm going
to mention here is
the ProfileLevel key.
This allows you to specify
specific profiles and levels
or specific profiles and allow
us to choose the correct level.
And this is definitely
not an exhaustive list.
There's a lot of these options
available, so go ahead and look
in VTCompressionProperties.H
and see what we have for you.
All right, let's talk about
providing CVPixelBuffers
to your VTCompressionSession.
Use VTCompressionSession
EncodeFrame to do this,
and you'll need to provide
CVPixelBuffers and, CV --
as I've mentioned,
CVPixelBuffers don't have a
presentation time stamp built
into them, so as a
separate parameter,
you'll provide the
presentation time stamp.
You need to feed the frames
in in presentation order.
And it's -- one more note about
the presentation order: they --
the presentation time
stamps must be increasing.
No duplicate presentation
time stamps,
no time stamps that
go backwards.
And so compression sessions --
compression operations usually
require a window of frames
that they'll operate on, so
your output may be delayed.
So you may not receive
a compressed frame
in your output callback
until a certain number
of frames have been
pushed into the encoder.
All right.
And finally, if you've
reached the end of the frames
that you're passing to the
compression session and you want
to have it emit all of the
frames that it's received
so far, you can use
VTCompressionSession
CompleteFrames.
All pending frames
will be omitted.
All right.
Let's talk about
your output callback.
So your OutputCallback is
where you'll receive your
output CMSampleBuffers.
These contain the
compressed frames.
If there were any errors or
dropped frames, you'll receive
that information here.
And final thing, frames will
be emitted in decode order.
So you provided frames to
the VTCompressionSession
in presentation order
and they'll be emitted
in decode order.
All right.
Well, so you've compressed
a bunch of frames.
They're now compressed
in CMSampleBuffers,
which means that they're
using MPEG-4 packaging.
And you want to send that
out over the network,
which means you may
need to switch these
over to Elementary
Stream packaging.
Well, once again,
you're going to have
to do a little bit of work.
So we talked about the
parameter sets before.
So the parameters sets will
-- in your MPEG-4 package,
H.264 will be in the
CMVideoFormatDescription.
So the first thing
you're going to have
to do is extract those
parameter sets and package them
as NAL Units to send
out over the network.
Well, we provide a handy
utility for that too.
CMVideoFormatDescription
GetH.264ParameterSetAtIndex.
All right, and the next thing
you need to do is the opposite
of what we did with
AVSampleBufferDisplayLayer.
Our NAL Units are all going
to have length headers
and you're going to need
to convert those length
headers into start codes.
So as you extract each NAL Unit
from the compressed data
inside the CMSampleBuffer,
convert those headers
on the NAL Units.
All right.
Quick summary of what we talked
about with the
VTCompressionSession.
We talked about creating
the VTCompressionSession.
We've talked about how
to configure it using the
VTSessionSetProperty column.
And we talked about how you
would provide CVPixelBuffers
to the compression session.
And finally, we talked about
converting those CMSampleBuffers
into an H.264 Elementary
Stream packaging.
All right.
And with that, I'd like
to hand things off to Eric
so he can talk about Multi-Pass.
>> Good morning everyone.
My name is Eric Turnquist.
I'm the Core Media Engineer,
and today, I want to talk to you
about Multi-Pass Encoding.
So as a media engineer, we often
deal with two opposing forces;
quality versus bit rate.
So quality is how pristine
the image is, and we all know
when we've seen great quality
video and we really don't
like seeing bad quality video.
Bit rate is how much
data per time is
in the output media file.
So let's say we're
preparing some content.
If you're like me, you go
for high quality first.
So great, we have high quality.
Now in this case, what
happens with the bit rate?
Well unfortunately, if you have
high quality, you also tend
to have a high bit rate.
Now that's okay,
but not what we want
if we're streaming this content
or storing it on a server.
So in that case we
want to a low bit rate
but the quality isn't
going to stay this high.
Unfortunately, that's also
going to go down as well.
So we've all seen this as
blocky encoder artifacts
or an output image that
doesn't really even look
like the source.
We don't want this either.
Ideally, we want
something like this;
high quality and low bit rate.
In order to achieve that goal,
we've added Multi-Pass Encoding
to AVFoundation and
Video Toolbox.
[ Applause ]
Yeah. So first off, what
is Multi-Pass Encoding?
Well, let's do a review of what
Single-Pass Encoding is first.
So this is what David covered
in his portion of the talk.
With Single-Pass Encoding,
you have frames coming in,
going into the encoder
and being emitted.
In this case, we're
going to a movie file.
Then once you're done appending
all the samples, we're finished,
and we're left with
our output movie file.
Simple enough.
Let's see how multi-pass
differs.
So you have uncompressed
frames coming in going,
into the compression
session, being emitted
as compressed samples.
Now we're going to change
things up a little bit.
So we're going to have
our Frame Database.
This will store the
compressed samples
and allow us random
access and replacement,
which is important
for multi-pass.
And we're going to have
our Encoder Database;
this will store frame analysis.
So we're done appending
for one pass,
and the encoder will decide I
think, "I can actually do better
in another pass, so I can tweak
the parameters a little bit
to get better quality."
It will request some
samples and you'll go through
and send those samples
again to the encoder,
and then it may decide I'm
done or I'm actually --
or, I want more passes.
In this case, let's
assume that we're finished.
So we no longer need
the encoder database
or the compression
session, but we're left
with this Frame Database
and we want a movie file,
so we need one more step.
There's a final copy
from the Frame Database
to the output movie
file and that's it.
We have a multi-pass encoded
video track on a movie file.
Cool. Let's go over
some encoder features.
So my first point is -- I
want to make a note of --
is David said that Single-Pass
is hardware accelerated
and multi-pass is also
hardware accelerated,
so you're not losing any
hardware acceleration there.
Second point is that multi-pass
has knowledge of the future.
No, it's not some crazy,
time-traveling video encoder.
(Bonus points: whoever files
that enhancement request!)
It allows, or -- is able
to see your entire content.
So in Single-Pass, as frames
come in, the encoder has
to make assumptions about
what might come next.
In multi-pass, it's already
seen all your content
so it can make much
better decisions there.
Third, it can change
decisions that it's made.
So in Single-Pass, as soon as
the frame is emitted, that's it.
It can't -- it can no
longer change, uh --
Yeah, it can no longer
change its mind
about what it's emitted.
In multi-pass, because the frame
database supports replacement,
each pass you can go through
and change its mind about how
to achieve optimal quality.
And as a result of this,
you really get optimal
quality per bit, so it's sort
of like having a very awesome
custom encoder for your content.
So that's how multi-pass
works and some new features.
Let's talk about new APIs.
So first off, let's
talk about AVFoundation.
In AVFoundation, we have a new
AVAssetExportSession property.
We have new pass descriptions
for AVAssetWriterInput
and we have reuse on
AVAssetReaderOutput.
So first, let's go
over an overview
of AVAssetExportSession.
In AVAssetExportSession, you're
going from a source file,
decoding them, then
performing some operation
on those uncompressed buffers --
something like scaling
or color conversion,
and you're encoding them and
writing them to a movie file.
So in this case, what does
AVAssetExportSession provide?
Well, it does all this for you.
It's the easiest way to
transcode media on iOS and OS X.
So let's see what
we've added here.
So in AVAssetExportSession
multiple passes are taken care
of for you automatically.
There's no work that
you have to do
to send the samples
between passes.
And also, it falls
back to Single-Pass
if multi-pass isn't supported.
So if you choose a
preset that uses a codec
where multi-pass isn't
supported, don't worry,
it'll use Single-Pass.
And we have one new
property; set this to yes
and you're automatically opted
into multi-pass, and that's it.
So for a large majority of
you, this is all you need.
Next, let's talk
about AVAssetWriter.
So AVAssetWriter, you're coming
from uncompressed samples.
You want to compress them and
write them to a movie file.
You might be coming from an
OpenGL or OpenGL ES context.
In this case, what does
AVAssetWriter provide?
Well, it wraps this portion,
going from the encoder
to the output movie file.
Another use case, it's
similar to AVAssetExportSession
where you're going from
a source movie file
to a destination
output movie file
and modifying the
buffers in some way.
Well in this case, you're going
to use an AVAssetReaderOutput
and an AVAssetWriterInput.
You're responsible for sending
samples from one to the other.
Let's go over our new
AVAssetWriterInput APIs.
So like AVAssetExportSession,
you need to enable multi-pass,
so set this to yes and you're
automatically opted in.
Then after you're done
appending samples,
you need to mark the
current pass as finished.
So what does this do?
Well, this triggers
the encoder analysis.
The encoder needs to decide if I
need to perform multiple passes
and if so, what time ranges.
So the encoder might say,
"I want to see the entire
sequence again," or "I want
to see subsets of the sequence."
So how does the encoder talk
about what time ranges it
wants for the next pass?
Well, that's through
an AVAssetWriter
InputPassDescription.
So in this case, we have time
from 0 to 3, but not the sample
at time 3, and samples from 5 to
7, but not the sample at time 7.
So a pass description is the
encoder's request for media
in the next pass, and it may
contain the entire sequence
or subsets of the sequence.
On a pass description, you
can query the time ranges
that the encoder has requested
by calling sourceTimeRanges.
All right, let's talk about
how AVAssetWriterInput uses
pass descriptions.
So when you trigger the encoder
analysis, the encoder needs
to reply with what
decisions it's made.
So you provide a block on this
method to allow the encoder
to give you that answer.
So this block is called when
the encoder makes a decision
about the next pass.
In that block, you can get
the new pass description,
the encoder's decision
about what content it
wants for the next pass.
Let's see how that
works all in a sample.
So here's our sample.
We have our block
callback that your provide.
Inside that callback you
call currentPassDescription.
This asks the encoder
what time ranges it wants
for the next pass.
If the pass is non-nil
(meaning the encoder wants data
for another pass) you
reconfigure your source.
So this is where the
source will send samples
to the AVAssetWriterInput,
and then you prepare
the AVAssetWriterInput
for the next pass.
You're already familiar
with requestMediaData
WhenReadyOnQueue.
If the pass is nil, that means
the encoder has finished passes.
Then you're done.
You can mark your
input as finished.
All right, let's say you're
going from a source media file.
That was in our second example.
So we have new APIs for
AVAssetReaderOutput.
You can prepare your
source for multi-pass
by saying supportsRandomAccess
equals yes.
Then when the encoder
wants new time ranges,
you need to reconfigure
your AVAssetReaderOutput
to deliver those time ranges.
So that's
resetForReadingTimeRanges
with an NSArray of time ranges.
Finally, when all
passes have completed you
callMarkConfigurationAsFinal.
This allows the
AVAssetReaderOutput
to transition to
its completed state
so it can start tearing
itself down.
Right. Now there's a couple
short cuts you can use
if you're using AVAssetReader
and AVAssetWriter
in combination together.
So you can enable an
AVAssetReaderOutput
if the AVAssetWriterInput
supports multi-pass.
So if the encoder
supports multi-pass,
we need to support random
access on the source.
Then you can reconfigure your
source to deliver samples
for the AVAssetWriterInput.
So with your readerOutput
call resetForReadingTimeRanges
with the pass description's
time ranges.
Let's go over that
in the sample.
So instead of delivering
for an arbitrary source,
we now want to deliver for
our AVAssetReaderOuput.
So we call
resetForReadingTimeRanges
with the pass description
sourceTimeRanges.
Great. So that's the new API
and AVFoundation for multi-pass.
Let's talk next about
Video Toolbox.
So in Video Toolbox, our
encoder frame analysis database,
we like to call this
our VTMultiPassStorage.
We also have additions
to VTCompressionSession,
which David introduced in
his portion of the talk,
and decompressed frame database,
or as we call it,
the VTFrameSilo.
So let's go over
the architecture,
but this time replacing
the frame database
and the encoder database
with the objects
that we actually use.
So in this case, we
have our VTFrameSilo
and our VTMultiPassStorage.
We're done with this pass.
The encoder wants to
see samples again.
We're sending in those
samples that it requests.
Then we're finished and we can
tear down the VTMultiPassStorage
and the compression session and
we're left with our FrameSilo.
So this is where we
need to perform the copy
from the FrameSilo to
the output movie file.
Great, we have our
output movie file.
So first off, let's go over
what the VTMultiPassStorage is.
So this is the encoder analysis.
This is a pretty simple API.
First you create the storage
and then you close the
file once you're finished.
So that's all the API
that you need to use.
The data that's stored in
this is private to the encoder
and you don't have
to worry about it.
Next, let's talk about additions
to VTCompressionSession.
So first, you need to tell
the VTCompressionSession
and the encoder about
your VTMultiPassStorage.
So you can do that by
setting a property.
This will tell the
encoder to use MultiPass
and use this VTMultiPassStorage
for its frame analysis.
Next, we've added a couple
functions for multi-pass.
So you call beginPass before
you've appended any frames then
after you're done
appending frames
for that pass, you call endPass.
EndPass also asks the encoder if
another pass can be performed.
So if another -- if the
encoder wants another pass
to be performed then you need
to ask it what time ranges
of samples it wants
for the next pass.
That's called
VTCompressionSession
GetTimeRangesFor NextPass
and you're given a count
and a C array of time ranges.
Now let's talk about
the VTFrameSilo.
So this is the compressed
frame store.
So like the other objects you
created, and then you want
to add samples to
this VTFrameSilo.
So frames will automatically
be replaced
if they have the same
presentation time stamp
and how this data is stored
is abstracted away from you
and you don't need
to worry about it.
It's a convenient
database for you to use.
Then you can prepare the
VTFrameSilo for the next pass.
This optimizes the
storage for the next pass.
Finally, let's talk about
the copy from the VTFrameSilo
to the output movie file.
So you can retrieve samples
for a given time range.
This allows you to get a
sample in a block callback
that you provide and add it
to your output movie file.
All right, that's the
new Video Toolbox APIs.
So I want to close with
a couple considerations.
So we've talked about
how multi-pass works
and what APIs you can use in
AVFoundation and Video Toolbox,
but we need to talk
about your use cases
and your priority in your app.
So if you're performing
real time encoding,
you should be using single-pass.
Real time encoding has
very specific deadlines
of how much compression can take
and multi-pass will perform
more passes over the time range,
so use Single-Pass
in these cases.
If you're concerned about
using the minimum amount
of power during encoding,
use single-pass.
Multiple passes will
take more power and,
as will the encoder analysis.
If you're concerned with
using the minimum amount
of temporary storage
during the encode
or transcode operation,
use single-pass.
The encoder analysis storage
and the frame database
will use more storage
than the output media file.
However, if you're concerned
about having the best quality
for your content,
multi-pass is a great option.
If you want to be as close to
the target bit rate you set
on the VTCompressionSession
or AssetWriter
as possible, use multi-pass.
Multi-pass can see all of the
portions of your source media
and so it can allocate bits
only where it needs to.
It's very smart in this sense.
If it's okay to take longer
in your app (so if it's okay
for the encoder transfer
operation to take longer
for better quality)
multi-pass is a good option.
But the biggest takeaway
is that in your app,
you need to experiment.
So you need to think about
your use cases and your users
and if they're willing to wait
longer for better quality.
Next, let's talk about content.
So if you, if your
app has low quality --
or, low complexity
content, think of this
like a title sequence or
a static image sequence.
Both single-pass and
multi-pass are going
to both give you
great quality here,
but multi-pass won't give
you much better quality
than single-pass.
These are both pretty
easy to encode.
Next, let's talk about
high complexity content.
So think of this as classic
encoder stress tests;
water, fire, explosions.
We all love to do
this, but single-pass
and multi-pass are
both going to do well,
but multi-pass probably won't
do much better than single-pass.
These are -- this kind
of content is hard
for encoders to encode.
Where is multi-pass
a better decision?
Well, that's in varying
complexity, so think of this
as a feature-length
movie or a documentary
in Final Cut Pro or
an iMovie trailer.
They might have low complexity
regions, a title sequence,
high complexity transitions.
Because there's a lot of
different kinds of content,
multi-pass is able to
analyze those sections
and really give you the
best quality per bit.
But again, the message
is: with your content,
you need to experiment.
So you know your content
and you should know
if multi-pass will give you a
good benefit in these cases.
So let's go over what
we've talked about today.
AVFoundation provides powerful
APIs to operate on media,
and for most of you, these are
the APIs you will be using.
And when you need
the extra power,
Video Toolbox APIs provide
you direct media access.
If you fall into one of the use
cases that David talked about,
this is a good way
to use Video Toolbox.
Finally, multi-pass can
provide substantial quality
improvements, but you need
to think about your app,
your use cases and your
users before you enable it.
So for more information,
here's our Evangelism email.
You have AVFoundation
Documentation
and a programming guide.
We can answer your questions
on the developer forums.
For those of you that
are watching online,
a lot of these talks
have already happened.
If you're here live, so these
are the talks you might be
interested in.
Thanks everyone and have
a good rest of your day.
[ Applause ]