>> Welcome everyone.
Welcome. Welcome to WWDC,
and welcome to our
Introductory Session
about Working with Metal.
Now we're incredibly
excited to get to talk
to you today about Metal.
We believe it's literally going
to be a game changer for you,
your applications, and for iOS.
Now as you've heard
in the keynote,
Metal is our new
low-overhead, high-performance,
and incredibly efficient
GPU programming API.
It provides dramatically reduced
overhead for executing work
such as graphics and
compute on a GPU.
And with the support
for precompiled shaders
and incredibly efficient
multithreading, we designed it
to run like a dream
on the A7 chip.
Now today in this session,
I'm going to talk to you
at a relatively high level
about the background, the how
and why we created
Metal and some
of the conceptual
framework for the API.
I'll also touch briefly on
the Metal shading language
and our developer tools.
The sessions that follow
will go into much more detail
about exactly how to use
the Metal API and how
to build your applications,
but we'll keep things
at a high level for
this session.
So, first, a bit of
background on Metal itself.
Now you also heard in the
keynote that Metal provides
up to 10x the number of draw
calls for your application.
Now what does that really mean?
Well, it's important to think
about draw calls in this way:
each draw call requires its
own graphics state vector.
So when you're specifying that
you would like to draw something
with the GPU, you also need
to tell the GPU which shaders,
which states, how you want
to configure the textures
and the rendering destinations.
This is very important in order
to get the effect you're
looking for from the GPU.
But, unfortunately,
with previous APIs
changing state vectors,
it'd be extremely expensive.
You have to translate between
the API state and the state
that the hardware's
going to consume.
When I say expensive, I mean,
not for the GPU, but for the CPU
because it's the CPU that's
doing that type of translation.
So let's take a look
at a quick example.
If your application is
setting up for a new draw call,
you'll want to specify
the shaders and the state
and the textures for each
draw operation, and you'll do
that each time you want to
specify a new draw call.
And then the CPU gets
involved and spends a bunch
of time translating those state
changes and those requests
to draw into hardware commands
before sending it to the GPU.
So if we had a way to make
that much less expensive,
we could give you a lot
more draw calls per frame,
and you might ask
yourself, well,
why do I want more
draw calls per frame?
Well, more draw calls lets
you build much better games
and applications.
You can build many
more unique objects,
have many more bad guys, or
other characters in the scene.
You can add a lot more
visual variety to your games.
But probably the most important
reason is your game artists
and designers are going
to thank you profusely
because you're going to
give them more freedom
to realize their vision without
having to jump through all types
of draw call gymnastics to fit
what they'd like to see onscreen
into a tiny number
of draw calls.
Now let's take a
little bit of a look
at what life was
like before Metal.
Now, Apple has a long history
of GPU programming APIs,
both implementing them,
maintaining them,
developing them.
We've supported standard
APIs like OpenGL and OpenCL.
We've supported APIs across
a wide variety of domains,
both at the high level and the
low level of GP programming
for things like 2D, 3D,
animations, and image
processing.
And we've supported a wide
variety of architectures
in the hardware, across
platforms, computers, devices,
phones, iPads, and a
wide variety of GPUs.
And during all this time,
as we're supporting all
of this variety, we realized
that there was something pretty
fundamental missing from all
of these APIs, and that was
the level of deep integration
that Apple brings
to its products.
Now Apple, as you know,
provides the operating system,
the hardware, and the
products as a complete package.
They're designed to work
together seamlessly.
And so we thought to ourselves:
what if we could take the same
approach to GPU programming
that we take to our
products as a whole?
If we could build these
to work seamlessly,
we knew we could do the
same for GPU programming,
and that's what we've
done with Metal.
Now as I said, we have a
long history of looking
at these different types
of programming APIs,
and we realized that if we
wanted to get a tenfold --
an order of magnitude --
improvement in performance,
we're going to have to do
some pretty radical things.
We decided to take a clean
sheet approach to this design,
and the key design goals that
we had were outlined here.
First, we knew we wanted to
have the thinnest possible API
that we could create.
We wanted to be --
reduce the amount of code
that was executing in
between your application
and the GPU to a bare minimum.
We knew it needed to
support the most modern GPU
hardware features.
We didn't want it bogged down
with the cruft of 20 years
of previous GPU designs.
We wanted it focused entirely
and squarely on the future.
We knew that there were some
expensive CPU operations
that needed to take place, but
we wanted to carefully control
when those happen and
make sure they happen
as infrequently as possible.
And we wanted to give
you, the developer,
predictable performance so
you would know exactly when
and how those expensive
operations could take place.
We wanted to give
you explicit control
over when the work was executed
on the GPU, so you could decide
when and how to kick off that
work, and never be surprised
by what the implementation
might do behind your back.
And, last but not least, we
knew it had to be highly,
highly optimized for
the A7 CPU behavior
as this will become
key in a few moments.
So how to think about Metal.
Well, where does it fit?
Well, let's say you have your
application here represented
at the top of this
diagram in green,
and you'd like to
talk to the GPU.
Well, Apple provides a wide
variety of APIs to do just that,
but they come at different
levels of abstraction,
different levels of
conceptual distance
between you and the GPU.
So at a high level, you have
awesome APIs like SceneKit
and SpriteKit that give high
level services for scene graphs
for 2D and 3D animations,
and they're great.
They provide a lot of services,
but they are relatively far
from the GPU in terms
of abstraction.
And then, of course, we have
our 2D graphics and imaging APIs
such as Core Animation, Core
Image, and Core Graphics,
and these, too, provide
a lot of services.
And if this is the type
of operation you're doing,
these are perfect APIs for you.
And, as always, we have the
standards-based 3D graphics
approach with OpenGL ES.
But when we wanted to
do something better,
and to give you high
efficiency GPU access
at the thinnest possible
API layer,
that's where Metal comes in.
So how do we do this?
Well, first thing we wanted
to understand is how
most modern games try
to manage their CPU
and GPU workloads.
So most games will
target a frame rate.
Oftentimes, it could
be 60 frames a second,
sometimes at 30.
In this example, we're using
30, which works out to be
about 33.3 milliseconds
per frame.
Now on this timeline, you can
see how most games would try
to optimize for this
type of timeline.
They'll try to balance the
amount of CPU work and the type
of GPU work to fill the entire
frame, but they'll do so offset.
So the CPU will be working
and generating commands
for one frame, and the GPU will
then consume those commands
in the next frame, and
while the CPU is doing that,
the GPU is busily working on the
previous frame, and you lay this
out on a timeline, and you
can see how you get relatively
perfect parallelism.
Well, let's look at one frame
in particular, and you'll notice
in this example we're assuming
a completely balanced frame
where the CPU and the GPU are
occupying all of the time.
Now, unfortunately, real life
is not quite so balanced,
and oftentimes you'll find
that the CPU can take more time
to generate these commands than
the GPU does to consume them,
and this is unfortunate because
it often leaves the GPU idle.
So you're not even using the
system to its fullest capacity,
and if you were, it would be
like having a 50
percent faster GPU,
but it's just sitting
there dark.
So you say to yourself, "Well,
I'd like to fix this problem.
I'm just going to give more work
to the GPU", and, unfortunately,
what you'll find is that to give
more work to the GPU you have
to first spin up
more work on the CPU.
And if you were already bound by
the amount of work you could do
on the CPU, this pushes out
your frame time even further.
Now we're below our 30
frames per second target.
And to add insult to
injury, the GPU is still idle
because now our frame
time is actually longer,
and the GPU can't
fill that work either.
So to understand what's
happening here, it's helpful
to realize that the CPU
workload is actually split
into two parts.
You have the applications
workload (what you guys are
providing) and then you have
all the implementation work
for the GPU API itself.
So whenever you make a
GPU programming call,
we're going to have to translate
that in the way I
described earlier.
Well, it's this GPU
programming API time on the CPU
that we're focused
on with Metal,
and Metal dramatically
reduces this time
down to a bare minimum.
Now in this example,
we've actually freed
up additional CPU time.
Now it's the CPU that's idle,
and our frame time has
become limited by the GPU,
and we're actually beating our
30 frames per second target.
So if that was your goal,
you can now Render faster
than 30 frames per second,
but you have another option.
You can actually use that
CPU time to improve your game
and make it even better.
You could add more physics,
or more AI in, or other types
of workloads to your
application.
We have a little bit of
CPU idle time here left.
We can actually choose
to go back
to our 30 frames
per second target,
and add even more draw calls
with Metal providing you
up to a 10x increase
in efficiency,
and you can either draw
more things with the GPU,
or maybe just draw them in
a much more flexible manner
so you can get more
visual variety.
So that's what we're
trying to do with Metal.
Now why is this GPU programming
so expensive on the CPU?
To understand what we did
with Metal, it's helpful
to take a deeper look here, too,
and there are 3 main reasons.
First, you have what's
called state validation.
Now some people think state
validation is just having the
implementation verify that
you're calling the API
in the right way and
that's certainly true,
but it also involves encoding
the state from the API
to the hardware and translating
it and oftentimes looking
at different aspects
of the state
and different state objects in
the API and figuring out how
to combine them into a way
that the hardware's
going to understand.
This can be expensive,
and perhaps the most
expensive version
of this is actually the
shader compilation itself.
So you take your source
code shaders for your vertex
and pixel shaders, and they
have to be compiled at run time
and to generate the
GPU's machine code.
What's worse is that in a lot
of APIs before Metal, the state
and the shader code was not
described in the API in a way
that really mapped well to what
the hardware actually was going
to expect.
And so when you change
certain states, you could find
that behind the scenes,
we actually had to go back
and recompile your shaders,
causing even more CPU work.
And, last, they're sending
the work to the GPU itself,
and this can be expensive.
The resources, the memory, the
textures have to all be managed
and given to the GPU in
the way it can expect.
And because those first
two items are so expensive,
we often have encouraged you
with previous APIs to batch
up lots of work to send --
to try to amortize
these expensive costs
across a fewer number
of draw calls
and just give more per
draw call to the GPU.
And, of course, this tends to
work at the cost of flexibility
to you, the developer, and
to your game designers,
but it also increases latency
because now the GPU has more
to work on in a single chunk.
So we wanted to fix
these 3 key areas
of expense for GPU programming.
To do that, we thought
about 3 times, 3 occurrences
in the application life
cycle to focus in on.
There's the application
build time,
there's when you're loading
the content for your game,
and then when, there's
when you draw.
And they occur at
different frequencies.
So, first, application
build time.
This basically never occurs.
I see some surprised
look on your faces
because as developers you think
you're building your application
all the time, and that's true.
But from your customer's
perspective,
from the people using
your application,
they never see this.
So if we can move things to
occur at application build time,
you've just eliminated
this expense
from the experience
of your game.
And then you have
content loading time,
which is relatively rare, again,
from a user's perspective.
They're only going to load a
level a few times per play.
You have draw calls,
on the other hand...
you're going to do this
thousands (ideally thousands)
of times per frame.
And before Metal, unfortunately,
all three of those
expensive bits of operations
for the CPU occurred in this
last time, at draw call time.
Thousands of time per
frame, or more likely,
a few hundred times per frame
because that's all
the CPU could absorb.
Now with metal, we've moved
these expensive operations
to occur much more optimally.
So you put shader compilation to
occur at application build time,
again, out of the field of view
for the users of your game.
And content loading, that's
when we do state validation.
This, again, is relatively rare.
This means the only
thing we have to do
at draw call time is the
most important thing to do
at draw call time, which is
kick off the work on the GPU.
So that's the how and the why
we created Metal, and now I want
to take a deeper look at the API
itself, and we'll take a look
at some of the conceptual
framework for the API starting
with the objects in the API.
So the first object to talk
about in the Metal
API is the device,
and this essentially is just
an abstraction on the GPU,
the thing that's going
to consume your rendering
and compute commands.
Those commands will be
stored and submitted
to the GPU in a command queue.
Now the command queue, its
job is simply to decide
and let you specify in what
order those commands will
be executed.
Those commands themselves
are stored
in what's called
a command buffer.
This stores the translated
hardware commands ready
for consumption by the GPU.
And the command encoder is the
API object that's responsible
for that translation.
So when you create a command
encoder, and you use it to write
into a command buffer,
that's the translation.
The state of the API is
described in a series
of state objects for things
like how your framebuffers are
set up, how you're blending
and your depth and your
sampling state is set up.
These are all described to the
API in objects, which we'll talk
about in all three
sessions today.
And you have the
code: your shaders,
your vertex, your pixel shaders.
And, last, you have your data:
your resources, your memory,
the textures and
the vertex buffers
and the shader constants.
Those are all stored
in resources.
So let's take a look
next at kind
of how these objects
fit together by walking
through a bit about how
we construct the objects
in the API.
So first thing you
have is the device.
So like we said, this is
the device in the GPU,
the thing that's going
to consume your commands.
And from that you
create the command queue,
and typically you'll have one
of these in your application.
From the command
queue, you'll create one
or more command buffers to use
to store the hardware commands,
and you'll write
into those commands
with a Render Command
Encoder (in this example).
Now, in order to
generate those commands,
you need to specify
some information
of the Render Command Encoder,
and you do that by
attaching various objects
to the Render Command
Encoder before you use it.
So, for instance, you
specify your data buffers
and your textures
that you want to use
to do this rendering operation.
Now you'll notice in this
diagram we also show something
called the texture descriptor,
and the texture descriptor is
used to create the textures.
It specifies all of the
necessary state used
for texture object creation.
Probably the biggest state
object is the Render Pipeline
state, and it, too, is
constructed from a descriptor,
and the descriptor in
this case describes all
of the 3D rendering
state you need
to create a single
Render Pipeline.
Similarly, you have descriptors
for your depth and stencil state
that you use to create those
objects, and we have a series
of state for describing
the render pass itself;
how you're going to
output your rendering.
Now the reason we split the
state up into descriptors
and state objects is because
once you've specified what all
these state combinations should
be, Metal bakes all of these
into a small number of
state objects, that --
Now, all of the state
has been translated,
all the shaders have
been compiled,
and the system is ready to go.
You can now issue your draw
calls incredibly quickly
without worrying that the
implementation's going to have
to come around and do some late
binding translation or figure
out if what you're trying to
do is valid in the first place.
A couple more notes.
So, the source resources (the
textures and buffers here),
you can change those as you go.
The render targets
themselves are fixed
for a given render
command decoder.
We'll talk more about why that's
important in just a moment.
Now inverting this
diagram a little bit,
we can see how objects
are actually sending data
to the device.
You can have one or more
Render Command Encoders,
one for each rendering pass,
writing into the command buffer.
You can also interleave
different types of commands.
In this case, I'm
using compute commands
in the middle of my frame.
And, as we said, Metal supports
efficient multi-threading.
You can actually construct
multiple command buffers
in parallel using
multiple threads.
So let's talk a little bit more
about the command
submission model itself
to understand how this works.
Just as we've said, command
encoders will encode the API
of your, uh, it will
encode the API commands
into the hardware state,
and then they'll
store those commands
in the hardware command buffer.
There are 3 types
of command encoders
for generating 3 different
types of work on the GPU.
We have Render, Compute,
and Blit, and we'll talk
about each of them in detail.
But important to realize here is
that you can interleave these
different types of operations
in a single command buffer
and within a single
frame very efficiently.
And this is because the command
encoders themselves encapsulate
all the state necessary
so that we don't have
to do implicit transitions
between different types
of operations and behind the
scenes we don't have to try
to save and restore all
of the state necessary
for using these different
types of operations.
It's all under your
explicit control.
The command buffers themselves
are incredibly lightweight,
and most applications are
going to create a large number
of these in their frames.
And you control exactly when
and how these get
submitted to the GPU.
Once they've been submitted,
Metal signals you
(the application)
when those command buffers
have completed their execution
on the GPU.
And so you get very fine grain
control and clear notifications
about exactly what's happening
at any one point in time.
And very important to realize
is that these command encoders,
they're not just sending some
work off that later is going
to be consumed by the CPU.
They're actually generating
these commands immediately.
There's no deferred
state validation.
It's essentially like
they're making a direct call
to the GPU driver.
Now as I mentioned, you can
also multi-thread this command
encoding to get even
more performance.
Multiple command buffers
can be encoded in parallel
across threads, and, yet,
you get to decide exactly
when those commands
will be executed.
So you have the control
to both --
to split out the order in which
the commands will be constructed
while maintaining
the order you wish
for their execution on the GPU.
And we've provided an incredibly
efficient implementation
with no automic locks, to
make sure you can get scalable
performance across CPU cores.
So that's the commands.
Next we're going to take a look
at the resources, the memory,
the objects in the API
for specifying data.
Now we've designed the resource
model in Metal explicitly
for the A7's unified
memory system.
This means that the CPU and the
GPU are sharing the exact same
memory for exchanging data.
There's no implicit copies.
We're not coming in behind
the scenes and taking the data
and moving it somewhere
else for the GPU to see it.
We also manage the CPU and
GPU cache coherency for you.
You don't have to worry
about flushing caches
between the CPU and the GPU.
You simply have to make sure
that you schedule your work
to occur such that the GPU
and the CPU are not writing
to the same chunk of
memory at the same time,
but you don't have to do
anything to manage caches.
And by you taking on
this responsibility
for synchronization
between the GPU and the CPU,
we can offer you
significantly higher performance
because we're not implicitly
synchronizing things
that didn't necessarily
need to be synchronized.
There are 2 different
types of resources for you
to use in your application.
The first is textures, which
are simply formatted image data
that you use for
rendering for source data
or for rendering destinations,
and there are data buffers
which are essentially
unformatted ranges of memory.
You can think of them
like just a bag of bytes
to store your vertex data,
your shader constants,
any output memory from
your GPU workloads.
The important thing to remember
with Metal is that the structure
of these resources is immutable.
You cannot change it.
Once you create a texture of
a given size or given level
or a given format, it's baked,
and this lets us avoid
costly resource validation
that would previously have
taken place in other APIs
where we'd have to
figure out, "hey,
now that you've changed how
a texture is structured,
is it still valid?
Can we still use it as
a rendering destination?
Is it still mipmap complete?"
We don't have to do any of that
because you've specified
it all up front.
If you want to use two different
textures with - Ah, sorry.
formats for your texture,
you simply create two
different textures,
and this is actually
much more efficient.
We can rapidly switch
between these on, ah,
in the Metal implementation.
Of course, you can still change
the contents of your textures
for your buffers,
and to do that,
we provide several methods.
So you can update
data buffers directly.
You simply get a pointer
to the underlying storage.
There's no lock API needed
because, again, this is running
on a unified memory
system, and for textures,
we have what's called an
implementation private storage.
Now this doesn't mean that
we're copying the data
and moving it somewhere else.
This simply means that we
will reformat the textures
for efficient rendering
on the GPU,
but we provide some
blazing fast update routines
in Metal to do that.
If you need an asynchronous
update routine for your textures
or your buffers, you can do
this via the Blit Encoder,
and we'll talk in just a
moment about how that works.
Now one other thing you can do
with resources, and textures
in particular, is you can
actually share the underlying
storage across multiple textures
and reinterpret the pixel
data differently in each one.
So, for instance, if
you have a texture
that is using a single
32-bit integer pixel format,
you can have another texture
which is using a 4-component
"RGBA eights" pixel format, and
they can actually be pointing
at the same underlying storage
because the pixel size is
the same between the two.
And you can also share
the texture storage
with data buffers.
This will allow you direct
access to the underlying storage
with the CPU and to use
the underlying storage
as a data buffer, and we
simply assume row-lineal --
row-linear pixel order
in this particular case.
OK. Those are resources.
Now I'm going to talk briefly
about the command encoders
themselves, and as I mentioned,
there are 3 basic
command encoder types.
You have your Render, Compute,
and Blit command encoders,
and I'm going to talk about
each of these in sequence.
So first off: the
Render Command Encoder.
Now the Render Command Encoder,
you can think about this as all
of the hardware commands
necessary
for generating a single
rendering pass, and by pass,
I mean all of the rendering
to one framebuffer object,
one set of render targets.
If you want to change to
another set of render targets,
to another framebuffer,
you simply use another
Render Command Encoder,
and this is all the state
for specifying the vertex
and fragment stages
of the 3D pipeline.
It allows you to interleave
these state changes,
the resources, and any
draw calls necessary
for constructing your
pass, but, critically,
there's no draw time
compilation.
You get to control --
the app developer --
exactly when and how all
of the state compilation
and expensive validation
actually takes place.
And you do that with a series
of API calls and state objects,
and I'll show you just
a few of those here.
So as we talked about, you have
your depth and stencil objects,
sampler objects,
the Render Pipeline,
and they describe
various aspects
of the 3D rendering state.
Basically, almost everything
fits in the Render Pipeline
where you -- that's where
you specify your shaders,
your blend states, all, how
your vertex data is actually
specified, and all of that can
fit into these state objects.
Now important to
realize in Metal is
that not all state
objects are created equal.
Some of the states are actually
very expensive to change,
and for these, we've put them
in what's called immutable
or unchangeable state objects,
and you can't change
these states
after you've created
the objects.
These are the types of things
that affect expensive operations
or cause recompilation to occur.
So things like the shaders
themselves we don't want
to be -- you don't
want us to be --
recompiling them all the time.
So once you specified
those into a state object,
you can't change them.
But other things, like
the viewport and scissor,
are actually really cheap
to specify and really cheap
to change, and so
those remain flexible.
Now I talked a few times
about how the API was designed
with the A7 in mind, and one of
the key ways you can see this is
in how we handle
framebuffer loads and stores.
Now the A7 GPU is a tile-based
deferred-mode renderer.
Now I'm not going to go into
the details of what this means,
but one important
piece of that is
that it has what's called a tile
cache, and a tile cache is used
at the beginning and end
of each rendering pass
to load the contents of
the previous framebuffer
or to write it up to memory.
And so you need some explicit
control over this tile cache
to get optimal performance
and to make sure you're
not doing needless reads
and writes to memory.
In Metal, you can specify
load and store actions
on the framebuffer to make
this incredibly efficient,
and I'll show you an example
of how that works here.
So let's say, as an example,
this is before Metal,
you had one frame
for which you wanted
to do two rendering passes, and
in this example, you're going
to take the color framebuffer,
you're going to have to redo it
at the beginning,
you're going to write it
out at one pass through, and
then you're going to do the same
for the second pass...
and you'll probably want to
use a depth buffer as well.
So before Metal, you can
actually see here there was
quite a lot of memory
bandwidth taking place
across these passes.
You end up with 2 reads and 2
writes for each of the color
and the depth buffer, which
is a lot of memory traffic.
Well, with Metal, we
actually let you specify
which of those reads and writes
you actually need to occur.
So, for instance,
you can say, well,
I'm going to render every
pixel of my frame anyway.
There's no point in loading
the tile cache at the beginning
of the frame, and I can
save that bandwidth.
And if you're going to write
out the pass and then read it
in the second pass, you probably
would need to actually do that,
but when you look at the depth
buffer, you can see a lot
of unnecessary reads and writes.
And so you can specify that we
should probably just clear the
depth buffer at the
beginning of the frame
because you're not going to
need its previous contents,
and you don't need to write
it out at the end of the frame
because you're not using
it in a second pass.
You're simply going to clear it
again, and then you don't need
to write it out there either,
and we can get some
dramatic reductions
in memory traffic
as a result of this.
You can reduce the overall
amount of reads and writes
to a fraction of
what it was before,
and you can gain
significant performance
for your application.
So this is just one of the ways
in which we've designed
Metal with the A7 in mind.
Alright. That's rendering.
Now we're going to look at
the next area we introduced
with Metal, a functionality,
which is Compute.
So we're not going to spend
a lot of time today talking
about general-purpose
data-parallel computation
in the GPU, but for those of
you who have done this type
of operation before,
you're going to find
that this is a very familiar
run-time and memory model.
It uses the same
textures and data buffers
from the Metal graphics APIs,
has the same basic kinds
of memory hierarchy,
barriers, memories,
and load stores you might find
in other data parallel
programming APIs,
and you can configure
and specify exactly
how the work groups
for your Compute operations
will be executed by the GPU.
Probably more important
to realize with Metal is
that it is -- the Compute
operations are fully integrated
with graphics.
This means you get a unified
API, a single shading language,
and a single set of
fantastic developer tools
for both graphics and
compute operations on the GPU.
And probably more
important for performance,
we can efficiently
interleave these operations
between Compute, Rendering,
and data [inaudible]
operations and Blits.
Similarly, to graphics, there's
no execution time compilation
with the Compute operations.
You control exactly when these
expensive compilation activities
will occur.
And probably a little
bit different
from how graphics looks in
Metal, there's very little state
in the Compute Command Encoder.
There's some state
for specifying exactly
which Compute kernels
you're going to be using
and how you're going to
configure work groups,
and that's pretty much it.
And that's it.
If the Compute Command
Encoder seems simple,
that's because it is,
and that brings us
to our last command encoder,
the Blit Command Encoder,
and this is what you're going to
use for asynchronous data copies
between resources on the GPU,
and this can happen in parallel
with your compute and
your graphics operations.
You can use this to upload
textures, to copy data
between textures and buffers,
or to generate your mipmaps.
You can also update the data
buffers themselves, again,
copying to and from
textures or other buffers,
and you can actually fill
the buffers themselves
with constant values in
Blit Command Encoder.
Alright. That's it for the
API high level summary.
Now I'm going to
take a quick tour
through the shading
language itself.
Alright. So the Metal
shading language is a unified
shading language.
This means using the same
language, syntax, constructs,
tool chains for both graphics
and compute processing,
and it's based on C++11,
essentially a static subset
of this language, and it's
built out of LLVM and clang,
which means you get
incredibly high performance
and incredibly high quality
code generation for the GPU.
The only thing we've really
had to do was add some syntax
for describing certain
hardware functionality
such as how you're going
to control texture sampling
and rasterization, and then
we've added a few things
to make shader authoring
much more convenient,
such as function overloading
and basic template support.
But that's it.
If you know C++, you understand
the Metal shading language.
As I said, we added just a
few data types and some syntax
for handling graphics and
compute functionality.
Some basic data types you'll
probably find very useful
such as scaler, vector,
and matrix types,
and then we've used what's
called the attribute syntax
to specify a lot of the
connection between the Metal API
and the Metal shading language.
So things like, how do you get
data in and out of your shaders?
You specify those with
function arguments
and you use the attribute
syntax to actually identify
which textures and
buffers you want to use.
Or how to implement programmable
blending in your shaders?
You can actually use
the attribute syntax
to specify pixels you want
to read from the framebuffer.
The Metal shading language
itself is incredibly easy
to use.
You can put multiple shaders
in a single source code file,
and then we will build those
source code files with Xcode,
when you're building
your application,
into Metal library files.
And the Metal library files
are essentially just an archive
of your Metal shaders.
With the Metal run-time APIs,
you can actually
load a Metal library,
and then you can
finalize the compilation
into this device's
machine-specific code.
We also include an
awesome standard library
of very commonly-used and
incredibly performant graphics
and compute functions.
One other thing to realize
about the Metal shading language
is you need to get data in
and out of your shaders.
So we specify -- use a
method called argument tables
to let you specify which
arguments, which resources,
and which data needs
to move between the API
and the shading environment.
So each command encoder will
include what's called an
argument table, and
this is simply a list
of the resources you want to use
in the API that you want to read
and access and write in
the shader themselves.
There's one table for each type
of resource, and then the shader
and the host code will simply
use an index into that table
to refer to the same resource.
Let's see an example.
So on the right here, I simply
have a representation of one
of the command encoders;
it could be Render Command
Encoder, for instance.
And you have a table
in the command encoder
that describes the resources.
So you have a list of all
of the textures you want
to use in your shaders.
Similar tables exist for
buffers and samplers.
Now I've simplified
this a little bit
because there's actually one of
these sets of tables for each
of the vertex and
fragment shader stages.
Well, let's take a look
at an example shader.
So in this, we have a vertex
shader and a fragment shader
in Metal shader code
on the left,
and you'll see it
looks quite familiar.
You'll get a lot more
information about how this works
in the next session, but
you can get a good sense
of how this works
just from looking
at the code itself right here.
So in the fragment shader, we're
simply referring to texture
at index 1 to identify that we
would like to use the texture
that we set up in the
command encoder to read
in this fragment shader.
And, similarly, in the vertex
shader, we can do the same thing
with the buffers, and use those
as inputs to the vertex shader
and refer back to the
argument index table
in the command encoder.
So you set up the command
encoder's argument tables
with the API and simply
refer to those resources
in your shaders using
the attribute syntax
in the function arguments
themselves.
And that's it.
The shading language is
actually pretty simple,
and we think you're
going to really like it.
And, next, I'm going
to talk about how
to build your Metal
application using our awesome
developer tools.
And probably the most important
of those developer tools is
the Metal shader complier.
Now, ideally, you don't
even know this exists
because we're simply going to
build your shader sources just
like we build the rest of
your application sources
at application build time.
There's no need for you to
separate out your shaders
and specify them at run time.
You can actually ship them
with your application already
having been precompiled.
So there's no source
code that needs to go
with your application
for your shaders.
But probably more important from
the developer's point of view is
that we can actually give you
errors and warnings and guidance
about your shaders at
the time you're building
your application.
So you don't have to wait
until your customers are
running your game to find
out that you have an error
in one of your shaders.
This is awesome.
Those shaders will then be
compiled into Metal libraries
by Xcode and then
compiled to device code
at the time you create your
state objects themselves.
So, again, there's no
draw time compilation,
and we will cache
this compilation --
this final device
machine-specific compilation --
on the device.
So we won't be continually doing
even this last translation step.
Now for those of you who like
to specify your source code
at run time -- perhaps
you're constructing strings
on the fly -- we do provide a
runtime shader compiler as well.
This can also be really
useful for debugging.
It, too, has no draw time
compilation overhead.
It operates just like
the precompile shaders,
but for best performance,
we generally recommend you
use the offline compiler.
We can give you the
most information
to help you build the
best possible shaders
if you do it this way.
Well, let's see what
this would look like.
So here's an example.
You're building your application
in Xcode, and you have a series
of Metal shader files, and
these shader files are passed
to the Metal shader
compiler, the compiler
of the Metal shader sources,
at the time you build
your application,
and a Metal library
file is generated.
That Metal library file will be
packaged with your application,
and so then when you deploy
your application to a device,
that Metal library file
goes along for the ride.
Then at application run time
when you're constructing
your pipeline objects,
you specify which vertex
and fragment shaders you'd
like to use from
that Metal library.
Metal implementation then will
look up those shaders to see
if it's already cached them
once before, and if not,
will compile them to the
final machine device code
and send it to the GPU.
And that's it.
Most of this happens
automatically for you, but,
critically, exactly
when you want it to.
Now if you've used our OpenGL
ES debugging tools in Xcode,
you're going to feel
right at home.
We have an awesome set of
GPU programming, debugging
and profiling tools integrated
right into Xcode, and I'm going
to give you a quick
tour of those now.
So this is an example
application inside Xcode
where you get visual
debugging tools built right
into the same environment
you're using
to build the rest
of your application.
On the left-hand side, we
have what's called the Frame
Navigator, which shows you
exactly which Metal API calls,
draw calls you issued and
in what order they occurred,
and in the middle, you
have the Frame Navigator --
or, sorry, the Framebuffer View,
where you can actually see the
results of those draw calls
and state operations
happening live
as you're constructing
your frame.
We also have the Resource
View, where you can see all
of the textures, resources, data
buffers, everything you're using
to construct your frame,
inspect them, and make sure
that they're exactly
as you set them up.
And at the bottom, you can
see the Metal State Inspector,
where you can see all
of the API state and all
of the important bits of
control and information you have
about your application in Metal.
We also provide some
really fantastic profiling
and performance tools.
So in this example,
we're showing the Metal
Performance Report.
You can see things
like your frame rate
or how much you're
using the GPU.
You can also see exactly which
shaders are the most expensive,
and you can see how much time
they're taking per frame.
This is awesome.
You can also see for
each of those shaders
in milliseconds how much time
they're taking as a whole,
but you can get a feel
for exactly what are the most
expensive lines of each shader.
So if you want to really
optimize your shaders,
you can find out which line
is taking up the most time
and focus in on that,
and this is all built
for you right inside of Xcode.
[ Applause ]
Yeah, excellent.
I'm glad you like it.
So you can also build
your shaders,
as we said, inside Xcode.
You can actually
edit them as well,
and you get all the
familiar syntax highlighting
and code completion, and you
get warnings and errors right
for you inside of Xcode, too.
We think this is
really fantastic.
It makes writing and editing
and profiling shaders a
much more natural part
of the process, and
we've designed Metal
to work seamlessly
in this environment.
Alright. So that's the developer
tools, the API concepts,
and the shading language.
Now as you heard in the keynote,
we've been working, with Metal,
with some leading
game engine providers
such as Electronic Arts,
Epic, Unity, and Crytek,
and we've been amazed at what
they've been able to create
in just a short amount of time.
Well, I'm very happy
to introduce
up on stage Sean
Tracey from Crytek,
who's going to show you what
they've been able to create
with Metal in just a few weeks.
Sean?
>> Thanks a lot, Jeremy.
Crytek is known for
pushing the boundaries
and for developing
blockbuster hits such as Crysis
and Ryse for the consoles.
The CRYENGINE is going
mobile, and our latest game,
The Collectables, was recently
released on the App Store.
Integrating Metal into the
game gives us opportunities
that we didn't have before,
and the added performance
changes the way we think
about creating mobile game
play and mobile game content.
Today, we'd like to show
you the next version
of The Collectables, and to
show you how we used Metal
to change the game.
Let's take a look.
In The Collectables, you control
a renegade team of mercenaries,
and today we're on a daring
hit-and-run mission to take
out the enemy artillery.
As you can see, the environment
is incredibly dynamic
and very rich with wind
affecting vegetation and more.
Looks like the enemy's
set up a roadblock ahead.
Let's take out these
jeeps with our RPGs.
Booyah! So you can
see this level
of cinematic destruction
simply wasn't possible
on mobile before.
When those jeeps explode,
there's over 168 unique
pieces that come flying off.
The tires, windshield,
engine block, and more.
Using the power of Metal,
we're able to leverage
our Geom cache technology
as seen in Ryse on console.
And there it is, our
objective, the enemy artillery.
It's a pretty big mother.
So let's go ahead and call
in our AC130 gunship
for air support.
[ Background Sounds ]
Geom cache uses cache-based
animation
to realize extremely complex
simulation and special effects,
as you saw in the
destruction of those buildings.
So as our players make their
way to their next objective,
let's take a look
at another example
of how we can use this power
to turn the environment
into a weapon for our player.
Sounds like trouble ahead.
Yeah, they've got a tank.
Alright. We need to block off
that road and get out of here,
or we're going to be toast.
Let's try taking
out the chimney.
And that's how you stop a
tank in The Collectables.
When that building
and chimney come down,
there's over 4,000
draw calls on screen,
4,000 draw calls -- on an iPad!
Oh, they've got another tank
and, um, we're out of chimneys.
So mission accomplished.
Let's get out of here.
As you can see, the
performance gained
with Metal gives us a
tenfold performance increase
that allows us to bring the
Crytek DNA alive on mobile.
We look forward to seeing
you guys in the game.
Thanks a lot.
[ Applause ]
>> Alright.
Thanks, Sean.
That's really amazing.
So 4,000 draw calls
is a tenfold increase
over what was previously
possible before Metal,
and we're are truly, truly
excited to see it in action.
Alright. So that's Metal.
Metal is our new low overhead,
high-performance GPU programming
API which can provide you
with dramatic increase
in efficiency
and performance for your game.
We've designed it from
scratch to run like a dream
on the A7 chip and
our iOS products.
And we've streamlined
the feature set
and the API footprint to focus
on the most modern GPU features,
such as unified graphics
and compute,
and the most modern GPU
game programming techniques,
such that require
fine-grained control
and efficient multi-threading.
With support for precompiled
shaders and a fantastic set
of developer tools, we
believe you're going to be able
to use Metal to create
an entirely new class
of games for your customers.
We're really looking forward
to what you guys are going
to be able to create with Metal.
We think it's just a truly,
truly fantastic thing.
For more information
about Metal,
you can come see our
Evangelists, Filip and Allan,
and we have an amazing set
of documentation about Metal
on our developer
relations website.
You can also check out
the developer forums
where you can talk with folks
about Metal, and you can come
to the next two sessions which
we're going to go into Metal
in a much more level of detail.
So you can see how Metal
works in your application,
how to build your first Metal
application, how to build scenes
out of Metal and use
it to control the GPU,
how the Metal shading
language itself works,
and then we'll have
a second session
where we cover some
more advanced techniques
such as using multi-pass
rendering and Compute.
We're really looking forward
to what you're going to be able
to create with this API.
Thank you very much for coming.