>> My name is Olivier Bonnet.
I'm the engineering manager for
the CloudKit on the client side.
So, up until today Apple
had many iCloud technologies
and they looked like
this to you.
We had iCloud Drive, iCloud
Core Data, iCloud file Library
and how they interacted
with the iCloud,
the Apple iCloud server
was kind of a mystery.
So today we're lifting
some of the mystery
in introducing CloudKit.
So let's look at
what we're going
to cover here in this session.
First we're going to start
with what is CloudKit.
We're going to walk you through
the couple of steps you need
to enable CloudKit in your
application and start using it.
We're going to do a walkthrough
of the different APIs,
we're going to talk about
how CloudKit interacts
with the Apple, the iCloud
user accounts and last
but not least we'll cover when
to use CloudKit as opposed
to other existing iCloud APIs we
already have on the platforms.
So let's start.
What is CloudKit?
You'll notice the new batch
but the whole session is new
so it's share only
on that slide.
[Laughter] CloudKit is
a way to give you access
to iCloud servers and
we really mean it.
CloudKit is the foundation
for both iCloud Drive
and iCloud file Library.
Those features were written
from scratch on top of CloudKit.
CloudKit is supported
on both OS 10 and iOS.
It's a new public
framework, cloudkit.framework.
Check it out in SDK.
CloudKit uses the iCloud
accounts infrastructure.
That means that if there's
a logged in iCloud account
on the device we'll use
that to identify the user.
If there's none, we'll provide
read only anonymous access.
CloudKit supports both a concept
of public and private databases.
You can see public
databases as a soup
of data that's all your
user can access to.
Private databases are meant
to store the actual data just
on behalf of a specific user.
CloudKit support both
structured and bulk data.
You can use it to store
large files on iCloud servers
and we'll take care of
transmitting them efficiently
from the iCloud servers.
Importantly CloudKit is
a transport technology.
It doesn't provide
any local persistence.
It enables you to send and
receive data from the servers.
So let's start.
How do you enable CloudKit
in your application?
So first you'll want to navigate
your application's capabilities,
pane and X code.
See that big iCloud off switch?
You want to turn
it on and you want
to check the CloudKit
checkbox here.
At that point you're ready.
There's no fourth step.
Your app is ready to
read and write data
to Apple's iCloud server and to
walk you through the API on how
to do this I'm going to hand
over to Paul to chat about it.
[Applause]
>> All right.
Thank you, Olivier.
[ Applause ]
So, as Olivier said,
my name is Paul.
I work on the CloudKit client
framework, and I'm very excited
to talk to you guys
today about CloudKit.
We're going to start off
we're going to start talking
about the fundamental
CloudKit objects.
These are going to
be the set of objects
that you're initially
exposed to when you open up
and start playing with
the CloudKit framework.
Just running through a quick
list of them we're going to talk
about containers and we're
going to talk about databases,
we're going to talk about
records, we're going to talk
about record zones
and RecordIDentifiers,
we're going to talk
about references
and we're going to
talk about assets.
It's quite a list.
This is going to be a really fun
and really jam-packed session.
So let's get started and we're
going to talk about containers.
This is sort of the
idealized model
of your application
talking about iCloud.
Now you guys are
application developers,
you guys are client
developers, and you know
that your application
running on a client whether
that client is a iPhone
or whether it be a Mac Book
yours is not the only process
running on that client.
Rather yours is one of many.
Now on your client your
process is going to be siloed,
sandboxed in some ways.
In some cases, it's
a literal sandbox.
Certainly in others
you're running
in your own memory space.
This concept of taking
your client
and actually running
it separated
from other clients
is pretty powerful.
It has got a couple
of advantages.
It helps with security,
it helps with stability
and it helps with privacy.
So as we are figuring out how
we wanted to build CloudKit,
we thought to ourselves how can
we take these three advantages
and replicate them
up in the server?
So here's what we did.
Just as your client is
one of many, I'm sorry,
your application is one of
many running on the client,
so too the part of
iCloud that you're talking
to is one of many up on iCloud.
We call these different
silos containers.
So containers.
Containers are exposed
in the CloudKit framework
as the CKContainer class.
CK is our prefix
and you're going
to see this all over the place.
By default one application
talks to one container.
Containers afford us the
ability to segregate data.
That means that your application
can read and write data
to iCloud, another application
to iCloud and the two datasets
up on the server will
not be intermingled.
In addition to data segregation,
this containerization
of iCloud storage allows us to
encapsulate user information.
Now as Olivier mentioned,
CloudKit involves using the
iCloud account infrastructure
and we want to give
you some limited access
to that iCloud account
and we want to make sure
that we're doing so in a
privacy conscientious manner.
So in order to do that, we
encapsulate user information.
User information available
to your application is going
to be container scoped
and, therefore,
different than the view
of user information seen
by another application.
Containers are managed
by you the developer.
You're going to be managing
them via the WWDR portal.
It's important to note
that the name space
of containers is
global to all developers
so when you're choosing a name
for your container make sure
that you're using
it in a reverse,
you're using a reverse DNS name.
Now, right up there just like
a little while ago I said
that by default there
is one container
to one application,
a one to one mapping.
We think this is going to be
successful for 99% of use cases
and certainly as you go and
start using CloudKit it's going
to be great as you start
exploring the framework.
We recognize that there
are some scenarios
where you need a
more complex mapping
so we support a many
to many model.
What we mean is that multiple
applications can coordinate
on the same iCloud container.
Also a single application
can talk
to multiple iCloud containers.
On to databases.
One of the chief purposes
of CloudKit is the ability
to take your object model in
your application and replicate
that up to the server.
So when we start
thinking about how we want
to present this modeling
to you we thought
to ourselves how can we
divide up application objects?
Obviously all objects
in my application are
not treated equally.
One of the first things that we
notice was there's a fundamental
difference in the
audience of data.
Some data is intended to be used
by the user that created it.
If you imagine an application
where I'm writing up notes
and I want to see my notes
everywhere else, that's my data.
I create it, I consume it.
On the other hand, there's use
for what we call public data.
This is data that can be,
a, created by the user
for the benefit of a community;
think perhaps a review
on a restaurant.
Or it could be information that
you the developer has uploaded
to iCloud because it's
useful to your application.
In either case, the audience
is not just a single user
but a community of people.
So how did we solve the fact
that we've got these
different types of data.
Let's break open a container
and have a look inside.
Inside of a container
you're going to notice first
and foremost the
public database.
This is the soup, this is
where all of the public
and communal data
co-lives, co-mingles.
Additionally, you're
going to notice
that there's private databases
and you're going to find
that there's an individual
private database
for each user of
your application.
Now this is sort of the
50,000 foot overview
of what the iCloud
infrastructure looks like,
but you know, how much do
you guys care about that?
What you guys are interested
in is what does this
infrastructure look
like to me the client running
on a phone or running on a Mac.
Obviously you're only
going to have access
to the currently
logged in iCloud user.
So rather than seeing
a public database
and a gajillion private
databases, your view is going
to look a little
bit more like this.
You're going to have a choice
between a public database
or the private database
that is correlated
to the currently
logged in iCloud user.
So databases.
Databases are exposed in our
API as a CK database class.
Every application has
access to two of them,
the public and the private.
Let's have a look at
a little bit of code.
The container is the initial
entry point into CloudKit.
Here we see that I am talking
to my default container
and getting its public database.
I can also talk to
the default container
and get it to private database.
Let's have a look
at the differences
between these 2 databases.
As we mentioned, the
desired audience is going
to be different between
the public database
and the private database.
The public db is for shared
data, the private db is
for the user's own data.
As such, we have different
requirements for whether
or not an iCloud account
needs to exist on the client.
In the private database,
since I am reading
and writing a user's data if
we have no notion of the user,
that is if we don't have a login
iCloud account there's really no
utility in moving
this information
to and from the server.
So we require an iCloud account
to be logged in if you want
to use the private database.
In the public database since
the audience is more communal,
we allow you read only anonymous
access to the public database.
You'll recall from
yesterday's talk
that CloudKit is
free with Linux.
So we've got some
pretty aggressive quotas.
That being said we
still need to account
for where data is being used
so that we can talk to you
when we start approaching
those limits.
Data stored in the public
database is accounted
for on the developer's quota.
Date stored in the private
database is accounted
for on the user's quota.
By default data written
into the public database is
world readable.
Data written to the private
database is user readable.
Again it's the user's own data
so they're really the only ones
to have access to it in
the private database.
We recognize that world readable
is not an appropriate permission
for a lot of data in
the public database
so we give you the ability
to edit these permissions
on a record class level.
The mechanism by which you edit
these permissions is something
that we call the
iCloud Dashboard roles.
iCloud Dashboard is the
administrative interface
into CloudKit.
I invite you guys to
come back on Thursday
for the advanced talk.
We're going to go into a lot
of detail about the dashboard.
Suffice it to say there's
an ability to set ACLs
so that a user is
a member of a role
and a role can have
certain enlarged access
to a class of records.
In the private database,
things start
out in lockdown there's
no need to edit them.
The user is the only
one to create data
and the user is the only one
to be able to read that data.
When I say that the user is
the only one to be able to read
that data, I really mean it.
You as the developer
do not have access
into somebody else's
private database.
Their data is their own.
All right so those
are databases.
Let's talk about records.
So, here's our model
that we have so far.
We've got a container, within
containers are databases.
Let's keep going down the rabbit
hole and crack open a database.
Inside the database we see
that it's full of records.
Records are exposed in our
framework as the CKRecord class.
They are the mechanism by which
you've moved structured data
to and from CloudKit.
CKRecords wrap key value pairs.
Lest you think that a CKRecord
is just a glorified dictionary,
there are some additional
attributes
that make it worthwhile
of being in its own class.
To start off with records
have a record type.
If CloudKit is a mechanism by
which you take your object graph
from your application and
move it into CloudKit,
then let's continue
with that analogy.
An instance of an object in
your application is equivalent
to an instance of a CKRecord.
Similarly the class
of the object
in your application
is equivalent
to the record type
of the CKRecord.
Records have a just
in time schema.
You do not need to tell CloudKit
about what your data looks
like before you hand
CloudKit your data.
Hand us your data and
we'll figure it out.
CloudKit, excuse me,
CKRecord also supports a raft
of metadata.
For example, a record
understands
when it was created
and who created it.
It understands when a
record was last modified
and who last modified it.
Lastly a record contains
a notion of a change tag.
A change tag is a
version of a record.
It represents a specific
revision of this record.
It's use so that we can
have a lightweight way
of determining whether or not
a client server had the same
version of a record.
Let's talk a little bit
about record values,
CKRecords wrap key value pairs.
What are the acceptable
value types
that you can put
into a CKRecord?
Well, we've got your usual
suspects, your P list types,
your strings, your numbers,
your datas and your dates.
We think that especially
in the public database
domain location is an
interesting scenario.
So, CLLocation is a native type
that you can set on a CKRecord.
You can set CKReferences and
CKAssets and we're going to go
over what those are
in just a moment.
Lastly any value can
be a single instance.
I can have a string or a date
or it can be a homogenous array.
I can have an array of numbers
or an array of CKAssets.
Let's have a look at
a little bit of code.
Here we see a CKRecord.
The CKRecord Initializer
takes a record type
because that's an invaluable
and necessary piece of a record.
You can set objects
and get objects
from a record using
a dictionary syntax
or a keyed subscripting syntax.
We also give you the ability to
enumerate all keys on a record
so that you can dump the
entire key value pair.
Let's have a look at
a specific example.
Now, throughout this
talk my example is going
to be an application that I've
created for me and my friends.
This application allows us to
create parties and we're going
to stick party records
in the public database.
A party might be a
structured data it's going
to have a summary, a
start date and end date
and it might also have
additional metadata
that we associate with it,
pictures of the party,
et cetera.
So, how do I create
a party record?
Well I create one just
as you might imagine
with a party record type.
I can now set values on
it and I can read values
from it using the dictionary
or key subscripting syntax.
Those are records.
Let's talk about record zones.
This is the model that we've
just presented and it was kind
of a lie but it was a
useful lie at the time.
So, records don't exist by
themselves just as objects
in your application don't
exist by themselves.
There's going to be a
natural grouping of objects
within your application.
Similarly we want a way
to express this grouping
in CloudKit.
Fundamentally we're trying
via CloudKit to take as much
of your knowledge about your
object graph and reflect
that up to the server.
So the way that we group
records is via something
that we call a record zone.
There can be multiple
records within a record zone
and there can be multiple
record zones within a database.
Every database has a
default record zone.
Some databases support
additional custom record zones.
Record zones are the
default granularity
at which you're going
to do atomic commits
and change tracking.
If either of those sound
interesting to you,
I invite you back on Thursday
for the advanced talk.
We're going to go over
a whole bunch of that.
So, those were record zones.
Let's talk about
RecordIDentifiers.
RecordIDentifiers, let's get
the code up there, are a tuple.
They represent both a
client provided record name
and also the zone in which
that record name exists.
So what are their
characteristics?
Number one they are
created by the client.
You get to specify the ID,
the record name of the record,
but because we are
coupling this record name,
which is scoped per record
zone, along with a reference
to the owning record zone,
they become a fully normalized
representation of the record.
It's the full path to it.
We think that it's going to be
fairly common for you to try
and bridge an external
dataset into CloudKit.
If you're doing so and if your
external dataset has a unique
key, using that unique key
as the CKRecordID allows you
to have a foreign key back
into your external dataset.
Totally an approved usage.
Let's have a look at some code.
Here we are, you know,
creating a record,
you've seen that already,
and we've got multiple
initializers for CKRecord.
You can either choose
to provide us a RecordID
or you can choose not to.
If you choose not to
provide a RecordID,
we're going to assign a random
view UUID to the record.
Also note here that when I
created my RecordID I chose not
to give it a zone.
Throughout CloudKit's
API if you choose not
to give us a record zone,
we're going to assume
that you meant the default zone.
So here, I am creating
a RecordID
with the name well-known
party that exists
within the default zone.
So those are RecordIDs.
Now let's talk about references.
Just as there's a natural
grouping of records that we want
to expose via a record
zone, there's also going
to be a natural relationship
between objects.
For example, let's say that in
addition to being able to write
up parties I can assign
different clowns to parties
because what is the
point of a party
if you don't have a few clowns?
So, I want some way
of representing the object
relationship that I have
between parties and clowns up
to the server and the way we do
that is via something
that we call references.
Now you'll note here that in
this contrived example parties
own clowns.
That is we've got a parent/child
relationship with the party
as a parent and the
clown as a child
and that the reference
goes from the child object,
from the clown, up
to its parent object.
We call that a back reference.
References are exposing API
as the CKReference class.
They are a way of letting
the server understand the
relationship between records.
When the server understands
the relationship
between records it can do
very interesting things
such as cascade delete.
If the server notices that
you've deleted a record
and that record is the parent in
a parent and child relationship,
the server will automatically
go ahead
and cascade delete all
the children of that item.
With any database
the scope and scale
of CloudKit dangling pointers
are going to become a necessary
and inconvenient truth
of your use of CloudKit.
By the time you fetch a record
and you read a reference,
then you go and fetch the
target of that reference,
the target may not exist.
So it's important that you're
code is resilient to this.
Again, as I mentioned, we
prefer back references.
It's not a requirement, but it's
more efficient if references go
from child objects
to parent objects.
This is the tip of the iceberg
in a very large topic
called data modeling
and if you come back
on Thursday we're going
to tell you a whole bunch about
data modeling in CloudKit.
Let's have a look at some code.
Here we see creating a reference
between two CKRecord instances
that I have in memory,
but it's not necessary
that I have the target
of a reference in memory.
I can make a reference
that points at a RecordID.
This allows me to refer to a
record that I've got, you know,
reason to believe
exists up on the server.
If I were to save this record
and the target didn't exist,
I'd actually be creating a
dangling pointer and that's okay
because the code you're going
to write is going to support
and be resilient in the
face of dangling pointers.
So those are references now
let's talk about assets.
Here we have our
model again just
to refresh our container
database record
and now let's take the idea
that I want to write a record,
I want to write a party record
up to the server, but let's say
that I want to associate a
large file with that record.
Let's say, for example,
that we're going
to have a get together after
the presentation and I'm going
to read you a screen play
that I've been working on.
Now I know, I understand
that there's different
characteristics
between these different datas.
I understand that the record
about the party is structured,
you know, it's got a summary,
it's got a start date,
it's got an end date and, you
know, just innately I believe
that I want the server
to understand those
bits about the record.
If you contrast that to
the screen play, well,
the screen play is just
essentially a bag of bits.
I don't feel any real need
to tell the server how
my screen play breaks
down into amazing acts and,
you know, dashing scenes,
but I do know that
I want to treat them
as just an opaque bag.
So how do we solve this?
Well, we're going to
solve this and we're going
to solve the fact that data
has different characteristics
like this in two different ways.
Up on the server we're
going to introduce a notion
that we call bulk storage.
As you might expect,
bulk storage is great
for storing bulk data.
Similarly on the client
you're going to tell CloudKit
about the different
characteristics of your data
by treating some
of it as a CKRecord
and other bits of
it as a CKAsset.
A CKAsset is the representation
of this bag of bits.
Now when you ask CloudKit
to save this record,
the appropriate bits
are going to go
in the appropriate database.
Structured data in
public database,
bulk data in bulk storage.
So assets.
Assets are exposed in our
framework as the CKAsset class.
They represent large,
unstructured data.
Because you don't necessarily
want large unstructured data
in memory, the way you
communicate assets to
and from CloudKit is
via files on disks.
Assets are owned by records.
This gives us a nice
tight coupling
between a record and an asset.
What this allows the server to
do is garbage collect assets.
Even though that we're storing
this data in two separate areas
when the server detects a delete
for a record it can go ahead
and clean up any assets that
were owned by that record.
Lastly because we expect CKAsset
to be large, opaque data,
we go through some great pains
to try and move that data to
and from the server as
efficiently as possible.
This is all sort of inside
of CloudKit but we're going
to send only the bits
that the minimal amount
of bits that we can.
Let's have a look at some code.
Here I'm creating a
CKAsset based on a file URL
to my screen play
on disk and just
like any other CKRecord value
supporting class I'm setting it
on CKRecord.
So these are the fundamental
objects in CloudKit.
The first thing you
talk to is a container.
Within a container are
two different databases.
Databases contains
records, records are wrapped
and grouped within record zones.
You identify a record
via a RecordIDentifier
and records are related to
one another via references
and large bulk data
is transmitted to
and from CloudKit via CKAssets.
All right you guys made it
through the nouns now
let's get into the verbs.
[Laughter] CloudKit we
offer two different APIs
for using CloudKit.
We call them the operational
API and the convenience API.
The operational API
has every single bell
and whistle you might
care about.
In some cases, you're going to
want to tweak every single bell
and whistle to fit your
application's model,
but not every application really
wants to do all of this tweaking
and not every application
has enough knowledge
to set these bits correctly.
Sometimes you want to let
the framework make some
of these decisions
on your behalf.
So, we offer the
convenience API.
It's convenient, it's
going to be what you want
to start off playing with when
you start looking at CloudKit.
For many uses of
CloudKit it's all
that you're going
to need to touch.
So quickly we're going to go
over how you save a record
in the convenience of API,
how you fetch a record
from the server via
the convenience of API
and how you can take a
fetched record, modify it
and save it back
up to the server.
Let's start off with
saving a record.
Here I am creating a record.
You guys are now very
well familiar with this.
When I want to save the
record, I have to choose
which database I
want to save it into.
Here I'm going to save the data
into the public database
and how do I do that?
Well, I call the save record
with completion handler method.
Now I want you guys to
note three separate things
about this code right here.
First of all it's very simple.
You guys aren't providing
a lot of options,
you're delegating a lot
of the bells and whistles
like how important is this,
what interface should
I send this data over,
you're delegating those
choices off to CloudKit.
Second, it's asynchronous.
As Olivier mentioned,
the CloudKit does not
have local persistence.
We are a transport technology.
We're going to transport
your data up to the server
and we'll store it on the server
and we'll transport it back
down to other clients.
So when you save a record
via CloudKit, we are going
to attempt to save that
record directly to the server.
If it fails, we're going to tell
you about that immediately or,
you know, as quickly as we can.
Now we don't want
to block threads
and we don't want you
to block the user.
So we don't want to make
this a synchronous call.
So here we've got an
asynchronous call.
Now the third thing
I want you to note is
that even though is a very
simple method we do provide an
error as part of the call back.
Now if you've been
to WWC in the past
or if you've watched
any presentations,
you've seen something
that looks like this.
We've got an Apple
developer up here
and the Apple developer says
you need to handle errors
that return from our framework.
Now, I'm not calling them
liars it's true you do need
to handle errors
returned from frameworks.
In many applications, it's
the difference between a good
and functioning application
and a great application.
CloudKit is a little
bit different.
CloudKit by its very
nature is going
to be talking over the network.
Networks are inherently
lossy [phonetic].
Phones like to fall off
the network all the time.
So, in CloudKit, the difference
between handling an error
versus not handling an error
is really the difference
between a functional and
a non-functional app.
Error handling has got to
be one of the first things
that you look at when
you start using CloudKit.
I'm going to be a little bit
glib throughout the slides here
but every time you
see a comment imagine
that you're seeing just some
really nice error handling.
[Laughter] So let's talk about
now that we've saved a record
up to the server, how do
we fetch a record back
down from the server?
I'm going to start by
deciding which database I want
to fetch a record from.
I'm then going to construct
a RecordID, the identifier
of the record I care
to fetch down.
Here I've gotten this name
either via some side channel
or something that's built
into my application.
I then can ask the database
to fetch a record with ID
with completion handler.
Again, asynchronous, simple,
amazing error handling.
Once I fetched a record let's
get that code back up here,
I want you to note that the
successful return value is an
actual CKRecord instance
and this is a live
honest to God CKRecord.
Let's say I'm having so much
fun at this party I pulled
that I want it to last
a little bit longer.
I can take a record off of it
and I can bump out the end date
by half an hour and I
can set that record,
that value back on the record.
Once I've done that I can take
my CKRecord instance and just
like one that I've created
locally I can turn around
and save it back up
to the database again
with amazing error handling.
All right so that's
the convenience API,
the initial typical flow
that you're going to go
through when talking
with CloudKit.
You're going to be saving
records, fetching records
and taking those records that
you fetched modifying them
and putting them back
up to the server.
So now let's say my party
application starts becoming
really popular and it's grown.
My user base is no longer me and
my friends but it's all of you.
Everyone is really excited
about joining into the parties.
What are some of the problems
I'm going to run into?
Well, let's assume
that when I started
out I was a relatively
naive developer
and because the developer on
stage said CloudKit is all
about taking your object
graph and moving it to
and from the cloud,
that's exactly what I did.
I had the one to one mapping.
My objects went up to the Cloud
and on every client I would
fetch the entire cloud state
and that would become
my object graph.
What are some problems
we're going to run into?
Well, at that point we've got
big data and a very tiny phone.
The more popular my app
becomes the more data
on the database the less
reasonable it is to have a cache
of that entire data
locally on my device.
So how are we going
to solve this.
Let's think about
what we want to do.
We want to keep the large
data up in the Cloud.
The Cloud is very good at
storing large datasets.
My client wants to view
a slice of that data.
Because I'm writing an
application for my users
and my users have their own
preferences, I want each client
to be able to view a
different slice of that data
and each individual
client might want
to change its view of that data.
The way we saw this is via
something that we call queries.
Clients use queries to
focus their viewpoint
so that they can see a small
section of a large dataset
that exists up on the cloud.
So what is a query?
As you might imagine,
it's exposed in our API
as the CK query class.
A query combines three
different things.
It combines a record
type, a predicate
and optionally a
sort descriptor.
If you've used NS
predicate in the past,
you know that NS predicate
is very expressive.
CloudKit supports
most of NS predicate.
We document the parts that we do
and if you hand us a predicate
that we don't understand, we're
going to throw an exception.
So you're going to learn
pretty quickly which ones are
and are not supported.
Let's have a look at
some that are supported.
Here we see a predicate
that would match records
where name is equal to
a value I had in memory.
Predicates allow you
to use dynamic keys
so that I don't have to know
the key name at compile time.
We can do relative
ordering comparisons
as opposed to strict equalities.
We mentioned that location
is an interesting aspect
in the public database.
So you can query with
location as a filter.
This is every location
within a 100 meters
of where we're standing
here in Moscone.
CloudKit supports a
tokenization search.
So, what this predicate is going
to do is it's going to tokenize
that string after session
and it's going to come
up with two different
tokens, after and session.
This predicate will
match any record
that has those two
tokens as values.
These two tokens don't
need to exist side by side,
they don't even need to exist
in the same key value pair,
but so long as the
record has the token after
and the record has the token
session the record will be
a match.
Lastly, CloudKit supports
compound predicates joined using
the and operator.
Here we see a predicate
that does that.
Here we see the creation
of a query
and as we mentioned it's
combining both a record type
and a predicate.
How do I perform queries
after I've created them?
Well, just like saving records
performing a query is going
to be a database
specific operation.
So I'm going to choose
the database
on which I want to
perform a query.
Even in the simple API and the
convenience API we give you the
ability to restrict these
queries by record zones.
You see here that we're
not choosing to pass
in a record zone filter.
So this query is going to search
across the entire
public database.
Let's have a look
at what happens
in the completion handler.
First, of course,
amazing error handling.
Second, if we don't have errors,
let's have a look
at the results.
You'll see here that the results
are actually CKRecord instances.
These are live objects.
If I wanted to, I could
pull data off of them,
I could set data on them
and I could even choose
to save them back to the server.
So a way to think about queries
is that queries are polls
and polls are great
in some scenarios.
They're great for slicing
through large datasets.
If your application wants to
start up and, for example,
show all the parties, the top
10 parties that are near me,
a query is absolutely the way
to go, but there's other things
that you might be
tempted to use a query
for that are not perfect.
If you find yourself issuing
the same query over and over
and over again and you're
getting back a static,
a mostly same data
result set, well,
then you've got a large
mostly static dataset
and queries are bad for that
use case for a few reasons.
They're bad for battery life.
You have to constantly
wake the device up, poll,
run the same query and get back
more or less the same results.
They're bad for network traffic.
All those questions
go to the server
and if they're not
pulling down new
and interesting data,
why do we bother?
They are also bad for
the user experience.
By definition, you're only
going to learn about new results
on the period of how
often you're polling.
Users nowadays have
come to expect push.
So as opposed to using
a client-generated query
in the scenario, what you really
want is you want the server
to be running the
query on your behalf.
You want the server to be
running the query on your behalf
in the background and
you want that to happen
after every single record
save whether it was you
or somebody else that
saved the record.
Lastly, of course,
you want pushes
when the results have changes.
Well, we've given you this and
we call that subscriptions.
Yay.
[ Applause ]
So subscriptions are
exposed in our API
as the CKSubscription class.
They combine a record
type, a predicate and push.
Push is delivered via
the Apple Push Service.
If you've used APS in the
past, you're largely familiar
with this, but note CloudKit
pushes are slightly augmented.
They contain CloudKit
specific information
about what caused
the push to happen.
Let's have a look at an example.
Here we have a phone and that
phone is interested in parties
that are going to be
happening in the future.
This phone when it sees that
happening wants to be alerted
with a push that
says party time.
The phone is going to go ahead
and save that up to iCloud
and iCloud is going to,
you know, shuffle it away
with all the other
subscriptions.
Now along comes the Mac.
The Mac creates a new record.
It's a record-type party
and it's happening tonight
and because the Mac didn't chose
to give us a RecordID we created
that random UUID you see.
The Mac goes ahead and
saves that to ICloud.
ICloud is then going
to loop through all
of the subscriptions
that it knows about.
Eventually it's going
to come across this one.
It's going to check
and say, yeah, okay,
this is a new party and, yeah,
it's happening in the future.
So at that point it's going to
create a push and it's going
to take some information
from the subscription.
Here it took the alert
string party time.
It's going to take
other information
from the record itself.
Here we're pulling
in the RecordID.
Now that I've constructed
this augmented payload,
I can send that augmented
payload down to all clients
that are registered
and interested in it.
So let's look at some code.
How do I create a subscription?
Well, a subscription combines
a record type and a predicate.
Because a subscription
is also in charge
of telling the server how
you want to be alerted,
we introduce a notion
called CKNotificationInfo.
Here we're requesting that
the server badges our icon,
that it plays a particular sound
pulled out of my resources,
and that it shows an alert
string based on a string
in my localized strings file.
I can associate that
notification info
with a subscription and now
I've created everything I need
in my subscription.
Let's go ahead and
save it to the server.
As you might imagine via the
convenience API, it's simple,
it's asynchronous and it's
got great error handling.
Let's look at how you're going
to be handling subscriptions,
how you're going to handle
pushes as they come in.
If you've used APS in the
past, you're probably familiar
with this code snippet.
This is your application
delegate implementing the
ApplicationDidReceive
from notification method.
Now in most scenarios
if you know the format
of the push payload
that's coming in,
you would just then iterate
through that dictionary pulling
out the key value pairs
that you care about.
However, because
CloudKit was the one
that generated this push,
we ask that you let
CloudKit do that parsing.
So the way you would do that
is via CKNotification then
that really long one
I'm not going to name.
Once we've actually parsed
out a CKNotification you can
pull off APS level information
from it and you can also pull
off CloudKit level information
from it.
Here we're taking the
RecordID of the saved record
that caused the push to happen.
So between queries and
subscriptions we have an answer
to the big data,
tiny phone problem.
You're going to leave your
large data up in the cloud
and you're going to use
these two capabilities
to give your users a quick
view into that large dataset.
Now, I want to talk about
CloudKit user accounts.
As Olivier mentioned,
CloudKit is built on top
of the iCloud account
infrastructure.
So what does that mean?
I want to focus a little bit
on how accounts are exposed
to you explicitly
throughout the API.
When you think about
an account system,
the first thing you think
about is authentication
and CloudKit supports
authentication via the logged
in iCloud user, but
that's not, you know,
that's sort of behind the
scenes and you guys don't care
about that, that's implicit.
Let's talk about
the explicit things.
What do we give you
because we're built
on top of iCloud accounts?
We give you identity; a way
of identifying the user.
We give you metadata;
the ability to save
and retrieve information
about users.
We do all of this in a
privacy conscientious manner
and we don't want
to disclose anything
if the user hasn't agreed to it
and lastly we give
users the ability
to discover their friends that
are using your application.
Let's dive into each
one of these.
First of all we're going
to talk about identity.
So, here's our model.
We've got our client,
our application running
on the client, and all
of these different users
and their private databases
up in the container.
Your specific client is
going to be linked to one
and only one of those users.
This is related to
the user that's logged
in via iCloud locally
on your device.
Because this is iCloud we've
got a rich backing store
of user information and
because iCloud is the one
that is hosting your container
we can correlate users.
For example, here we
see that the user,
whose email address is
c at iCloud dot com,
is linked to your
current client.
So given this setup how are we
going to present an identity?
How are we going to let
you know, your client,
your application, know
what user is logged in?
Well, natively you might
think let's give them an
email address.
We're not going to
do that obviously.
That's private user
identifiable information
and we don't want
to give that out.
So, instead what we
do is on a container
by container basis we
come up with a random ID.
This is an identifier
that is stable
so that is your application no
matter what client it's running
on talking to this container
will get the same identifier,
but it's not identifying
the user via any
personal information.
So we feel confident
giving you this identifier.
You can take this identifier
and do with it what you will.
Note that different applications
running on your phone
because they're talking to
different containers are going
to get back different container
scoped RecordIdentifiers
for the same user.
This goes back to what we
talked about in the beginning
that we've got user
encapsulation.
So user identity.
We expose user identity
via API as a user RecordID.
It is a stable identifier
for this user.
It will be the same for
your application no matter
where your application
is running.
It's scoped to the container
so 2 different applications
are going to come
up with different
identifiers for the same user.
This is a feature.
Lastly this is an
independent API.
This is a section of
the CloudKit framework.
You can use this
in collaboration
with the database API or you can
use this completely separately.
We've given you enough
support that if you wanted
to you could implement
a login via iCloud flow
in your application using
the CloudKit framework.
Let's have a look at the code.
[ Applause ]
All right let's have
a look at the code.
Because identity is a
container-scoped notion
and not a database-scoped
notion, we go to our container
to learn about our user.
Here we're asking our container
to fetch the user RecordID.
Now because we may have
to talk to the server
to figure this out, for example,
the first time you access
and try to learn about
a RecordID we have to go
to the server to do that
translation and come
up with a container-scoped info.
So, asynchronous and we
have to do error handling.
That's user identity.
Let's talk about user
metadata and quickly
to recap the problem what we
have here is we have a stable
identifier and we've
got a desire
to set key value pairs
based on that identifier.
I don't know about you but
to me that sounds very much
like what a record
was built to do.
So we expose users
as user records.
Looking inside a container
within a database we see
there is one user record
in the private database
that user record
represents your user.
There are many user records
inside the public database
representing each one of the
users of your application.
One of them will have a RecordID
that matches your
currently logged
in iCloud user's RecordID.
So, user metadata.
Exposed via our framework
as a user record.
There's one per database that
represents your current user.
User records in the
public database
like any other default
record are world readable.
They're treated mostly
like an ordinary record
with a record type
that we exposed
in the framework
CKRecord TypeUserRecord,
but there are a couple
of caveats.
First off these records
are reserved by the system.
You do not create a user record.
Rather you fetch an
existing one from the server.
What that means is
that you can be assured
that when you fetch a
record for your current user
but it has not been spoofed.
It was, indeed, iCloud
that created
that record in the first place.
Secondly, we think that it
doesn't make sense for you
to be able to query the
entire set of user records
in the public database.
It doesn't really make sense to
be able to say I want to look
at all users whose first
name begins with A.
It's a little bit too course
grained for something that's so,
that we want to protect
privacy around.
So we don't allow you
to query user records.
Don't worry we're going to fix
that in a couple of slides.
All right so what
does it look like?
Here we have the same
code that we saw earlier
and we're fetching
a user RecordID.
Once I have that CKRecordID I
can go ahead and I can fetch
that record from either
database that I choose.
Here I'm choosing to fetch a
record with that identifier
from the public database.
Assuming that I don't get an
error I now had a live CKRecord
that represents this
user and I can treat it
like I would any other CKRecord.
I can pull records, excuse me,
I can pull key value pairs off
of it, I can set key value
pairs on it, and if I wanted to,
I could go ahead and save
it back to the server.
Now let's talk about privacy.
We care very much about
our user's privacy.
Therefore, we disclose
no information,
no personally identifying
user information
about the current
user by default.
Now we recognize that in some
cases your application is going
to want to have limited access
to metadata about the user.
So, if you want that data, you
can request that from CloudKit.
When you do, we're going to
go to the user to make sure
that they're okay with that.
Here we see an example
of the party application
requesting the ability
for my user account
to be discoverable
within the application.
The user can either choose
to allow or deny that.
Assuming that the
user has acquiesced
to this privacy request,
we can go on to the next
phase, which is discovery.
So let's talk a little
bit about user discovery.
Here's our image.
We've got our client
talking to a container
and the container
is backed by iCloud
and iCloud has all this
rich user information.
If we look a little bit
more on the client side,
we see there's actually
two different processes
involved here.
There's your client process
and then there's
the CloudKit process
and it's the CloudKit process
that's the one that's actually
talking over the wire.
So let's examine what
user discovery would look
like if you want to
discover information
about a user given a RecordID.
You take that RecordID and you
can send it off to CloudKit.
CloudKit is going to in turn
send it up to the container.
Once it hits the
container we're going
to ask the iCloud
account info to exchange
out for different information
for information about that user.
If that user has opted
in to discoverability,
we're going to get
information back.
That information can
traverse back to CloudKit
and back via the process
boundary over to your client,
but we're not restricted
to just RecordIDs.
If your user enters
in an email address,
we can do the same
sort of dance.
This email address is sent from
your client over to CloudKit
and CloudKit is then going
to hash it out a whole bunch
of times so that we're not
sending personal info off the
client, and we'll send
that up to the container.
That container exchanges it
with iCloud and if the target
of this discovery has opted
in to discoverability,
we're going to get
a result sent back.
Those results can
go back to CloudKit
and can traverse back
up to your client.
Now, I'd like to think
that are we are pretty good
about naming things in
CloudKit but this one we sort
of didn't really do well.
So we offer a different
way of doing user discovery
that we call the whole address
book and it's a way for you
to discover the whole
address book.
The way this works is that your
client is going to say I would
like to discover the user
RecordIDs and more information
about every user that is friends
with my currently
logged in iCloud user.
You send that request over
to the CloudKit process.
The CloudKit process
is then going to pull
in the user's address book.
We're going to take all
the emailed addresses
in that address book and
we're going to hash them up
and we're going to
send, you know,
a non-personally
identifying version
of that address book
up to the container.
The container is going
to send it off to iCloud
and for those members of my
address book that have opted
into discoverability I'm going
to learn information about them.
That information is going
to come back to CloudKit
and it's going to be sent
over the process
boundary to your client.
Now if you'll note at
no point did your client
in this little flow have access
to the user's address book.
What this means is that we
can give you the support
without requiring that your
user allows your application
to the address book meaning
that you don't have to have
that blue alert, which
is now the white alert,
giving your application
access to the address book.
You can leverage it
without access to it.
[ Applause ]
So user discovery.
These are the three
different kinds of inputs
that we can have
for user discovery.
You can start off with a user
RecordID, an email address
or request to view the
entire address book.
What do you get back
from user discovery?
Well, you'll get
back a user RecordID.
In the latter two cases,
that's new information.
You also get back the first
and last name of this user.
Of course it bears
repeating first
and last name is personally
identifying information
so you're only going to get
discovery results for users
that have opted into
discoverability.
Let's have a look
at some code here.
Here we are asking our default
container to discover all
of my users that are
part of my address book.
In the response, again,
asynchronous error handling
in the successful response
case what we see is
that we get back a
CKDiscoveredUserInfo object
and that user info from that
I can pull a user RecordID
and a first and last name.
So these are really
the four tent poles
of how we do user accounts.
We give you a stable identifier,
we give you the ability to store
and retrieve metadata about
users, we protect user's privacy
and we give your
users the ability
to discover their friends
in your application.
Now, to tell you when it's
appropriate to use CloudKit
versus some of the other
iCloud technologies
that we already have exposed,
I'd like to invite
back up Olivier Bonnet.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Paul.
So CloudKit is the new framework
but it doesn't obsolete
or deprecate any of
the existing tools.
It's really just a new
tool in your toolbox.
Let's look at all the four
tools you now have and look
at where different use cases
where we think they make sense
and they're appropriate to use.
So, first, iCloud
Key Value Store.
iCloud Key Value Store keeps
small piles of data up to date
between your app and
the iCloud servers.
This is done asynchronously.
Your app doesn't
really need to care
about when and how this is done.
We think this is great
for small amounts of data
like application
preferences game states.
Conflict resolution is pretty
simple, last writer wins.
So, that's iCloud
Key Value Store.
iCloud Drive builds on top
of the existing iCloud
document APIs.
Doing so it provides full
offline cache on OS X;
all the files on
the iCloud drive
of the user are downloaded
on the OS X.
It's completely unstructured
and internally tied
to the file system.
You use the file coordination
APIs to read and write data
in your application iCloud
container on the file system
and the iCloud Drive daemon
takes care of uploading
and downloading those changes
up and from the iCloud servers.
We think it's great for document
centric apps or apps that need
to deal with an existing
file formats.
ICloud Core Data built on top
of iCloud Drive replicates
off specific user data
between all the user's devices.
It's great for keeping
private structured data in sync
but because it downloads
all the data
to all devices you're also
constrained to the size
of the smallest device
in that case.
Enters CloudKit, the
new kid on the block
and we think there are a
number of interesting use cases
where CloudKit makes sense
and complements pretty well
the existing technologies.
So first any public data.
If your app, if you need to
give access to all the users
of your app to large datasets,
CloudKit public databases are
pretty good compiling tool.
CloudKit supports both
structured and bulk data.
So you can use it to store large
files on iCloud and we take care
of downloading and uploading
them to the iCloud servers.
As Paul described, CloudKit has
good support for large datasets
where your app will want
to give a specific slice,
a specific view of large
data set to the user
at a giver point in time.
CloudKit lets you use the
existing accounts infrastructure
whether you need to
identify the user
or to let the user discover his
friends using your app CloudKit
enables you to do that.
Last but not least compared
to the other three technologies
we think CloudKit is closer
to the middle in some way.
In this case when you're using
CloudKit, your app is really
in control of when
the app is uploaded
or downloaded from the server.
Your app is controllng
the operations
and that is also why you need
to do this [inaudible] will do.
So, in summary, what
have we covered today?
CloudKit gives you
access to iCloud servers.
It supports both
public and private data.
structured and bulk data.
You can use it for large files.
It leverages the existing
iCloud account infrastructure
which means that the over
400 million iCloud accounts
out there are here for
you to take advantage of.
Apple is building
on it in a big way.
Both iCloud Drive and iCloud
file Library were built
from scratch on top of CloudKit.
We're super excited to see what
you're going to build on top
of this new framework.
So for more information
Dave is our evangelist.
We have some awesome
framework reference
on developer.apple.com website
as well as developer forums.
We have an advanced
CloudKit session on Thursday
and Jacob is going to tell you
everything you want to know
about that, Data Modeling and
Advanced Record Manipulations.
Thank you very much
for being here
and thank you for
your attention.
[ Applause ]