>> Good afternoon.
Welcome to Storyboards
and Controllers on OS X.
My name's Mike, and I work on
the Interface Builder team.
Today, I'd like to show you
how you can build your OS X
applications faster and easier
using the all-new Storyboards
in Xcode 6 and Yosemite.
I'm also going to be joined
later by my colleague Raleigh
from the AppKit team, who
will come up and take us
under the hood of the
new controllers API
that make Storyboards work.
So just a quick show
of hands here,
who is already building an app
today for iOS using Storyboards?
Oh, awesome, cool.
So you'll probably notice
a little bit of what I'm
about to show you is going
to look pretty familiar.
So what are we going to see?
First, I'm going to start by
giving you a brief overview
of how storyboards work.
Then, I'm going to give a demo
showing how you can quickly
connect the top-level
controllers
and interface your app
together using Xcode 6.
Hopefully, you'll see how
Storyboards can help you
structure your app into modular
and reusable view controllers.
Then, Raleigh's going to come up
and show us the view
controller API.
We'll see how all of the pieces
click together underneath the
Storyboard scenes, and he'll
show you the best places to hook
into the infrastructure.
And finally, as a bonus,
he's going to show you how
to use the new gesture
recognizers in OS X
without having to write
an NS event tracking loop.
All you have to do is just drag,
connect to your target
in action.
They're so simple,
it's simply amazing.
So in Xcode, Storyboards are a
great way to see all UI parts
of your application laid out in
a way that's easy to understand.
Take for example an
application like Pages.
We can decompose each of
the major pieces of the UI
into each major section
of functionality,
like the window toolbar,
the document area,
and the shape picker.
Each of these views has a
corresponding controller,
and we show that in the
storyboard as a scene.
Each scene represents a view
and view controller pair.
The lines connecting the
scenes, known as segues,
show the relationships
between them.
Some of these relationships
represent a containment
of view controllers
inside of each other.
Other segue lines
represent transitions
between view controllers.
But each one represents
a flow of data
in some form within the app.
In your code, view controllers
are where you, the developer,
actually get your hands
into controlling both the UI
and the underlying data model.
Each top-level scene
in a storyboard represents one
view controller in your code.
Each controller is a
reusable self-contained module
of user interface
and control logic.
Within that controller scene,
you can do everything you
would normally do inside
of a ZIB file, like
place the UI,
set up auto layout constraints,
connect outlets and actions
to their parent view controllers
and its represented object.
So how do these scenes actually
connect with each other?
Well, segues are really the
glue, or the connective tissues,
between each of the major
blocks of your apps UI.
You may have noticed
that on iOS,
segues usually represent
a transition
between whole full-screen views.
When we took a look
at the relationships
between view controllers
on OS X, though,
we noticed a somewhat different
relationship: containment.
On OS X, most applications tend
to group their views
together in the same window.
There aren't many
transitions bringing views on-
and off-screen because you
actually have the screen real
estate to show them all
inside the same window.
Some are grouped in splits
or sometimes hidden in tabs.
That's not to say that we
don't have presentation segues
on OS X as well.
We just have fewer of
them: at modal dialogues,
window modal sheets,
and popovers.
Like the presentation
segues on iOS,
in order to make these work
it's your responsibility
to override the Prepare
for Segue method
in your parent view controller.
From there, you can
take the passed in
and a storyboard segue object,
get the destination view
controller and configure it
and set the represented object,
or do any other initialization
you need,
right before it's
presented up on screen.
So if there's one line of code
that is absolutely necessary
and that you need to remember,
it's Prepare for Segue.
So at build time, each
storyboard scene is broken
down into each of its
constituent parts.
Views are separated
from view controllers,
windows are separated
from window controllers,
and the transition
segues are embedded inside
of their parent controllers.
This is done to make the process
of loading your user interface
as lazy as possible at runtime.
Then, as a performance
optimization,
the container controllers
absorb all
of their child controllers
together in the same unit.
This is because all of
those controllers are going
to be needed at the
initial load time
of the top-level
container controller,
and it's just more efficient
to unarchive one file.
Then, each unit is compiled
into a NIB file, and then all
of the NIBs are bundled together
inside of a .storyboardc bundle.
Then, that bundle
is nestled inside
of your Applications
Resources Directory,
and then Up Your App
can go to the store.
So we've put a lot
of thought and work
into the Storyboard Compiler
to make sure you get the
most efficient loading
at runtime while letting you use
the most flexible UI to be able
to connect and rewire
the relationships
between your controllers
on the canvas,
all with the absolute
minimum of glue code.
So let's see how this all works
over here on the demo machine.
So as our way of testing
storyboards and to make sure
that everything that we're
building is actually working,
we started by rewriting an
old piece of sample code
that you may be familiar
with called Sketch.
In our storyboard based
Sketch: The Next Generation,
we're taking a classic
document based app
and we're remodeling
much of the control logic
into view controllers.
So as you can see here, we
have the main storyboard
of our application.
It already has a number of
scenes that we've prepopulated
with view controllers, and what
we want to do is to show a UI
that has our canvas where you
can drop shapes and use gestures
to manipulate them
and then have a split.
And on the other side of that
will be the inspector area
where you can see the
different properties
of the currently selected shape.
So to model this, I'm going to
use a split view controller,
and I'm just going to drag
that out into the canvas here.
And it comes with two
view controllers already,
which I don't really need
because I already have my canvas
that I can just wire up
here and drag, connect
and create a split
item out of that.
And then we want to wire
up the inspector as well.
And you can see here we
have like a little preview
of what the canvas and
the inspector look like.
And it's using the
auto layout constraints
that have already been
set in those views.
Also, to get this to show up,
we want to take our
window controller
and connect the new split
view controller and say
that this is going to be the
windows content view controller.
So looks like all of
our boxes have all
of the lines connected to them.
Let's run this and
see what shows up.
So here is our application,
and as I resize it,
you'll notice that, you know,
we have a good enforced
minimum size
from our auto layout
constraints,
but the split is not
sticking kind of to the side
where we would want it.
As we resize the window it
just keeps getting bigger.
So I know what I
can do to fix this.
I just have to go to the
split view controller
and find the split view item
that corresponds to that.
And I can set the holding
priority of the split
to be just a little bit
more than the default.
And while we're here,
we might as well mark it
as saying it can collapse
because, you know,
we might not want to always
see the details of all
of the shapes on canvas.
So let's run this
and see how it looks.
All right.
Now, as I drag this, we notice
that the split view edge is
actually hugging the side
of the window, as we want it,
so let's try and add a shape.
Oh, and it looks like we don't
have our Shape Add button hooked
up, so I'm going to
create a new kind of segue.
And I'm going to show the shape
picker controller as a popover.
And in order to make this work
though, there is one piece
of code that we all have to
remember to implement in order
for these to work is
the Prepare for Segue.
So I'm actually going to
open up the Assistant Editor
and I should see the
canvas view controller.
Here we go.
And it looks like somebody has
already helpfully written the
code for me, so I'm just
going to uncomment it here.
And what it does is it takes
the destination view controller
out of the Passed In
and a storyboard segue.
And what we're doing is we're
initializing it and saying
that the shape container
is going to be the canvas,
which is ourself in this case.
The canvas is initiating the
segue and it's also going
to be the destination where we
want to add new shapes to it.
So let's build and run this.
And when we click on it, great.
So now we have a shape.
I can't seem to do
anything with it.
I can't move it, but I think
I'll leave that for Raleigh.
But as one more little bonus
before I leave, I want to hook
up what is going to be
a Preferences window.
And I just want to show you just
how easy this is 'cause this is
one of my favorite features.
I just couldn't wait
to show you guys.
Right here we have
a TabViewController
that has both a General
Pref pane
and some keyboard shortcuts.
And what I can do
is I can wire this
up to the Preferences menu item.
And just say for the sake
of demo we're just going
to show this as a
modal dialogue.
And if I run this, you'll
notice that we have a sketch
with fully functional
preferences.
And you notice the
nice new crossfade
between these two views,
which comes with the
TabViewController.
But this doesn't look exactly
like Preferences windows
that you're used to.
One of the really cool
options that have been added
to the TabViewController
is a new style that,
besides just tabs on
top or tabs on bottom,
we can actually say we
want toolbar style tabs.
And if we actually specify the
class of our view controllers --
in this case this is the General
Prefs pane view controller,
and then this one is the
keyboard shortcuts view
controller -- we will find
within your document the images
that are named the same as the
class of the view controller.
So when we run this now, you'll
see a new Preferences window
that has the icons
and the titles
of the child view controllers.
[ Applause ]
So let's switch back to slides.
So how easy was that?
Just by wiring up a few
segues on the canvas
and overriding Prepare
for Segue,
we are able to plumb
together the view controllers
into a fully functional
application.
And that Preferences window
didn't even use a single line
of code.
So now I'd like to
ask Raleigh to come up
and show us how storyboards
actually works under the hood.
>> Thank you, Mike.
[ Applause ]
Now that you've seen how
incredibly easy it is
to design your application
using storyboards
and to wire everything up,
I'm going to pop open the hood
and we're going to take a look
at the machinery underneath
that drives this whole thing.
We've got a lot to cover here.
Just a little bit of API
with storyboards itself.
There's a lot of new API
with view controllers.
We're going to talk a little bit
about how window controllers
fits in with our proliferation
of view controllers
that we're now adding.
And we'll wrap it up
with gesture recognizers
and how they really mesh really
nicely with view controllers
and designing your application.
It's really awesome.
So let's dig right
in with storyboards.
Storyboards are a resource file
in your project like NIBs are.
By default if you
do the checkbox
when you create a new project,
you can start off
with a storyboard.
Or if you just create a
storyboard in your project,
a new one in the settings of
your project for your target,
you could just right there
in the main interface set
which storyboard to use
as your main interface.
Or even a NIB file, if you
happen to be transitioning
from an old project
to a new one,
and the right thing will happen.
If you find yourself
with the need to dig
down into the Info.plist
and set the keys manually,
this is the
NSMainStoryboardFile.
This is the key you need
to set in your Info.plist
to bring up the storyboard.
When we load the initial
storyboard, it's going to go
through this path just like
you can use this API storyboard
with name to load any storyboard
that you have in your resources,
and you could load
it from a name.
And then you'd need
to instantiate the
initial controller.
What's the initial
controller you might ask?
Well, that's the controller that
has the arrow pointing to it
without some beginning
part to it.
This is the initial guy.
There's always one of
them with your storyboard.
That's going to be the
initial controller,
and it's generally the
one you want to load up.
When we load your
main storyboard file,
we'll automatically instantiate
the initial controller
and set it running
on your behalf.
Not every controller that you
have in your storyboard needs
to be wired back up to that
initial view controller.
You can have some that just
stand alone all on their own
and you can give
them an identifier.
And you can access
them by asking
to instantiate the
controller with identifier.
We'll find it in the
storyboard with that name.
We'll instantiate, start doing
the wiring up and hand it back
to you, then you can
take it from there.
So that's really all there is
with storyboards as far as API.
There's not much
there; they just work.
It's really nice.
With view controllers -- we'll
move on to view controllers --
there's a ton of new API here.
There's so much new API in
view controllers that I've got
to break it down into sections.
So we'll talk about loading and
layout and the life cycle there.
About containerships; we've
got some really nice new stuff
with containership.
Triggered segues, as you saw
with the Plus button
to do the popover.
And we'll wrap it up with how
to do things completely manual
if you need to get
down to that level.
So we have a lot of new
properties in NSViewController
for loading, display,
and layout.
All of these methods
here are new except
for View Loaded,
which is the top one.
And the way I want
to talk about them is
in the life cycle
and how they're used.
You'll have your
view controller.
It will get initted
and allocated.
And it doesn't have a view
yet because view controllers
like to lazily load their
views, so there's no view yet.
View loaded is going
to return no if you ask
for its property at this point.
Then load view is
going to get called.
This has generally been the
place where you've gone ahead
and subclassed NSViewController
and overrode load view just
to call supernormally.
By default, AppKit will go
ahead and try and load the NIB
with the name that you gave it
if you initialized it
init with NIB name.
But new on Yosemite is
AppKit will go ahead
and if your NIB name is
nil, will look for a NIB
that has the same name
as your view controller
and automatically
load that NIB for you.
So now you don't have to
subclass your view controller
to get the right NIB loaded.
You just name your NIB file
the right thing and it'll do it
for you automatically.
During load view, set view
is going to get called
and your view is finally
set on your view controller.
View loaded will now return yes.
And then we return
from load view,
but before we continue the
run load, before we go back
to giving control to you
and your application,
view did load is going to be
called on your view controller.
It is at this point now
instead of overriding load view,
you override view did load
and you do your one-time
instantiation finalization stuff
that you need to do there.
So this is something that
you only want to do once
when the view is loaded and
you'll never need to do again
because your view is going
to be hanging around.
Now you're going to go ahead
and put your view in a window,
get the window on screen
and we're going to go
through the life
cycle of the view.
So before your view gets
in the window as you add it
into the window, we'll
call view will appear.
And there are a few other places
that view will appear
gets called.
Whenever the window is
becoming visible for example,
as you're ordering it front,
perhaps the user has
previously hidden the window
or minimized it and now
they're unminimizing the window.
And so this is another case
where you'll get a
view will appear.
So you could do some really
interesting things here.
For example, you might want
to set your highlight color.
So the first time that
your view is asked to draw,
it draws with the correct
highlight color for example.
The animation is
now going to occur
after you return from this.
The window will be
animated on screen.
If you're unhiding the view
or you're doing some kind
of transition, that
transition animation occurs.
When that completes and your
view is drawn at least once,
view did appear will be
called in the view controller.
And now you can wire up
things that you didn't want
to interfere with
that animation.
And you only want it
to be visible while
the window is visible
and your view is displayed.
You might want to set
up, just as an example,
some animation that's running
here that just runs constantly
but only once it's visible.
At this point, the user
interacts with your view,
interacts with your
user interface.
You're going to update your
constraints on your view,
you're going to dirty them.
Your view controller
gets to participate
in updating the constraints
with Update View Constraints,
and you get informed of when
layout is going to happen
with the will layout and
after layout happened
if you did layout.
So you can participate in
this as you normally would
with auto layout, but
you get to do it now
at the view controller level.
And at some point you're going
to remove the view
from the window.
Perhaps you've changed tabs and
now the view is being hidden
or you've hiding the window.
The user is hiding the window,
or you're just outright
closing the window.
In either of these cases
you will be preceded
with a view will disappear.
That animation we started
in view did appear,
this is where we
would want to stop it.
Then the animation
occurs and the view
or the window disappears with
the appropriate animation
and will call you back
with a view did disappear,
and now you can release
any kind of final resources
that you don't want to hang on
to as the window is not visible
or your view is no
longer part of the window.
Then the life cycle just
continues as you switch tabs
and the views come back and go
away and windows hide and show.
We just continue this cycle.
New in Yosemite,
NSViewController is now
in the responder chain.
Where if we would start
off with our canvas view,
as we had in our demo
application there,
an event is hit tested to
the canvas view and flows
up through the split
view to the window
and finally your
window controller.
Your view controllers,
our canvas view controller
and split view controller,
can now participate in this.
And they're automatically wired
up in the responder chain
right after their view.
So you can now participate
in events
and more importantly
in action methods.
And action methods is where
it really comes in handy.
For example, cut,
copy, and paste.
In your menu bar, cut, copy, and
paste is wired up to the cut,
copy, and paste actions
to the first responder.
And that might be the
canvas view in this case.
Well, our canvas view
doesn't really do much.
Most of our logic is in
our canvas view controller.
And previously you would've
had to catch cut, copy,
and paste in your view
and somehow get it
to your controller.
And now that canvas
view controller is
in the responder chain, you
can put the copy method right
in your canvas view controller
and canvas view can be
totally oblivious to this.
And it works out really nicely.
I do want to point out,
though, that we only wire
up view controllers
automatically
in the responder chain if
you're linked on or after 10/10.
So let's move forward and
talk about containment.
We've got some really exciting
things to do with containment.
View controllers can
now have children
and you can give
back to your parent.
And the best way to talk about
containment is with an example.
So let's start off with tab view
controller and let's dive deep
into tab view controller.
So NSTabViewController is
going to manage in NSTabView.
And it manages a couple of
other views, and I'll get
into details there, but mainly
it manages the tab view.
It's going to lazily
load your tab views.
And this is one of
my favorite things.
In a past life, I've had tab
views that had a fair number
of tabs and a lot of content
in each one of those tabs.
And loading this NIB file
from disc took forever.
Now that we lazily
load the tab views,
just the initial selected
tab is going to get loaded
when you first bring
up your interface.
And it is much more
responsive to the user
that way; I really love this.
It's now much easier
to customize your tabs
using a tab view controller,
and I'll get into specifics
about that in a little bit.
And as you saw in the
demo it's incredibly easy.
Without code, you could get a
nice preferences user interface
style using a tab
view controller.
And I'll show you exactly how
you would do that in code.
And it's just as easy as Mike
did it in the demo in IB.
On Mavericks an NSTabView looks
like this: There's an NSTabView.
It manages a collection
of NSTabView items.
Those tab view items
each have a view
and some additional
properties, such as the label.
So we know what label
to put in the tab.
With tab view controller,
logically things are
now laid out like this.
There's an NSTabViewController
and the tab view
controller owns an NSTabView
and manages the collection
of NSTabView items.
NSTabView item now has a couple
of additional properties:
the image, which is kind of
fun so you can get an image
in there, and of course
the view controller.
And it's the view controller
that now owns the view,
and it can lazily load the view
as you switch to those tabs.
Since NSTabViewController
manages a collection
of tab view items, you can
of course get the
tab view item array.
You can also find out what the
selected tab view item index is.
And this is KVO-compliant,
so you can observe this.
This is much easier to observe
the selected tab view item index
than it was previously to have
a delegate and have to respond
to all the delegate methods.
So you don't have
to do that anymore.
As with any sort of containment
API, there's the add, insert,
and remove tab view items.
And if you have a child view
controller that is in one
of the tabs, you can just ask
for the tab view item associated
with it via tab view
item for view controller.
NSTabViewItem also has this
really nifty class method on it,
Tab View Item With
View Controller.
So you could take any generic
view controller that you have
and you can create a
default tab view controller
for it using this method.
And what this does is it doesn't
just create a generic tab
view item.
It tries to populate it with
the appropriate information
from the child view controller.
For example, it will
take the title
of your child view
controller and set
that as the label of
the tab view item.
And we'll also take
it a step further.
As Mike showed in the demo,
we look at the class name
of the view controller and we
try and find imagery sources
with that same name or we
prefer if it's the name
with a dash tab view item
and we'll automatically set
that image as the image
as the NSTabView item.
So you can get the label and
the item just automatically
that way.
TabViewController has some
additional properties,
which are pretty interesting.
There's the tab style
as Mike showed you.
We have segmented control
on top and on bottom.
So the tabs are now drawn
with the segmented control.
We'll touch on that a
little bit more real soon.
There's the toolbar style.
That's all you have to do.
You set the tab style
to toolbar.
The TabViewController
will create the toolbar
on your behalf and
place it in the window
as the toolbar; you're done.
And then there's unspecified,
which is really interesting,
and I'll get to that a little
bit more in just a second.
As I talked about, there
is a segmented control
that now displays the tabs.
You can get the segmented
control.
You can supply your own
segmented control subclass
if you want and draw them in
your subclass however you wish.
But if you set the tab
style to unspecified,
what you can do then is go
and apply your own
layout constraints
to the segmented control
and have the segmented control
appear where you want it
to appear and do
the layout yourself.
So you have much more customized
ability with tab view controller
than you've had previously.
There are some transition
options.
Automatically by default
we set it to crossfade.
Mike showed you this in
the demo as he changed tabs
in our preferences UI.
It did this nice
little crossfade effect.
You can set it to none
and have the old style
where it just switches.
We have various sliding
directions:
up, down, left and right.
You can combine directions
that are on different axes,
so you can combine
an up with a left,
but you can't combine
an up with a down.
That wouldn't actually
animate anything,
so we don't let you do that.
I do really want to
point out, though,
slide forward and
slide backwards.
These are really important if
you're going to do any sort
of horizontal sliding
because they work
in the appropriate direction
for your users language.
So they work correctly in
right to left languages.
They will go the right way and
they will go the correct way
for left to right
languages as well.
And you just let AppKit worry
about what the right
directions are
and we'll handle that for you.
As I mentioned,
NSTabViewController
manages the tab view item.
In NSTabView it owns a tab view.
So it's important that you let
NSTabViewController manage it
for you.
You don't really need to
get to it and change it.
There are a few properties,
very few properties,
that you can modify directly
to get to the tab view.
If you find you really
need to do this,
look at the NSTabViewController
header.
It specifies exactly
what you can set,
but in general let's have
your controller manage it.
I also want to point out here
that as NSTabViewController
is a subclass
of view controller,
it has a view.
The view is not the tab view.
Tab view controller has a
view that contains a tab view
and a segmented control
and perhaps other views
as tab view controller
needs to manage it.
So let tab view controller
handle it for you.
When you are using
the toolbar style,
NSTabViewController is the
delegate of the toolbar.
And you might want to
override these methods.
Create a subclass of
NSTabViewController
and override these
delegate methods.
Perhaps you want to do something
like add some additional items
to the toolbar that aren't tabs.
For example, a search
field, right.
If you want a search field,
then your purpose is UI.
Search isn't a tab,
so you will need
to override these
toolbar delegate methods
and insert the search
field yourself.
I do want to point out that
these have the nice NS required
Super attribute on them, so if
you do override these methods,
you must call Super, and
the compiler will help you
remember that.
So that's tab view controller.
Let's take a look
at another example.
We're introducing split
view controller in Yosemite.
It manages it in a split view
and it does lazy
loading of views.
And it requires auto layout.
It does all of the managing of
the splits and how they move
with window resizing,
all view, auto layout.
It would just start adding
constraints to your window.
But we have all migrated
our apps forward
to using auto layout, so that
won't be a problem, right?
So in a split view
controller today on Mavericks
in a split view it
manages two or more views.
It has a divider in there.
And in a split view controller,
logically it's now laid
out like this, in a split
view controller owns.
And in a split view it manages a
collection of split view items.
Those items have some
nice new properties.
And a split view item is
a completely new class
in Yosemite.
Of course it has
a view controller,
which will lazily load its view.
And you can set property such
as collapse, can't collapse
and the holding priority.
Mike showed you how important
the holding priority is.
These were properties
that you used to have
to override the delegate for
split view and be the delegate
for the split view controller.
You don't need to
do that anymore.
You can just set
these properties right
on the split view item.
So it's a lot easier
to do it that way.
And of course you can create
a default split view item
if you have some
child view controller.
Pro Tip: If you want to
animate a collapsible split,
you use the animator proxy
on the split view item.
So you see split view item
animator, set collapsed yes
or no, and the collapse or
expansion animation will happen
for you in a nice,
animated fashion.
Some additional properties.
Since we manage a
collection of split view items
of course you can get to
the split view items array.
The obligatory add and
certain remove split view item,
and if you have a child view
controller you can find its
associated split view item
by asking split view item
for a view controller.
Now that we've taken a look
at a couple of examples
that we're doing in
AppKit, I want to point out
and stress the pattern
we're using here.
And this is the pattern that
we think you should use as well
if you find the need to write
your own containment style
of view controllers.
There's your containment
view controller that's going
to manage some collection
of items
so those items can have the
specific information associated
with that.
The item will go ahead
and own a view controller
that will then be able
to lazily load the view.
If you're familiar with iOS,
this is a little different
than iOS, where iOS you
have to have a special type
of view controller
subclass that then may
or may not own a
special type of item.
We've inverted that
on OS X Yosemite,
and one of the reasons is
that now your child view
controllers can be a lot
more generic.
And this is the pattern that
we're using on OS X Yosemite
and the pattern we
suggest you follow as well.
There are some generic container
API with view controllers
that are exposed at the
NSViewController level.
You can get an array of child
view controllers and add-ins
or remove child view
controllers.
But these APIs only manage
the collection itself.
It's up to the subclass to
know what to do with them.
Like tab view controller will
go ahead and create another tab,
but won't show the views
or load the views yet,
where split view
controller will go ahead
and immediately add
it as another split.
So it becomes important
to do the right thing
in your subclass there.
But now, with these generic
APIs, you can dig down and look
at the child view
controllers associated
with the view controller.
Or if you have a child view
controller, you can go back up
and find its parent and as a
child view controller you can
just call on it, remove
from parent view controller,
and that's the easiest way
to take apart the
parent/child relationship there.
In view controller we have
this method transition
from view controller
to view controller,
which will do a nice animated
transition on your behalf.
This is what we have
with tab view controller
so it's the exact same options.
You can do none with a crossfade
or slide in various directions.
And that's containment
in view controllers.
There's another type
of relationship
with view controllers
and storyboards called
triggered segues.
These triggered segues
perform a presentation.
And a presentation needs to have
an identifier so we can find it
in a storyboard if
needed manually.
And it's to have some
source view controller.
For example, the
canvas view controller
in this case is our source
to do our shape picker popup.
A destination controller,
which is going
to be our shape picker
controller, and then a style.
And as we did in the demo,
the segue style was a
popover and this was a segue.
Depending on the style,
there might be some other
attributes you need to set up.
For example, with a popover you
need to set up the anchor view.
Since we had dragged it
directly from the Plus button,
the anchor view was
wired up automatically,
but you could actually go in IB
and set the anchor
view for the popover.
As Mike pointed out,
the one line of code
that you really need to write
in the source view controller --
so in this case our
canvas view controller --
in your source view
controller you need
to override Prepare For Segue.
From the segue you can get
the identifier, so if you have
to deal with more than one
segue you can switch on that,
get the destination controller
and wire up anything that needs
to be wired up so that you
can have the proper lines
of communication or you can get
to the right model data objects
and show the UI with
the correct information.
Often, this is the
represented object
and you can just set the
destination controller
that represented object
to the right thing.
There are a couple of
additional segue APIs
that you might find
useful: shape perform segue
with identifier sender.
This will give you
a chance to step in
and dynamically prevent a segue
from performing if you need
to determine that pretty late.
And if you determine that
here, we will stop the segue
from really getting
off the ground.
Then you can call perform
segue with identifier,
identifier sender and we will
find the segue in the storyboard
for you and call perform,
which will flow back
through shape perform
segue with identifier
and of course call prepare
for segue and you could wire
up the represented object.
If you get nothing else out
of this whole talk today,
it's with your segues you need
to implement Prepare For Segue
in the source controller, wire
up your represented object
or whatever pieces of
information that you need
to bridge between the two,
and then let the segue happen.
Using Interface Builder
to wire up your segues
and do it all visually,
it's the easiest way to go.
It's our recommended approach.
We can take apart the
engine a little bit more
and we could look at the
manual API that's going
on under the hood that you
can also call directly.
So we're going ahead and
we're exposing this API.
You can ask source
view controller
to present some other
controller as a sheet,
as a modal window,
or as a popover.
And as the destination
controller, the sheet
or the modal window,
the controller
that is being presented,
you dismiss yourself
by calling dismiss controller
and AppKit will do whatever the
appropriate thing to do there is
and dismiss the controller
for you.
This is incredibly powerful
because it allows your
destination controllers
to be a lot more
modular and reusable.
For example, when Mike and I
were first doing this project
in IB, it was like,
"Oh," you know,
"sheet's the first
thing in there.
We need to have our picker
come down as a sheet."
And we wired up present
view controller
as sheet, and that was easy.
Then we said, "No, no, it'll
look much nicer as a popover.
That'd be cool, yeah."
So the only thing we had to
change was the segue type
to present it as a popover.
Our destination controller just
calls it dismiss controller.
It didn't need to know
how to dismiss a popover
or that dismissing a sheet
in raw code is actually
dramatically different.
Just go ahead and let
NSViewController handle
that on your behalf and it'll
do the appropriate thing.
We can actually go yet
one more level deeper,
and there's at the
lowest level present view
controller animator.
And there is a view controller
presentation animator protocol,
and we're publishing
this as well in Yosemite.
So you can create your own
presentation animator object,
implement the protocol, which
is just these two methods,
animate presentation of view
controller from view controller.
So when you do a presentation,
we will take the instance
of your animator object,
called animate presentation
of view controller
from view controller,
and then you can handle the
animation however you want.
Once the user is finished and
dismiss controller is called,
it will bubble up
to the right place.
We will take that same
instance that we had before.
We've stashed it.
We will call animate dismissal.
The animate dismissal view
controller from view controller.
You're now responsible for doing
any dismissal animation however
you see fit, and once we return
from that we will go ahead
and release the animator object.
So that's view controllers.
There's a lot of new
API in view controllers.
It's really powerful.
We can't wait to see what
you are going to do with it.
It's going to be a lot of fun.
So let's move forward and talk
about window controllers a
little bit and how they fit
in with this large
collection of view controllers
that we're going to be
adding to our applications.
So let's just look at some
of the new API we have
in window controller.
There's just a little bit.
Namely, there is a
content view controller,
and this is a requirement.
And when you're wiring up your
storyboard, you need to set
up a content view controller
to your window controller.
NSWindow also has a content view
controller property that's new
on it.
And what happens is when window
controller lazily loads the
window, it sets the windows
content view controller
to be the content
view controller
that the window controller
has associated with it.
Of course, like view controller,
you can also get the storyboard
that loaded the window
controller,
if one loaded the
window controller,
or it will return nil if your
window controller wasn't loaded
from a storyboard.
And of course window
controllers,
like view controllers,
can be presented
and you can call
dismiss controller
on the window controller and
the right dismissal will happen.
NSWindowController also
implements the segue protocol
so that it can prepare for
segue and you can override that.
You can ask it to perform
a segue with an identifier,
and you can of course
override Should Perform Segue
to do dynamic suppression
in rare instances.
But what really does a window
controller responsible for now?
Because we have these
view controllers
and all your logic is leveling
way down in view controller.
So your window controller
should just manage the window,
you know, things like
should I really close
when the Close button
was pressed?
Manage the titlebar
and the toolbar,
make sure that has the
appropriate look there.
Manage the content
view controller.
We're going to have a
content in the window,
the window controller's going
to go ahead and manage that.
Window controllers over
time has become a place
where you put a lot
of view logic.
It was a convenient place to
put view logic for various parts
of your user interface.
But now that we have
view controllers
and a specified parent/child
relationship
and a hierarchy here with
segues, you can move all
of that unrelated logic
down to their appropriate
view controllers.
And now you have
a few controllers
which are reusable modules,
and they're more cohesive,
independent modules.
And you don't have unrelated
code in your window controller
that you don't need anymore.
So your window controller
is a lot smaller
and is a lot more
readable and maintainable.
So that's window controllers.
So let's talk a little bit
about gesture recognizers.
I'm really excited about
gesture recognizers.
I'm an event guy at heart, so I
like to play around with events.
So we're introducing gesture
recognizers to OS X Yosemite.
The API is nearly identical
to what it is on iOS.
They're a lot of fun.
But when you're looking
at it on the desktop,
most gestures aren't
determined the same way
that they are on iOS.
On iOS, you have to
look at the raw touches
and figure out what that means.
If you do a pinch gesture
on the trackpad on OS X,
the trackpad itself recognizes
that as a magnification
and it sends magnification
events.
So you don't have
to figure that out.
But not everything
that we can recognize
as a gesture is prerecognized
for us at the lower levels.
For example, what is a click?
You press on the
trackpad, which is going
to emulate a mouse event,
or you press a mouse button,
you get a mouse down event
followed by a mouse up event
without any drags in between.
So this is some different
events, and we can look
at them all together
and combine them for you
and go, "Oh, that's a click."
So we can recognize a click.
We can recognize that
independently and differently
than something that's a
click, a drag, and a release;
that's something else.
NSGestureRecognizer
is really good
in helping you disambiguate
user input.
How good? Well, this is code
that you might've had to write
if you had to figure
it out yourself.
This is seven tracking
loops deep of [inaudible].
And what this code is
trying to do is figure
out is this a click,
a double click,
a triple click, or a drag?
And it's trying to
sort all of this out
and all the logic that's
associated with it.
Gesture recognizers
clean this all up
and make it much more simpler
to disambiguate the user input,
gives you hooks to tap
into there when you need
to add some custom logic, and
it's much easier to maintain.
Gesture recognizers are a really
good fit for view controllers.
You really don't want to
have to override mouse
down in your view controller.
That's not something your
view controller should really
be doing.
And when you go to read your
code in your view controller,
you're going to see mouse down
and you're going to have to try
and figure out with
comments or by really looking
at the code what is this
mouse down trying to do.
View controllers have
a target action pair.
It will recognize the full
click or the full drag for you,
and now you can wire
that up to an action
in your view controller.
So instead of having mouse
down you have Select
or you have Drag.
And it's now obvious
in your code.
It's much more readable
on what to do
and it's partitioned out better.
Much more maintainable code.
Here's an example of
using gesture recognizers
in place with code.
This is alloc initting
a magnification
gesture recognizer.
You init the target
in the action.
I want to point out a slight
difference here from iOS.
On OS X, all of our controls
and our menus have a
single target action pair.
That's the pair down we use.
That's the pair down
we're continuing to use
with NSGestureRecognizer.
That's a little bit
different than iOS.
Once you have your gesture
recognize alloc initted,
you go ahead and
set it on some view.
Gesture recognizers need
to be attached to a view
and recognized for that view.
Optionally, you may
need to set the delegate
of your gesture recognizer
to your view controller.
Perhaps you need to
set up some more logic
to help disambiguate
some things.
Then you implement your action
method, Magnify in this case.
The sender of the
action method is going
to be the gesture recognizer.
And you'll probably want
to switch off the state.
So for Magnify you'll look
at it started, it began,
you set up some initial state.
You do your magnification
during the changes,
and when it finally
ends, you go ahead
and you commit your
changes to your data model.
That way, with this
commit, when you do undo,
you'll just get one undo instead
of just part of the
magnification.
Something like a click,
there is another state
which is just recognized.
So if there's not a recognizer
that goes through begin, change,
ended because it's just a
single collection like a click,
you could just check
the recognize state.
The gesture recognizer
that we're exposing
in Yosemite are the
Click gesture recognizer.
This is a mouse down and up.
You can set which button
to recognize or even chord
of buttons to recognize.
There's the pan gesture
recognizer,
which is a mouse button
down, drag and release.
And this is very similar to the
pan gesture recognizer on iOS,
but on iOS, it's a
touch, move and release.
And the equivalent of that
on the desktop is
obviously the mouse:
mouse down, move, release.
And just like click
gesture recognizer,
you can set which button to
recognize or chord of buttons.
There's a press gesture
recognizer,
which is holding
the mouse button
down with a time component.
So a long press is another
way that we've said it,
but an NS Press Gesture
Recognizer,
click with the time component.
And then we have
magnification gesture recognizer
and rotation gesture recognizer.
I mentioned earlier
that magnification
and rotation are
already recognized for us
at the hardware level.
And that's true, but they can
still be bundled up inside
of gesture recognizer so that
you can get this nice target
action association with it and
it continues to fit in the model
with these other gesture
recognizers in your application
so you have a consistent use
of gestures inside your app.
And of course you can
also set the magnification
and rotation gesture
recognizers to work
at the same time simultaneously,
or you can have them where, no,
I only want to recognize
magnifications
or rotations one at a time.
So you can wire those up
with your various properties.
I do want to make one quick
aside on magnification
and rotation gestures.
The raw event, the magnification
and rotation events,
we've added the phase
property to those events,
so the events also
have a begin, changed,
and ended phases
associated with them.
So if you're looking
at the raw events,
you can determine there
are phases right there.
Event flow is really important
with gesture recognizers.
Let's look at mouse
press for an example.
In Mavericks it would work
like this: Mouse press goes
through NS Application
send event,
and if it doesn't
get consumed there,
send event will send it off
to the event observers,
if there are any.
If the event observers don't
consume it, it will flow back
up to send event and send
event will send it off
to the appropriate window.
That window send event
method is called.
It looks at the event and
figures out via hit testing
which view to send it to.
That view gets a
mouse down message.
If the view doesn't
consume the mouse down,
it bubbles up through the
responder chain as normal,
and whereas normal now
in Yosemite includes
your view controllers.
And gesture recognizers
are here.
Once the event is sent to the
window, NS Windows Send Event,
it will do the gesture
recognizing.
You might notice we have some
dashed arrows now instead
of solid arrows, and the reason
for that is gesture
recognizers might delay events.
Gesture recognizers
will take a pan,
for example, which is a drag.
You'll do a mouse down and
it goes, well, I'm not sure
if they're dragging yet or
not and we don't want any
of your other code
to start trying to go
into a tracking loop or do
anything with the down yet.
We want to wait till we know
for sure if it's a drag or not.
And so your gesture
recognizers can delay events.
And if they end up not consuming
them, then they will continue
to flow through the
system as normal.
What's really important
for you to understand
as developers here,
send event is a place
that is often overridden.
If you do override send event
in NS Application or NS Window,
if you consume events
that gesture recognizers have
already started to process
in that sequence, you could
really confuse your gesture
recognizer and then your app
will not work right at all.
So you need to be careful
about that and think about that
when you're using
gesture recognizers.
This also goes for
event observers.
If you add an event observer,
it can consume the events before
the gesture recognizer gets
to them.
And the gesture recognizer
really needs to have all of them
that belong in a
sequence together.
If you want to subclass
gesture recognizer you can.
We fully support that.
Check out the
nsgesturerecognizer.h file.
There's an NS subclass
use category.
This is where we've
put our category
for the additional methods that
subclassers need to worry about.
And you can write a subclass
and recognize a drag wiggle
as whatever you want
to recognize it to be.
I'm not going to go
into details here,
so if you want more information,
please come see me at one
of the labs, and I will be
more than happy to talk to you
about gesture recognizers.
So let's put this all together
a little bit, and let's go back
to our demo and let's
get that shape to move.
Mike couldn't get the shape
to move, but I think I can.
OK, so we'll run this
again real quick,
make sure we're all right back
in the same spot that we were.
We've added a shape and sure
enough we can't get it to move.
Well, I know that in the canvas
view controller I wrote a select
action method here and a drag
with gesture recognizer
action method here.
So I know that this
stuff exists.
They should be getting
called, so we'll need to figure
out why they're not
getting called.
And it's, you know, just like I
showed before, you just switch
on the state and you do
what you need to do there.
So let's go back into
our Storyboard and look
at our canvas view controller,
and there's the canvas
view controller.
My gesture recognizers
aren't there,
so let's go ahead and add some.
We'll quickly add a
pan gesture recognizer,
and we'll wire the pan gesture
recognizer up to the drag.
And we'll go ahead and add a
magnify gesture recognizer.
There you go.
There we are.
We'll add that and wire
that up to magnify.
And now it should be quite
obvious what code is going
to get run.
We run our app, add a shape,
and now we can drag it.
And we can do a pinch
and resize the shape
and we can add another one.
And they work independently
of each other.
And there we go.
[ Applause ]
View controllers
backing storyboards,
super-easy to design
your applications now.
Window controllers can
just control your window,
but they also have some nice new
API to work with storyboards.
Wire up your gestures
with gesture recognizers.
It's easier than ever,
it's a lot of fun.
Everything here is really great.
Can't wait to see
what you do with it.
For more information
you could see Jake.
He's over here up in the
front with a nice shirt.
Last night somebody
commented on his shoes,
so I figured I'd comment
on his shirt today.
Check out the "What's New
in OS X" documentation.
We're working like crazy
on the documentation
for View Controller, so
that is going to be coming.
It's going to be really nice.
Some related sessions,
check out the "What's New
in Interface Builder."
This and along with other
things are going to be covered.
I really want to point out
"Creating Modern Cocoa
Apps" on Thursday.
If you're just new to
writing apps on Mac OS X,
modern Cocoa apps will cover
view controllers a little bit,
but they'll cover a lot
of other technologies
that you should be also
implementing in your application
as an OS X application.
So thank you.
Enjoy the rest of
the conference.