[ Applause ]
>> Hi, everybody.
Good morning.
My name is Rachel
Roth and I'm one
of Apple's User Experience
Evangelists.
Now this session is
not about monetizing.
It's about having a great
experience with in-app purchases
because a great experience
is what's going
to keep people coming back
to your app or game time
and time and time again.
Think about the last time you
had a really fantastic meal
at a great restaurant.
So it's a place you always
want to come back to, right?
So this is the bigger
picture of what it takes
to have a great experience
with in-app purchases
and today's session is all
based on the assumption
that you already have a
really amazing app or game.
Your app meets the
needs of your audience.
It's got a really
intuitive interface design.
It's been executed really well.
For game, it's just fun to play.
And there's really
no design secrets
or shortcuts around this one.
But I know that you guys
all have it handled.
So we don't have to dwell
on this for too long.
Now, if you're using the
freemium or the paymium model
with in-app purchases,
it's so important
that people can enjoy your app
or game without buying anything.
I mean, I think most of us
have had the experience.
You get a new app from the
App Store and you download it
and you launch it only to find
that you can't do
anything with it.
That's frustrating.
You need to make it
a purchase in order
to get some utility out of it.
It would be like if you bought
a mixer for your kitchen
and it didn't come
with any attachments.
You couldn't mix anything.
That would be really
disappointing.
And that's why mixers come
with a basic attachment
that you can use to mix and
see how great the mixer is.
And then you buy some additional
attachments for specialty tasks
like making bread or
some kind of pastry.
And that's what you want
to achieve with your apps.
You want to let people really
enjoy the functionality
and the utility, the
quality of your app,
and then you offer
them advantages
or additional functionality,
some advanced features.
And when you offer those
things, you want to make sure
that you make buying easy.
And I know this probably sounds
obvious but I'm not just talking
about sending the
transaction to the App Store
and getting a response back.
You want to make sure
that the decision
to buy something is really easy
for the people coming
to your app or game.
There's a lot of friction to
making that decision to buy
and a lot of it is
outside of your control.
But as app developers, you
want to eliminate any obstacle
to making that decision
to purchase something
inside of your app.
Make it easy as possible
because that decision
to buy is a fleeting moment
and there's many traps.
So one of the best
things that you can do is
to integrate your merchandise
into the experience.
I mean, people aren't
going to buy things
if they don't know
what you're offering,
if they can't see them.
I talk to a lot of developers
who create a really great store
section inside of their app
or game and then they're
really disappointed
because no one's going there.
They're not buying anything.
That's because people don't
know what you're offering.
It's kind of like the
difference of if I said,
"Do you want to buy something?"
Or if I said, "How would you
like a really great
drawing tool?"
And that's what you want to
help explain with your app
by putting the merchandise
out on display,
integrating it into
the experience.
But when you're doing
that, I'm not suggesting
that you become a pushy
salesperson about it.
Nobody wants this guy following
them around saying, "Hey,
you want to buy something?
Hey, hey, hey.
You want to buy something?
Do you want to buy something?
Do you want to buy something?"
Every minute, and that's
what you're risking
if you're flashing a lot
of alerts or notifications
or crazy animations to try and
entice people into that store.
It's really about timing.
And with some apps, it's
about offering the right
thing at the right time.
Like at a restaurant, when the
waiter brings you the dessert
menu at the end of the meal.
I mean, you might not
even want dessert, right,
but it doesn't feel pushy
that they offered it.
It would feel pushy if they
offered it to you before you sat
down and while you're
eating your appetizer.
So you want to think about
what's the right moment
to offer something
to someone and do
that in a way that's
really thoughtful.
Now with other apps, it's
about the presentation.
You want to think about a
really great window display
for a store.
I happen to be very partial
to the Apple Retail
window displays.
I'm sure that will come as
no surprise to you guys.
Now they do a great job
of showing off the
merchandise and drawing you in.
It makes you want to find
out more about the products.
It's really intriguing.
And that's what you
want to think
about with your app
or your game.
You want to integrate
the merchandise in a way
that feels really natural.
This is Paper by Fifty Three.
It's an Apple Design Award
winner from years ago
that is still a fantastic
example
of integrating in-app
purchases into their experience.
If you haven't used it, the app
is designed to capture ideas
through sketches and
diagrams and notes.
And like that mixer
in your kitchen,
they give you some basic
drawing tools for free,
your pen and your eraser.
And you can see from
this example
that you can do tons with it.
But there might be an occasion
when you need a more advanced
drawing tool or a different kind
of line or texture and so that's
why they leave these empty spots
here where the advanced
drawing tools should go.
And that's like that
window display in the store.
It's putting them
out for you to see.
There's no question
what's available.
What they didn't do
is hide everything
in an arts supply store or
tuck it in a pencil case
that then you have to go push
open to see what's available.
That's creating friction.
That's expecting the
player, or your audience
to do work, to see what's there.
And another thing that
they didn't do is trick you
into thinking that you
already owned all these tools.
Because if you could see them
all but then when you tapped
on one to use it, it
told you that you need
to pay money just
to test out a brush?
Well, that would
be disappointing.
That's not a great experience.
It's a frustrating one.
And that's why this design
is so elegant and so great.
It's informative
but it's not pushy.
Now next up, let's look at that
timing I mentioned earlier,
a totally different kind of
app, Bloomberg Businessweek.
And this is a business
publication
that has regular
updates, new content.
And without a subscription, you
can still browse, read several
of the articles,
browse all the headlines
and the introductory sentences.
Now if you tap on something
that requires a subscription,
they bring up the
subscription options.
It's like the dessert menu.
You're interested in
reading some of their content
so here's the information about
subscription so you can get it.
They're presenting it right
at that perfect moment.
They're making it easy for
you to get the subscription.
Now, they also have this
Subscribe button down here
in the corner of every
screen and that's great too.
But having that in addition
to the integrated message
helps them reach more people.
So I'm not saying you
can't have a store section.
You just don't want to
make it the only place
that people can find
what you're offering.
Now this also works for games.
I don't know how many of
you have played "Smash Hit".
It's a really fun arcade game
that involves smashing things
as you might have guessed, very
satisfying after a long day.
The way that it works is
that it's an arcade game
and the more accurate you
are at smashing things,
the further you're going to get.
You progress through the
checkpoints unlocking them.
And they also offer a premium
version and they've a great way
of illustrating exactly what
that advanced feature
does for you.
[ Music ]
So here we are.
Let's start from checkpoint 2,
maybe I can get a little
bit further this time.
[ Music ]
Oh, but this requires
the premium version
and I'm not ready to buy it.
[ Music ]
Pretty compelling, right?
I mean, if you had any doubt
about what that advantage is
that they're offering,
that spells it
out for you right away.
Now I don't know how
many of you notice
that there's also this
Get Premium button here
in the corner.
And if you did, would
you have guessed
that that's what the
premium version meant?
I mean, some of you might
have tapped on it to find out
and some of you may not have.
And they have the details
here about what you get.
But having this in addition
to that integrated message
is just much more effective
at explaining what the feature
does for you and offering it
to you at the time
that you can use it.
Just remember, don't
be this guy.
Nobody wants someone pushing
in your face pestering you.
Pestering people is not going to
get the results that you want.
But thoughtful integration
of the merchandise will.
Now another challenge is to
help people understand the value
of what you're offering.
And if you walked
into a clothing store,
this is easy to figure out.
You can touch the merchandise,
feel what the fabric feels like.
Does it feel luxurious or
does it feel kind of cheap?
Is it well made?
Are the seams are falling apart?
Most importantly,
does it fit you?
Does it look good?
Is it going to suit
your purposes?
So letting people try
out merchandise before they buy
it is a really effective way
of helping them understand
the quality and the value
and the utility of
what you're offering.
I mean, you wouldn't buy
a car without taking it
for a test drive first, right?
It's the same principle.
Letting people use it will
be the best way for them
to understand how
awesome they are.
And again, Paper by Fifty Three
does a great job with this.
In addition to providing
a lot of samples
of what the tools
are capable of,
they put together an
entire journal made
by their staff showing
off the different tools
and their capabilities.
And then of course, they
let you use the tools,
the basic tools for free.
And if you haven't used
this app, I can tell you
that the tools respond
beautifully to your finger.
Now me telling you that
isn't nearly as effective
as you actually using the app
and so that's why when you go
to find out about these
advanced drawing tools,
they let you test
them out right there.
You've got these sketch pads
along with detailed information
and testing them out is how
you can determine the quality
and the utility.
What kind of texture
do they provide?
How do they react to your
finger when you're drawing?
Which one is going to be right
for what you're trying
to achieve?
And each of those sketch
pads has drawings already
in progress.
It's kind of like the test
drive where they take you
down certain roads to show
you how well the car handles?
Paper by Fifty Three is
setting up the sketchpads
to show you the optimal uses
or some suggested
uses for those tools.
This one's great at watercolors.
They've set up a
watercolor drawing for you
so then you can jump in and add
on or try your own drawings.
And it might seem obvious
to take this approach
with drawing tools but
I promise it will work
for almost any kind
of virtual good.
Here's a really different
example and that's Line.
So it's a popular messaging app.
You can send and receive
messages for free.
Now one of the things
that differentiates Line
from its competitors
is the vast array
of stickers that they offer.
Stickers are kind of
like really crazy Emoji.
You can include them in your
messages and send them back
and forth to your friends.
It gives your text
messages a whole new life.
Now Line gives you a
very generous selection
of these stickers for
free so you can try them
out plus the ability
to earn stickers
without paying anything.
So all you have to do is
add Hello Kitty as a friend
and then you get
Hello Kitty stickers.
And some people love
And using them really helps you
understand how great they are.
Now another thing that
they offer are themes.
And when I first investigated
themes, I'll be honest,
I had no idea what to expect
and I thought, "Oh great,
there's some free ones.
Let me try out the Brown Bear."
Let's see what happens here.
So when you choose
the Brown Bear theme,
instead of getting the
standard UI, you get bears!
Hurray! Everywhere,
all over the place.
Even the tab bar
icons are bears.
Now, sure they could have put a
description of what a theme is
or even a screenshot but that
wouldn't have been nearly
as effective at conveying what
happens when you use the themes.
Giving people some free ones
to try out is the best way
to really understand
what they're all about.
And this works for publications.
Does anyone have any
question about where
to get the free preview
content on the screen?
They've made it really
easy for everybody.
"Esquire Magazine" wants
to make sure that you know
that reading their content
on an iPad is the best
experience possible.
And so they give you free
content to check out.
It's got videos, interactivity
and this is the equivalent
to standing in line at the store
and flipping through a magazine
or going to a comics store
and checking out the artwork.
It helps you to really know
whether the reading experience
is going to be good and
whether the content's going
to be something that
you're interested in.
And again, this also
works for games.
Now, I'm pretty sure
that everyone
in this room has played Candy
Crush Saga at some point
but for the 2 of you who
haven't, it's a puzzle game.
And they've done okay with
in-app purchases, you know.
So what they do at the
beginning of every level is
that they offer you
these boosters.
And these boosters give you a
leg up on completing the task
and they've become much
more valuable the harder the
puzzle is.
And if you've never used one,
you can just ignore them,
go for that big pink play button
and you're into a puzzle game.
So that's why they introduced
the Daily Booster Wheel.
Every day you can come and get
one of their boosters for free.
So there is nothing standing in
the way of you trying them out.
And once you try them out,
you really know what a
difference that they can make.
So that's what I mean about
offering a test drive.
Letting someone really
experience that merchandise,
trying it out before they
buy it, is the best way
to communicate the value and
the usefulness and the quality.
And that's why it's going
to make the decision
to buy something
easier on people.
Now, another way to reduce
the friction to buying is
to stick with your theme.
It's really important that
every screen in your app
or your game is cohesive.
And you want to carry
that visual design
all the way through.
That interaction model
needs to be consistent.
And you want to put as
much effort and time
into designing these screens
as you do anything else
in your app or your game.
So this is Ruzzle Adventure
and it's got hundreds of levels
of puzzle games and all
these various theme worlds.
You start out in the
forest and you work
through the different
puzzles in the forest
to get to other lands.
Now, every aspect of the
forest looks like the forest.
They've got -- it doesn't matter
the objective of the game.
You can see the forest details
creeping in at every corner.
Now there are in-app purchases
involved and in-app currency
which you can use to
then buy advantages
for the different
levels, powerful boosts.
And you can earn the in-app
currency as you're playing
but you can also, of course,
make an in-app purchase
for their in-app currency.
So imagine you're up against
Chief Smartypants here
and he's tough.
So it might be worth
getting some in-app currency
so that you can -- so that you
go buy some in-app currency
so you can get some
of those boosters.
So imagine you're excited.
You want to beat
Chief Smartypants.
But the next screen
you saw was this.
It would be terrible, right?
I mean, suddenly there's
an entirely different UI
that you have to understand.
You got to think about it.
It's really sterile-looking.
It's not very well laid out.
It takes you right
out of the experience.
You're not in the
forest anymore.
And that creates friction.
It makes you feel
more like work.
That's making it
harder to buy something.
Now thankfully, Ruzzle
Adventure does not do that.
They have a nice forest
theme purchasing experience
and all the visual design
and interaction is consistent
with everything else
in the game.
So make sure that you
maintain the world of your game
or the look of your app
on every single screen
and with every single control.
Because when you suddenly
snatch people out of that world
and they have to deal with a
new interface or a new look,
it's going to feel like work.
It's going to be hard.
And buying, we want
it to be easy, right?
Now just a word of warning
while you are busy sticking
with your theme,
don't take it so far
that language becomes confusing.
You want to make sure
that people can really
understand exactly what they're
going to be getting
for their money.
You use clear language.
Now have you guys ever seen a
description for an apartment
or house that said something
like "needs a little work"?
And then you show up
and it's, you know,
it looks more like this.
I think we've all
had that experience.
Now with any purchase, it's
so important to be honest.
There is really a fine line
between trying to be positive
about something,
highlighting the features
and really being
overly optimistic
about what you're selling.
Nobody wants to be disappointed
when they see what the
merchandise actually is.
And especially when you're
coming to subscriptions
or recurring content, you want
to be as specific as possible.
Set people's expectations
correctly.
When are they going
to get new content?
How much content are they
getting for the price?
And if you just saw something
like this, you don't know.
Is it expensive or
is it a bargain?
I mean, if it's 12
issues in a year,
that's less than
a dollar an issue.
That's pretty reasonable, right?
But if it's only two
issues, well, I don't know.
Is that content really
worth that much money to me
and see now, I'm off
thinking about whether
or not this is a purchase
I want to make instead
of quickly coming to a decision,
getting the new content
and going off to enjoy it
because that's what I've
come to an app to do.
I've come to enjoy content.
I've come to an app to
help me achieve something.
Jamie Oliver does a much
better job with this.
He's a famous chef and
he has a recipes app.
And you'll see here that
here they let you know
that new content is coming
on the second Wednesday
of every month.
Crystal clear, very specific.
I know exactly when
to expect things.
FitStar is a personal
training application
and they have a number of
workouts and they're tailored
to your goals and also
your actual performance.
Now their subscription screen
gives you detailed outlines
of all the programs.
I mean, you can find out
the length of the workouts.
Do you want something short?
Do you want something long?
They are offering both of
those, the advantages of them.
Are you interested in fat
burning or are you trying
to do strength training?
They've even pointed out which
one is recommended for me based
on a couple of questions
I answered earlier.
And when you're ready to
buy that subscription,
that screen is so clear about
exactly what you're going
to be getting, all
of the programs,
unlimited free style moves.
And they've even highlighted
the annual subscription
with a discount.
They've made it so easy
just through the use
of clear language for
me to make a decision
about buying something.
And now I really understand
what I'm getting for my money
and I can appreciate it.
Now another way that
you can make this clear
to your audience is to
do the math for them.
I don't like doing math.
That's not fun for me.
Don't make me do the math.
It's your job as the app
developer to make it easy
on people to make a decision.
So quick, which one of
these is the best value?
I mean, I'm sure some of you can
really quickly calculate this
but most people are
not going to want to.
It's this one, by the way.
And so that's why you really
want to help people understand
which is going to be the
most cost effective for them.
This is Lovoo.
It's a dating application and
they offer tons of utility
without a subscription.
You can fill out a
profile, message users.
There's lots of ways to
browse potential suitors,
including this.
This is a radar screen.
That's what you're seeing here.
You can see all the people,
all potential dates around me.
And of course, they have some
premium features that'll help
you get more exposure to people.
And here is how they explain
the subscription options.
It's called pennies
a day to find love.
Pennies a day to find love!
Who can afford pennies
a day for love?
Now, there's no guesswork here.
I know exactly which
subscription is going
to be the lowest cost per day.
But it's really important.
If you're going to
take it to this level,
make sure that you're
still calling
out the total purchase
price because again,
we want to be honest and
clear with our language.
People are going to want to
know what they expect to pay.
Don't make them do the
math in reverse, right?
Now, if your app is available
worldwide, I want to make sure
that you localize your currency
because that's a huge
roadblock if you don't.
So that's what I mean about
doing the math for people.
It can be so helpful in
making that decision quickly.
Now, another thing that's really
helpful is showing fewer things.
It's about quality,
not about quantity.
Too many choices, you
risk overwhelming people.
And I don't know how
many of you have heard
of the paradox of choice.
It essentially means that the
more choices that you have,
the harder it is
to make a decision.
And in fact, when
you've too many choices,
that choice overload,
it stresses you out.
And what you, people wind
up doing is avoiding making
a decision altogether.
And you want people to make a
decision to purchase something.
It's kind of like if you've
ever gone on to make a recipe
and it calls for apples.
Maybe you're making apple
pie and so you got your list.
You go to the grocery store and
then you're faced with this.
Well, what kind of apples?
Is it Golden Delicious
or Red Delicious
or Fuji or Pink Lady or oh!
It's too much!
It's overwhelming!
Too many apples!
And this will result in you just
abandoning that pie altogether.
You want to avoid that
reaction in your app.
Too many choices becomes
stressful and that's going
to result in people avoiding the
purchase decision altogether.
So here is Match.
It's a different
dating application.
Again, loads of utility
without subscription.
More than letting you
test-drive the app.
They're practically
giving you an entire car.
You can fill out your profile,
message people, a million ways
of browsing including
recommended partners.
They do offer some premium
features though and one
of the things is
seeing who's viewed me.
So tapping on that
viewed me button brings
up their subscription choices.
So they're offering
me that information
at the time that I need it.
Now look, I've got
3 easy choices here.
They've even highlighted
the one with the best value.
3 choices is an easy
decision to make.
I don't have to scroll through
a long list of options or page
through screen after screen
with different subscription
numbers on it.
Then I have to remember
them in my head
and try and figure it out.
That makes it hard.
Buying things shouldn't be hard.
So fewer things all on one
screen, no paging, no scrolling.
People want to be able to see
all their options at once.
Now, if someone's ready to
make that decision to buy,
they're ready to press that
buy button, you really want
to execute on it as
efficiently as possible.
I mean, have you ever gone
to get a cup of coffee
and then you're faced with
a long, slow-moving line?
And so, you're just
like, "Forget it."
That's what you don't want to
happen in your app or game.
Minimizing both the time and the
number of steps that it takes
to make a purchase keeps people
really engaged in your app,
not thinking about that
purchasing process.
So this is Supernauts.
It's a builder game that
takes place in space.
It's not quite out worldwide
yet so stayed tuned very soon
because you're probably going
to want to play it after this.
Now right now, I'm
in the process
of repairing my tiki hut.
As you can see, it's a little
pathetic at the moment.
I want to add some more
timber but this is going
to cost me 8 diamonds.
Now, I only have 1.
So what happens when I
press that green button?
I can get some gems right here.
I don't have to go anywhere.
I can stay right in that
moment of tiki hut repair.
So in addition to clearly
stating what I'm going to get,
200 gems for $4.99, they're also
reminding me why I'm seeing this
in the first place.
I need 7 more.
I only have 1.
I needed 8.
And they've even
selected the package
of gems that's closest
to what I needed.
It happens that this is the
smallest package of gems
but then I can make a
decision really quickly.
I mean, yes, they have
a gem store and yes,
it has many more options in it.
But taking me away from my
tiki hut is more disruptive
than letting me just stay
put, stay focused on building
because building is
what I came here to do.
You never want to
distract a game player
from playing the game.
That's the fun part.
Distracting them makes
it easier for them
to just walk away entirely.
Similarly, Candy Crush Saga
handles this really well also.
You have those boosters at
the beginning of every level
and you have the option of
purchasing them right here.
They're not shipping
me off to a candy store
with a million different
things to choose from.
It's just, "Would you
like this booster?
Here's the price.
Buy it. Back in the game."
Fast and efficient, right at
the moment when I can use it.
Now another thing to think about
is preloading images and data
so it's there when
people need it.
This is the Bejeweled Blitz.
It's another kind of
match-3 puzzle game.
Now you earn coins
as you're playing
and then you use the
coins to buy rare gems
which then help you to do
better on the various puzzles.
Now every day, you can
also get some free coins
from this daily wheel.
Now you get 1 free spin
per day but of course,
you can buy some more
spins, if you like.
And the wheel's pretty generous.
So imagine that you're excited
and you're like,
"Okay, you know what?
I'm doing really good on
the tournament this week.
I want to beat my friends.
Let me go get some more
spins and see what happens."
Well, what if you're
faced with this?
People don't like waiting.
That's like that long
line at the coffee store.
You risk them not
sticking around.
Now thankfully, Bejeweled
Blitz doesn't do this.
They load everything
immediately.
What you want to do is to be
aware of what people are likely
to purchase based on where
they are in your app or game.
And then you can look for times
to thoughtfully preload it
so that the data and the images
are available should someone
need it.
So this screen is
only accessible
from that wheel screen.
So this is a perfect opportunity
to preload those images
so then they'll be available.
The images and data will be
there when people seek it out.
And 1 final tip is you should
cache artwork appropriately
so it's not going to have
to load every single time
if it doesn't need to.
Now after lunch in this
room, we have a great session
about optimizing in-app
purchases with StoreKit
so I highly recommend you come
back after lunch and check it
out because there's
a lot of great tips
for avoiding common pitfalls.
Now finally, what you can do to
make the buying process easier
on people is to inspire people.
Someone may not want something
because they don't know what
the possibility of it is.
They don't understand how a tool
or a feature could help them
or what they could
achieve with them.
Now, I'm not saying that
you want to turn everything
into an advertising experience.
Again, we're not
trying to be pushy.
But there's a lot of ways
that you can really naturally
illustrate how things can
be used.
Paper by Fifty Three
does this beautifully.
They've got this sample
journal that the staff has made
that shows off not only what
the tools are capable of
but also different ways
they could be used.
You know, maybe you
want a wireframe with it
or maybe you want to
make some artwork.
Now another thing they do
well is give suggestive titles
to the blank journals.
Maybe you hadn't considered
sketching or journaling
with this app but
now you're going to.
And they also have a
gallery of artwork created
by people using the
app, regular people.
And this gallery
shows off the variety
of styles that's achievable,
what you can do with the tools
and also how the
app can be used.
I mean, you can make
some amazing artwork
but you also might want to use
it for architectural renderings.
And if that doesn't get you
inspired, maybe the idea
of having your work featured
here is very exciting.
So you've just got a plethora
of ways that you can use the app
and see what the
tools are capable of.
Now again, with games, and with
Supernauts does this very well,
it's kind of a different
approach with the same idea.
So after you learn the basic
game play with Supernauts,
they reward you for visiting
other people's worlds.
Now like I said, this is a
builder game so you're working
on building up your property.
And seeing how creative other
people have been is super
inspiring for your own place.
Now this is how you
start off, pretty basic.
In the first 15 minutes,
you're going
to get some real basic
structures going.
And after a couple of hours,
you might wind up with something
like this or something
like my tiki hut.
And when you get through a
couple of hours, you think,
"Okay, I know what's going on.
I have an idea of
what's possible."
But it's only when you go
to visit other people's worlds
do you really get a sense
for what's coming, for
what can be created.
So check these out.
These are all real players.
This is not the Supernauts
crew who created these.
Amazing, right?
I mean, my tiki hut is
super lame by comparison.
[ Laughter ]
And now I'm excited.
Now I want to go in and add a
dragon or you know, a rainbow
or a flag or messages
to my friends.
I mean, it makes,
it gets you excited
about spending more
time building things.
You make something really cool
and you can see what materials
are still forthcoming.
So as you're thinking about how
to make the buying
process easier,
make sure that people can see
what's available with no effort.
Help people understand the
value of what you're offering.
Give them that test
drive experience.
And then when it comes
to the transaction,
make sure that you can process
on it fast and efficient.
And don't forget to
get people excited
about what you're offering.
But the story doesn't end here.
Your job is not over
just getting them
to push the buy button.
There's a lot of things
that need to happen
to complete the transaction
in order to have it continue
to be a really great experience.
The first of which is a new
feature coming in the fall
and Tim touched on
this very briefly,
but I'd like to spend a little
more time because this is going
to impact everyone
and that's Ask to Buy.
So in the fall, you'll be able
to associate up to 6 people
in the household as a family.
And as part of this, we're going
to have a new parental
control called Ask to Buy.
And if it's enabled, this
means that a parent is going
to approve or decline any
purchases that a child makes.
So it's basically the
equivalent of this.
"Can I have it?
Please, please, please?"
But it's all going to
happen through your devices.
So here's how it works.
Today, when your app sends a
request to purchase something,
you're going to get a
response right back.
That purchased or failed.
Now with Ask to Buy, we're going
to check with the parent first
if Ask to Buy is enabled.
So you're going to send
the request for purchasing.
The child's going to
ask for something.
And then the App Store is
going to check with the parent.
So what does that mean to you?
During this time, you're going
to get a response
back of deferred.
And then once the parent
accepts or declines the request,
that's when the App Store will
let you know whether it's been
purchased or failed.
And this deferred state can last
for up to 24 hours while waiting
for a response from the parent.
And if there's no
response within 24 hours,
it's going to default to failed
and the child can request again.
So what does this mean
from a design perspective?
Well, if you have
modal situations
where people are doing
purchasing, you need to shift
over to an asynchronous model.
Let's say your game offers
boosters at the beginning
of a level and a child
makes a request to buy one.
You don't want that child stuck
there waiting for up to 24 hours
to hear whether they
can have a booster
for the next level, right?
I can guarantee you, they're not
going to stick around that long.
So what can you do?
Well, you have to figure
what's going to be best
for your app or your game.
The important thing is that
you let people keep using
and enjoying your
app during this time.
So if a child's requested
a booster,
well you send the request
off for the parent to approve
but then you could let
them play other levels
or maybe they continue
playing the level
but without the booster and
when that approval comes in,
you bank it and let them
use it at a different time.
Another thing that you want to
think about is giving some sort
of feedback inside
of the application
so that the child remembers
that something is pending,
that they've already
asked Mom and Dad.
And so that you could update
the label on the button
to say something else or in the
App Store, we show a message
to help the child remember
that it's actually pending.
So if any people using
your app are under 18,
you need to start
preparing for this now.
That deferred state is
entirely new and you need
to make sure you're
handling it well.
Make sure people can still
continue to use your app
or your game while that
deferred state is happening.
And you want to make sure
that if a response is pending,
that they have some
feedback there.
It's really important to note
that this isn't just iOS 8.
So don't think that waiting to
update your app or game is going
to get you out of this
because it's not going to.
The ability to create families
is what's coming with iOS 8
but this Ask to Buy
permission is going to apply
to older versions of
iOS, Mac OS and Apple TV,
so start preparing now.
Now, whether or not a
transaction completes
immediately or up to 24
hours later, you always want
to confirm that that
transaction is completed.
Let people know.
So at a minimum, help people
find whatever they just bought.
Let them know that
it's available for use.
An example that you guys
probably see all the time is the
App Store.
So as soon as you confirm
payment for an application,
you see that the app
starts to download.
You get that feedback that
something's happening.
Nothing's gone wrong.
Your merchandise is
being transferred to you.
And then you can open that app
directly from the App Store.
You don't have to go digging
around all your home screens
filled with apps to find it.
You can just start playing
3's right there for hours.
Now, another thing to think
about is if you have a game
or a children's app,
something really fun,
you can make this
a fun experience
by using sound and animation.
So this is Heads Up!
It's a game that's really
popular with Ellen DeGeneres.
She plays it on her
TV show all the time.
It's a little bit like Charades.
It's designed to play it with
real people in real life.
Each of this deck of theme cards
are topics that you then act
out for your friends
and try and guess.
Now they give you a
couple of theme packs
to get going to start playing.
But then they also offer
a ton of other theme packs
to enhance the experience.
So check out what happens
when you buy one of these.
I happen to be into
the 80's one.
[ Music ]
So you get that sound
and that animation
that lets you know
something has happened.
The purchase has gone through
and then they animate back
up to the top so you can
see where your cards are
and start playing right away.
Now confirming that the
transaction is completed is
especially important
with Ask to Buy
because your customer may
not be at the same place
where they were when they
requested the transaction,
right?
So if you had a comic app
and say the child is
browsing all the comics
that are available, they request
one and while they're waiting
for Mom or Dad to accept it,
well then they go and read one
of the issues they already have.
So you need to think about if
that transaction completes,
how are you going to let
people know if it completes
at a later time how you're
going to let people know
where their merchandise
is and how to find it.
Now no one wants to see
Error Code 128, right?
It's confusing.
It's frustrating to someone and
it can be a little alarming.
So you want to know your error
codes and present information
in a way that's going
to be meaningful
to the people using your apps.
Not all errors may
require a response.
You don't have to tell
your people everything.
Now if someone did
cancel a transaction,
let's say that you're
using an app or game,
you change your mind
about something.
You cancel it.
Is this what you want to see?
This doesn't make sense.
You may not need to
notify people at all
or you may just want to
make this a little more
customer friendly.
So the best experience,
of course,
is to avoid errors entirely.
So again, this afternoon's
session
on optimizing StoreKit is going
to have a ton of technical tips
about avoiding errors and
all those common pitfalls.
Now another thing that I see
sometimes is that people tend
to over ask for purchases.
You want to let folks
get some enjoyment
out of what they just bought
before you start asking them
to buy something again.
Again, don't be this guy.
It's like at Christmas,
so you unwrap the toy
and you're all excited
and then you realize, "Oh,
it didn't come with
any batteries!"
It's disappointing right?
I mean, you just took something
that was a really joyous
occasion and turned it
into a frustrating
experience for people.
So make sure that when
someone buys something,
they can use what
they just bought.
Give them that satisfaction.
They shouldn't have to
make a subsequent purchase
in order to enjoy it.
And then like I said
earlier, less is more.
You want to prioritize
the remaining purchases.
Help people focus on what's
still available to them.
If there's things they
can't buy, do prioritize
that in the UI, especially
with nonconsumables.
There is no need to keep
showing people something
that they've already bought.
They already own it.
Now in some cases, it may
not make sense to hide items
that have already been purchased
but just don't let them
be the star of the show.
And I think you're all aware
that it's very important
that you let people
restore their purchases
that they've made previously.
They could have made
it on another device
or they got a new piece of
hardware and it's important
that they can retrieve what
they've already bought.
This is "Brooklyn Magazine"
and they make it super easy.
If you already have
a subscription,
well here's where to go to
start that restore process.
But they took it
one step further.
So if you were to tap on one
of these subscription options,
you get the confirmation
to subscribe just
like you would expect.
But if you hit Cancel, they ask
if you're already a subscriber.
And that's because there's
basically 2 reasons why you
might cancel subscription
confirmation.
One is if you changed your mind
about subscribing, of course.
And that's a much bigger
problem for them to tackle.
But the other is if you
already had a subscription.
So in this case, they're
helping get you back on track.
Now you all know it's
an App Store requirement
to make restoring available.
But a great experience
is going to make it easy.
All right, so one last
tip in this section.
And this is about notifications.
You want to use them
thoughtfully and this applies
to push notifications as
well as local notifications.
Now you're not going to have
to notify children about Ask
to Buy, purchases completing
because the App Store is going
to handle that for you.
But you do want to use
notifications to let people know
about new content for
a subscription or maybe
in those dating apps,
they could let me know
if I have new recommended
matches.
Circa does a great job
with their notifications.
They serve up bite-sized
news articles
and they give you
updates as it's happening.
Now they're only going to send
notification if it's an article
that I explicitly followed
or if it's something
that they consider
breaking news.
And they're very choosy
about what they consider
breaking news.
Now this is not breaking news.
This is what I followed earlier.
Swiping on that notification
takes you directly
to the article so you
can read all about it.
So they've made it really easy
for me to return to the content.
So you want to be really
thoughtful about the kind
and the number of notifications
that you're sending
because too many
notifications is just going
to annoy everybody.
And not only do you risk them
turning off notifications
entirely, they might just
wind up deleting your app,
if they get tired of
all the notifications.
That's not the experience
that we're after, right?
You want thoughtful
notifications
that will keep people
coming back
and make the app
feel more valuable
because suddenly there's
new content there.
Okay, so make sure that
you consider these things
after your customer's
pressed the buy button.
Completing the transaction
is super important.
Which brings us to the
final sort of stage
of a great experience
with in-app purchases
and that's measuring
and refining.
With all good design, it's
so important to iterate,
you want to measure the
success and quite frankly,
the failures of what you tried.
See how that has
an effect on things
and then make changes
based on those.
I mean, that all the things
that I mentioned today are going
to work for all product
types and all audiences.
So the more that you really fine
tune your approach, the better,
the more effective
it's going to be.
So here are some questions
that you can ask yourself
about the changes that you made
to help determine whether
they were successful.
So when were the changes
made and what were they?
Super important, you want
to make a detailed note
about exactly when you made
changes and all the things
that you updated so
you have something
to measure against later.
You also want to think about
how has the number of changes,
how has the number
of purchases changed?
Hopefully they've
gone up, right?
And are different things being
purchased from different places
in the application as a result
of integrating your merchandise?
Are you selling higher
value items?
And what's the average
revenue per device?
And this is going to be
really easy to see in the fall
with the new iTunes Connect
because we have a ton
of app analytics coming
for you all for free.
And this helps you learn whether
or not a marketing
campaign was worth it.
If you invested a certain
amount of money per device
and you're not seeing that
revenue come back in, well,
that campaign's not going to
be a good investment for you.
And finally, keep an eye out.
Are people returning
more frequently?
Because if they are,
that's an indication
that you have a really great
experience, that the quality
of the experience has gone up.
So I hope that you guys
will take at least one
of the design tips that I gave
you today and implement it
in your app or game and
then see how it affects the
overall experience.
Because I think you're going
to be really happy
with the results.
And I would like to
hear how it goes.
This is my email address.
So let me know.
Let me know what you changed.
Let me know the effects that
it's having on your sales.
And if you would like more
design advice, we have tons
of it at Designing Great Apps
up at developer.apple.com.
And if you don't all have a copy
of the Human Interface
Guidelines,
it's a great resource,
a lot of good tips.
It's available on
the iBooks Store now.
So here are all the related
sessions you might want to see.
Ingredients of Great Games
was yesterday and that talks
about how to have a really
great gaming experience.
And so the video should
be available online
and you can watch it.
And just before the session
was the new iTunes Connect
which had all the information
about app analytics.
So look for that video
to be out later today.
And then we have our Optimizing
In-App Purchases later today
in this room, tons of
great technical tips.
And there's a prototyping
session tomorrow morning that's
going to tell you all about
how to quickly iterate and test
out the value and it's a great
session to figure out how
to quickly test things
out that you might want
to integrate into your app.
And finally, on Friday, come
to Preventing Unauthorized
Purchases with Receipts
because you're offering
really valuable things
and we only want you
to be giving them
to people who've paid for them.
So it's going to be a very
detailed technical heavy session
that you'll want to check out.
So thanks so much everybody!
Enjoy the rest of
the conference.
[ Applause ]