[ Silence ]
>> Good afternoon.
[ Applause ]
>> My name is Brandon Newendorp
and I'm the Software Engineer
on iOS, and welcome to Creating
Custom iOS User Interfaces.
If you take a look at
iOS today it is filled
with really interesting
and engaging,
unique interfaces for our users.
You can see that in things
like the Notification Center
which takes advantage of a
blur effect to give you a sense
of it being at a different depth
above the operating system.
Notification Center also
uses effects like vibrancy
to create text that is
highly legible at all times.
You also see interesting
interfaces
like what we call the
Suggestions View in Siri
where we have these pieces
of text that are animating on
and off screen at all
times, getting the sense
of being pulled on
and off of the screen.
We use custom UI in a lot
of places across the system,
and you might be
thinking to yourself,
"I want to build really cool
stuff like this as well."
There's some things
that you should think
about that are questions we
also like to ask ourselves
when creating new pieces of
UI for the operating system.
The first thing that you
should think about is
where are you going
to use this UI?
How does this fit into
your app and what kind
of purpose does it serve for
your users and your customers?
Sometimes you want to
create UI that needs
to represent multiple states.
For example you might be
creating a download control
that needs to have states
like in idle, downloading,
in progress, cancelled
and complete states.
So you want to think about those
and think about how to design
and craft your control in a way
that supports those different
states it's intended for.
You also want to think
about whether you're going
to share this control
or this piece of UI
across several applications.
Starting in iOS 8 you can
create frameworks for your app,
which are a great way to
share code between apps
that your team is creating or
even release it to the public
to help other people use the
same kind of pieces of UI.
And then the last thing
that you might want to think
about are what pieces
of API can you leverage
to make your job easier?
A lot of times we have
UI or controls in UIKit
that will make it very easy
for you to create custom things
without having to subclass code.
So what are some APIs that you
might find useful if you were
to want to take advantage
of things we offer in UIKit?
One of those is the
UIAppearance system.
UIAppearance allows you
to configure certain
characteristics
of the default UIKit controls
without having to subclass them.
One of the most popular uses for
UIAppearance is the tint color
which allows you to configure
the color of controls
that we provide as part of UIKit
without having to subclass them.
One particularly useful piece
of the UIAppearance system
is the UIImageRenderingMode.
This is something that we
introduced in iOS 7 last year,
that allows you to
provide a single image
into your application.
We take a look at the alpha
channel from that image
and can apply tint colors to it.
So if you would like
to change the color
of this image during
your app's lifecycle
or if your design team would
like to change the tint color
of your application while
it's in development it's very,
very easy to apply
universally across your app.
We introduced Dynamic
Type with iOS 7
which gives you a
really great way
to respect your users request
for larger or smaller type
across the system
and it's important
that you do the best you can
to honor those preferences
to help things be more
legible for your users.
Accessibility is a
critical part of iOS.
We care very deeply about making
sure our operating system is
accessible to as many
people as possible
and there's some very powerful
APIs around accessibility
that are important for
you to use if you decide
to build custom UI
in your application.
There's no reason to not support
accessibility in your app.
And finally localization,
another very critical
part of iOS.
We really on localization to
extend iOS to as many customers
as possible and there's some
new localization tools in iOS 8
that make this even
easier for you.
Beyond those I'd like to
introduce four new topics today.
The first is we're going to
talk about spring animations,
which are a great way to
make your controls feel
like a native part of iOS.
The next thing are
some new techniques
for vibrancy and blur.
After that we're going to
talk about CAShapeLayers.
CAShapeLayers are a great way
that you can draw custom UI
within your application
and animate changes to it.
And then finally,
we're going to talk
about Dynamic Core
Animation behaviors
and how you can make changes
and have even more control
than you may realize
over the behaviors
that Core Animation
provides today.
Let's get started with
Spring Animations.
The first thing to
understand is you need
to understand what a
Spring Animation is,
and you probably think
of a Spring Animation
as a bouncing effect
that mimics a spring
or a slinky in the real world.
And while you can create
very bouncy effects like that
with Spring Animations that's
not the only things you do
with springs.
Really you can think
about Spring Animations
as a new default timing
curve for animations
within your applications
and in fact we use that --
these new timing curves
for nearly every system
animation starting in iOS 7.
Nearly everything you see
that we provide as part
of iOS is built around
Spring Animations now.
You can actually create new
animations or Spring Animations
in your app without the
use of UIKit Dynamics.
Dynamics is an incredibly
powerful tool
for creating physics
simulations within your app
but there's easier ways to
get at Spring Animations.
In fact the API for
making a Spring Animation
in your app is nearly the same
as using the animateWithDuration
block that you're used
to using today on UIView.
So what do Spring
Animations look like?
On the, uh, left side
of the screen (for you guys)
I have a red box that's going
to animate using the default
Ease in/Ease out timing curve.
On the right side we have a
blue box that's going to animate
with a Spring Animation.
Both animations will
use the same duration
and they're moving
the same distance.
But when the animations
start you'll notice
that the Spring Animation
very quickly gets up to speed
and then slowly tappers off
as it reaches its
final position compared
to the Ease In/Ease
Out animation.
Let's slow that down
a little bit more
so you can take a closer look.
You can see when the animation
begins the Spring Animation
quickly moves up to speed
and then spends a
considerable amount
of its animation duration
reaching that final position,
its final resting state.
Compare this with Ease in/Ease
out where it takes a little bit
more time to get up to speed.
Another way to visualize
this is to plot what
that timing curve
looks like over time.
You can see a default curve very
slowly builds up its velocity
and then immediately
starts to slow
down its velocity for the end.
Spring Animations, however,
launch up to speed
almost immediately
and then spend the
last third or so
of their duration reaching
what we call the "long tail"
or that slow bit where
we finally reach the
final position.
Where do we use Spring
Animations in iOS today?
One place is launching apps and
opening and closing folders.
If you pay close attention
to these animations you see it
feels like the animation begins
and very quickly shows the
user the content that they're
about to see and
then, when closing,
very quickly pulls the
folder out of the way.
Another place that we like
to use Spring Animations is
in the default push
and pop animations
for navigation controllers, as
well as presenting modal views
on and off of the screen.
And finally, that Siri
suggestions view that we looked
at earlier is built
with Spring Animations.
We use a single Spring Animation
to pull the text onscreen,
off the bottom, and allow it to
slowly drift across the screen,
and then a second Spring
Animation to quickly pull it
out of the way, making room
for the next set of strings.
What does the API look
like for Spring Animations?
It's -- like I said, there's
a single method on UIView
that makes this really
straightforward for you
to take advantage of Spring
Animations in your app.
Many of these parameters
look familiar to you.
But I'd like to call out
the two that are unique
to Spring Animations and
those are the damping
and initialSpringVelocity
parameters.
Damping takes a value
from 0 to 1
and controls how much
resistance the spring has
to completing the
animation at the end.
The initialSpringVelocity
is used
to give the animation a
kick to push the object
into the animation curve.
You can also use it to
synchronize the animation
with something that's
in flight today.
Let's take a look at how these
different values have an effect
on Spring Animations.
We're going to start out with
the same blue box and a damping
of 0.1, and you can see when the
animation completes there's a
lot of oscillation at the end.
It feels like you would expect a
spring to be in the real world.
You might want this effect...
but you might not.
By stepping the damping
up to something
like 0.5 you can see we
considerably reduce how much
oscillation we get
with this animation.
There's still a fair amount
of bouncing at the end
but it's much more controlled.
Bringing the damping
up to 0.8 reduces most
of that damping effect.
You can see there's a very
small bounce back at the end
of the animation but for the
most part the animation just
smoothly reaches the end.
And finally bringing the damping
up to 1.0 gives us no
oscillation at the end.
It just smoothly reaches
that final position
giving a very nice,
fast feeling to the animation.
So let's bring in the
initial velocity parameter.
We're going to leave
damping the same
but give our spring
a much stronger kick
to start the animation.
You can see it almost
immediately launches the box
past its first position and
actually overcomes the spring
to have it bounce back
a little bit at the end.
An even stronger initial
velocity can blow even further
past that final position but the
damping value very quickly pulls
it into rest.
And then finally we
can combine these
to make very unique effects
giving us a damping value
that resists oscillation
and an initial velocity
to give a nice fast
kick to our spring.
So where would you want to think
about using Spring
Animations in your application?
They're a fantastic
substitute for linear animations
that you're used to using
with the current UIView
animateWithDuration.
In fact, any place that
you would like to fit
into the native UIKit controls
that we provide you should
consider using Spring Animations
instead, because nearly every
animation that's part of UIKit,
that's part of the OS, is
built around Spring Animations.
Spring Animations also
give your controls
and your animations a more
natural feeling to the users,
because springs are
something that are part
of the real world around us.
It's also important
to keep in mind
that while I've showed
you examples
with the position property
you can use Spring Animations
to apply to any animatable
property in UIKit.
That means if you want to
have the alpha for your layers
or your views change you can do
that on a spring timing curve.
I have a demo application put
together and let's take a look
at what Spring Animations
can do for us there.
So this is my demo application.
I have this very nice
rainbow gradient background
and then a control
bar at the bottom
where I have some custom
controls that I can use
to configure that
gradient's rendering.
I can change the
number of colors
and I can also pick
how many colors repeat
within the gradient.
Now these controls are currently
being animated on and off screen
with the default Ease in/Ease
out timing curve
and it feels very...
very normal, but it also feels
like there's a lot of time spent
with the control
getting in the way
of the user actually
interacting with it.
So I'm going to substitute in
a pair of spring animations.
So in my demo code I
have a couple of blocks
that I'm doing animations in
already that I use to present
and dismiss the modal view,
and you can see here I'm already
using UIView animateWithDuration
and passing it in
Animation Block.
What I'm going to
do is just replace
that with a Spring Animation.
You can see the API is almost
exactly what we had before,
just with a couple
of extra arguments.
For my presentation we're going
to use a damping value of .75
and if you remember the boxes
on screen this will give us
just a little bit of oscillation
or a little bit of bouncing
at the end of the animation.
I'm also going to use an
initial spring velocity of 10
to give it even more
of a kick to get
that control on screen quickly.
We're also going to take a
look at my dismiss animation.
Again right now we're using
the same animateWithDuration
and we're going to substitute
in another Spring Animation.
For the dismiss I'm going to
use a very strong damping of 1
because I don't really
want it to be bouncing
when it reaches its final
position in the dock
and I'm going to give it
no initial velocity --
to just let the spring
itself pull
that view back into the dock.
With those changes
let's take a look
at what that does to the app.
Just as a quick reminder: this
is what it looks like right now,
without the Spring Animations.
The control very
smoothly slides in and out
but it still feels a little bit
like it's getting in the way.
When we switch over to a version
with the Spring Animations you
can see there's a very different
but subtle effect.
The spring quickly
pulls the view onscreen.
You can see that very small
bounce when it presents,
but it feels like it gets on
and off the screen and available
to the user much faster
than it did before.
And that's how we can
use Spring Animations
to bring a new feeling to
animations within your app.
The next thing I'd like to talk
about is something
called UIVisualEffectView.
Before we get to that however,
I'd like to spend a couple
of minutes talking about
how we render things on iOS.
Some of the APIs that
we're going to be talking
about today can have
a dramatic effect
on the rendering performance
of your application
and it's important to understand
how they actually work
within the rendering system.
So if you were to take a look
at the entire system there's
largely four steps that we take
to render content
for your application.
We give your app a
chance to handle events
and then commit a transaction
to the render server.
The render server, which is
part of the system on iOS,
processes that transaction,
does some more work
and then composites
layers which are handed off
to the GPU to be rendered.
The GPU will take
its own block of time
to render all those layers and
then hand it off to the display
to present to your user.
Let's focus in just a little
bit on the steps that we take
within your application.
There's largely four things
that take place within your app.
The first thing we'll
do is do any setup work
and ask your views to
lay themselves out.
If you're using auto
layout we're going
to take the time here to
compute the layout for your app.
If you're doing manual layout
for your views we're going
to call layout subviews
and ask your views
to lay themselves out.
The next thing we'll do is
do any necessary drawing.
If any views need
to draw themselves,
if you've implemented
drawRect on some of your views,
we'll ask that to occur here.
We'll also do some string
drawing at this time.
Next we're going to give Core
Animation a little bit of time
to prepare some images if it
needs to decode or convert them
for rendering before we
finally package up the layers
and send them off to
the render server.
This is a very, very
broad overview
of how the render server works.
If you'd like to find out more
there was a fantastic talk
yesterday by the
performance team
that I would really
encourage you to check out.
They go into a lot
of great detail
on how all these
depths actually work.
So with that quick
understanding, let's go back
to UIVisualEffectView.
Last year at WWDC we
introduced a new API called
drawViewHierarchyInRect,
and a system to go with that
for creating fast, static blur
effects within your application
and we continue to recommend
you to take advantage
of this technique if the
content that you want
to show behind the blur is not
actively changing for the user.
The reason for this is it's
just incredibly well optimized
for your application.
So we encourage you to continue
using that as much as possible.
However, we heard
that one or two
of you wanted something a
little bit more advanced.
You wanted to do live blur
effects like we have across iOS,
and to that end we are
introducing UIVisualEffectView.
UIVisualEffectView
creates two effect types.
It's a technique for creating
live blurs in your application
and for creating
vibrancy effects.
Let's take a look at what both
of those effects actually mean.
A live blur effect is exactly
what the name suggests.
It's where you can have content
behind a view that is blurred,
and has some color effects
changed to it as well,
all rendered in real
time on your device.
Vibrancy is used to create
content that is highly legible
at all times on top of a blur.
In the screenshot you see
right now the Facetime icon
and the text are being rendered
with vibrancy and you can see
that that text is always
legible no matter what colors
or content are being
blurred behind it.
[ Applause ]
We have three styles
for blur effects.
The first of those
is a Dark blur.
You can see that we're
darkening the background here,
we're also desaturating
the colors a little bit.
It's more than just
changing a blur.
A Light blur effect is
almost the opposite of that.
Again we're blurring, but
we're starting to wash out some
of the colors as well.
Finally we introduce
ExtraLight blur,
which almost entirely
desaturates the content
and blows out most
of the colors,
but still gives you a blur
effect to give you a sense
of what content is
behind the view.
So what steps do we make to
take -- to create a blur effect?
As I said, it's more than
just a simple Gaussian blur
within your application.
The first thing we do when we
create a blur effect is we're
going to downsample all
of the content that's
waiting to be blurred.
The reason we're doing
that is for performance.
You aren't going to see the
fine details of the view
when we're going to blur it.
So we go ahead and downsample
that to a much smaller size
before applying blur effect.
The next thing we do is modify
the colors and this is based
on what blur effect
you requested.
We'll either desaturate
or oversaturate colors
to create the various styles.
And then the final step is
we're going to compute the blurs
and then composite this
back into your application.
Vibrancy effect, as I
said, is a technique
for making legible content
that is typically
placed on top of a blur.
And we create this with
a few steps as well.
The first thing we'll do
is boost the saturation
of your content and
then we're going
to apply a custom blend
mode to the vibrant content
and that blend mode is going
to change based on what kind
of blur you expect to
put the vibrant effect
on top of that with.
And for that reason you
need to tell us what kind
of blur you're using when
you create a vibrant effect.
So how do we use this
in your application?
The first thing you'll do is
initialize a new UIVisualEffect,
and you can initialize
either a UIBlurEffect
or a UIVibrancyEffect.
UIVibrancyEffect actually takes
the blur in its initializer
so we know how to create
that vibrancy effect
for the blur you plan to use.
After that you can instantiate
a UIVisualEffectView and pass
that visual effect that
you've just created.
Finally, the UIVisualEffectView
provides a content view
and you should add your
subviews to that content view.
That way we know what views
you want to have manipulated
or effected by the
visual effects.
There's a couple of
things you can do
to customize VisualEffectViews
in your application.
The first thing you can do
is you can tint the blurs
by changing the backgroundColor
property
on the VisualEffectView's
contentView.
So if you would like to
create a dark red blur effect,
for example, you
can make a dark blur
and then set the contentView's
backgroundColor to a red color
to have the desired effect.
You can also do some
animations to the frame changes
within your application
to change the position
and size of the blur effect.
Now visual effects also come
with a number of caveats
when you consider using
them in your application.
The first of those is the
idea of setting alpha.
If you think about the
purposes of blurs in alpha,
they're at odds with each other.
You apply alpha to
a view in order
to make content legible
behind another view;
to see what's back there.
You use a blur effect to show
that there's something there
but you're not interested
in the details.
So it's not really sensical
to apply an alpha to a blur
at the same time and for
that reason we're going
to drop the blur feature if
you try to change the alpha.
You should also be very cautious
about placing VisualEffectViews
in a view hierarchy
that uses masks.
They're not going to
work very well together.
You also should be conscious
of whether you're going to --
if you place a Visual
Effect View in groups,
they can have an
impact on its rendering:
either animation groups
or opacity groups.
It's very easy to have -- to
forget that you have, say,
a blur or a vibrancy
effect really deep
in your view hierarchy and
then, when you add an animation
over here, forget that
it's going to pick
up that VisualEffectView and
try to make changes to it.
So I started this
section by talking
about the rendering
pipeline and I'd
like to highlight what
impact VisualEffectViews have
on the rendering of
your application.
All of the work
for VisualEffectViews is
having an impact on the GPU.
So if we look at a standard view
in your application it's going
to take a pretty typical amount
of time to render on the GPU.
In order to create blur
effects we have to take all
of those steps that
were outlined
and render those offscreen.
It's just the way that we
have to create blur effects.
So we're going to ask the GPU
to stop rendering
your app's main views,
and create this blur
effect offscreen,
and then combine
everything back together...
and that can take
considerably more time
than rendering a standard
view without blur effects.
Vibrancy takes additional passes
in addition to the blur effect
that they're placed on top of.
So to add vibrancy into a view
takes even more offscreen time
for your application.
Now to contrast this with
drawViewHierarchyInRect,
we can do that considerably
faster because we don't have
to do all of those
offscreen passes every frame.
So this is why we still strongly
encourage the static blur
techniques from last
year if at all possible.
Let's take a look at how we
can use VisualEffectViews
in that same demo application.
So going back to the demo app,
I still have these controls
that come onscreen and right now
they're just being placed on top
of a dimming view and you can
see I have this white text label
at the bottom that's not
really legible anyway
and it just doesn't
look very interesting.
We're going to use -- we also
have a control bar at the bottom
which is just solid white
right now and kind of feels
out of place on this rich,
colorful gradient background.
So we're going to
use blur effects
and vibrancy effects
to improve this.
So back in my demo application
the first thing we're going
to do is go to the gradient
view controller and we're going
to set up that control bar
at the bottom of the screen.
The control bar is that
white bar at the bottom
with the different controls
in it and we're going
to create an ExtraLight blur
effect, and the key things
that you should take a look
at here are: the first part,
where we create a new UI blur
effect and give it a style.
In this case we're using an
ExtraLight blur effect style.
Next we're going to
create a UIVisualEffectView
and pass it the effect
that we just created,
that ExtraLight blur effect.
And then finally we'll add
this to our view hierarchy.
We're also going to do this
on the clickwheel controller
and I want to do both
the blurred background
and a vibrant title here.
First we're going to make
that blurred background view.
Very similar to before we're
going to make a UI blur effect
but give it the Dark
blur effect style
and then again create a
UIVisualEffectView and pass it
that blur effect that we
just created and then add it
to our view hierarchy.
The next thing we do
is we want to modify
that title label
to use vibrancy.
You can see right now
I'm creating my label
and just giving it
a white color.
It's pretty straightforward to
upgrade that to use vibrancy.
To do that we're going
to make a vibrancy effect
and you notice the initializer
is effectForBlurEffect.
We're going to grab a
reference to the blur effect off
of that backdropView that
we created right up here,
and pass that into the
vibrancy effect because we plan
to composite this title label
on top of that background blur.
Same as before, we'll make
a new UIVisualEffectView
and give it the vibrancy
effect that we just created,
and then down here at
the bottom we're going
to add my title label
to the content view
of that new vibrancyEffectView.
So those are the three steps
I needed to take to add blurs
and vibrancy to the
demo application.
Let's take a look at
what those look like.
You immediately see that we're
picking up that blur effect,
that ExtraLight blur
effect, at the control bar
at the bottom of the screen.
It's reflecting the purple
color of the gradient behind it.
When we bring our controls
onscreen you can see
that we're blurring that
gradient as well as picking
up vibrancy for that
text label at the bottom.
You can see the purple
and the white
from the views behind
it taking place.
Now you're probably thinking,
"Well that's great Brandon,
but you're probably just
faking it with that live blur
or that static blur thing."
I promise you we're not.
Because if I start scrolling
this you can see the blur
effects are all taking place
in real time and you can see
that the vibrancy
is also picking
up all those really cool
colors behind everything.
You'll also see that
control bar picking
up those colors behind
itself as well.
It's that easy to add vibrancy
and blur to your application.
[ Applause ]
So moving on, next we're going
to talk about CAShapeLayer.
CAShapeLayer is a
really powerful tool
for drawing custom Bézier
paths within your application.
CAShapeLayer, as the name
suggests, is a subclass
of CALayer, which makes it
very, very easy to use in all
of your app's existing view
hierarchies because on iOS all
of your views are already
backed with CALayers.
The other really powerful part
of CAShapeLayer is that all
of the properties on it
that control its
appearance are animatable.
So where am I going to
use this Shape Layer?
One place is if you were going
to create a download control
similar to the one that you see
in the music app or of
different store apps.
These need to have a
few different states:
one that shows a thinking state
(where there's a ring that's
partially completed, that's
spinning); it shows a state
with a stop; and then it also
shows a download progress (where
it completes the ring,
going from zero to 100%).
This would be a great
thing to draw
with CAShapeLayering
in your application.
I'd like to show you a few of
the more interesting properties
on Shape Layers right now.
The most important one
is the path property.
As the name suggests,
this defines what your shape
layer actually is going
to look like.
You create these by
handing us a CGPathRef.
Personally, I like to
work with UIBezierPath
and then hand off the CGPath
version of that at the end.
So there's a few steps
that we're going to take
to create the curve
that you see onscreen.
You can think about creating
paths as very similar to drawing
on a piece of paper, where you
move your pencil to a point
and then move the pencil
on the paper to draw lines.
The first thing we're going to
do is move to a specific point
where we want to start the line.
In this case we're
going to start
on the lower left-hand corner.
The next thing we'll do is
add two curves to the point
and you'll notice we pass
this a pair of control points.
Bézier paths are defined
by a point and then a pair
of control handles which you see
in blue on the diagram above.
Those control points
define what the curve looks
like between the first
-- the previous --
and the current point.
So we're going to add two
curves with their control points
to my path and then finally set
that path on my shape layer.
The next set of properties
control what the line looks like
and there's a few particularly
interesting properties
on the line.
The first is the
lineCap property.
This defines what the ends
of each line look like.
By default they're
just a flat line.
In this case we're going to
set a round lineCap on them
to give them a nice,
rounded effect.
The lineDashPattern defines
how we draw dashed lines
and it gives you
a lot of control
over what that looks like.
You create a lineDashPattern by
giving us an array of NSNumbers
and we go through this array to
decide how many points to draw,
and then how many
points to not draw.
So in this example, we're
asking the CAShapeLayer to draw
for two points and then not draw
for four points, draw for six
and then not draw for the
final six, and then repeat
that pattern across
the length of the line.
LineDashPhase is used
to control how far
into that array we
start the line drawing.
So by setting a lineDashPhase
of four it essentially shifts
that dash pattern four
points along the line.
The next set of properties
relate to the stroke
of the line, which is what
we actually draw it like.
The most obvious one is
called strokeColor and,
as you would expect, it
defines the color of the line.
Pretty straightforward
to use I hope.
The next two are a little
bit more interesting
and that's the strokeBegin
and strokeEnd properties.
StrokeBegin defines how far
into the line we're going
to begin stroking
it or drawing it.
In the video above, I'm actually
drawing the original path
in a dark red behind that, so
that you can see the difference
between the actual --
what the code is doing.
So by setting our stroke
begin to 0.2 we're going
to skip drawing the
first 20% of the line.
StrokeEnd is very similar
but defines how far
from the end we're
going to draw that path.
So by saying it's
0.6 we're going
to not draw the final
60% of the path.
You can imagine this particular
property will be very powerful
if you were creating
a download control.
Because you could take that
download progress from zero
to 100% and directly map that
onto the strokeEnd property
on CAShapeLayer, which
is again animated
so the shape layer is
automatically going to animate
between states for you.
The final property that
you'll probably find useful
in some cases is the fillColor.
You don't always want
to add fillColor.
It doesn't always look awesome,
but it's a very powerful thing
to have if you want
more of a closed path.
Shape layers also
can have a big impact
on the rendering performance
of your application.
So let's go back to that
rendering pipeline one
more time.
In this case shape layers have
an impact on all the rendering
that occurs within
your application itself
and there's a few things
that we want to talk
about when you're
rendering shape layers.
When you have a shape
layer we have
to rasterize the shape layer on
the CPU within your application.
What that means is
when we're doing all
of your view drawing we're
going to actually have
to ask the shape layer
to compute itself
and then draw it
into, essentially,
an image that we
can composite later.
We're going to send
that rasterized layer
over to the render server
for later compositing
and this process can get very
expensive in terms of CPU time.
Especially if you have
a very complex path
for your shape layer.
The more complex it is, the
longer it's going to take us
to draw and prepare
that shape layer.
So one thing you
could do to minimize
that effect is you can use more
layers with less complexity
and then stack them behind each
other to get the same effect
that you're asking for.
For example, with
that download control,
that's showing the download
state: you might want
to draw the square as one
shape layer, the outer ring
as a second shape layer and
then show the download progress
as a third shape layer and
then composite the three
of them together by just
stacking them in the same place
in your view hierarchy.
You should also be very
conscious of frequent changes
to shape layers within
your application.
Every time a shape layer changes
we have to re-rasterize it
and send that new result
over to the render server.
So if your shape layer is
changing every frame we're
constantly having to redraw it
and hand this new object off
which can get very expensive
and have a negative impact
on your app's performance.
I actually have a shape layer
hidden in the demo application
that we've been taking
a look at,
so I'd like to show you
how that's implemented
and then we'll make a
couple of quick changes
to the appearance
of my shape layer.
So first let's see
where that's at.
If we look in the demo
application you probably notice
that there's two controls
that I haven't touched yet
and those effect the line
end and the dash size.
So let's bring the stroke
end all the way up to 100%
and you see I suddenly
get this nice red box.
It's the world's most
interesting shape layer.
I also have a dash size property
that controls the length
of the dashes in that array.
So if I bring my dash size
up we're creating a
dashed line effect instead.
If we bring the stroke end back
down to something else like,
68% you can see we're
only drawing the first 68%
of the line.
My shape layer's line starts
in the upper left corner
and then progress around
the box from there.
Let's take a look at how
this is implemented in code
and make a couple of
quick changes to it.
What I've done is I've created
a custom UIView subclass
that I'm calling Shape View and
my Shape View, like all views
in iOS, is backed
with a CALayer.
We give you the ability to
actually override what kind
of layer that your
view is backed
with by implementing
the Layer Class Method,
and I've asked my
view to be backed
with a CAShapeLayer instead.
In my awakeFromNib I'm going
to do some configuration work
to create that shape layer.
The first thing we'll do
is create a CGPath Ref
and create it with a rectangle
that represents my
view's bounds.
That's how we're
creating that nice,
simple, square shape layer.
We set the path and then spend
some time configuring a few
of the properties
of my shape layer.
The stroke color, again, is
what defines the color we use
to draw the outside
of the path width --
in this case a red color.
We're setting our line width to
six to make it nice and visible
on top of the background and I
had the strokeEnd start at zero,
so that none of you would see
the shape layer in advance.
I also have the line Join.
LineJoin defines what the
corners of those lines look
like when they come together
and we're defaulting
that to a round join.
We're also setting the
lineCap (which is, again,
what controls the
edges of each line)
and making those round as well.
And finally I'm not using a
fill color for my shape layer.
Down here at the bottom I
have two methods that are used
to configure properties
based on those controls
that you see onscreen.
One controls the strokeEnd,
the other is setting
that lineDashLength.
Right now what I'm
doing is making an array
that creates two NSNumbers
that use the same value
for both the distance to draw
and the distance not to draw
and we're going to make
a change to that first.
I've decided that the
dashes just look too close
to each other so
instead what we're going
to do is first use the same
NSNumber to draw for a distance
and then we're going to
multiply that by four
to have a much larger
gap between our dashes.
I'm also going to make a
quick change to the line joint
of my shape layer and switch
over to a bevel line join.
Let's take a look
at those changes
in the demo application now.
So again we're going to bring
that strokeEnd all the way
up first to see the
changes we've made
and the first thing
you see is the change
that we made to the line join.
If you take a look at
the corners of my boxes,
instead of having that nice,
rounded effect they
had this nice, like,
diamond-cut chamfer
around the edges.
It looks fantastic.
We're also going to take a look
at those dash size changes we
made so we'll dial that up a bit
and you can see a
dramatic difference
in what we had before.
We're drawing a very short dash
followed by a much longer gap.
And again, just to illustrate
those changes, let's dial some
of these effects back and you
can again see the difference
that makes on our shape layer.
Now you might have
noticed in code
that I have a tap
gesture recognizer setup
on my shape layer.
Let's take a look at
what that's doing.
Every time I tap on my shape
layer I'm picking a random alpha
value to animate to and
changing the opacity of my view
and of the shape layer itself.
It's an interesting effect but
it's kind of boring and I'd
like to do something a
little bit more interesting
for my users and to do that
we're going to take a look
at how we can create Dynamic
Behaviors with Core Animation.
As you're probably aware
UIKit and UIView provide a lot
of interesting animations
for your application
and you have a lot of control
over how these animations
look and behave.
Core Animation provides implicit
animations on your layers.
Nearly every property
that you would change
on a layer would be implicitly
animated by Core Animation.
That means you set the property
and CA will just provide an
animation from the current value
to the new value for
you automatically.
What you might not
be aware of is you
as a developer have the ability
to override the implicit
behaviors
that Core Animation
provides to you.
And you might be
thinking, "That's nice.
What would I want
to do with that?"
One thing you could do is
you could just disable the
implicit animations.
You could just say, "You know,
I don't want any animations.
Thanks anyway.
Don't do anything at all."
And that's fine.
You can also use this capability
to change the behavior
of the default animations
that Core Animation provides.
For example you might
want to have your layer
or your view show a different
color while the opacity
animation takes place.
You also might decide that
you're implementing OS X Weed
and you want to have that path
be less than linear as it moves
from point A to point B.
If you were to create a new
CALayer subclass you can also
add your own properties
and make them animatable
with this technique.
The key part of this is that
we can use this technique
to define behaviors that
are inherent to custom views
within your application.
This encapsulates any custom
animation behaviors you'd like
and bakes them into
the view itself.
So if you want to reuse this
view elsewhere in your app
or in a framework it just comes
along as part of the view.
How do these work?
In this case I have my view
which, like all views in iOS,
is backed with a CALayer.
CALayers have a CALayerDelegate
protocol that all
of your views implement and
your view is always the delegate
for its layer.
So let's say in my application
I want to animate the alpha.
I'm calling UIView
animateWithDuration
and setting the alpha
on my view to 0.2.
Let's take a look at the steps
that take place when
we request this.
Your CALayer is going to ask its
delegates actionForLayer:forKey
and that's going to be
called on my custom view.
If you haven't implemented
this it will automatically go
to the superclass.
If you have implemented it,
you have a couple of options.
The first thing you can do is
call back to your superclass
and just say actionForLayer:
key and pass the same result
back on to Core Animation.
If you decide that you would
like to have a little
bit more control
over the animation instead,
you can create a new action
result and pass that back.
You create objects to conform to
the CAAction protocol and hand
that new action object
back to Core Animation.
The CAAction protocol
defines a single method;
runActionForKey:
object arguments.
And you can implement the
CAAction protocol on any object.
Typically you just want to
make this on an NSObject --
a very nice, lightweight object
to pass back to Core Animation.
You can do whatever you would
like in the implementation
of runActionForKey.
Typically you're going to want
to actually run some animations
there but you might decide you'd
like to do something else:
fire some notifications,
start or cancel timers,
keep count of something,
whatever your minds
come up with.
You can do whatever you
like in runActionForKey.
There's two arguments in here
that are particularly
interesting.
The first is the key.
This specifies what property
just changed on the CALayer
that you're being
asked to interact with.
The second is the
object argument.
This is providing a reference
to the CALayer that's
being animated right now,
or having values
changed on it right now,
and this is how you have
access to the new values
that have been set as well as
how you can apply these changes
to the layer that
you've been manipulating.
It's hard to talk
about this in slides
so instead let's take a look at
it back in the demo application.
We're going to go back
to my shapeView class
and I've decided I'd like
to add some custom behavior
for when the opacity changes
on my layer and on my view.
The first thing I need to
do is create a new object
that conforms to the
CAAction protocol.
So to do that I've defined
an opacity action object
and it has a single method
in its implementation;
runActionForKey:
object arguments.
Let's take a look at some of
the steps we're making here.
The first thing we're going
to do is check what the
event is that's being asked
for this animation --
or for this action --
and we're only interested
in doing things here
if the layer's opacity
was asked to change.
I'm going to give myself a
nice pointer to the CALayer
that was passed in and
define a duration to use
for all of my animations.
I'm going to create
three CA basic animations
for my application
that take place
when this opacity change occurs.
What I've decided I'd like to
do is have the background color
of my layer change as the
opacity animates as well
and we're going to do
that with these few steps.
Now the things I'd like you to
notice is: first, the fromValue.
Core Animation needs to know
what to start an animation with
and what to end it with.
The fromValue is defining
the beginning of that.
Now my layer already has
the new value set on it
when my action object
is called...
which means I need to know
what it looks like onscreen,
and layers provide what they
call a presentation layer.
The presentation layer
is a representation
of what the layer looks
like onscreen to the user
at that instant in time.
So I'm asking my
presentation layer
for its current background color
to be the starting
point of this animation.
My toValue is the new value
that we're requesting.
And what I'm doing here
is animating changes
to the hue value and leaving the
saturation and brightness alone.
If you're not familiar
with hue, saturation
and brightness you can
think about a color wheel
where the hue is defining
what point along that circle,
what color we're using.
So I'm going to take the
opacity value and use
that to define my hue.
I'm also going to make the same
animation to the stroke color
of my shape layer, but
this time we're going
to use some modifications
to the value
that we're setting on the hue.
And then finally
I do in fact want
to animate the opacity myself
and since I'm overriding
the action I have
to provide my own
opacity animation as well.
So I'll set that using the
same presentation layer
and the toValue, and
that's all there is
to making a new action object.
Now I need to make sure that my
action object is actually going
to get called.
And we're going to do
that within my layers
implementation - or,
my views implementation itself.
So my view is going to
implement actionForLayer:forKey.
This is that CALayerDelegate
method.
It's pretty straightforward.
I'm going to check to see if
I'm being requested to make --
to provide an action
for the opacity value.
If I do, I alloc-init a new
instance of my opacity action
and hand it back
to Core Animation.
In all other cases I'm going to
call through to my superclass
and allow the default
behaviors to be returned.
And those are the
steps we need to take
to provide a custom CA action
within your application.
Let's see what effect
that has on our box.
So we're back in the demo app
again and I'm going to bring
that box all the way up
for full visibility and --
to make sure that it's, y'know,
really going to stand out --
we'll bring some more
colors into things as well.
Actually...
I like it with less colors, so
we'll do that; put a little bit
of a dash size on, just for fun.
Now if you remember, the way
this is configured is I'm going
to tap on the box which will
pick a random opacity value
and animate to that over
the newly defined 0.75
second duration.
Whenever we get that new
opacity value we're also going
to animate the hue of the
background color and the stroke.
So you can see: every time I tap
on that we're getting
a very interesting set
of color combinations and
we're also still making changes
to the background.
It's a very interesting
and very unique effect.
We can see the opacity
better this way.
But the opacity is
changing alongside the hue
for the background
and the stroke colors.
And the really powerful part
of the way I've built this is:
all of these behaviors
are inherently part
of my custom view.
So any time I use
that view I can add it
to my view hierarchy anywhere
in the app and I don't have
to remember to animate
all three properties.
I just set the alpha
and it automatically gets
all the new behaviors
that I've requested.
It's a really powerful
capability.
[ Applause ]
So to summarize what
we've talked about today:
we've presented four
new techniques.
The first is how you can
use Spring Animations
in your application.
Think about Spring Animations
as a new timing curve
for animations within your
application that make them fit
in better with the rest of the
platform and feel more dynamic
and engaging for your users.
UIVisualEffectView is a great
new API introduced in iOS 8
that will allow you to create
live blur effects as well
as vibrancy to keep content
highly legible on top of blurs.
CAShapeLayer allows you to
design custom Bézier paths
and draw them within your
application and animate changes
to those properties, and we've
talked about how to use CAAction
to get more dynamic behaviors
out of Core Animation.
If you'd like to learn more
about these technologies
there's some great documentation
for UIKits and for
Core Animation.
You can also talk to Jake, he's
our Apps Frameworks Evangelist.
He has great shoes and he loves
getting email from all of you.
There's some fantastic new
sessions going on this week
that talk about more of these
topics that we have covered.
Many of them happened
yesterday and there's going
to be a fantastic session on
Friday at 11:30, in Presidio,
that I really encourage
you to check out.
Thanks for coming and I
hope you enjoy the rest
of your time at WWDC.
[ Applause ]