>> Good morning everybody.
Welcome to Prototyping.
I'm Jeff Bernstein.
I brought along Linda
Dong, Julian Missig
and Mark Hauenstein
from the team.
So who is this session
for today?
Well, it's for developers
at companies.
Show of hands.
Excellent.
To be expected.
Solo developers.
All right.
People who don't
code at all, anyone?
All right, great.
Very brave of you.
[ Laughter ]
And designers, designers?
Yeah, all right.
And management types?
[ Laughter ]
Sort out you guys, yeah.
So our plan today: We're going
to design and prototype an app.
We're going to go through
the steps we would go
through to try something out.
And we're going to
show a variety
of different prototyping
methods.
All of this is going
to be with a focus
on prototyping an experience,
not trying out an API or testing
out some kind of
technical feasibility.
So who are we?
Who are we to come here and
tell you how to make your apps?
Oh we're a small
secret team at Apple.
We work across all
of Apple's products.
We explore what new
interfaces mean to our devices,
operating system
and applications.
And we do this by making
interactive prototypes every
day, sometimes 24 hours a day.
So today, you're all very lucky.
I'm going to unveil to all of
you today a world-changing,
disruptive application, and I'd
like to show it to
you right now.
[ Music ]
This is an application
to explore
and discover artisanal toast on
the streets of San Francisco.
Browse for toast
that's near you.
Find the top toast in town.
Go and get some toast.
Share the toast with
your friends.
Take a picture.
Share it with your
friends and loved ones.
Today, I give to you ladies
and gentlemen, "Toast Modern."
Thank you.
Thank you everyone.
[ Music & Applause ]
And it's available now.
So go and get it.
Except it's not.
None of this is real.
It's just a prototype.
So why? Why would
we go to the trouble
of creating this
beautiful, world-changing,
disruptive application
that is completely fake?
Well, this is the picture
in most people's head.
I have an idea.
Then, I build my application,
and then, step three, profit.
Except, what I see frequently
is that people have an idea,
they build their application,
and somehow they're
disappointed by the result.
Maybe the experience isn't
what you've hoped for.
Maybe it just doesn't
resonate with your customers.
And building applications
are difficult.
You guys know this.
It takes time.
It takes money, people,
sleep, heartache.
And frankly, it's
a lot of typing.
So, that's a lot of
work for something
that you're not happy
with in the end.
So instead of going
from an idea directly
to building your application,
we're going to go from an idea
to a prototype, and then
build our application.
And it's best if we can do
that over and over again.
The more prototypes we
can put between our idea
and our application, the better
the result is going to be.
And the way that we do this is
by beginning with something fake
and then gradually
adding elements
that are more real
along the way,
sprinkling it with
interactivity.
So there are two
important reasons
to prototype I want everybody to
keep in mind throughout today.
Number one is to test
ideas, to save time
and money building the right
things for your application.
And number two is to get new
ideas, to make the experience
of your app even
better in the end.
So how do we do this?
It's actually really simple.
Make fake apps, show people
and learn from their feedback.
Again, make fake
apps, show people
and learn from their feedback.
Do that over, and over, and
over again until the experience
of your app feels great.
So how do we make fake apps?
What does that mean?
Well, we want to ask ourselves
three questions before we begin.
The first one is what
needs to be more real?
Everything else is
going to be fake,
but what one element
are we trying
to explore and get feedback on?
The second question
is what can we fake?
And that's everything else.
Everything else will pretty
much just be a picture.
The third important question
is where will they use it?
We want to make sure that
if we're making a prototype,
it's something that we can try
out on the device in the place
where people will be using it.
So, we've made a fake app; now
it's time to show it to people;
we want to ask them three
questions as we're showing them.
Do you know how to do
this one particular thing
that we have prototyped?
Is it easy to do that thing?
And in general, how can
we make this better?
We want to solicit
kind of freeform input
on how we can improve our app.
You'd be surprised what
interesting things people have
to say.
So who do we show
our fake apps to?
Makes sense, the
people your app is for.
So, if your app isn't
for engineers,
go and find some people
who are not engineers.
Don't argue, defend or dismiss.
You're not there to
debate the pros and cons
of what you've prototyped.
You're there to get information
from people and learn from them.
So we've showed some people.
We've probably taken some notes.
We've probed.
We've asked a few questions.
Now we ask ourselves three
questions about what to do next.
What's working in
what we showed them?
What's not working?
What did people did
not understand?
What did they stumble over
or was confusing in some way?
And what other ideas
does this give us
about what we might
want to do next?
So again, make, show and
learn, and we do this over
and over again until
the experience
of our product is great.
Now today, we're going to do
that in a few different
ways for you guys.
We're going to prototype
with pictures,
just drawing for the device.
Then we're going to
prototype with animation,
so we can see how
different screens
that we've drawn work together.
And then we're going to
prototype with interaction,
so we can see how the
entire experience feels
in our hand on the device.
Now to prototype with
pictures, we're actually going
to do it in Keynote today.
Keynote is fast, easy
and cheap and a lot
of you probably already
have it on your computer.
But in practice, you can
use anything that can chop
up pictures and draw
a few basic shapes.
For animation, we're actually
also going to prototype
with Keynote, which is a
surprisingly sophisticated
animation tool.
But you can use anything
that can move pictures
around on the screen over time.
And to prototype
our interactions,
we're actually going to use
-objective-C and Core Animation.
That's what we use frequently
to prototype concepts.
And it's actually
easier than you think
if you're not a developer.
If you are a developer,
you're going to see us use it
in a slightly different way
than you might be used to.
So, I'd like to recap
for you the key features
of "Toast Modern," our
beautiful, world-changing,
disruptive application.
We want to find toast
to eat near me,
want to find the top toast to
eat, post toast, rate toast,
and review and discuss toast
with my fellow toast
aficionados.
These are a lot of
toast features.
So, we're actually just going
to pare it down to talking
about the first two,
finding top toast to eat,
and finding toast
to eat near me.
To begin the prototyping
process,
I'd like to ask Linda
Dong to come to the stage.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks Jeff.
Good morning.
So, to figure out how finding
toast in our app is going
to work, we're going to
begin by making pictures.
So here we start off by drawing
just a ton of different sketches
to quickly get down all
the ideas in our heads
for ways we can show nearby
as well as top-rated toast.
Now, on our team, we always
start from hand drawn concepts.
I'm going to really emphasize
that you guys all do it too
if you're not already
doing this.
There's just no faster
or cheaper way
to get ideas flowing,
to explore a whole slew
of directions than
through drawing.
And drawing is fun.
Like who doesn't want
to dream of a ton
of crazy disposable ideas.
Not you guys, right?
And keep in mind.
You don't have to be
an artist to do this.
Maybe your drawings
look more like this.
Whatever. I mean
don't go showing this
to like board meetings or
anything, but the point remains
that we're trying to emphasize
that you should not
start prototyping
from just a single idea.
You want to explore and
understand the whole space
in order to figure out the
best direction for your app.
So when we were comparing all
of our ideas, there were four
that stood out as really
compelling: this list,
grid, map, and gallery.
So why did we choose these four?
Well, not only do
they convey our type
of information really well.
They also, unlike some
of the other ideas,
aren't overly complex
or too elaborate.
We want to start simple.
Also, they represent
four distinct directions
that our app can take as opposed
to being variations
of a single idea.
And great, isn't this awesome
that we found all of this
out super quick on paper
before devoting a lot
of time exploring
just one concept.
And so, I've got my sketches
and it's no big deal now.
They're just sketches, so I can
just throw away all the other
ideas that didn't
work out to just focus
on making these four more real.
And to do that, we're going to
turn them into some fake apps.
So, the first question we're
going to ask ourselves is,
what needs to be more real?
Why are we making
these fake apps?
What's our goal?
So right now we just
have drawings.
So before we even think
about touching any code,
we're going to determine
how these ideas will look
on the screen in our hands.
Second question we're going to
ask ourselves: What can we fake?
What shortcuts can we take?
Well, we can fake pretty
much all the content.
We don't need a database of
toast photographs or locations,
we can make up filler
text and we're going
to use temporary icons.
And lastly, where
will we use it?
Well, we're going
to put these screens
on an actual iPhone
and use them outside.
So, we're going to start
off with the sketch
of a toast list view
sorted by rating.
Now, before we dive straight
into translating this
to the screen, we're
going to see
if we can save ourselves some
time by borrowing elements
from existing iOS apps.
And just from browsing
on my phone, I've noticed
that the music app actually
has a really similar structure
to our sketch.
So let's use this as a way
to kind of lay out our idea.
And the way we're going to
do that is we're just going
to take a snapshot of
the screen from our phone
and import it into
Keynote for Mac.
Now, we on our team use
Keynote really frequently
to make super quick
prototypes because it has a ton
of really useful tools that
make aligning photographs
and images really easy.
But you guys should be using
whatever image editing tool
you're most comfortable in.
So if you've done this type
of stuff before, maybe you're
in Photoshop or Pixelmator
or Sketch.
If you're a developer who's
never done image editing before,
a great place to start
off is Preview for Mac.
So we've got our screenshot.
What do we do next?
Well, we want to block off the
main areas of the UI in order
to create ourselves a
type of template to drop
in our own content into.
So the way we're going to do
that in Keynote is actually open
up the Shape Menu and drop
in just a ton of boxes
to block off the navigation
bar, all the photographs,
the borders and the background.
So great, now we have a basic
structure to work off of.
Next up is to get
that navigation bar
to be the right color.
So to do that in Keynote,
you open up the Color Picker,
and using that magnifying
glass tool, sample the color
of the status bar above it.
And now we've got ourselves
a blank navigation bar.
Now, that was really
simple, right?
Well, that's because
we're using a screenshot.
So, you don't need to know exact
pixel dimensions or even colors
of UI elements in order
to re-create them,
which saves us a ton of time.
And so, the next thing I want to
do is just add in some content.
And in particular, some images.
So, here's some photographs
I took this morning
on my daily toast excursion,
and I'm just going to put
in this good looking one.
And now that I'm looking at
that photograph, I'm thinking,
maybe instead of just a
plain square thumbnail,
we could do something cool where
we crop the image to a circle
so all you can see is
the plate and the toast.
And so, luckily for us,
Keynote actually has a great set
of options to be able to
mask an image to any shape.
So, we're going to
choose the Oval Mask here,
and now we've got a perfectly
cropped plate of toast
that we can - yes, thank
you guy - that we can put
into our placeholder, and
we're just going to repeat
that same process
for other images.
Now, notice, we're just using
the same three images over
and over again, and that's
because we don't want
to spend more time than
necessary creating content.
Three pictures of toast for all
of your screens, totally fine.
And so, once these images are
in place, now we can get rid
of those placeholders.
And right off the bat, I'm
sure you're noticing this,
you can't see the plates of
toast on that background.
So, how do we fix that?
Do we add borders?
Do we add drop shadows?
Do we change the
background image?
Like what are the
parameters that we use?
Well, hold on.
Those are all visual
design decisions
that we can make further down
the line if we even decide
to go with this direction.
For now, we're going to
do something super basic
and just add in a simple
one pixel border around all
of our images, and done.
We're - it's already
more visible.
We can worry about the
details of it later.
And so now I've got
my images of toast.
I want to label them.
And so to help us out with that,
we're actually going to take
that white box we were
using as a background
and make it transparent.
So, this way the music app
is now peeking through,
and we can see how the labels
in that screen are laid
out in order to help us lay
out and size our own text.
And now notice, these
locations don't exist.
You can't get toast with
goat butter and trout on it.
That's not a thing.
We're just faking text
because it's quick
and we don't have
to worry about it.
So, cool, this is actually
really coming together.
We just can up the opacity
of the background again
and make some little
tweaks and adjustments
so that the layout works
for our composition.
So, the only thing that's
missing right now is ratings.
And so, for this, I'm
actually going to go
into the Special Characters
menu, which some of you guys may
or may not be already
familiar with.
So here, we actually get a giant
list of pre-existing symbols
and characters that
we could repurpose
as icons for our layout.
So, I found myself a really
nice star symbol that I want
to use to represent ratings.
I'm just going to drop a ton of
those in, align them together,
and we've got some
ratings, awesome.
Now, I think this
looks pretty OK,
but I think those stars
could really use a tint color
because I want to make
them look active later.
So, what particular color
you use now doesn't matter.
So, we're just going to go into
Keynotes default color palette
and choose a color
that makes sense.
So, here I chose orange
because it's the toastiest color
of the rainbow.
Great, now I've got
some orange stars
and they look more
active already.
And I really like that
color so I'm actually going
to change the borders around
my image to be the same color.
And now we've got a
nice relationship going
between the picture of the toast
and its rating through color.
And so, last but not least,
I'm going to add a control
to the top right-hand side of
this app so that someone can add
in a new photograph
of a piece of toast.
And here, we could get all fancy
with custom shapes, and masking,
and doing all sorts
of intricate stuff.
But remember we only care about
temporary icons right now.
So instead, we are literally
going to add in a text box,
type in the plus symbol, and
now you've designed an icon
in five seconds.
Congratulations.
All right, yeah,
plus signs, cool.
And last but not least,
just scribble on a title
for your screen,
and there you go.
One freshly baked screen
ready to be tested.
Now, one thing to really keep in
mind when you're making screens
on any program is to remember
to zoom out to the physical size
of the device that your
screen is going to live on.
It's really easy to get caught
up working at a zoom level
where everything is big,
and clear, and legible.
So, remember, every time
you added a new element
onto the screen, to zoom out,
and check if that piece of text
or that picture is both
readable, legible, and tappable,
and catch that early on.
So, now we've got
one screen ready.
And that screen took us
about 10 minutes to make.
If we were to have
worried too much
about all the visual nuances
that the screen could have,
we would be here
for the next hour
and this would be a
really boring presentation.
Instead, we took shortcuts.
And that's fine because
these aren't going
to be our final screens.
And so, I'm going to rinse
and repeat that process
of screenshotting,
masking, arranging objects,
and adding basic content
to the rest of our ideas,
like our GridView idea, which
looks like the camera roll.
And in practice, it's like,
ah, kind of too much toast.
That's a lot of toast
to look at.
Or our map idea which
- I don't know,
that looks pretty interesting.
I think that would be
really fun to play with.
Or our gallery weather app idea,
which just like looks
really cool.
And so, now I've
got my four screens,
and again they're not going
to be our final designs.
There're many places where
we could refine the visual
appearance and/or the
styling of all of the screens.
But we're not going to
do that because it's OK,
because we didn't make
these applications
to become gorgeous hero shots.
We made them so that
we could test
out how successful
each concept will be.
That way when we
do devote our time
and effort polishing the
visuals of our final screen,
we'll know we're doing
it to the right idea.
And so, what's next?
Well, we have our screens,
we're going to drop them
onto an iPhone and give
them to people to test out.
So, the way we're going to do
that is we're going to go back
into Keynote and export our
presentation into images,
and specifically PNGs.
And then use whatever
method you want
to get those images
onto your phone.
So that might be Photo
Stream, the new iCloud drive,
or you can just email
them to yourself.
And then once you've
got them on your phone,
give them to your friends,
give them to your coworkers,
give them to a variety of
people and just observe them
like looking at the
screens for right now.
See if they can even figure
out what this app does.
See if it reads differently
indoors as opposed
to outdoors - it probably will.
And then once you've just
observed them for a little bit,
you want to ask them three
questions: "Do you know how
to find top-rated toast?"
"What about nearby toast?"
And the feedback that we
got was, "Yeah, ratings,
the star icons make
it really obvious how
to find top-rated toast.
But, nearby toast is
really hard to figure
out if it's not laid
out on a map."
So, that's really useful
information for you to have
in order to make
iterations of your screen.
Second thing you want to ask,
"Is it easy to browse
through toast?"
And it seems that, yeah people
are having a pretty easy time
reading through all the
screens except for of course
that grid view that no one likes
because it's hurting
the retinas.
And then lastly: "How
can we make this better?"
"How can we improve?"
And maybe we just got the
consensus that, you know,
you guys should really go
through the list and the Mappy,
that seems to really
resonate with people.
We should probably
refine the interactions
of those two screens more.
And so, to tell you how
to do that with animation,
I'm actually going to invite
Julian Missig on to the stage.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you Linda.
Now, that we've gathered
some of this feedback,
I'm going to take you
through another spin
around this prototyping cycle.
So, we should take a step
back and learn from some
of the feedback we got.
What's working so far?
Well, we have a variety
of methods
of organizing this information.
We have lists and
galleries, grids, maps.
We don't yet have one best way
to find and discover toast.
We have a couple of them.
Sometimes, people seem to prefer
to look for toast by rating.
And sometimes, they just want
to find the closest toast.
So perhaps, our app
could let people choose.
Sometimes, people could
search for toast by rating,
and sometimes they could
look for it on a map.
So we'd like to make
a prototype to try
to understand how
this could work.
The thing that we
want to make more real
in this prototype is the
connection between a screen
that has top toast and a
screen that has a map on it
because our app is going to
have both of these things in it
at some point in time.
We don't yet need to make
fully interactive screens.
We don't need to be able to
tap on each piece of toast.
We don't need to scroll
through these lists.
We actually don't even need
to have final designs
for these screens.
Because, if we're
doing things correctly,
we're probably actually going
to go back and redraw some
of these screens based
upon what we've learned.
As we make a more
realistic prototype,
we should also make our
context a little bit more real.
So in this case, this is not
the part of the app where we're
in a restaurant taking pictures.
We're still trying to find
the restaurant we will be at.
So, I'm probably walking around
on a busy sidewalk starting
to get really hungry looking
for a piece of toast to eat.
I'm going to be kind of
distracted, not paying a lot
of attention to my phone.
This means that I'm not going
to spend a lot of time trying
to figure out how this app
works and navigate through it.
I'm just looking for
those restaurants.
As I was mentioning before,
the thing that we want
to make more realistic in this
prototype is the connection
or relationship between
two difference screens.
At one point in time, this
app is going to have a screen
that will have Top
Toast, the ratings.
At another point in time,
this app will have a screen
that will have Nearby
Toast or a map.
So this app is going to
be changing over time
between these two screens.
And a change over time
is an animation, right?
Now, there are variety of tools
that you can use
to make animations.
If you're a designer, you
might be familiar with tools
such as Motion, AfterEffects,
or Quartz Composer.
If you're a developer, you
might use tools such as HTML,
CSS animations or Processing.
Either way, we think you
might be able to use tools
such as Hype, iAd
Producer or Keynote.
As Jeff mentioned earlier,
we're going to be building
these animations in Keynote.
We can actually run
Keynote on our iPhone
and see the animations
live there.
We can make modifications
rapidly back on our Mac
and see those changes
reflected on our iPhone.
It's really quick,
and it's a tool
that we use a lot in our team.
So, we're just going
to open up Keynote,
and we will grab the two
slides that we made earlier
and drop them in as the only
two slides in our presentation.
We will go over to the Animate
palette and choose a transition.
Here, we'll just choose
Move In from Bottom to Top.
Let's just see what
that looks like.
So, this slide in from bottom
to top is perhaps like some
of the sheet animations
that iOS has
where it's some temporary
information laid
on top of other information.
Maybe let's move
out horizontally.
Well this looks a lot like
the navigate back animation.
You're going back up the
navigation hierarchy.
Maybe we could flip it over.
Maybe this is some
kind of setting
or information behind
that other screen.
The thing that I'm trying
to get across here is
that any animation you choose
is communicating something
about the relationship
that these screens
have with one another.
Even if it's no animation
at all, if it's just a pop,
that's something that shows
almost no relationship
between the screens.
They're just being
replaced by one another.
But in this case, that's not
really what's going on here.
What we have is two different
views of the same information.
Perhaps those three
restaurants that are
in the map are three
restaurants from that list.
So that's something we want to
communicate as we transition
between these screens.
Now, before we get a little
bit further within Keynote,
I just like to explain something
about two different types
of animation within Keynote.
The first is called
a build animation.
These are animations
that happen on objects
or shapes within a slide.
You can build in a shape,
perform some actions
on it, build it out.
You can use the Build
Order palette to set
up a pretty sophisticated
sequence
of build animations
all within a slide.
But there's another type of
animation called a transition.
And the transition
is an animation
that happens between two slides.
Those were the animations we
were just playing with now.
There's a particular kind
of transition called Magic
Move that's really interesting
for our purposes.
What Magic Move does, is it
tries to identify objects
or shapes that are the
same on the two slides
and it will create an
interpolation of the position,
sizing, opacity and other
properties of those shapes.
So for example, if Magic Move
identifies the three circles
as the same on these two slides,
it might produce an
animation like this.
Now if you're familiar
with animation tools,
you might recognize, we're
starting to use these slides
as if they are key frames
in a larger animation.
That makes it a lot
easier to sequence out
and separate the different
steps of our animation.
So we're going to
go back to Keynote
and choose the Animate palette.
Now that you know about
Keynote's two types
of animation, I'll just
note here real quick,
if you have a shape selected,
the Animate palette will
show you Build animations.
If you have no shape selected,
if it's just the slide,
that's when you'll get
these transition animations
that we're using today.
We're going to change the
transition to Magic Move.
And without changing anything
at all about those two slides
that we've dropped in, let's
see what Magic Move gives us.
So you can see there's
already a lot more interesting
than the transitions we
were playing with earlier.
Because we built these slides in
Keynote and use the same images
on both the lists and the map,
the Magic Move transition
moved those images over,
and we can start to see
that maybe those restaurants are
the same on those two screens.
Maybe that's an interesting
way to do this transition.
But there are a couple of
things that we can make better.
The first thing that I noticed
was that, within our prototype,
we don't really even
have a fake way to get
between these two screens.
So to make it a little bit more
realistic so that we can kind
of imagine how you would
navigate between these screens,
we'll just drop in
a tab bar for now.
And this tab bar, similar
to the things Linda was showing
you earlier, is just a rectangle
from the Shapes tool in Keynote.
The star could be from
the special characters,
the star shape, and
that little map icon,
that's just using the Line tool
to draw a quick little
placeholder.
These don't need
to be perfect just
yet because we don't even know
if this is the direction
we're going to take.
I also noticed how
the list faded out.
We had white for a while,
and then the map faded in.
This is because what Magic Move
is doing is fading out shapes
that won't exist first for the
first half of the animation.
And then after that
midpoint, the second half
of the animation is
fading in new shapes.
So we can get around
that by making sure
that our shapes exist
on both slides.
So I'm going to copy that
map image that I want to fade
in throughout the entire
duration of the animation.
I'm going to copy that
from the second slide,
paste it on that first slide,
move it all the way behind all
the other shapes, and then,
just for fun, I'm going to
make it a little bit larger
than it is on the second slide.
So, what the Magic Move
animation will give us will be
maybe a little bit of
a perspective shift
as the map is shrinking
as it's fading in.
Let's see what that looks like.
It's pretty neat.
But there are a couple
of other things we can do
to make this even better.
Because right now, we're not
writing any code, so we can try
out some- maybe over-the-top
animations and take them
out later, pare it down
to just what it needs.
But for now, it's so
little work to explore a lot
of interesting alternatives
that we should just try
everything we think we
might try.
In this example here,
I am looking
at the title of those
two slides.
The title was another
one where we faded
out that Top Toast title and
then faded in Nearby Toast.
Then it faded through gray.
But I didn't really
like how that looked.
So, I'm going to copy
the Top Toast label
from the first slide.
Paste it on the second slide.
Do vice versa so that both
of those labels exist
on those slides.
I'm going to shift the
one that should be fading
out horizontally
off to one side,
drop its opacity down to zero.
Here I have it a little bit
higher just so you can see it.
But the effect that it will give
is the title will be fading in
and sliding horizontally
at the same time
as the other one is fading out.
I also wanted to do something
about those restaurant
names in the list.
I didn't like that they
just faded out in place.
So I copied those restaurant
names from the first slide,
that list; pasted them on
the second slide, the map;
and I shift them way off
of the side of the screen.
It'll drop their
opacity a little bit.
So look on a slide out.
Now, a little bit
of a pro tip here.
If you stagger them
horizontally a little bit,
the animation speeds will
be a little bit different
for each item.
So they will feel like
distinct items, not like part
of one sheet sliding away,
because these are distinct items
in a list and we'd
like to reinforce that.
Finally, once I've built up both
of these slides to the point
where I'm pretty happy with
them, I will have an animation
from the list to the map.
But to get an animation from
the map back to the list,
all I have to do is duplicate
that first slide, that list,
and place it at the
end as a third slide.
And now, without doing any extra
work, I have an animation back
in the other direction.
It's important to test
out both directions,
and it really didn't
take much to do this.
So let's see what we
have after we've built
up all that animation.
In the back.
And I'll show it to
you a little slower
so you can see some
of the details.
Maybe this isn't as slow as we
would have it in the real app.
We did all of this without
having to write any code.
And you can see how - maybe some
of it is a little over the top.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
Maybe some of it is a
little over the top.
But it's so much easier to
pare down and take away things
when you don't have
to throw away code.
It's just moving shapes around.
That's a really great way to try
out some really sophisticated
animations.
We also really like this
very graphical gallery view
that Linda called out
as pretty cool earlier.
I wanted to see how
it would work
if we have these angled plates
of toast and we zoom in on one
of them just to see
a detail view.
And then back out.
When we tap the Back button.
And I'll show this to you
again a little slower.
[ Applause ]
Thank you
So how did we build
this animation?
Well, it really was
not all that different
from the process I
showed you earlier.
That one piece of toast
that we zoom in on?
That's an angled image
behind all the other shapes.
The other pieces of
toast are similar images
but they're masked
out and on top.
That navigation bar
that slides in?
That's a black rectangle
that we've shifted off
the top of the screen.
So, we shifted it off a little
ways up there so it slides
in a little bit later
in the animation.
And that detail view
of the toast?
That's that same toast
image rotated back straight,
made a bit larger.
The other pieces of toast
are just shifted off the top
and bottom of the screen.
That's really all
there is to it.
It's moving some
images and shapes
around until you
get an animation
that feels pretty good.
So now that we've built
these animations in Keynote,
we're going to launch Keynote
on our iPod touch here.
And either through iCloud
or email, however you prefer
to get them across, actually
open that same presentation
in our hand on the device to
get a sense for how it feels.
We can hand it to someone
and see what they try to do.
Now, here you'll notice that
we're tapping on what seem
like interactive elements.
Those aren't actually
interactive.
It just so happens that you
can tap anywhere on the screen
to advance a sliding Keynote.
So you can kind of pretend that
the interactive elements work.
Of course, if you
tap anywhere else,
it's still going to
advance the slide.
Or you can still get a sense
for where people are trying
to interact with your
screens and animations
and what they expect to happen.
We can do a similar
thing with the tab bar.
And after we show people and
let them express what they think
these animations and
these screens are about,
we can ask them a couple
of questions to try
to get specific feedback.
So we ask if they know
how to find nearby toast.
Well, they were able to find
toast although they didn't
understand our placeholder
icons.
But that's fine because we knew
those icons were placeholders,
and if we decide to go in this
direction, we can refine them.
When we ask if it
was easy to switch
between these two screens,
certainly they were
able to use a tab bar.
They've seen those before.
They could tap at the
bottom and switch screens.
But when we asked, how
could we make this better?
That's where we got some
really interesting feedback.
Someone suggested they
might want to be able
to see restaurant names while
they're looking at the map.
Another person suggested
they'd like to be able
to see the map while they're
looking at the ratings.
Perhaps they want to make
their own calculations
of highest-rated
but closest toast.
So those were both really
interesting bits of feedback,
and I think I'm going
to invite Mark
up to discuss how we can
explore these interactively.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks Julian.
Good morning.
Let's have a look at
what we've learned
from the feedback so far.
What's working?
The transitions between the
map and the list feel great.
Julian showed us how we can
do some really cool animations
without writing a
single line of code.
What's not working?
We still have to switch between
two screens to get to all
of the information about toast.
So what other ideas
does this give us?
Well maybe, we can put
the map and the list
on the screen at the same time.
A list, a map on one screen.
Great. Now we've got all
the information accessible
on one screen.
Problem solved.
But wait a second.
Is this really a good idea?
If you think about it,
the map is only half
of its original size;
so is the list.
We have to pan the map more.
We have to scroll the
list more in order
to access the same
number of information.
To figure out whether
it's a right thing,
we need to really try it out,
and that's why we create
an interactive prototype.
We make another fake app.
And we start off by asking
what needs to be more real?
Finding nearby toast on the
map needs to be more real,
and scanning the list for the
best toast should be more real.
We want to be able to pan
the map and scroll the list.
Now, what can we fake?
What can we do to speed up our
process of making the prototype?
We can fake the map and
the list by making -
using draggable images, but
more to - more about that later.
And where will we use our app?
Let's keep that in our mind
while we are creating our
fake app.
And of course in our case,
it's when we walk the streets
of San Francisco trying to
find the hippest toast in town.
Now making fake apps
is really easy.
We are following one
principal guideline.
That is, to make pictures
move in response to touches.
And one more thing, is to
make pictures move in response
to touches on the device
that you are prototyping for.
Use whatever you want
that can do this.
If you are from a
web background,
you could use HTML,
CSS, a bit of jQuery.
If you're a game developer
who happens to use Unity 3D,
it's another great program
to make some pictures move
around in response to touches.
Or, you could use Swift.
We are super excited
about Swift.
But today, we're going
to use Core Animation
and Xcode with Objective-C.
This is because that's
what we've been using
in our prototyping group so far.
Quick word about writing
code for our prototype:
It's different from
writing code for a real app.
The idea is not to engineer it,
just hack it together
as quick as you can.
It doesn't have to be good
code or reusable code.
Because the idea is that
you make your prototype
to make a better decision
about whether you really want
to spend the time
engineering the real thing.
We generally use three steps to
build an interactive prototype.
First step: Put the
picture on the device.
Once you have a picture on the
device, it's a good indicator
that you have got your
workflow sorted out.
Second step: Break
up the picture.
You want to prepare the picture
so you can apply interaction
to selected areas on the screen.
And third step: Move the
pictures when you touch them.
This is all about
implementing the interaction.
All right.
First step: Get the
picture on the device.
We create our picture
in Keynote.
And the one thing we have
to consider is that we work
to the actual pixel
dimensions of the device.
We export our slides
as a PNG and save it
into the folder structure
of our Xcode project.
Now it's time to write
a little bit of code.
And what you see here
is the setup function
in a classical screen.
Now, another class that you
will see a lot, in our case,
is a class called Layer.
And for those of you who
know about coordination,
it simply just inherits
from UIImageView.
So it also has got all the
functionality of UIView.
All we did is add a little
bit of convenience functions
to make our lives easier
to position a layer
and to load an image
into that layer.
So by default, we have
a Layer called screen.
It stretches across the
whole of the physical screen.
And so to get our
picture onto our screen,
we create another
Layer called picture
and we load our image into it.
That's it.
We press Play in
Xcode and here it is.
Our first Fake App.
Looks pretty real
already doesn't it?
[ Applause ]
Thanks. All right.
Let's get to our second step.
We want to break up the picture.
In our case, we break it up into
a navigation bar into an image
of a list and an image of a map.
Let's start with the list.
I use Keynote again.
And Linda showed how you can
really quickly create a fake
image of a list.
Now this time we want to apply
some interaction to the image.
We want to be able to scroll
the image up and down.
So let's make sure
that it's much longer
than the screen height
of our device.
Next thing, we want to
create a fake image of a map.
Where do I get it from?
We improvise a little bit.
I've got the OS X Maps App.
I open it up.
Make it full screen.
Take a screenshot.
Put it in to Keynote.
And there it is.
We also want to display a
few shared toasts on the map.
So, let's sprinkle a few
icons onto my toast map.
Just kind of in an
artisanal way.
No need to be precise or work
with latitude, longitude values.
Just get it done.
Again, make sure
it's large enough
so we can implement some
direct behavior on it.
And fast forward, here we have
our three discrete images.
Now it's time to
rearrange the images
so they become one screen again.
Same type of code,
create a Layer called Map,
load my map image, position
it a little roughly.
Create another list layer -
or a Layer called List rather.
And this time, I'm going
to position it roughly
down half of the screen height.
And I realize actually, OK,
it already masks my map.
And so does the Navigation
bar at the top.
Cool, we are ready to go.
Let's make some pictures
move when you touch them.
Now I want to talk to you
about the drag image behavior.
What happens is, you hit the
map, a touchdown event happens.
Then you move your finger
and you get a series
of TouchMove events.
And on each TouchMove events,
we are actually moving the
underlying image with it.
And the last event
is a TouchUp event.
I lift off my finger.
Now in order to make that
image move, we essentially go
into each-- well, within
each TouchMove event,
we can deduct the
data translation
between the previous
touch position
and the current touch position,
and that's what we
used to move the image.
It probably becomes
more clear in code.
So, this is a bit of -
this is the code block
that gets called every time
a TouchMove event happens
on our Map layer.
What we do there is we
get our touch object.
From there, we can retrieve
the current touch position
and the previous touch position.
And we calculate our delta
by subtracting the
previous touch position
from the current touch position
and add it to our map position.
And we do the same
thing for the list.
But in this case, we only
apply the translation
to the y-coordinate because
we are just going up and down.
Quick look at how it looks like.
Cool, we can drag the map,
and we can scroll the list.
Now, we have cheated a bit here.
You can see a little
bit of inertia,
and we're also constraining
some movement
with some bit of
a spring behavior.
If you're interested in that,
you can download our Xcode
project after this session.
Let's move on.
I want to divert a little bit
to the part of our prototype
where we can share a toast.
So the idea is that you take
a picture of your toast,
you add a little bit
of information, and
then you post it.
First thing is I
need a camera view.
For now, I'll just hide it at
the lower edge of the screen.
And now, I need a button.
But I realized Linda already
created a lovely Plus button
in my navigation bar.
So what I do is, I
hook up a TouchUp event
onto my Navigation bar.
And so, when you tap
that Plus button,
it will trigger this
line of code
which animates the
camera image back in.
And this is just an example
of how your code doesn't have
to be beautiful, but you can
just hack things together
with what you've
got on the screen.
Here it is.
Tap the Plus button, you
see the camera image.
Now, you saw probably that
there was a live camera preview.
We added that to add a
little bit of realness to it.
But that's where we stop.
When you press or tap
the Shutter button,
we switch to a fake
image of a toast.
And that's what we
continue with.
You add a few information
about your toast and post it.
Now how did we do the
keyboard typing sequence?
Probably already gave it away.
Of course, we just used
a sequence of images.
[ Laughter ]
I didn't bother about using
any dynamic text fields
or a keyboard sliding in.
I did all of these images just
from one slide in Keynote.
And this brings us back actually
to what we're actually doing.
So, we're creating a prototype
by making pictures move
in response to touches.
And we're doing this to help
us make better decisions
about whether we really
want to pursue an idea.
And part of this
decision making process is
to show your prototype
to people.
And if it's an interactive
prototype, it's really important
that you let people
try it out with
as little explanation
as possible.
The first impressions
are really important.
Look at where people are
struggling with the interactions
that you created, and also
look at what delights them.
And ask some questions
like, "Do you know how
to find nearby toast
or top toast?"
So value your feedback
is one which is critical.
"Is the toast on the map
and the list the same?"
This is something we
didn't really think
about when we had our genius
idea of putting the map
and the list onto one screen.
Something we should resolve
before we build the real thing.
"Is it easy to explore toasts?"
is another good question.
And ask for suggestions, "How
can we make this better?"
"I wish I could sort a toast
in a few more different ways."
Yeah, it makes sense.
Not everyone wants to spend $4
or more for a slice of bread.
By this, I want to
reintroduce Jeff
to summarize our
session and conclude it.
Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mark.
[ Applause ]
So, we learned some
very important things
from Mark's interactive
prototype.
Quick recap.
Drew a bunch of pictures,
then we saw how the pictures
worked together using some
animations, and then we built
an interactive prototype.
So, we could see how the
whole thing worked together
in our hand.
Now, a couple of quick
comparisons to hit this home.
This screen on the right
takes a lot of real code.
For our prototype, all we did
was move a picture around in 2D
and move a list up and down.
That was really quick.
This grid view of toast
would've taken a whole bunch
of real code.
For our prototype, we
just made a quick drawing,
which was enough to realize
that this concept sucked.
What have we learned today?
Well, we prototyped with
pictures, and we learned how
to take screenshots, mask
them and rearrange them
so we can make a lot
of different options.
We prototyped with
animations, and we learned how
to animate pictures using
Magic Move and Keynote
so we could see how different
screens work together.
And, we prototyped
with interactions,
and we made pictures move on the
screen in response to touches
so we could see how the
whole thing felt together.
Why do we do this?
Two reasons, hope
that you'll remember.
Number one is to test ideas, and
number two is to get new ideas.
And how do we do it?
This one I really hope
you guys remember.
Make fake apps, show people
and learn from their feedback.
And do that over and over
again until the experience
of your app feels great.
So here's what I want all
of you to go and do now.
If you're a developer
at a company,
I want you to tell
your management
that prototyping
saves time and money
by helping you build
the right things.
If you're a solo developer,
I want you to draw, animate
and hack before you go
and build something.
And if you can't
code it all - again,
thank you for coming
- draw and animate.
You don't need code yet, but the
person next to you might be able
to help you with that part.
Designers, don't just draw
pictures, also make animated
and interactive things to
fully understand your designs.
And our management types,
please, go and make time
for your designers and
engineers to prototype.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
There's a lot of
toasty code on the web.
Go check it out.
Thank you very much everybody.
[ Applause ]