[ Silence ]
>> Hello. Welcome to Session
225, What's New in Core Data.
I am Melissa Turner.
I am one of the engineers
who works on Core Data,
and I'm going to be here
talking to you about sort
of all the new stuff
that we have been doing,
stuff that you're likely
to be interested in.
So, what are we going
to talk about today?
Well, first on the list, first
on the agenda is some new API,
batch updates, and
asynchronous fetching.
I am going to talk about the
implications of those two APIs
for those of you have
implemented your own
incremental stores.
I'm going to talk about the
Core Data concurrency story.
That's the theme
that seems to come
up every year in
our presentations.
I'm going to give an iCloud
update, state of affairs,
and I'm going to talk
about what I'm sure is
on all your minds, Swift.
Batch updates, what are
they, why do you care?
Well, they're a way to mass
update data in the database,
bypassing the Managed
Object Context
and editing the store directly.
It's primarily centrally
intended
for updating attribute values,
and it's really a
performance optimization
because if you think about how
Core Data works, up until now,
if you wanted to edit, say
10,000, 20,000 lines in a field,
you've gone on vacation and left
your phone behind and come back
to discover that your coworkers
have been really, really busy,
and you have a lot
of SCM messages.
If you wanted to mark all of
those read in one fell swoop,
you would have to load
all of the objects
into the Managed Object Context,
edit them, and save them,
and there was a problem
here, which will kind of look
like this, which is on a
memory-constrained device,
loading every single object
into memory doesn't
necessarily work that well.
Jetsam may take offense.
So version 2 was simply that
you would do this in batches.
You'd load a few objects,
edit them, save them.
Load a few more objects,
Well, there's sort of a problem
with this approach as well,
and it kind of looks like this.
It takes time, and
users are likely
to encounter a progress
indicator as they wait
for whatever set of changes
it was that you were making.
So what we've done now is
we've added a new method
to NSManagedObjectContext.
It's executeRequest:error.
It takes an
NSPersistentStoreRequest,
some of you are probably
familiar with that class name.
It's the base class
for NSFetchRequest
and NSSaveChangesRequest.
It's now the new parent class
for NSBatchUpdateRequest
as well, and we'll talk
about that in this slide.
ExecuteRequest returns
a PersistentStoreResult.
That's a new class.
It's sort of an abstract super
class intended to be the parent
of anything that's
returned from this method.
And we've added
NSBatchUpdateResult
as its first child subclass
to return the results
of a BatchUpdateRequest.
BatchUpdateRequest itself should
look pretty familiar to those
of you who are familiar
with FetchRequests.
It allows you to
specify an entity;
it's the entity whose
instances you want changed.
It allows you to specify
the affected stores,
one or more stores containing
data that you want to change.
It allows you to give
a predicate specifying
which specific instances
you're interested in changing.
It's the same kind of predicate
you set on NSFetchRequest,
has all the same
power and flexibility.
You can use subqueries
if you want to.
It allows you to specify
the properties to update.
This is a dictionary.
It specifies the
property as a key
that will be either
the property name
or the NSPropertyDescription
and NSExpression describing
the update as a value.
This can be a constant
value expression,
a function expression operating
on keypads in the object graph,
pretty much anything
that's supported as part
of PropertiesToFetch
is supported here.
Pretty much anything that's
either a valid left-hand side
or a right-hand side in a
fetch predicate is going
to valid here.
It also allows you to
specify a result type,
and the result type
is kind of interesting
because you'll always get
an NSBatchUpdateResult
from executeRequest.
That will indicate whether, you
know, your operation succeeded
or failed-- the existence
of the instance itself.
But it may also have
result properties set on it.
This result property can
be a couple of things.
If you're just interested
in finding out whether
or not anything changed in
the database, you can set it
to return Account, which will
just give you the number of rows
that were actually
changed as a result
of that batch update
operation, or if you want,
you can get a list of the
object IDs of the rows
that were changed
in that operation,
and that's interesting
for one particular reason,
which is that because this
is a batch update operation,
and because we're operating
directly on the store itself
and bypassing the Manage Object
Context, none of the changes
that are made in the
store as a result
of that operation
will be reflected
in the Managed Object Context
until you call refresh
Object on those objects.
So if you're interested in
updating your database en masse,
setting a flag on a
particular column for example,
and then reflecting those
changes in the UI, you're going
to need to get the results or
the Managed Object IDs back,
so you can tell the object,
tell the Managed Object Context
to refresh the objects
with those IDs.
Another implication of the way
this is set up is that, well,
context doesn't know anything
about the changes you're making,
so the validation
rules are not run.
This means it is
now possible for you
to add bad data to
your database.
Please don't do that.
Your customers will
not appreciate it.
But if you do do this,
accidentally fill
in a bad field, what it
means is that your customers,
the next time they load that
object, edit the object, and try
and save, are going to
get a validation failure,
and they may be fairly
confused as to what happened,
since that may not have
changed that actual field.
We do update the optimistic
locking version in the database
for all of the rows
that are changed.
This means now that
even if you're
in a single persistent
store coordinator
or single managed
object context,
single persistent store
coordinator, single instance
of NSPersistentStore, and all
of the changes you make go
through that setup, you can
now create a merge conflict
with yourself as you go
down and edit the database,
and the context doesn't know
anything about those changes.
So you're going to need to
remember to set a merge policy
on your Managed Object Context
if you're using this
API because, well,
otherwise you may confuse
the heck out of your users
as they get save failures.
And now I'm going to do a demo,
show you that this
actually does really work.
OK, what I have here is a
simulacrum of a mail system,
since this is the case where I
most frequently see this kind
of batch update happening.
Got a little application
that displays, you know,
messages coming in,
my manager asking me
if I got my graphics ready
for the presentation.
Managers are so demanding,
and you say no.
This is a few days old.
I can come through and as I edit
the, as I select these messages,
you can see that the Read
indicator is being marked
as well, or the Unread
indicator is being vanished.
I'm going to come down here.
I'm going to look at
this other mailbox,
which contains a whole bunch of
random SCM messages that, well,
nobody cares about, and I forgot
to reset my database,
but oh well.
And I can come up here and
batch mark these as Read,
and we're going to wait, wait,
wait, wait, wait, wait, because,
well, this mailbox
contains 200,000 messages,
and Core Data is going to
have to load every single one
of those, edit them,
and save them again,
and that takes a little while.
As a matter of fact, if
I come down here and look
at my project, I'll find
out it took several seconds.
Then I'm going to come down,
this mailbox contains the
exact same set of messages
that the previous mailbox did.
We can come down here and
mark it as Read, New style.
That took less than a second.
[ Applause ]
So yeah, we think your
developers are going to be kind
of happy with this, and just
as, or your customers are going
to be happy with this, and just
as sort of a frame of reference,
this is the effective command
that I'm running in SQLite
to make that update
happen, and you can see
that we're pretty close to
just the raw SQL update times.
So as I said, changes are
not reflected in the database
when the UI updated in that
application; that was being done
by KVO tracking that I had
updated the root property.
I refreshed the objects
that were being displayed
in the table because
the table view was set
up to do lazy fetching.
All your standard Core Data
make this app perform nice
and responsive tricks.
Validation rules, as
I said, are not run.
This is kind of running
with scissors.
Please don't hurt
yourself or anybody else.
We update the optimistic
locking version in the database.
I'm just repeating all of this
to reinforce it, bring it home.
You can create merge
conflicts on yourself, so,
you know, set a merge policy.
So that's our first new API.
Our second new API is
asynchronous fetching.
What is that?
Why do you care?
Well this is actually
a feature that a lot
of developers have been asking
for, for quite some time.
It allows you to execute a fetch
in a Managed Object Context
that will populate that
Managed Object Context
without actually blocking
access to that context
for the duration of the fetch.
It's cancellable, which means
if your user loses interest
in whatever triggers that
fetch, you can tell us
to stop doing it,
and it provides progress
reporting along the way.
Little brief refresh of how
synchronous fetching works.
You've got a Managed Object
Context, you get a FetchRequest,
execute FetchRequest on
the Managed Object Context,
sends the request
down to the store,
which takes some
time, thinks about it,
returns a response in
the shape of an NSArray,
updates the Managed
Object Context,
and returns the result to you.
Well, asynchronous fetching
is a little bit different.
It returns a future, which
is returned immediately
from executeRequest.
There's no waiting.
The request specifies
a callback block
that will be invoked whenever
the fetch finishes executing.
If the fetch specifies
this is an NSFetchRequest,
we'll go into more
detail in a couple slides,
the context should be updated
as a result of the fetch.
That will happen.
And this means that asynchronous
fetching is only supported
for Managed Object Context
that are using either the
PrivateQueueConcurrencyType
or the
NSMainQueueConcurrencyType
because this is the only way
that we have a separate queue
that we know has sole
access to the state
in the Managed Object Context.
It's not supported for the
ConfinementConcurrencyType.
So this is sort of how
asynchronous fetching works.
Again, you have Managed
Object Context,
only now you have an
NSAsynchronousFetchRequest.
Execute Request on the context,
and the context immediately
creates
and returns an
AsynchronousFetchResult.
At the same time, it takes the
AsynchronousFetchRequest you
gave us and sends it
down to the store.
You can now continue
editing managed objects
in that Managed Object Context.
You can do fetches,
faults, yeah,
all kind of work you're
going to want to do
on your managed objects.
And at some point, the
store will finish executing
that request and send the
results back, update the context
as necessary, and invoke the
callback on the NSFetch that is
on the AsynchronousFetchRequest,
and tell you, hey,
you have data, maybe you
should do something with it.
So NSAsynchronousFetchRequest
is a new subclass
of NSPersistentStoreRequest.
As I said, it's initialized
with a fetch request,
an instance of NSFetchRequest,
and a completion block
should be invoked
when the fetch is finished.
You pass it to
executeRequest:error,
which will return immediately
the NSAsynchronousFetchResult,
or nil if there's
something badly,
badly wrong with
your fetch request.
And NSAsynchronousFetchResults
are also pretty simple classes.
Again, it's a subclass of
NSPersistentStoreResult,
and this will provide results
immediately on a property
on a fetch result, or
there'll be an error on it
after completion if for some
reason the fetch failed.
It's returned immediately
from executeRequest:error or,
you know, nil if
there is an issue.
How do you set one up?
It's pretty simple.
Here, we're just setting up a
fetch request that does fetch
for all instances of my entity.
I could, if I wanted to, add a
predicate, add sort descriptors.
All the usual goodness
is fully supported.
Create an
NSAsynchronousFetchRequest
with that fetch request
and a completion block.
Completion block here
just takes an id,
but it would normally take
an NSAsynchronousFetchResult;
that's just a little bit
too long to put on a slide.
Completion block checks to see
if the result has a
final result, and if so,
it does whatever processing
you want done as a result
of that fetch finishing.
Otherwise, you'll need
to handle the error.
Once you set up the
AsynchronousFetchRequest,
you just tell the context to
performBlock, executeRequest,
AsynchronousFetchRequest,
and away things go.
I said something about
it tracking progress.
How does that work?
It's pretty simple.
We use NSProgress,
standard use of NSProgress.
You create your own before
you call executeRequest.
Core Data will notice if you
have done this and will go off
and create nested
child NS Progresses,
which will report their
progress to the parent.
And this is also how
we allow cancellations.
If you want to cancel the
request, cancel the NSProgress.
How does the setup
for this work?
Well, again it's pretty simple.
Create an instance
of NSProgress,
set the unit count to 1.
Why do we set the unit count
to 1 as opposed to the number
of objects we expect
to get back?
Well, because database
operations are streams,
and it's kind of indefinite
how many objects you're going
to get back.
You may get 100.
You may get 1.
We can't tell up front, so we
only ever say we're finished,
or we're not finished.
Progress become current
with pending unit count 1,
and this is the same
context performBlock we saw
on the last slide, progress
resignCurrent, and you're done.
And at this point, I'm going
to bring my manager, Ben,
up and he's going
to show you how all
of this works in real life.
[ Applause ]
>> Good morning, everyone.
My name is Ben Trumbull, and
I'm the apparently unreasonable
manager of the Core Data team.
So, to give you a
little demonstration
about what we've
been working on,
we have asynchronous fetching
and progress reporting.
We're going to show you a little
simple app here, and in order
to give you something that
you guys can actually witness,
we're actually going to
need a pretty long operation
so you can observe the progress.
So in this case we're
going actually be working
with database that has 10
million rows, and we're going
to be fetching about 5
million of them into memory.
And for the purposes
of the demo,
the app has pre-computed
the total number
of objects in the database.
I don't actually
recommend doing this.
That can actually be kind of
slow in and of itself, but,
as Melissa had mentioned,
database queries
are sort of streams.
You don't really know how many
rows you're going to get back
until you're done, and sometimes
your audience must positively
know exactly what's going on.
So, we've already
preflighted that.
So, I'm going to give you
a quick demonstration here,
and you can see in the status
bar it's counting along.
And we've populated the last
few objects in the array
up here in the table view.
I have not actually just
put 5 million objects
into a table view because
that would be pretty cool.
And as you can see sort
of in the background there
from the fetch request, it
actually goes by pretty quickly.
Core Data will actually
spin up multiple cores
if the fetch request
is long enough,
and I've been logging some of
the KVO updates we see there.
So then, one of the other things
we can do here is cancellation.
It's pretty straightforward.
So we're going to do
the same fetch again,
and as we're going along,
we can decide to cancel it.
And what will end up happening
is the fetch will abort,
and Core Data will return
an NSUserCancelled Error.
And you can see the
status bar update there,
that we've canceled that,
and that's pretty much
all there is to it.
We, basically most of the
work here is going to be
in your KVO observer for doing
something on the NSProgress,
so in this case, I'm dispatching
back to the main thread
to update the status bar
and doing some throttling
of the updates.
So you'll get progress bar
updates probably a little bit
faster than you might
otherwise want
if you're fetching 10 million
rows, and that's what we have.
[ Applause ]
>> So onward.
Incremental stores.
We know some of you
have implemented them.
We've seen them out there on the
web, and that means that some
of you are going to
have a few questions
about how these new
APIs affect you,
if these new APIs affect you.
Well, they kind of do.
If you want to just publish
your store and have it used
by random people, your
implementation of executeRequest
on your incremental store
is going to now need
to handle the new Core
Data request types.
And if you're curious, and
some of you probably are,
saying well, does that mean
I can now implement my own
subclasses of
NSPersistentStoreRequest
and NSPersistentStoreResponse?
And the answer is yes, you
can do that if you want.
We'll talk a little bit about
that in a couple slides.
If you don't want to support
any new request types,
please fail gracefully.
By this, I mean do
what seems reasonable.
Probably you're going to want
to return an error and say,
I don't know how to do that.
This is why the
PersistentStoreRequest allows
you to specify which stores
you actually want to target
with any given
PersistentStoreRequest.
I mean, it doesn't make sense
to send a request to a store
that doesn't know
what to do with it.
Whatever you do, don't
throw in an exception.
That never ends well.
New request types.
You should still be using
with your new request types
NSManagedObjectContext
executeRequest:Error.
This will cause the access
to your Persistent Store
Coordinator to be serialized.
This is kind of important
if you want multiple
things running around,
talking to the same coordinator.
You'll want to do what
we've done with fetching
and batch updates, create
a request/response pair.
The context is going to
return an aggregated result,
which will contain the results
of all of the individual stores
that knew what to do
with your new subclass,
and the default stores
aren't actually going
to recognize custom
request types.
So if you're using a Core Data
stack that has multiple stores,
some of which are
defaults and some
of which is your custom store
types, you're going to want
to target the request being
executed, specifically
at the stores that know
what to do with them.
Why might you want to
add your own subclass
of NSPersistentStoreRequest?
One of the big things that we've
heard repeatedly is that well,
I want to minimize requests,
minimize trips to the store.
This is particularly
relevant in cases
where you've got a
disjoint object graph,
and as part of your app launch,
you want to bring in instances
of lots of different entities.
You don't want to have
call executeFetchRequest
for n different parts
of your subgraphs.
That can get expensive if you've
got 10 chunks of your graph,
you're having to make 10
separate network calls, that a,
takes time, and b, there may
be a lot of overhead involved
in those calls going
across cellular networks
that your users don't want
to waste that bandwidth.
So that's one thing you might
want to consider implementing
or put in a special request
for is a launch time setup.
You may want to do
something with object refresh.
Hi, database.
I've got these 10 objects.
Send me back data for
the objects that need
to be refreshed and
only the objects
that need to be refreshed.
You may want to do status
checks, that kind of thing.
That's just a few of the things
that people have talked
about over the years.
If you're going to do
an AsynchronousRequest,
you want to model it pretty
much on what we've done
with NSAsynchronousFetchRequest.
Return a future immediately,
message that future call back
when the request completes.
And if you're going to
be updating context,
as a result of whatever
you do asynchronously,
remember to use perform
block to update the context
because that will make sure
that only your request updates
are happening in the context
at any one time, will
make sure the [inaudible]
and as an implication, yes this
does mean that if you're going
to be implementing
your own request types,
then your context must be
using either the private queue
concurrency type or the
main queue concurrency type,
which brings us to concurrency.
And at this point, I'm
going to take a little bit
of a winding path to get
to our new stuff and sort
of do a retrospective
of the evolving Core
Data concurrency story
over the years.
Why am I going to do this?
Well, it has changed a number of
times, and well, if you go out
and hit up your favorite
search engine Duck Duck Go
and Yosemite, for example,
or iOS 8 and say, OK,
tell me how to do
Core Data concurrency.
You're going to get a lot
of different responses,
and this is sort of intended to
help you filter through those
and figure out, you know,
what really is the best current
advice, and I'll talk about,
you know, also the
new state of affairs.
So, making sense of what
you see on Stack Overflow.
In the beginning,
NSManagedObjectContext
and NSPersistentStoreCoordinator
implemented the
NSLocking protocol.
And what this meant was
that before a developer started
accessing the Managed Object
Context, and that included
things like accessing properties
on NSManagedObjects created by
that managed object context,
the developer had
to lock the context.
If they wanted to message
PersistentStoreCoordinator,
they needed to manually lock
PersistentStoreCoordinator
before they sent whatever
message they wanted.
And, you know, because
this is a locking protocol,
they are also going to need
to unlock after they're done
with the context or
coordinator, respectively.
And this kind of works like
this, you've got a context.
It has an object in it.
You want to do something.
You lock the context.
You make your edits,
maybe more than one.
You save a revert,
unlock, and things go away.
But this actually has a
couple of problems with it,
the biggest of which
is that it's easy
to forget a lock or unlock.
Well, forget is probably
the wrong word.
Occasionally something
would throw,
you fed Core Data
a bad predicate,
passed [inaudible] through,
the exception went straight up,
and now you're context
is locked.
That's kind of a bad state of
affairs because anything you try
and do now is going
to dead lock.
It's also kind of tricky
doing some UI programming
because a lot of
the binding stuff
for example doesn't really have
a place you can hook in a lock
or unlock as you attempt to
populate your table view,
so that really wasn't a
satisfying answer and we moved
on to Thread Confinement.
This is sort of the first
step of our evolution towards,
you know, more interesting
and robust answer to how
to do concurrency in Core Data.
And Thread Confinement is
basically stepping back
and saying, OK, why are
developers trying to, you know,
edit the same context
and it turns
out there weren't actually a lot
of really great reasons
for that.
So we said, OK, just
don't do that.
A Managed Object Context
should only be edited
from a single thread.
The developer is making sure,
responsible for making sure
that only one thread ever
uses Managed Object Context,
and at this point, a lot
of us learned about things
like thread local variables
because that was the easiest way
to associate a context
with a thread and make sure
that no other context
ever had access to it.
And in this model, the
developer still had
to lock the Coordinator
before they used it
and this kind of
looked like this.
You had a thread.
That thread had a context.
That context had objects.
You could edit the context
as much as you want, and no,
you don't have to lock it.
And sort of because people do
want to do things in parallel,
if you wanted to actually
make changes to, you know,
other objects, you would
set up a separate thread
that had its own context, and
if you wanted to pass data back
and forth between these, you'd
generally do it by, well,
passing managed object
IDs back and forth
and having the context
refresh data from the store.
This was kind of awkward.
It's still a little bit
difficult to get right.
I mean, it involved, you know,
making sure that you didn't
accidentally message a thread
or a context from another thread
or fire a fault on
another thread.
So we wanted to make working
with the context easier,
and about this time
another group
at Apple was inventing a really
cool technology or technology we
at least thought was really
cool, you're probably familiar
with it, called GCD or
[inaudible] dispatch
if you're working
at the [inaudible].
And we looked at
this, and we said,
you guys are solving this
huge problem that we have.
We like you.
And in this case, the
context encapsulates the
threading model.
Basically each context
got its very own queue
and that queue was
the only thing
that would ever access
the internal state
of that managed object context.
This is called the actor
[phonetic] pattern for those
of who are familiar
with patterns.
There were a few
concurrency types we set
up Private Queue
Concurrency Type,
which says this context
has its own private queue
and everything should
happen there.
A Main Thread Concurrency
Type, which was used
for operating primarily from the
UI because AppKit, as well know,
likes to run in the main thread.
This basically said that as long
as whatever is happening is
happening on the main thread,
you can message the
Managed Object Context
as much as you want.
And we also had the Concurrency
Thread Confinement Type,
well that said, well, I've
got Legacy code and I want
to continue using that
Legacy code in the same way
that I have had it working
for however many releases.
I don't want to have to
rewrite my application.
Under this model, when
you wanted to do something
with Managed Object Context,
you would pass it a block,
tell it to performBlock
or performBlockAndWait,
and in this model you
also no longer had
to lock the coordinator
before use.
I forgot I had that slide.
That's just the concurrency
types I talked about, main,
private, and confinement.
And this kind of inverts
the previous order.
We go from having a thread that
has a Managed Object Context
to a Managed Object
Context that has a queue
and any thread can create a work
block and dispatch that block
over the queue for processing
or the context for processing.
The context will do
whatever it wants to,
update all of its internal
state, and then return
to the calling thread.
This actually made things a
lot neater, a lot cleaner.
It was much easier to
talk to the context
and get it doing things right.
And at this point, we had
a debugging mechanism.
It was default.
If you launched your application
with com.apple.CoreData
.ConcurrencyDebug 1,
we would be very, very picky
about how you message threads,
and we would very, very
vocally let you know
if you had done something wrong.
But this required
downloading a debugged version
of the framework from ADC.
It was-- I think
it's WWDR these days.
It had one problem, which
is that it often got stale
because it's hard to
push debug frameworks
through that mechanism at the
same time we push OS updates,
and it wasn't available
on iOS because, you know,
iOS didn't allow you to install
new versions of frameworks.
So that brings us to today.
Well, the story at the context
level is exactly the same.
Context is still an actor.
It still has a queue.
It still has concurrency types.
It still has the same
concurrency types.
You still message it
using performBlock
and performBlockAndWait.
We've also added
the performBlock,
performBlockAndWait API to
NSPersistentStoreCoordinator.
This is mostly relevant
to those of you
who are subclassing
NSPersistentStoreCoordinator.
You should now be
using these methods,
which is what our
existing methods do.
They all wrap call
through to performBlock,
performBlockandWait.
PersistentStoreCoordinator,
though,
because it doesn't actually
need to be messaged directly
by AppKit always uses
its own private queue.
The debugging default is
now available everywhere.
As of Yosemite,
[ Applause ]
As of Yosemite and iOS
8, if you launch your app
with com.apple .CoreData
ConcurrencyDebug 1,
we will be very, very picky
about how you do concurrency,
and we will let you know if
you have done something wrong.
And this is available
on iOS as well.
No special debug version
of the framework necessary.
Looking ahead, and this
isn't a sort of predictions,
not promises, because
making promises is way
above my pay grade.
NSThreadConfinement is
pretty much obsolete.
That includes the
confinement concurrency type.
We saw earlier with the
asynchronous fetching
that it just can't be supported
in a confinement concurrency
model, so as we move forward,
it's likely there will
be more kinds of changes
that also only work for contexts
that are using either
the private queue
or main queue concurrency types.
As a bonus API, make that
go down a little bit easier
because debugging is
hard enough already,
we've added a name property
to the NSManagedObjectContext
and PersistentStoreCoordinator.
It only applies if your actor
is using the Private Queue
Concurrency Type, but if you
do set a name on your context
or your coordinator, this will
be displayed in LLDB and Xcode
when you're debugging,
so you'll be able to see
which queues are
actually associated
with which managed object
context in your application.
[ Applause ]
On to iCloud, this
is actually going
to be a fairly short session
because most of what you need
to know is encapsulated
on this slide.
Internally, I'm sure you--
at the conference so far,
I'm sure you've heard
some buzz about,
you know, changes to iCloud.
We are transitioning
to new infrastructure.
You should see some
reliability improvements
and some performance
improvements for those of you
who are using the Core
Data with iCloud stuff,
but all of the changes should
be completely transparent
to developers.
If you're using the
patterns that Nick
and Ben showed you last year
in their presentation,
nothing has changed.
Your application
completely, completely,
everything will migrate
over just transparently.
Everything should work.
It should just be more
reliable and faster.
[ Applause ]
And I do want to talk about
CloudKit since that sort
of a new and related technology
that might be of some interest
to you but in order to
do that, I sort of want
to assess the full scope of
the iCloud-related technologies
at Apple and sort of give
you some context to decide
if it really makes sense
for your application.
The basic iCloud technology
is the Key Value Store.
This allows you to store
small amounts of data
on an application-by-application
basis.
It's great for things like
preferences or, you know,
view state, that kind of thing.
It's asynchronously
kept up to date
and it has some data limit
constraints, only allows you
to store a small amount of data.
There's iCloud documents.
This is probably
familiar to those of you
who implement document-based
applications.
It's fairly simple API,
basically replace all
of whatever is in the cloud with
whatever I have just created.
Mac OS X is greedy and
will automatically download
everything that's in the cloud,
so you've got a full offline
cache of all of your documents.
This is good for
unstructured data
and is tied to the file system.
This is good if you want to
replace everything on all
of your devices with whatever
the latest greatest state
from one device is.
Now we come to iCloud Core Data.
This is good for when you want
to merge data that is created
across multiple devices,
instead of replacing it.
If you add a contact on machine
1, you want that to be added
to your global cloud data store.
You don't want it to replace
your global cloud data store.
It's used to keep private data,
user data, structured data
in sync across multiple devices
and it's replicated between all
of your devices, but
it is single-user data,
which brings us to CloudKit.
CloudKit is the new API
in Yosemite and iOS 8.
It's a client server model,
which means that it
has no local store.
If you're going to be using it,
your users are going to need
to be connected to the
network at all times.
It allows for predicate-based
queries, not the full power
that Core Data gives you,
but a really substantial
and pretty much everything
you're reasonably going
to want to do.
And it's application-centered
data.
What does that mean?
Well, the data is public
and shared by all users
of your application or can be.
If you want to implement
a, I don't know,
restaurant reviewing
application,
where all of your users can
see what everybody else thought
about a given restaurant,
this is probably the
technology you want to look at.
It's good for structured
and bulk data
and it allows for
a large data set.
The data set will scale
proportionately with the number
of users of your application.
It uses iCloud accounts and has
client-directed data transfer,
and I don't know what
either of those means.
You should probably go watch
the video of their session.
Somebody gave me these
slides and asked me please
to talk to you guys about it.
So that's the iCloud
alternatives
that you have on our platform.
Some of you may want to actually
go look at CloudKit, and,
you know, do interesting
things with it, which brings us
to the session I'm sure
all of you have wondered
about since Monday's
announcement, which is Swift.
You have questions, and I'm
here to give you answers.
This is a fragment from an
email that came through one
of my mailboxes sometime
over the last several months.
It basically says-- well,
the rest of the message
basically said,
Swift is intended as a
language for Cocoa programmers.
Cocoa is nice and
powerful and dynamic.
Core Data is a very dynamic and
very powerful piece of Cocoa.
Well, Swift must support
Core Data, period.
So it does.
You get the full power
of Core Data in Swift.
You can create managed
object subclasses in Swift.
I'll show you how to do
that on the next slide,
and if it makes sense for
your application, you can mix
and match between Core
Data and SWF files.
It's all the same story as
they've been telling you in all
of the other Swift
sessions and Swift labs.
How do you create a
managed object subclass?
Well, they're pretty much
like Objective-C, only instead
of using @dynamic, you'll
be using @NSManaged.
This is a Core Data
specific property
that tells the Swift compiler
that the Core Data runtime
is going to be responsible
for managing the data storage
and accessors for the properties
that you specified is at manage.
Unfortunately, you're not
going to be able to, you know,
create your own dynamic
mechanisms.
Talk to the Swift
guys about that.
The one change other than this
that you'll need to remember
that might trip a few of
you up is that you now need
to add the module
name in the data model
when you specify the class
that your entity is going
to be using, and
that's just done up here
in the data modeling tool, where
you used to specify the class,
now you need to specify
the fully qualified class,
namespace.classname.
But that's really
the only change.
This is what an Objective-C
subclass looks like.
You should mostly be
familiar with this
if you're in this session.
Import Core Data,
declare your interface,
declare the properties,
you're done.
But you've also got
a separate file
and this file is actually
pretty basic looking.
Import your header file because,
well, that's how C works.
Declare your implementation,
declare that Core
Data is responsible
for these properties,
and you're done.
Swift collapses both of
these into a single file
that looks a lot like this.
Small, sleek, contains all
of the same information
that you saw in the previous
two files in one place without,
you know, duplication of lines.
Some things to remember about
Swift is that it uses types.
It's very, very firm
in the beliefs
that static typing is a
good and important thing.
Core Data has not, does not
use types, but if you want
to use types, and you probably
will in your Swift code,
you probably want to be creating
your own NSManagedObject
subclasses, custom
subclasses, so you can use
that subclass name
as a type name.
Otherwise, you're going to
have to use NSManagedObject
because entity names
are not going
to suffice as type specifiers.
It's going to kind
of look like this,
should be what you pretty much
expect having had a chance
to look at Swift.
And now I'm going to do a demo,
talk about how things
work in Swift.
So here we have a Swift
application or a project
that builds an application
that looks awfully
like the last thing I demoed.
It's got an app delegate.
It's got all of your standard
code, sets up IB outlets
for your controllers, adds key
value observers, so you notice
when things have changed,
you can refresh contents
of controllers.
It's got batch update
code to run batch updates.
All the same stuff you'd expect.
It's got a utilities class,
and I've actually split my
Core Data stack setup off
into utilities and
that's due to the way
that Swift handles
variable initialization,
either initialize
something to a simple type
or you set up computer property.
But if you set up
computer property,
that gets reevaluated every time
somebody accesses the property,
which is not what you want
when you're setting
up a Core Data stack.
You only want to access it once.
I was playing around
as I built this,
so you can see a lazy
property, deferring binding
to managed object models data
until you actually
try and access it.
Computer property for Persistent
Store Coordinator sets
up my stack.
Computer properties
can deal with nil.
@lazy is not happy with nil,
so there's another
minor gotcha there.
Here, we've got our
function that sets up
and returns our managed
object context.
It looks pretty familiar to
those of you who are familiar
with Core Data, all of the
[inaudible] calls are the same.
Our mailbox, here we've
got our message instance,
which has a KVO observer setup,
set it up in the init method.
Whenever the observer
gets triggered,
we'll update our read badge.
Messages controller does the
same thing the previous messages
controller did.
I'm going to build and run.
Whew. It's a Swift
application using Core Data.
It's actually a little
bit faster
than the Objective-C version.
[ Applause ]
So, yeah, and if I come up here,
Mark as Read, whew, it's read.
So I talked about batch updates.
We talked about asynchronous
fetching and incremental stores
and what that means for you,
talked about our
concurrency changes
and our concurrency story over
the years, gave you a sense of,
you know, where we were, where
we wanted to be, iCloud update,
and I talked about Swift.
I think I've covered everything.
This is where you get
to see Anthony the alligator
telling you to file bugs.
We can't fix what
we don't know about.
We don't guarantee we'll fix
what we do know about, but,
you know, we can't fix
what we don't know about.
File a bug report.
It helps if you give us steps
to reproduce, really helps
if you give us an app.
If you give us an app that
reproduces your problem, well,
we fix those first because,
you know, we know what to fix.
If you want feature requests,
enhancement requests,
performance issues,
documentation stuff,
all goes through Bug Reporter.
For more information, you
can talk to Dave DeLong.
He's our technology
evangelist, delong@apple.com,
or you can send whatever
your feedback is
to cocoa-feedback@apple.com.
We have a lot of documentation
online at developer website.
There's a programming guide,
some examples, tutorials,
code fragments, that
kind of thing,
and there's always the
Apple developer forums.
Related sessions,
I mentioned this.
There was a CloudKit session,
Introducing CloudKit,
Tuesday at 3:15.
If you're interested in that,
you probably want
to watch the video.
There's also, although it is
not appearing on this slide,
was a What's New in
Cocoa session on Tuesday.
You may be interested in
watching that as well,
and welcome and thanks
for coming.
[ Applause ]