>> Good morning.
[ Cheering and Applause ]
Welcome to "The New
iTunes Connect."
I'm Dave Van Tassell,
Engineering Manager
here at iTunes Connect.
We have a lot of great things
to talk to you about today.
To do so, I'm going
to need the clicker
over on this desk right here.
It all starts with a new design.
We want to take you on a
little bit of a walkthrough,
some of the new features
that we've added,
some of the new flows.
Second thing is app previews.
It's a great chance for you to
upload a video 15 to 30 seconds,
dynamic view of what
makes your app magical.
App bundles - you can bundle
up to 10 apps together
with an easy set-up
flow in iTunes Connect.
App analytics - we're
very excited about this.
This is the best end to end
view of your app with data
that only Apple can provide.
[ Applause ]
And last, TestFlight
beta testing.
[ Applause ]
We're very excited about this.
Give you a little
more insight and depth
into what we have planned
for TestFlight beta testing.
So we start with the Home page
of iTunes Connect,
an all new design.
We have the same sections as
today, with great new icons.
If you have any news or
announcements for you,
like perhaps you haven't
signed the latest contract
that released, that's going
to go right there on the top.
But we came here to work
today, so let's jump
into My Apps and
see what we have.
The first thing you're going
to notice is it's
wall to wall apps.
We're trying to give it
as much space as we can
for all these apps, fit
more apps onto the page,
at the same time giving each app
a little more space to breathe,
the full name of the app, the
complete iTunes Connect status.
Easier to tell the
difference between waiting
for review and in review.
Also we've added a little badge
there to show the difference
between iOS and Mac apps.
If you came to the My Apps page
to check on, perhaps the status
of an app, to see if the "Hair
Salon" app has been approved
and is ready to go, there at
the top we have an iSearch bar,
type in "hair salon," and
all the hair salon apps float
to the top.
I see it's all green;
green is good.
My app's been approved,
it's ready for sale,
I'm off to go check
and see how it's doing.
We've also added some filtering.
You can see there in the
top right-hand corner,
the search by status.
You can filter - and see I
have 24 different statuses,
23 are ready for sale.
I have one prepared for upload.
If I want to click on
one of these statuses,
then I'll filter away
all the other apps
and show just the apps with
this iTunes Connect status.
Some of you like the list view;
we've improved that as well.
More apps on one page, the
same search and filtering
that we've provided on
the icon view also exists
on this list view.
You can sort by the different
column names, change that up.
And what's great is if you leave
the My Apps page and come back,
or if you sign out iTunes
Connect, when you come back
to My Apps we'll take you
right back to the list view.
We're going to go back into the
icon view and jump into an app.
What we've done here is
combine the app pages
and the version pages into one,
because at the top
we have the app icon,
and going across we have
different tabs, we have pricing,
we have In-App Purchases,
manage your Game Center.
We take you by default to the
version tab and to the ready
for sale version of My App.
I can see the screenshots
right there in front of me
and other metadata as it goes.
What we want to do is
create a new version.
So we click on the upper
right-hand corner there,
it's the new version button,
and we're provided with a window
to enter in our version number.
You'll notice there's no "what's
new" text on this window.
This information is still
required, but we understand
that you don't always have
all the marketing data ready
when you want to take actions
like create a new version.
And in fact, we've added this
to the new app flow as well.
When you create a new app,
all you need is a name,
a bundle ID and a SKU.
[ Applause ]
This is the new iTunes
Connect, right?
You can come back when you're
ready to do those descriptions,
those screenshots
and what have you.
All right, so we're going
to create this new version.
It'll create a new sub-tab
there with the 1.0.2.
It's copied over the screenshots
from the previous
version, like normal.
We can see that the What's New
in this version text
hasn't been filled in.
I can fill it in
now, either way.
I keep scrolling down,
and I see the rest
of my version information.
I can change that right
now, easy to edit.
I can save and come back later.
But we came here today to
create the iPad version
of this app, make it universal.
So I'm going to click on the
iPad tab, and what I need
for an iPad is new screenshots,
that's really the only metadata
difference iPhones and iPads.
And screenshots are great:
five snapshots of what's going
on in my app, right now.
But we also want to give
a more dynamic experience.
We want to upload
an app preview.
Giving people more insight:
What is it about my
app that's magical
that makes people
want to click on it?
So we're going to go ahead
and upload this app
preview here as well.
Now we could do screenshot
1, then upload screenshot 2,
and then upload screenshot
3, and then upload the video,
but this is the new iTunes
Connect, and we're just going
to drag and drop all
six files at once.
[ Applause and Cheering ]
And in they come.
You can see the app
preview's going to be first,
followed by the screenshots.
And what we've done on the app
preview is selected a default
poster frame.
The poster frame is the
image that people will see
on the App Store before they
click Play on your video.
If you don't like this poster
frame, it's easy to change,
the new iTunes Connect.
We hover over the
poster frame image,
we click edit poster frame,
and up pops the video itself
and the poster frame
that we've selected.
We can press Play on the
video, find that spot
that we want, we
can drag and drop.
Anytime we find a frame that we
like we click set poster
frame, we're off to go.
I know in my case, the frame
that I would like to use is
at the end of my video, so I'm
just going to scrub on through,
find this one that I
like, this is great.
I click Set as Poster Frame,
and that's all there is to it.
I'm done. We can clap.
This is fun.
[ Applause ]
Now I have my new poster
frame with my app preview,
my screenshots, any other
changes that I want to make,
and click Save, and
I'm good to go.
This is what it looks like in
the App Store, the same idea.
We have the poster
frame video right here,
followed by all the screenshots.
We've talked a lot
about the app preview.
Let's take a look and
see what one looks like.
[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
And that's it.
These are really great.
I'm excited to see
what you come up with,
further enticing people
to download your app.
A few things to mention.
Remember an app preview
is a UI walkthrough.
They want to see your app.
What is it about your
app that's great?
They don't want to be sold
to it; it's not an ad.
You can capture this
video straight
from iOS 8 onto OS X Yosemite.
App previews are up to
30 seconds in length,
and we accept both H.264
and ProRes content.
And that's app previews.
[ Applause ]
Now we move on to App Bundles.
App Bundles is a great
feature to bundle together apps
of the same kind, giving
your customers and people
on the App Store just
one choice instead
of many on what to download.
The first step if you want to
have an app bundle is, well,
what apps do I put in my bundle?
So, you have all the apps
in your head whether it's iTunes
Connect, and you're trying
to think about it, you got
to choose some of them.
You can have up to 10.
In this case I'm going
to pick four of them
and create an app bundle.
And this is great.
It offers more value for
the people on the App Store.
It's a single install to get
all of your great apps at once.
And we've included in
this Complete my Bundle.
It's the same feature we
give for music and for TV,
where if somebody's already
purchased one or more
of the apps in your bundle, then
they'll get a discounted price
to purchase the rest of your
bundle to encourage them
to get all of your apps.
[ Applause ]
So that was step one, selecting
what apps go in my bundle.
The next thing we're going
to want is the metadata
to show in the iTunes store.
We're going to need
a bundle name,
we're going to need
a description.
It's probably going to need
screenshots, app preview,
got to select categories,
rating, marketing URLs,
privacy URLs, all
these different pieces.
Because we want to make this
as simple as possible for you,
and we realize that we have a
lot of this information already.
So it starts with information
that is specific to the bundle.
Each bundle will
need its own name;
it'll need a description
about the bundle.
Obviously it has its own
price, has its own SKU
and a marketing URL so you can
market this bundle on its own.
And then we have
this information
that comes from the first app.
It was that key app, the
first app for this bundle.
So the first screenshot
will come from that app,
the first app preview
that you see
on the App Store will
come from that app.
The categories of
your bundle will match
that of the first app, and the
App Store contact information,
App review information,
all of that will be pulled
from the first app as well,
as well as the privacy URL.
The rest of the information from
your bundle will come from all
of the apps in the bundle.
If you have three apps that are
4 plus, and one app is 12 plus,
your bundle will
be rated 12 plus.
If you want your bundle to be
made for kids, all of the apps
in the bundle must
be made for kids.
The rest of the screenshots
and app previews will come
from the other apps in your
bundle - and equal share
for every app in your bundle.
And for keywords we'll take
all of the keywords from all
of the apps in the
bundle and apply those.
You don't have to
re-enter any new keywords.
Let's take a look and see how
we do this in iTunes Connect.
We come back to the
My Apps page.
We click New App Bundle.
The first thing we want to enter
as our new app bundle
name, "Toca Toy Box."
We start selecting the apps.
At this point I realize, OK,
this first app is
important, it's key.
So, I know which four I
want in my app bundle,
but I would like to make
this one that primary app.
Once I've selected my apps,
I can now see I have my
screenshots have already been
populated for me
from that first app.
I can fill in the app bundle
description, the marketing URL.
Privacy policy URL
has already been done.
Let's scroll down further.
I need to select a price tier.
It needs to be a discounted
price tier, less, one tier less
than the sum of all the apps in
the bundle - it is a discount -
as well as give it a SKU.
Then the rest of the information
has already been filled in:
categories, the rating.
I'm good to go, at
this point I'm done.
I've created my app bundle,
I'm ready to submit it.
One thing to remember
with app bundles is
that once they've been submitted
to the App Store you
can't change the apps
in a bundle; they're immutable.
If you want to make a
bundle with now five apps
or six apps instead
of this four,
then just create a
new bundle and submit
that to the App Store.
Here's what it looks
like on the App Store.
You can see your app icon.
You can see all the
apps in the bundle.
The app preview and
screenshots come down below.
You can have up to 10 paid
apps in an app bundle.
You have to give it
that discounted price.
The first preview and screenshot
come from that first app.
We're going to link
to all the other apps
in your bundle right
there on the App Store.
And with Complete My Bundle,
people who have already
purchased one or more
of those apps will
get discounted price
to purchase the rest
of your bundle
and get the whole package.
And that's App Bundles.
With that, I'd like to turn
the time over to Trystan
to talk about App Analytics.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Dave.
My name is Trystan Kosmynka,
Engineering Manager
working on App Analytics.
Really excited today to show
you what we've been up to.
Before we get into it,
let's talk about what it
takes to build a great app.
We're all here this week
to learn tips and tricks
on building a great app.
We know that it all
starts with a great idea.
Every app that's
in the store today
that achieves great success
starts with a great idea,
and how do you capture that and
present that to your customers?
You do that with
thoughtful design,
pixel-perfect design,
intuitive design.
You focus on really
complete flows
that make sense to
your customers.
We write bug-free code, we
all here write bug-free code.
Worked on my device.
We test, and we test,
and we test some more.
So, we have automated unit
tests, automated UI tests.
We're going to talk more
about our beta testing
service as well.
This is a really
important part of writing
and creating a great app.
Finally, we submit to the store.
These are all pieces,
developer responsibility
that we're familiar with today,
and Apple does a fantastic job
supporting you throughout this
process, with great tools,
with Xcode, more great tools
and services we're
talking about today.
But we know that our job
is not done as developers.
Once we submit to the store,
there's this whole new
set of responsibilities.
We're not all done.
And this is after launch.
And this is what App
Analytics is all about.
These new responsibilities
can influence this chart.
Hopefully, if you have
apps in the store,
this chart is familiar to you.
You have your downloads
over time, it's increasing,
and you see points of
acceleration over time as well.
Let's talk about what it
takes to influence that,
and why App Analytics
is really important.
So first, our App
Store presence.
We can see on this chart now I
have that orange dot and I see
that App Store presence really
can influence my downloads.
App Store presence is your name,
your description, your keywords.
We have these App Bundles now.
We also have our
App Store previews.
These are great ways to get
your app to have more downloads,
more customers, more
people using your app.
Marketing.
Once you have a great app
you want to get the word out.
As developers, we don't
just submit to the store,
we submit it to our
social networks,
we send it to our
friends and our family.
We create a home page,
potentially some newsletters.
Marketing's a really
important piece.
New updates.
When you're building an
application and submit it
to the store your
customers crave new content.
New levels, new ways to engage
existing customers and new ways
to attract more customers.
Your app needs to stay fresh and
unique, and to do that you go
through this constant
release and build cycle.
Next is advertising.
Advertising and marketing
are often used
in the same vocabulary,
but advertising's a
little bit different.
As a developer you may choose
to pay for advertising,
and that's a big decision.
You want to know if it was worth
the advertising investment,
if you got a nice
return on that.
App Analytics is there to help
you inform those decisions.
All of these dots, all these
lines, you want to monitor,
measure and see how
they're changing over time,
and App Analytics is there
to provide those answers.
And that is why we
use App Analytics.
Because App Analytics
provides answers.
It helps you answer questions
like, "How's my app doing?
Are people returning to my app?"
Are people converting on
your In-App Purchases?
App Analytics helps you make
good advertising decisions.
And this is one I'm
really excited about.
App Analytics helps you
reveal missed opportunities.
With App Analytics you can see
that your App Store presence
is great in the United States,
and a lot of customers
are looking at your app
in the United States
and actually turning
into real customers as
opposed to potential customers.
The same may not be
the case in Germany.
With App Analytics we can see
that the potential customers
in Germany can become
actual customers if we focus
on our German App Store
presence, localization,
really understanding the German
culture and understanding
that marketing to Germany may be
a completely different animal,
and we can do that with
our App Store presence,
and App Analytics can
point out those areas.
Finally, after we launch, it's
all about building a better app,
and App Analytics is there
to tell us and point us
in the right direction
to do that.
That is why App Analytics
is important.
So with that, how do we
look at this at Apple?
How are we looking at App
Analytics as a product
in the service for
app developers?
We're focusing on this concept
of the customer lifecycle,
and this involves
acquisition to engagement.
We want you as developers
to be covered
from the point your
app hits the store
to the point your
customers are using the app.
And let's look at that from
the customer's perspective.
And we start with
our first measure.
Here is your App
Store product page.
We have "Trip Guider," an app we
made up for this presentation.
The first thing we see
is App Store views.
We're really excited that for
the first time Apple's providing
you developers with a view
of your App Store Views.
All - thank you.
[ Applause ]
This is data only
Apple can provide.
It comes straight from the
App Store to you developers.
Next we have App
units and sales.
This data here gets tracked any
time a potential customer turns
into an actual customer
and touches your Buy button
inside your product page.
You have this data today
in Sales and Trends
if you're familiar with iTunes
Connect, but this is different.
We're tying this data
into a complete picture
with App Store views.
For the first time you can
see your App Store views,
and how that drops
for App units.
Next, we've combined App
Store data, Billings data,
and now we have Device data.
We have Installs.
A customer purchases
your application
but they may install
it on multiple devices,
and this is why Installs and App
units are two different metrics.
Once your customer installs the
application and starts engaging,
we have a new world
with device measures.
We have Sessions,
Active devices.
We have Retention.
We have this concept
of Stickiness as well.
Stickiness is great:
It's a single measure
that you can track over time to
insure that you're both growing
and retaining customers.
If there's one measure you want
to look at, it's stickiness.
Finally, if your application
has In-App Purchases,
we track that as well.
For the first time you can see
the entire customer lifecycle
from the point the user
became a real customer
to when they're converting
on Internet purchases.
This concept of average sales,
if you're using any
business intelligence today,
you may be looking at
average revenue per user.
This is average sales.
We provide that.
This in combination
with stickiness can tell
you a really powerful story
of how your app's doing and how
your customers are performing.
So, that's the customer's
view of this.
Let's look at your
view, the developer.
We have our App Store views,
we have our App Units,
Active Devices, Retention,
In-App Purchases.
This funnel starts to
drop, and that makes sense
because not every
potential customer becomes an
actual customer.
What does this look like when
we start to ask more questions?
How does this look by platform?
We start to filter this data
by iPhone, iPad, iPod Touch.
We can see the composition of
our App Store views across all
of the Apple platforms.
We can also answer that App
Store presence question,
"Should I be localizing
for Germany?"
Here, I can see my
apps reviews in Europe.
It's quite high, but my app
units in Europe, a little lower,
and this makes sense as well,
and there's an opportunity
there.
This is where analytics can help
you reveal missed opportunities.
If we just localize our app,
potentially we can
get more app units
and that will help us get more
active devices, more retention,
more In-App Purchases.
Maybe it's that simple,
and we don't have
to release another
version of our app
to get more downloads
in Germany.
So this is great.
Let's talk about what
it actually looks like
and show you guys what
we've been working on.
I think that's why we're here.
App Analytics shows up as a
new feature inside the new
iTunes Connect.
It's here beside My Apps.
The first view that we see
when we click inside
Analytics is our App List.
This is the older view of
your entire mobile business.
Here, I can see my "Trip
Guider" app at the top.
I can see all of my
other apps in my suite.
I can see filters.
I can see the ability to
change my time, my date.
Let's look at these metrics.
So, here is the key
vitals for an application.
Going from the left
to the right,
I see that lifecycle again.
It's consistent.
Start with My App Store
views and then My App Units.
I see my Sessions and my Sales.
See if they're rising,
falling in this period.
I hover over these, I get
tool tips telling me what the
previous period was as well.
I can select one.
Selecting one of these brings us
into the heart of this product
which is our Metrics Page.
The first thing you'll
notice is that great trend.
We can see how we're
doing over time
and this situation we're
looking at, data from May.
I can see over May that my
application is increasing
in App Store views,
which is awesome.
I can also change
my interval below.
I can change this from
Days to Weeks to Months.
Let's talk about
those measures again.
Here, I have those
lifecycle metrics.
I have my Sales, my Store Data.
I have my Engagement
Data, my Device Data.
I can select any of these
and change the chart.
Let's look at breaking this
down by a particular platform.
I select View By and now I can
see how this actually looks
across all of the Apple devices.
I can see my iPhone, my iPad,
my iPod touch, and it looks
like the trend is about
the same on all of them.
They're all performing
equally in this case.
It's great.
But a customer can't
have an iPhone
and an iPad at the same time.
They're not the same device.
They're two different devices.
So, we look at that
as a stacked area.
I go to Chart Type, I select
Stacked Area, like that.
I can now see the composition
of iPhone, iPod, iPod touch,
and the sum of these
will equal 100 percent
of whatever metric
I'm looking at.
There's different chart types
for different scenarios,
and looking at App Store Views,
here - Area looks the best.
We'll choose the
sensible default based
on the measure you're
looking at.
Let's swap to another measure.
Look at App Store Units.
Here, there's no issues here.
Analytics is providing an
answer that my conversions
from page views to App Units
hasn't dropped drastically.
It's a little bit lower,
but the trend is the same,
and on both devices
it's the same.
So, not a lot of opportunity
to improve my iPad
App Store presence
because it's performing
the same as my iPhone.
Maybe I improve them
all together.
Let's go to another
measure In-App Purchases,
and this is where our team
decided that on May 15th,
we would lower the price
of In-App Purchases,
and as a result, we got
a lot more app purchases
that occurred, and we can
see that with App Analytics.
We can see the spike there -
we can see that across
all platforms,
it performed much better
as a result of our change.
We also had intuition
that changing our In-App
Purchases would help give more
customers more content,
and that would result
in more engagement,
more active devices.
So with that, we select
In-App Purchases, Compare To,
select Active Devices, and now
we see our Active Devices went
up as did our In-App Purchases.
I can see these layer on top
of each other telling
me the story that, "Yes,
our changes to In-App Purchases
really did impact Active Devices
as well."
We've got more revenue
from our In-App Purchases,
and we've got more
retention and more engagement
from our Active Devices.
So, that's Metrics, and that's
the measures that we provide.
There's some questions
we haven't answered yet,
and we're going to
answer that with Sources.
So, what are Sources?
Sources are all about
how people find your app.
As developers, you work
really hard on your app,
your App Store presence, and
you have no idea right now how
people are getting to
your App Store page.
We're excited that Sources
solves that problem.
There's two types.
We have websites, and
we have campaigns.
Websites are really simple.
It's a link to your
App Store page.
You're familiar with
these links today.
Any time you hand a link to
your friends, to your family,
to your marketing sites, that
link is now trapped in the form
of a website as a refer,
as a Source, and we can see
that in App Analytics.
And Campaigns are that same
link with the campaign ID.
This is a friendly
link - friendly name
that you supply to the URL.
Let's talk about
what that looks like.
It's really simple.
This is the URL that
hopefully you're familiar with.
We add a Provider ID.
We get this Provider ID
inside iTunes Connect,
and then you add
your Campaign ID.
Friendly Name, you want
it as friendly as possible
because you're going to
view this name afterwards -
we'll show you that in a second
- inside your Sources Lists.
If you're using iAd today
to advertise your
application, this is automatic.
You do not have to go to iAd
and set up campaign names
for the purposes
of App Analytics.
It will all happen seamlessly.
Any campaign you create in iAd
will be automatically tracked
and available inside
App Analytics
and you can really
see the effectiveness
of that inside App
Analytics without any effort.
So what does this look like?
Come here, we select Sources
and get brought to
the Sources Lists.
Here, I see my Top Websites.
Beside that I can
see Top Campaigns.
I have the same key
vitals that I had
on my application list as well.
We're really trying to reinforce
the story of acquisition
to engagement and keep it
consistent for you guys.
I select Top Campaigns.
I get brought over to
my Top Campaigns List.
These are a view of all those
friendly names that we set up.
Let's zoom in on
one of these here.
I can see "Spring Email Blast."
That was my friendly name.
I see My App Store
views, my units, my sales,
and my sessions,
that same lifecycle.
This is great.
We select that, and we're
into this Source Details.
We think that if
you're marketers,
you're going to love this page.
You're going to sit
on this page.
You're going to share
it with your colleagues.
We can see all of
those key measures.
It's a nice visual.
We see it broken down
over time as well.
Every day has a bar
on these Key Measures.
We also see additional measures
that you can only get
on the Metrics Page.
You can see this broken down by
different data types as well.
So, here we're looking for
App Store views by Region,
by Territory, by Platform.
Changing those dropdowns,
I can change the measure
that I'm looking at and see
exactly how this campaign is
performing, how this
website is performing,
and what exactly the
customers are doing as well.
So that's Sources.
We think that you're going
to love Sources today.
You know that people are
downloading your app,
installing the app.
What you don't know is
where they're coming from,
and we're solving that problem.
So, we've answered the question,
how are people doing in the app?
Are they converting
on Internet purchases?
Where are they coming from?
We haven't answered in
detail, "Are people returning
or are they retained?"
What does that side of
the lifecycle look like?
And we answer that
with retention.
Let's just do a quick education
on retention, why
it's important.
This is obvious.
One-hundred percent of your
customers are customers
on the purchased date.
It's really simple.
Moving along, 45 percent
are customers on Day 2,
35 percent on Day 7, and
20 percent on Day 30.
Hopefully these numbers
aren't scary,
but there's an opportunity
there.
You can get them higher
and higher - focus on this,
it's really important because
if you have no more customers
at Day 30 or 90, you're
really going to have to focus
on the next stop or
improving your content
in your marketing to get more.
How do we show this in the UI?
Select retention, and I
can see my purchase date
on the left, May 23.
I can see my days
later on the right.
Here I'm looking at Day 7,
and there's a little story.
So of the active devices
that purchase on May 23,
18 percent remained
active seven days later.
This is great - single view
of how my retention
on May 23 was doing.
As developers, as
marketers, product managers,
we want to look at this with all
of our purchase dates
stacked on top of each other.
So that's the view
that we're providing.
The same on May 24th, and
now we show you the rest
of this matrix.
So, May 23rd to June 3rd,
I can see my retention
stacked a single quick view
of how my Day 7 retention is,
and you don't have
to do anything.
This is amazing.
So, we're providing -
[ Applause ]
- metrics, sources,
retention, your app list.
What do you need to do?
Nothing. There's no SDK,
no third party code running
in your apps, no
performance degradation.
[ Applause ]
You don't have to
write any new code.
This is not an Apple provided
library that you have to embed
in your app, and you don't
have to instantiate it,
initialize it, no
code is required,
no app updates required.
You do not have to
recompile, re-sign,
resubmit your app to the store.
You really have to do nothing
to take advantage of this.
We're doing this
because it's all built
into the App Store and iOS 8.
Everything from the store
metrics to the sales metrics,
to the device metrics,
this is all automatic
in the App Store in iOS 8.
And what have we kept in
mind while doing this?
Privacy. So App Analytics has
been a really highly requested
feature of iTunes Connect.
We're excited to bring it to
you guys, and we're excited
to bring it to you with
privacy at the forefront.
We're not in this
business to sell your data;
we're not in this business
to write informative blog
posts about your data.
Apple is providing App Analytics
as a service to the developers,
and we love our customers
as much as you do,
and we respect their
privacy as much
as we know you would
like to as well.
Rest assured that as we're
building this product,
as this product rolls out, the
privacy is at the forefront.
We're not making any
compromises in this area.
We're really excited about that,
and we think that's
a really unique thing
that we're offering.
Finally, maybe the
best news: It's free.
App Analytics is
completely free.
[ Applause ]
Lots of great views, lots of
great way to see your data,
revealing missed opportunities,
answering questions;
we think you guys are
going to love this.
We think that you're going
to love the setup
time, which is nothing.
Love the cost; we're
excited about this feature.
With that, I like to
bring up Daniel to talk
about TestFlight Beta Testing.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks Trystan.
Hi, my name is Daniel Miao.
I'm a Software Engineer
on iTunes Connect.
Now, most of you heard during
Tim's keynote on Monday
that we're announcing
TestFlight Beta Testing.
Well we're very excited to
have this opportunity today
to bring you more details
about this great feature.
Now, before we get started,
how many of you used
TestFlight in the past?
Great. Well whether you've
used TestFlight or not,
I'm sure we can all agree
that great beta testing
tools go a long way.
We'd all like to see less
of these, and more of these.
So before we get into the
details, let's talk a little bit
about the history of
beta distribution.
In the beginning,
beta distribution
looked a lot like this.
Whenever you wanted to test
your app on your device,
you would connect your
device to your computer,
transfer your binary
over and test from there.
At some point you probably
decided it'd be helpful
to have others also take a look
at your app before you
publish it to the App Store.
So each time you
wanted to add a tester,
you would ask the tester
for the device UDID.
You would go to the
developer portal,
set up provisioning profiles.
And then you would send
your tester the binary.
They would connect their
device to their computer,
transfer the binary over,
and they would start testing.
Of course you would
have to do this
for every single
one of your testers.
So, what do we do for
you during this period?
How did we change your beta
distribution experience?
Well we went from this, to this.
We think we can do better.
With the new TestFlight
Beta Testing platform,
you can distribute your apps
to not one, not 100, not 500,
but up to 1,000 testers.
[ Applause ]
Now these are testers,
not devices.
In fact, each of your testers
can test on multiple devices.
Next, UDID and provisioning
profiles.
You no longer need
to worry about these.
[ Applause ]
All you need to get a tester
started is an email address.
So let's talk a little bit
about the two sides
of the new platform.
You start out in iTunes Connect.
As you work on your project,
you upload your builds
to iTunes Connect.
And from iTunes Connect you
can manage these builds,
manage the testers, distribute
these builds to your testers,
and as they're testing,
you can come back
to get insight into
their activity.
Now once your testers receive
an invitation to TestFlight,
I mean to to test your app, they
download the TestFlight iOS app,
and from here they can
manage what apps they want,
they're testing.
They can perform one-tap
installs and updates,
and they can send you feedback.
So, while we were working on
these features, we discovered
that building great apps
requires a flexible process,
everything from iterating
with your development team
to distributing to
a wider audience,
so we came up with
internal and beta testers.
Now internal testers are made
up of your iTunes Connect users.
A beta tester is anyone
with an email address.
You can have up to 25
internal testers and up
to 1,000 beta testers.
As you upload builds
to iTunes Connect,
your internal testers
will have access
to these builds right away, and
beta app review will be required
to unlock your 1,000 testers.
But while your build is in
review, you can continue
to upload new builds, and your
internal testers can continue
to test, and you can continue
to manage your testers
in iTunes Connect.
Finally, Sandbox Accounts.
As each of your testers
signs into the iOS App
for the first time, they'll
automatically have a Sandbox
Account created for them.
What this means is that
you don't need to come
into iTunes Connect anymore
to create test accounts.
We want your testers to be
able to test all aspects
of your application
including in-app purchases.
So let's see what
this all looks like.
Here we are, we're back
on the version page
of the new iTunes Connect, and
you'll notice a Prerelease tab.
If you click this, we'll
see a list of the builds
that we uploaded in Xcode.
So let's say you want to
test build number 103.
In order to do this, we
first have to enter metadata
for our testers so they
have something to see
when they receive
their invitation.
So we click into this build, we
enter things like a description,
and we also tell the
tester what we like them
to test specifically
on this build.
After we've had this information
inputted, we hit Save,
and we come back
to the Build List.
Once we're on the Build
List, we come to the corner,
we click the Testing
Switch, turn on testing,
and that build is now available
to our internal testers.
So let's say we want
to upload another build
to our internal testers, keep
entering, maybe upload one more.
Now, we're confident that
105 is a build that we want
to distribute more broadly
to our beta testers.
In order to do this, we
click the Submit button next
to the build, and after review,
this is now also available
to our beta testers.
You'll notice here that
there's a 30-day expiration
on this build so we know
exactly when we need
to upload the next
build for our testers.
Now let's take a look at
managing beta testers.
Here we are on the
Beta Testers list.
We see everybody that
we added or invited.
We see what they're doing.
We can see that some of our
testers have installed the app
and they're already testing.
Some of them have
accepted the invite
but haven't installed yet,
and some have not even
accepted the invitations yet.
For the ones who have installed,
we see the latest build
that they've installed.
And if we want to add another
tester, we come up here
to the top, we click
the Plus button,
add a few email addresses,
hit Submit
and those testers
are ready to go.
So that's iTunes Connect side.
Now let's take a look at the
tester experience in iOS.
Here we are on the device.
This is the "Mail" app,
and this is an invitation
that we received
from a developer.
We see the name of the app that
we've been invited to test,
and we see a link that
says, open in TestFlight.
So let's go ahead and tap that.
Here we are in the
TestFlight app;
from here we can install our
app, and once we've done that,
we can just start testing.
Few things to note here
is the Send Feedback link.
You, as a tester, can
tap this to send feedback
to your developer via email.
There's also the What to
Test section, which we talked
about earlier, the developer
telling us what they like us
to test specifically
on the latest build.
Now if we tap the TestFlight
link in the top corner,
this will take us
back to a list of apps
that we're actively testing.
From here we can open any of
these apps, we can take a look
at What to Test notes
and we can look
at the version we're testing.
Now let's go back to the
Home screen for a minute.
Here, we see the
app we've installed,
and we'll see a badge, a little
orange badge next to the name
of the app that we
just installed.
This indicates that this app
is currently being tested;
it's a beta build of the app.
And oh, what's this?
We got a notification.
This is telling us that
there's a new build available
for us to test.
So if you tap that,
it'll take us back
into the app, into TestFlight.
From here we can update the
app, and we're on our way.
And that's TestFlight,
the iOS App.
So in summary, we can have
up to 1,000 testers for each
of our apps with beta testing.
We no longer need to manage
UDID's or provisioning profiles.
We can perform one-tap
installs and updates.
Sandbox Accounts are
automatically created
for our testers to be able
to test, and our purchases,
and is all new TestFlight
for iOS.
And that's Beta Testing.
Back to Dave.
[ Applause ]
>> All right, thank you Daniel.
We have a few things to wrap
up here before we conclude.
Every year we ask App
Review if you had a few tips
and tricks we can
give to developers
at a developers' conference,
what would they be?
App Review does a great job.
I looked right before
I got on stage.
Ninety-four percent of all
updates review within five days.
And here are some suggestions
that can help get your
app through app review.
Number 1, app name
versus keywords:
Your app name is not place to
list all those different words
that you want people to search
on so they can find your app.
That's what keywords are for.
IDFA, if you serve ads, then
ads must be present in your app.
The description and screenshots
must match your app -
and I would add to this -
App Preview will probably be
on this list next year.
When you're ready to
submit In-App Purchases
for review you need to
make sure that all aspects
of the In-App Purchase work.
If you need a service
up and running
so the auto renewables work,
that needs to be ready,
not when your In-App Purchase
is live on the App Store
but when you submit
it to App Review.
If your app gets
metadata rejected,
and you submit it again
without making a change
to that metadata, it will just
get rejected a second time.
I say that because they say it
happens - just a friendly note.
As always, make sure you have
rights for all the content,
the keywords in your app.
This would apply to screenshots,
app previews, anything.
And lastly, testing.
I'm very happy this
has lowered itself
down on the list this year.
One thing of note is that, if
you're building an iPhone app,
it needs to also
work on an iPad.
Not to be outdone, the Apps
Mission Team said, "Hey,
we have some suggestions, want
to help people some things
to think about before they
submit their app to App Review".
IDFA again - answers
these questions correctly
in iTunes Connect.
If you serve ads using IDFA,
make sure you answer those
questions the right way.
We get a fair number
of apps delivered
but don't have all
the right icons.
Make sure all your
required icons are
in your project before
you submit.
Toolchains and bad signature:
These kinds of invalid binary
messages can all be solved
by making sure that you
upload and create your app
in the latest version of Xcode.
And Mac app sandboxing, if
you're going to send a Mac
out to the App Store, make
sure you check that box
in Xcode before doing so.
A little note about
iTunes Connect for iOS:
I hope many of you already
gotten the latest update;
we released it a few weeks ago.
This was our first foray
or step into the redesign.
Updated pages, sells and trends.
Take a look at your five
week, your two week,
your 26 weeks information.
New page view.
iTunes Connect for iOS.
At the palm of your hand you can
release the latest version live
into the App Store.
So today we talked about the
new design for iTunes Connect;,
a nice new UI as well as
cleaner flows; app previews,
15 to 30 seconds
of dynamic video
so you can show what
makes your app magical.
App bundles: Bundle up to
10 of your apps together,
providing people in the
App Store with one install
to get all of these apps.
App Analytics - this is the
best end-to-end view of your app
with data that only
Apple can provide.
And TestFlight Beta Testing.
If you haven't been beta
testing your apps until now,
you have no reason not to.
Just like iOS 8 and
OS X Yosemite,
these features will be
released later this fall.
For more information,
you can write to write
to evangelism@apple.com.
There's a Contact Us
form on iTunes Connect -
this really is the best way
to get your questions
answered by the right person.
It can take a lot time
to navigate those
emails based off your
questions appropriately.
There's iTunes Connect
Dev Guide you can get
on developer.apple.com as
well as the dev forms -
lots of good information there.
We have some related
sessions later today:
"Optimizing In-App Purchases."
If you have any questions
on how exactly
to use In-App Purchases,
check that out.
"What's New in iAd Workbench."
As Trystan mentioned, privacy
matters, so we have a session
on "User Privacy
in iOS and OS X."
Tomorrow, "Advanced
User Interfaces
With Collection Views."
This is a great session
where we'll talk about that
and show how we used it in
creating iTunes Connect for iOS.
And the session I
mentioned earlier about
"Creating Great App Previews,"
again right before
the bash tomorrow.
I encourage you to check
that one out as well.
And with that, that's
all we have today,
I hope you have a great day
and rest of the conference.
Bye.
[ Applause ]
.