>> So welcome.
So-
[ Applause ]
-oh, thank you.
So, my name's Richard
Schreyer, and I've been working
on the design of Metal
for quite a while now.
And so it's really exciting
to finally be able to talk
to all of you about it.
So this is the Metal
fundamentals session.
It's the second in our trio of
sessions, following concepts
and to be followed by
Metal advanced usage.
So this session is going to
be split into two major parts.
The first half, which I'm going
to present, is going to be how
to build a basic
Metal application.
I want to take all
of the concepts
that Jeremy just described,
a bunch of block
diagrams and arrows.
And turn those into actual code.
So, we'll try to make
everything more concrete.
During the second
half of the session,
I'm going to turn the stage over
to my colleague Aafi [phonetic],
who will take you
into a deep dive
into the Metal shading language.
Talk about, you know, the
various syntax and data types.
How to express vertex,
pixel and compute shaders.
And then a bunch of grab bag
of other interesting topics.
So, getting right into
building a Metal application.
So as I said, this is
going to be a fairly --
a set of slides that are
fairly heavy on code.
That's really what I want to
try to get across is, you know,
what you're going to actually
want to put down in Xcode.
So I'm going to try and
keep this application
as simple as possible.
So it's going to be a very
"hello world" kind of thing.
So in the interest of, is it
always that way in graphics?
So the application I'm going
to build is basically
just a triangle.
We're going to go
through all the steps
to go put a single shaded
triangle on the screen.
[ Applause ]
I know, really exciting stuff.
But it's actually pretty cool
because, and we're going to go
through some boiler
plate and some setup.
But once you get through that,
that's really the same
foundation you need
to start building, immediately,
much more complex
content on top of that.
So we're not going out of our
way to draw just a triangle.
So the first set of
things I'm going to go
through are just
the initialization.
I mean what's the
one-shot setup you'll do
when your application launches
or you start using Metal?
Then I'll get into the
contents of what, you know,
the actual drawing
will look like.
And then we'll get on to
extending the application
to do a little bit more stuff.
So these are the
steps that I'll walk
through in the code, in order.
So right at the top
is getting the device.
So what is the device API?
So in Metal, a device is sort of
the root object of a whole API.
It's your direct connection
to the GPU driver
and the GPU hardware.
Now as far as the actual API
that the device sends out,
what it really does directly,
it's the source that you go
to to create all of the other
objects in the Metal API.
So if you want to go create
a new texture or a new buffer
or a new RenderPipeline,
the device is
where you'll find that.
So, we want to go
create some stuff,
and so we need a device
to create them on.
So that's really easy.
So our first initialization
step is to just say, "hey,
I want the default device."
Our second initialization step
is we need a command queue.
The CommandQueue is our channel
to submit work to the GPU.
Now we're not actually going
to do any of that until we get
to drawing, so I'm going to
create a CommandQueue now
from the device and
save it aside.
The third initialization step is
to go create all of my buffers
and textures and
other resources.
My application is simple enough
that I have exactly one of them.
I need a vertexArray.
And so I'm going to
go back to the device
yet again and say newBuffer.
This particular variance
will go allocate a new block
of CPU/GPU shared memory, copy
the provided pointer into it,
and give me back a
handle to that buffer.
So right off the bat
we've gotten through three
of our five initialization
steps.
We're making pretty good time.
The fourth one is going to
be quite a bit more involved.
We're going to spend
some time on that one.
And that is creating
the RenderPipeline.
So this is all -- so as we
saw in the concepts session,
the RenderPipeline
is a collection
of quite a bit of stuff.
Most importantly, the vertex
and the fragment shaders,
but it also incorporates
every other piece of state
that the shader compiler needs
to generate the final
machine code for the A7.
That includes some
information on vertex layout,
some rasterizer configuration,
all of the framebuffer,
blend modes, and
some information
about the framebuffer
configuration
that this pipeline will draw to.
That's actually quite
a bit of stuff.
And so we've split
the RenderPipeline
into two separate objects.
The RenderPipelineDescriptor,
which is your object
that provides all the
configuration API,
and the RenderPipelineState,
which is the sort of baked,
finalized form of that.
It's just small, it's compact,
and they're really
cheap to switch between.
So let's go look at
the code to build --
I'm going to build
one RenderPipeline
in this application, so
let's go look at the code.
So first, I'm going to
conjure up a new descriptor.
And the very first things I'm
going to set on it are my vertex
and my fragment shaders.
And you'll notice that I'm not
providing any source code here.
So this is what the
runtime API looks
like when Xcode builds your
shaders offline for you.
Xcode's going to package up all
of the offline-built shaders
into a device independent
bytecode file...
and ship that in your
application bundle.
And at runtime I can
go ask the device
to load that default library.
Once I have that, I can
go start picking functions
out of that by name.
The second piece of
configuration I need
on the RenderPipeline is
the framebuffer format.
So, I'm only going to have one
color attachment I'm rendering
to, and so I'm going to
say, "hey, this is going
to be a BGRA render target."
A RenderPipeline has a whole
bunch of other stuff I can set
on it, but for my simple
little application,
that's really all I need.
The default values of all
the other properties are
already appropriate.
So I'm going to go ahead and
compile and ask the device
to compile a RenderPipeline
state.
I'll just go to the device
and call newRenderPipelineState
WithDescriptor.
So this is actually
the expensive API.
This is the API that is
going to, if necessary,
go call over to the
shader compiler
and finish the code generation,
taking into account all
of the other information
that you have provided.
Once we have this
RenderPipeline, now you,
you know -- it's all baked.
It's all finalized, and
we can toggle between them
at draw time very, very cheaply.
So that's our fourth
initialization step,
building the RenderPipeline.
But before I move on from that,
you know, since we're pointing
at our vertex and
fragment shader here,
I do want to take a
really quick little detour
and show you the vertex and
fragment shader code itself.
So I'm not going to explain to
you every part of the syntax,
because Aafi is going to
tell you all about that
in just a few minutes.
But I'm going to show you
just, I'm going to focus
on just the dataflow from the
vertexArray through the vertex
and fragment shader and
into the frame buffer.
So, I've split this
up into two slides.
My first slide are
a couple structures
that describe the input and
output of the vertex shader.
The vertex structure defines
how my vertexArray is laid
out in memory.
Position followed by a color.
My vertex shader is going
to be a really simple
pass-through shader.
I'm going to read my position
color from the vertexArray
and pass them right out
down the pipeline unchanged.
So, unsurprisingly, my
VertexOut struct looks,
well, just like it.
The only difference is that
the rasterizer needs to know
which of the outputs
is the position,
so we have to use an attribute
to identify that
to the compiler.
All of the other outputs
will get interpolated
across the triangle as usual.
So on to the body of
the vertex shader.
So here's my simple
pass-through VertexShader.
So we have a normal
C-style declaration
with some extra key
words and attributes.
We'll go into more
detail on them later.
But I'm getting a
pointer to my vertexArray
into my VertexShader, along
with a vertex ID that tells me
which of the three vertexes
that this thread is
going to be processing.
From those I'm going to
read from the vertexArray,
copy to the output struct, and
I'm going to return an instance
of the VertexOut struct.
So this is sort of in comparison
to GLSL where all of the inputs
and outputs are specified
as global scope.
In the Metal shading language,
all of your inputs come
in via function arguments.
All of your outputs are
returned via the C return pipe.
[ Applause ]
Okay, this guy likes that!
So now the FragmentShader
is of course even easier.
The input to my FragmentShader
is again, a single argument.
In this case the same
VertexOut structs
that the VertexShader
just returned.
Except now it contains
an interpolated position
and an interpolated color.
So I'm going to go
read my color.
And I'm going to
return a float4,
which will write
into the framebuffer.
And because we told them --
put in the pipeline state what
the framebuffer for it is,
the compiler knows how it
needs to pack this down
and compress it to the actual,
final framebuffer format.
So that's the vertex
and frag-pass-through
vertex and FragmentShaders.
And that's really the end of
how to build a RenderPipeline.
The one last bit are just the
function names themselves,
which are the strings that I
use to pull up these functions
up when building
another pipeline.
So our fifth and final step to
initialize is creating the view.
So if you've been working
on iOS for a while,
you're probably aware that
if you want to get anything
on the screen, it
basically needs to be part
of a core animation layer tree.
So, iOS 8 provides
a new subclass
of CA layer called CAMetalLayer.
And that class is
really interesting
because it can vend
out textures.
It will manage a swap chain
of typically three textures,
and you can ask for the
next one in the chain.
And I can say, "Give me a
texture," render into it,
and when I'm done
I can push it back
to be swapped on to the display.
To create a layer,
that's typically owned
by a UIView subclass.
I'm going to show you a very,
very bare bones UIView
subclass on the next slide.
And you can find a much more
complete implementation,
with a bunch of functionality,
in our sample code.
And then because this is
iOS, and this is you know,
entirely typical, your view
is then typically owned
by a ViewController, which is
usually typically completely
custom to your application.
So let's go look at our
really bare bones view.
So really this is all
you really need to do.
I need to subclass UIView,
and I need to override the
layerClass method and say,
"I want this view to own
a Metal layer as opposed
to any other kind of layer."
There is some other
configuration we could do
on this view in this
layer (primarily
for efficient compositing) but
this is really the bare minimum
that you need to get
something on to the screen.
So with that, we've been
through all five our
initialization steps.
We breezed through getting the
device, getting a CommandQueue,
and creating a resource.
Spent a little bit of time on
the RenderPipelineDescriptor
and RenderPipelineState.
Also looked at the shaders.
And then we created a view.
So with that we can actually
get to drawing something.
And so that has a
few more steps.
So, we need to get a command
buffer, since all of our work
that goes to the GPU will be
enqueued into a command buffer.
We're going to encode
a renderToTexture pass
into that command buffer.
We're going to put some stuff
in that render texture pass.
And then finally we're going
to send that CommandBuffer
to the GPU hardware
to be executed.
So, step 1, getting
the CommandBuffer.
That's another one-liner.
You can simply go to the
command queue and say,
"give me the next
available CommandBuffer."
The second step is setting
up my renderToTexture pass.
One thing that sets Metal apart
from other graphic APIs is
that we have a, sort of,
very rigorous definition
of when a rendered texture
pass begins and when it ends.
And when you start a
renderToTexture pass,
we require that you tell us all
of the framebuffer configuration
right up front so we know how
to configure the hardware.
And most of what goes into
that configuration looks a lot
like a framebuffer
object in open GL.
There's, you know, what color
textures am I rendering too?
Up to four of those.
What depth texture?
What stencil texture?
Which bitmap levels that, the
load actions and store actions
that you saw in Jeremy's
presentation.
So given that there's so much
configuration that happens here,
we've again taken that
and packaged it all
up into a descriptor to do
convenient configuration on.
And then once you have
the descriptor configured,
you can then create the
renderToTexture pass.
So, putting that into code.
Right off the top, we need
to know what texture we're
going to render into.
So we're actually going to
go back to our CA ,metalLayer
and say, "give me the
next available drawable."
And a drawable is pretty
much just a wraparound
to texture plus a little
bit of extra bookkeeping.
This is one of the very
few API calls in Metal
that will actually
block your application
if there's no more
available textures
in the swap chain,
if they're all busy.
So this could block
and wait awhile,
especially if you're GPU bound.
Next, I want to set up
my RenderPassDescriptor.
I'm going to .colorAttachment
zero at my drawables texture.
I'm going to configure
the RenderPass
such that it will clear
that texture at the start
of the pass, preventing
the existing contents
of that texture from
being loaded
into the GPU's tile cache.
And then I'm going to
then actually, you know,
I'm going to choose some really
boring array to clear it to.
So again, if I had a
more complex framebuffer
configuration, there would be a
bunch more similar stuff here.
But again, that's all
I really need for my
"hello world" application.
So now I can go to the
CommandBuffer, and I can say,
"the next thing on
this CommandBuffer is
a renderCommand.
Here's the descriptor.
Give me back the interface
I can use to encode."
And this renderCommand encoder
you're getting back is the
object that has most
of the traditional 3D graphics
API you're expecting to find.
Things like setting
the depth stencil state
and binding textures and
colNodes and all that stuff.
So let's go actually
draw our triangle init.
So previously I created
my RenderPipeline,
and I created my vertexArray.
So I want to set them both here:
which RenderPipeline
we're going to use?
And I'm going to say, I'm going
to point right at
the vertexArray.
And I can finally
encode the command
to draw my single triangle.
So now we've gotten
through our third step
of drawing the triangle.
And now we get to the final one,
committing the CommandBuffer
to the GPU.
At this point we have basically
a fully-formed CommandBuffer
just sitting in memory, idle.
It's not going -- GPU
will not start executing
until you've committed.
So before we do that
though, we actually want
to do one more thing
and tell CoreAnimation
when you actually want
to present this texture.
Because we got a texture from
CoreAnimation, and now we need
to tell CA when we can
display that texture safely.
Because we haven't
rendered anything yet,
now's not the time.
So we want to be able to -- and
so this API addPresent will set
up an automatic notification
from Metal to CoreAnimation
that when this rendering is
complete, it will cross-call
into CoreAnimation and say,
"it's time to put this
on the display now."
And then finally we
have the big red button.
You call commit, and this
CommandBuffer gets encoded --
gets enqueued into the
end of the command queue,
and it will execute
on the GPU hardware.
So that is all of the steps to
go and draw my single triangle.
We needed to get a command
buffer, configure a render pass
with one target texture that
we got from CoreAnimation,
draw my triangle
with the vertexArray
and a pipeline state.
And commit the command encoder.
So that's my triangle.
That's pretty much all
the codes you need.
Go -- do it, yeah.
[ Applause ]
So it's kind of a
boring application.
So let's add at least
one little thing more
that every single
application is going to need
because I imagine
you're all not going
to be happy drawing exactly the
same thing over and over again.
We need to load some shader
uniforms because, you know,
we actually want to make things
move over time or what have you.
So, this is going to
take the form of --
so I want to use this
opportunity to show you how
to load shader uniforms,
also known as constants.
So, in Metal, shader constants
come in through buffers.
Just like vertexArrays
or anything else.
So back to my vertex
shader code.
I have declared a new
struct, which describes
to the compiler how my
uniforms are laid out in memory.
In this case it's just
a single 4x4 matrix.
And I've added a second
argument to my function.
I'm going to read from
a different buffer.
Now I'm going to read
from buffer location 1,
and that's where the compiler is
going to expect to find a buffer
that it's going to actually
load that struct from.
So that's the extent
of the shader changes.
On the API side, I've
allocated a second buffer
to -- hold my uniforms.
And I'm going to call
the contents property,
and that's just going to
return to me a void star.
And, err, these are CPU/GPU
shared CommandBuffers,
or shared -- not
Command Buffers.
These are CPU/GPU shared memory.
The GPU is reading from
exactly the same memory
that GPU's writing.
There's no lock or
unlock API calls
or flushing or any of that.
You can get a pointer,
[inaudible] it to a type
of your choosing
and start writing.
And then finally, I'm going to
set a second buffer argument
to the vertex stage to point
the hardware at uniformBuffer.
This is almost okay
but not quite.
Because we actually have
a race condition here.
So your application encodes
a frame and also writes
to a uniform buffer
at the same time.
And then we ship that off
to the GPU to be executed.
The execution is going to take
some amount of time depending
on the complexity of your scene.
So if you have like a
conventional game loop,
you're probably going to turn
around and immediately jump back
up to the top of your loop
and start encoding the
next frame right away.
Of course the GPU, being
an asynchronous device,
is still executing the
previous commandbuffer.
So if I have go right to that
unit, I have a new frame.
It's a new time stamp.
It's a new model view matrix.
But if I write that into
my buffer right now,
I'm writing into the same memory
that the GPU is reading from.
And I've created
a race condition.
At that point what the GPU
reads is completely undefined.
So, the easy thing to do is
write to a different buffer.
So there's no conflict here.
Then I come down into my
third frame and so forth.
But there comes a point where
you just, where you, you know,
you can't allocate
new buffers forever.
There comes a point where
you're going to want
to recycle an existing
buffer again.
And the problem here is that,
a CPU can get, sometimes,
depending on how you
structure your application,
several frames ahead of the GPU.
And the GPU might still
be working on that frame
that you submitted
two frames ago.
And we still have
a race condition.
So the final step to resolving
this is that we need to wait.
That your application needs
to not write to that buffer
until you know that your code
on the GPU is no
longer reading from it.
Fortunately, that's pretty easy.
It takes about four
lines of code.
So I'm going to show
you that now.
So I'm going to do this with
dispatch semaphores, which are,
you know, a common low-level
synchronization primitive
on iOS.
So for this example,
I'm going to have a pool
of three uniform
buffers I've created.
So I'm going to create
a dispatch semaphore
with a count of 3.
I'm going to add my
common CommandBuffer loop.
I'm going to build
a Command Buffer.
And I'm going to
send it to the GPU.
But right at the top, before
I write to any shared memory
that I'm recycling, that the
GPU is potentially still reading
from, I'm going to wait.
And I'm going to make sure
that the GPU has actually
finished executing
that previous CommandBuffer
before I reuse the memory.
So this is the second place,
apart from next drawable,
where you probably see
an application block
when using Metal.
Now the other side of this is
we need to signal the semaphore
when it is safe for the
application to proceed.
So, in Metal, you can
add a completion handler
to a CommandBuffer.
When the GPU finishes
executing this CommandBuffer,
the OS will invoke the
block that you provide,
and you can do whatever
you want in there.
In this case, I'm going to
signal the semaphore and say,
"Hey a CommandBuffer finished.
There's a uniform
buffer available.
Start writing to it.
Have a blast."
And that's really it.
So that's really the basic
walk-through through a simple
"hello world" application
with some animation.
It does shader constants.
Does vertexArrays, and we
still have this setup 3D state.
Went through some of the
basic initialization process.
We showed how to set up
basic CommandBuffer draw.
And we said hey, the moment
you produce any CPU dynamically
produced data, we saw how you
have to synchronize access
to that because we're just
giving you the raw memory
pointers now.
So, that thing -- these design
patterns actually go really far.
For example, that same pattern
of synchronizing with semaphores
or any other permit of your
choice, and the callbacks,
for example, are just as
useful for dynamic vertex data,
for streaming image
up-, texture updates,
if you have a large open
world kind of scene.
Or even if you're going
the other direction
and having the GPU produce data,
you know that the CPU
can read it as soon
as that callback fires.
So that's really your
introduction to a really simple
"hello world" application.
We made a spinning triangle.
Hooray. So, with that,
that wraps up this.
And so I'm going to turn the
stage over to my colleague Aafi,
to talk to you in detail about
the Metal shading language.
So thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> All right.
Thanks Richard.
All right, so we're going to
talk about the shading language.
And so Jeremy mentioned
in the first presentation
that this language is based
on C++, so a lot of you --
most of you -- are all
familiar with writing C++ code.
What we're going to talk
about is how we extended this
to be able to write
shaders in Metal.
So the things, the things
we're going to cover
in this session is
how to write shaders.
We're going to take a simple
vertex in the fragment shader
and see how we can take
C++ code and make it
into a vertex fragment shader.
We will talk about data
types that Metal supports.
We will talk about, you know,
well, shaders need inputs
and outputs, so how do
you specify that in Metal.
And, you know, if I'm
going to use them,
because in the RenderPipeline,
I need a vertex shader
and a fragment shader, well
how do I make sure I pair these
things together?
And then we'll talk
about math, okay?
All right, so how to
write shaders in Metal.
So let's take this in
a pseudo C code here.
So what you see here in
this function is it takes
three arguments.
The first two are some
pointers to some structures
and the return's this
vertex output struct which,
you declared it.
And what I want to
happen here is --
remember, the vertex shader
is executing for each vertex,
so if I have N vertices
in my primitive I want,
there may be multiple threads
executing these vertices
in parallel.
So what I want to be
able to do is read
in that thread that's
executing this vertex shader,
which vertex am I actually
accessing so I can go
and get the right index --
use that index to access
the right vertex data.
So, just you know,
imagine, just imagine
that this is that ID, okay.
So in this code, what we see
is we're going to use this ID
and reference into
the input arguments.
This is the vertex
data and UV data.
Arguments have passed
to this function.
And you will typically
probably do some computations.
In this case I'm not doing much.
I'm just going to copy
them and return them back.
Well okay, how do I make this
into a Metal vertex shader?
Well the first thing, note that
we don't -- and Metal doesn't --
support the C++ standard
library.
Instead Metal has its
own standard library
that has been optimized
for the GPU.
For the graphics and compute.
In addition to that, so
I want to include that.
In addition to that, you know,
types and functions defined
by Metal actually are in
the Metal's namespace.
So I'm just being lazy.
Instead of explicitly calling
them, I'm just saying I'm going
to use the Metal
namespace in my shader here.
The next thing I'm
going to do is I'm going
to tell the compiler, "hey,"
that "this function
is a vertex function."
Okay, so that's what
I'm going to do.
And then Jeremy showed you
that any resource that's passed
as arguments to your functions,
you need to have the
argument indices.
So in this case, you know,
anything that's a pointer
is actually a buffer.
So I'm going to assign
buffer indices.
And there's this global
thing that I have added here.
So just ignore that for now.
I'll talk about what
that is in a few slides.
So almost there.
And I need to tell the compiler
that that ID is actually
the vertex ID
so it can generate
the right code for me.
And that's it.
That's a Metal vertex
shader, okay?
What, nobody's going to clap?
[ Applause ]
[Laughs ]
All right.
And you know a fragment shader
is just very similar, OK?
So I need to tell the compiler
it's a fragment function,
so I use the fragment qualifier.
Now note, remember the fragment
shader typically takes inputs
that are generated
by the vertex shader.
The output of the vertex
shader goes to the rasterizer
and becomes inputs to
the fragment shader.
So in this case, the vertex
shader returns VertexOutput
and I want to use
that as an input.
Now, this is some struct
that you have declared.
So the compiler needs to know
that this is a per
instance input.
So anything that's user defined
and input to a vertex shader
or fragment shader that needs
to be generated uniquely
for instance, also
has to be qualified.
And so in Metal you do
that by declaring that with
that stage and attribute, okay?
So what I'm doing is in this
shader I'm going to look
at the texture coordinate per
fragment and use that to sample
into a texture that'll
return the color value.
So pretty straight forward.
So that's it.
It's really, you're going
to find that writing shaders
in Metal is really, really easy.
All right so let's
talk about data types.
So, I've broken data
types into two categories.
One I call the basic types.
And then we have
resources and state objects.
Note that one thing you
see is that all the inputs
to a shader are passed
as arguments.
There are no globals.
So you declare everything
as arguments,
and then if these are
resources or state objects,
then you specify the indices
that the runtime will use
to set the right resources to.
Okay, so let's talk
about the base types.
What are these?
These are scalars, vectors,
matrices and atomics.
So... the scalar is
pretty straightforward.
I mean it doesn't
usually tell much.
We support the C++11
scalar types.
In addition to that,
we have the half type.
Okay.
[ Applause ]
[ Laughs ]
All right.
So the half type.
So this is the IEEE 754
16-bit floating point type.
And so any operation
you could do with Float,
is half of a first
class citizen.
So anything you can do with
Float, you can do with Half.
In fact, we really
want you to use half
because they are
both performance
and power optimizations that you
surely can take advantage of.
Vectors: very similar.
So you have you know, two, three
and four component vector types.
So for example, a half2
is a two-component 16-bit
floating-plan vector.
Matrices: we have floating point
matrices, and they're stored
in column major order,
just like they are in GL.
The constructors and
operators: the things you can do
on them are very similar
to what you would find
in other shading languages,
so I'm not really
going to cover that.
But here's the thing
I want to talk about.
So, remember your path.
You're declaring a struct.
You're passing a
pointer to that struct
as argument to your shader.
So what you want to be able
to do is declare these --
let's say in a header file --
and then use them both on the
host code because you're going
to build this data
structure on the host.
And then use this header
file also in your shader.
Well you can do that
because these types --
So, in iOS 8 we have
the SIMD math library,
and so these define the
vector and matrices types.
And Metal uses the
exact same types.
So, what that means is: if
you include the SIMD header
in your host code and you
can build the structures,
you can share them.
You don't have to
do anything special.
It just works, okay?
[ Laughs ]
Not every slide, no
clapping every slide.
Again, just like I said
previously, use the half vector
and matrix types
whenever you can, okay?
All right, so the last -- Oh, so
one more point on vector types.
So they are aligned
at vector length.
So what does that mean?
So if I look at the struct,
what that means is: a float2,
which is what b is, is going
to be aligned on 8 bytes.
And similarly c is going to
be aligned with 16 bytes.
But if you notice, b is
actually at an offset of 4.
So that's a problem.
So what the compiler will do is,
it's going to generate
a padding variable.
Okay, so when you
do sizeof(Foo),
you're only going
to get 32 bytes.
So depending on how big your
data structure is and what kind
of scalars and vectors you use,
the compiler may
potentially have
to generate lots of padding.
And if you're going to declare
an array of these structs, then,
you know, it has
potential implications
to your allocation size
and even memory bandwidth
when you access these data
structures in a shader code.
So, well, you may want to
be smart and say, "well,
let me declare them in
order of decreasing size;
put all of my biggest
data types first,
and then the smaller types."
Well if you try to do
a sizeof(Foo) on that,
you're still going
to get 32 bytes.
And you're like, "why is that?"
The reason for that is the
compiler still has to guarantee
that each struct is
aligned to the site
of the largest data
type in that struct.
Because if you were to
use an array of these,
if you type index C at index 1,
you have to make sure
it's aligned on 16 bytes.
So that doesn't work.
So what if I wanted to tightly
pack all my data structures?
Yes, you can do that.
And we have packed
vector types for that.
So they are just like
the aligned vector types.
They're declared with this
"packed underscore" prefix.
You can do all of the operations
on these types as you can
on the aligned vector types.
The only benefit is that a
line is scalar type length.
So if I declare the same struct
now, but use the packed types,
then these are aligned
correctly.
And so the sizeof(Foo)
is going to be 28 bytes.
So then you are ask, "well why
shouldn't I always use these
packed types?"
And the reason, the
answer to that depends
on how you are going to
use these on the host.
Because the CPU, these types
are not a good fit for the CPU.
But the CPU likes vector
types to be aligned.
So if you're just
building a data structure,
and just filling it
out and going to pass
that to the shader (and
most of your computations
on these data types
are going to happen
in the shader) then you
can use the packed types.
But if you're going to perform
computations with these types
in host code, then you should
use the aligned vector types.
So use that to determine like
which types you need to use.
All right, so the last
of the basic types,
and these are the atomic types.
And so we support a subset
of the C++11 atomic types.
And the question is, "why
should I use atomic types?"
Well, the operations on
these types are race-free.
So, let's take an example.
Let's say I'm generating
a histogram for an image.
And so I have 8 bits
per channel.
So I have 256 bins for
each color channel.
So I want to update a bin.
So I'm going to read
the current value.
I'm going to increment
it, and then write it out.
So what I want to make sure
is that after I've read
but before I've written, nobody
else comes and changes it.
And that's what these
atomic operations guarantee.
Okay? All right, so that
covers the basic types.
So let's talk about resource and
state objects that you can pass
as data types to your shader.
All right, so we support the
traditional texture types
like 1d, 1dArray, 2d, 2dArray,
but how do you declare
these in Metal?
So these are declared
as a template.
[ Laughs ]
He likes it, all right.
So the template takes
two parameters.
One is the color type.
And this indicates if
you're going to sample
from a texture the vector
type you're going to return,
or as a color value, or
if you're going to write
to the texture, what
is the vector type
that would represent
the color value?
And the access mode.
And this tells the compiler
whether you're going
to be sampling from a
texture or reading or writing.
Reading is just saying, "hey,
go read this specific
location pixel in my texture"
or "write this color value
to this specific
location in the texture."
You can sample and
read or write.
You cannot do both to the
same texture within a shader.
And that texture is
of a different type
because the GPU actually
optimizes them differently.
And so we need to know
that you're actually
working with a depth texture.
So let's look at some examples.
So in this first one
we have a 2d texture,
and its color type is float.
So if you sample from
this, you're going
to return the float forward.
Notice I didn't specify
the access mode
because it has a
default, which is sample.
So the next one is a 2d texture
again which uses the half type
and its access mode is write.
So if I try to read from
this texture in my shader,
the compiler will
throw an error.
And then finally we
have a depth texture.
Okay? Samplers are
separate from textures.
So, what does that mean?
That means I can use the same
sampler with multiple textures.
Or I can use multiple samplers
of the same thing
with one texture.
You have the freedom.
How do I pass these?
Well, like I said, everything
is passed as an argument,
so you can pass them as an
argument to your shader.
In addition though, you
can actually declare them
in your source.
So it depends.
So like in a lot of cases,
especially if you're doing, ah,
image processing filters -- you
know, you just need a handful
of samplers that
you're going to use.
And data declared is
a variadic template.
And the reason for that
is samples have a number
of properties like the filter
mode, the addressing mode,
whether the coordinates I'm
going to use are normalized
or pixel, and a bunch
of other things.
I don't want to have to set
them explicitly every time.
All of these have defaults.
So you only change
the one you want to,
you are changing
from the defaults.
So in this example, I'm changing
the address more from clamp
to clamp to zero, and the other
properties take the default.
So you can choose to
pass them as an argument,
or you can choose them to
declare them in your source,
depending on your needs.
All right, so last of the types.
All right, so buffers is just
(as Jeremy mentioned) a bag
of bytes.
And so you just pass a pointer
or a reference to this type.
And notice in the first slide
I have this global qualifier.
Well let's talk about that now.
See, anything that's passed
as a pointer, or a reference
to some memory, you need to say
which memory region
it comes from.
And that's because GPUs actually
implement the member hierarchy.
With compute, you got an
additional memory region.
But if you're just writing
vertex and fragment shaders,
the two memory regions (we
call them address spaces),
you need to worry about
our global and constant.
So the question is, "well
when should I use which?"
All right, so if you are
writing a vertex shader,
you pass pointers to some
buffers, you're going
to use your vertex
ID to index into it.
That means for each, if the
vertex shader is being executed
over N vertices, all
of these instances
that are executing the
vertex shader are going
to be unique locations.
So when you see that data
pattern, you want to use global.
Okay, and the same
thing for compute.
You will find that
out when we talk
about computing in
the next session.
However, you will also find
in your shader that you may,
you are actually accessing
some data structures where all
of these instances actually
access the same location.
For example, if you
have a light descriptor.
Or if you're doing skinning.
Or if you're doing filtering.
So in this case you will find
that all these instances
executing your vertex shader go
refer to the same
light descriptor.
Or the same skinning matrix.
So let's look at an example.
One more thing here is
that when you use constant,
we really want you
to pass by reference.
Because that tells
us what the size is
and we can actually optimize
by prefetching the data.
And that can have a significant
impact to improvement
of performance of your shader.
So definitely take
advantage of that.
Okay, so let's take an example.
Here I have four arguments
passing three buffers
and my vertex ID.
So let's look at the
first data pattern.
Look at normal data
and position data.
I'm actually accessing
using my vertex ID,
so which address space
should these belong in?
Global. But if you look
at the other three data
pattern accesses and matrices,
you notice that if,
in a multiple vertices
root exiting this function
across multiple vertices,
they're going to refer
to the same normal matrix,
the same projection matrix.
So, therefore, I
should declare these
in a constant address space.
So hopefully this gives
you an idea of how
to declare your buffers
in which address space.
You don't have to do
that for textures.
All right, so let's talk
about inputs and outputs.
So that was a very high-level
overview of the data types.
So, how do you pass input
through your vertex shader?
Well there are two ways.
The first one we've
actually shown you, right?
In all of the examples I have
shown you, you pass the input
by passing a pointer to a
struct, so you've declared,
and then you use your
vertex ID to index into it.
So that means is you
actually know the data layout
of your vertex inputting
in a shader.
So if you do, this is
the way to do it, okay?
So in addition to your vertex
ID you can also use your
instance ID.
Like in this example, I
have two inputs I'm passing
in as buffers, and I'm using
the vertex ID and instance ID.
But there is also the
traditional approach.
So in this approach, you
don't know the data layout
in your shader.
And so if you want it all,
you may want to decouple.
You may want to declare in your
vertex shader the data types you
want to use for your
vertex inputs
because of the computations
you're doing in your shader,
and have the flexibility to be
able to declare the actual input
at runtime in the
buffers are showing,
and they may be different.
So, this is more like the
OpenGL's Vertex Array API.
And so this, this approach in
Metal is actually a good match.
And let me talk about
how it works.
So the thing you'll do
in the runtime is you will
create a vertex descriptor.
So in this descriptor for
each input, you're going
to specify the buffer it comes
from, where inside the buffer,
what is the format,
things like that.
And you may have one or more
buffers for your inputs.
In the shader, everything
that is an input, you're going
to declare them in a struct.
And remember I said, anything
that's user-defined information
that you want to
generate per instance,
you have to use stage-in.
So that's how you declare it.
So let's look at a code example.
Ah, before that.
So I declared my
struct and my shader,
and I declared my
vertex descriptor.
All my inputs and my vertex
descriptor, I need to be able
to say, "hey, this will work --
I need to be able to
map one to the other."
And the way I do that is
by specifying an
attribute index, okay?
So let's look at an example.
Let's say I want to
pass four inputs.
The first one is going to be
positioned, and it's going
to be an index 0,
and 12 bytes in size.
The next one is normal.
It's also at offset 12
and 12 bytes in size.
In fact, all four
inputs are going
to come from the same buffer.
And so the next one is color
at index 2, 4 bytes in size.
And then third is texture
coordinate at index 3,
4 bytes in size, okay.
All right, so how do I
declare this in the shader?
So I have a struct.
I have defined the data
types I want to use,
and the attribute indices
they're going to use.
And notice that I've declared
them with the stage-in qualifier
because this is going
to be per instance.
For every instance it
executes as a vertex shader.
Okay, so let's look at the API.
So the first thing I'm going
to do is create the
vertex descriptor.
So the first imput
was my position.
So I'm going to say
float3 is 12 bytes.
So it's going to
start us off at 0.
And notice I had a single
buffer for all of the input.
So my buffer index for all
of these is going to be 0.
The attribute index is 0.
So next I set the
normal, so at index1.
The next I set color, at index2.
Texture coordinate.
And for each buffer
that I'm using
to declare my vertex
inputs in my descriptor,
I have to say the
stride, what is the stride
so I can fetch the
right vertex data.
So in this case it's 32 bytes.
So I did that.
Then I put this vertex
descriptor
to in my pipeline descriptor.
And then I create
my pipeline object,
my RenderPipeline object.
And at that point in time,
Metal will go figure out how
to generate the code
to go fetch your input.
So, you have both
options available.
Use which works best
for your problem.
All right, outputs: well, there
are two ways of writing inputs,
so we wanted to make
sure you get two ways
of writing outputs too.
So, typically what you
would do is the output
of your vertex shader will go
the rasterizer, because you want
to show something on the screen,
so you want to rasterize
triangles.
So anything that you
return from the return type
of your vertex shader is what's
going to go to the rasterizer.
So what can I return?
I can return a float4.
At a minimum I must return a
float4, and I'll tell you why.
Or you can have a
user-defined struct.
What can be in this struct?
So there can be a scalar,
a vector or a matrix.
You can even have
arrays of these.
There's some special
variables we need to know
about like position, point size
if you're rendering a point
sprite or clip distance.
You must return a float4
because position must always
be returned.
It's kind of hard
for the rasterizer
to generate rasterized triangles
without knowing position.
So that's why.
All right, so here's an example.
I'm returning four things.
And I use the built-in variables
attributes to identify things
such as position and point size.
This is really pretty
straight forward.
Declare your struct, declare
some attributes and you're done.
Okay. So it's great.
I can generate output,
pass it to the rasterizer.
But I want to do more.
I want to be able to
write some buffer,
maybe more than one buffer.
I don't want to send
anything to the rasterizer.
Or maybe I want to do both.
Can I do that?
The answer is, "we
are here to please."
[ Laughs ]
[ Applause ]
So remember the vertex ID
you can use that to input.
Well guess what?
You can use that to output too.
So here is the structure
I want to write out.
I want to pass that as --
declare that as a struct,
ah, create a buffer...
Pass that as an argument
to my shader,
and output to it
using the vertex ID.
In fact, I can pass up to 31
buffers if one is not enough.
[ Applause ]
You notice I'm not
returning anything here
because of the return type.
But I could have returned
the same struct here,
or I could return something
completely different.
So you have a lot
of flexibility here.
All right.
So that's per-vertex
inputs/outputs.
Per-fragments are a lot simpler.
There's only one way
of doing things here.
So, the inputs to a fragment
shader are typically the outputs
of the vertex shader because
they go to the rasterizer
and they generate fragments
and that's the inputs.
So what can I --
must be declared
in with this stage-in qualifier.
Sometimes the raster also
generates information
that you may actually
want to know about, like,
"is my triangle front-facing?"
Or if I'm doing multi-sampling.
So things like that,
you can use attributes
to identify these inputs.
And if you wanted to
program a blending,
you want to read the
frame buffer color value.
So, you can.
So let's talk about
how I do that.
So here's an example.
In this case, my fragment
input was the output
of the vertex shader.
So I used the staging
qualifier to say
that this is a per-fragment
input.
I want to read whether the
triangle is front-facing or not.
So I use this attribute
to identify
that this front face is
a front-facing variable.
And I also want to do
blending in my shader.
So I'm going to read
front color attachment 0.
Though I passed as a
separate arguments here,
they don't have to be.
I could have declared them
in the struct itself, okay?
Outputs from a fragment
shader work just
like outputs from
a vertex shader.
You can't write to
memory though.
Only the first one.
So you only return type.
And you can return a scalar,
vector or user-defined struct.
A lot of flexibility here.
But the only thing
you can return
in a fragment shader is a
color, a depth or a sample mask.
And we need to know so you have
to four color attachments,
one depth.
And sample mask.
We need to know what
you're writing to.
And so you identify them
with attributes, okay?
So in this example, I'm
just returning a single
and a color value back.
This is going to be returned
to color attachment zero.
Here's another example where I'm
returning more than one color.
And notice here that the color
attachments don't have to be
in the right order, okay?
They can be sparse.
All right, you guys ready
for some matchmaking?
All right, so I've written,
you've written a vertex shader
and a fragment shader.
I want to pair them because
I can't do the RenderPipeline
without it.
So how do I pair?
What are the rules?
The simplest rule
is that types match.
That means the return type of
the vertex shader is the input
to the fragment sharer.
In this example,
that's what it is.
And this will always pair, okay?
But that's boring.
I want to just, I want
to declare my own struct
as my input to my
fragment shader,
and that can be a subset.
In fact, that's typically
very common
if I use one vertex shader with
many, many fragment shaders.
So where's the rule here then?
How do I pair?
The rule is really simple.
For anything that's an
input to the fragment,
it's attribute name and type
must exist in the vertex output.
So in this example,
you know, I have:
position is a float4
in my fragment input.
It exists, and it's the same!
Same thing for this
attribute, user(T).
So anything that's not a
built-in variable, you can come
up with your own name.
It just needs to use
the user-parentheses,
braces, and tags.
So that's the same thing here.
And so if I create a vertex
shader and a fragment shader
that uses these types,
they will pair.
Note that there is
no requirement
that all the elements
that I have
in my fragment input must
occur in the same order.
They can occur in any order,
they just need to occur.
That's it.
All right so that's
matchmaking for you guys.
Okay? All right, my
favorite topic: math.
Is anyone interested in math?
[ Applause ]
But why? Well because the two
common operations you guys are
going to do are loads
and stores.
And the rest is math.
By default, all operation
math operations
in Metal are in fast math mode.
So want to make sure you get
the absolute fastest experience
of your shaders running
on the GPU.
Did anyone say, "well, if you
want to give me fast mode,
why do I care about
precise mode?"
Well because, you
know, fast mode comes
with some caveats, it's fast.
So sometimes, like in fast
mode, we tell you behavior
of NaNs is not defined.
So NaN is not a number.
Well then what do
I care about that?
It's not a number.
"I'm not going to do math on
a not-a-number," you're like.
Well, sometimes you do.
So for example, if I'm clamping
an input with some minimum
and a maximum, if I pass
an input that's NaN,
in fast mode we're
going to say "ah,
we don't know what the
answer is going to be."
But if you actually follow
iTripoli's [inaudible] rules,
there's guaranteed
defined behavior.
And you may actually
care about that.
Or, let's say you're using
trigonometric functions
in your shader.
In fast mode, they work
great over a small range.
If your inputs go above
and beyond that range,
behavior is undefined.
So, let's say you want
correct behavior for those.
Then you want to
use precise mode.
So one option is you're going
to say, "I want my entire shader
to run in precise mode."
You can do that.
You can set the compiler option.
But that may actually...
So, you need to really know
what you're doing before you set
that option.
So. But that option does exist.
OK? All right, I think the more
common scenario is, you know,
you're going to do most of
your stuff in fast mode.
There may be some functions you
want to run in precise mode.
So, you can do that in Metal.
Because guess what, these
functions actually occur
in nested name spaces.
[ Applause ]
So by default, you get
the fast name space.
But you can call the precise
math function explicitly.
Okay? So that's it.
Ah! Metal standard library.
So we don't do the
C++ standard library.
We do our own.
And it is really
optimized for the GPU.
And I think you guys
are going to love it.
I think it has a nice
list of functions.
It's all described
in the documentation.
I'm not going to cover
details of these functions,
but please refer to
the specs, but...
these are some of the functions.
[ Laughter ]
There's quite a few, okay.
All right, so what did we do?
We covered, Richard talked
about how you build
a Metal application.
And he showed you how to
draw a simple triangle.
But then he took
it even further.
He showed you how to do
stream uniforms, okay,
with multiple buffers and how
to synchronize them efficiently.
Then I talked to you guys
about the shading language.
We went on a tour.
We didn't go much deeper,
but a very high-level tour.
We talked about how to write
shaders, given that it's based
on C++, it's actually going to
be really, really easy for you
to write these shaders.
We talked about the data
types Metal supports.
We talked about inputs
and outputs to shaders.
We talked about how
to match them.
We talked about math.
So really, now it's your turn.
I'm excited about how,
the amazing ways you guys
are going to use Metal.
And we want to hear from you.
We want to know how we can
improve this even better.
So, please come talk to us.
So, for more information,
please --
Filip Iliescu and Allan
Schaffer are our evangelists.
Their email addresses are here,
so bug them as much
as you can, okay?
And Jeremy talked
about documentation.
All documentation
for both the API
and the language
are on our website.
Please, you can use the
forums to ask questions.
But actually, there's
one more session.
The next session covers -- goes
into a deeper dive in Metal,
and we're going to talk
about data power
computing and tools as well.
The one session I
actually wanted
to highlight was what's new
in the Accelerate Framework.
And it actually happened
yesterday, okay.
But I think this is really
important because we talked
about sharing data structures
between the CPU and the GPU.
So this, actually, session
talks about the same library.
So I definitely recommend
you go listen to it.
And that's it.
Thank you for coming.