>> Good morning.
Welcome to session 702
Managing Apple Devices.
[ Applause ]
Wow. I wasn't expecting
that enthusiastic
of welcome this early
in the morning.
I'm Todd Fernandez, and I
am very happy to be here
with you even at this
ridiculously early hour
for techies like me.
Although for some of you, this
may be the middle of your day
if you work in schools
our otherwise have
to wear a tie to work.
Many of us are far more likely
to see this hour at the end
of a long night of coding than
at the beginning of our day.
Now, I open by recognizing
our differences
because this session's
content is intended
for a diverse audience.
From Indian vendors, who need to
learn how to take full advantage
of the powerful device
management capabilities
that we've built into iOS 8 and
OS X Yosemite, to app developers
who want to understand how their
apps may be used in schools
and businesses, to
administrators who need
to know what changes are coming
in the OS releases this year.
When I stood before you here
last year, I was thrilled
to announce 2 huge leaps forward
in managing Apple devices.
In the addition of
managed distribution
to our Volume Purchase
Program and the introduction
of the Device Enrollment
Program which Craig highlighted
in the enterprise section
of yesterday's Keynote.
It's hard to believe there
was an enterprise section
at the Keynote, but it
was very exciting to see.
[ Applause ]
When we set out to create
the device in Roman program,
we did so after wondering, why
does it have to be painful to do
that initial configuration
of your devices before handing
them out to their users?
And we started by
asking a simple question.
Why can't it be as easy as
just un-boxing that device
and handing that iPad or that
iPhone or that Mac to its user?
And it turns out many of you
are asking the same question.
And I'm very pleased to report
that our customers are just
as thrilled by the
transformative nature
of this new service
as we had hoped.
One noteworthy example is
Immaculata La Salle High School
in Florida who believe
that we, indeed,
turned this dream
into a reality.
And they proved it by completely
replacing their fleet of iPads
with 600 new iPad Airs including
restoring all the student apps
and data from iCloud
in 2.5 hours.
They made a wonderful video
showing just how they did it.
And if you've never seen the
Device Enrollment Program
in action, I highly
recommend checking it out.
So since we last met, we've
been very busy launching managed
distribution last fall.
The Device Enrollment
Program a few months ago.
And we've also been busy adding
all these features to fill
in the gaps and smooth
out the inconsistencies
between iOS and OS X.
So that vendors, like some
of you creating device
management tools,
and the administrators,
using those tools,
have a much easier time managing
all their Apple devices.
This session is going to cover
the entire life cycle device
management including both
new tools existing tools
and technologies and
all the changes coming
in iOS 8 and OS X Yosemite.
And we'll show you how
they all come together
to provide a great experience
for both the administrators
and their end users.
From enrolling devices in your
management solution of choice
to distributing content to
all those devices to the day
to day ongoing management
tasks that come
up as time goes on
and needs change.
So let's dive right in and
talk about enrolling devices.
Of course, we're going to
spend a fair amount of time
on the device enrollment
program,
the best way to do this.
I'll also talk about
Apple Configurator
as an alternative way
to enroll your devices.
You also need to be aware of
how to manage Activation Lock
on supervised devices
and be thinking
about that at enrollment time.
And then I'll conclude
with what's coming
in this year's OS releases.
So before we go any
further, I want to make sure
that everyone understands what
the Device Enrollment Program is
and is not.
So it relates, you know,
audience participation.
Let's get going, although I
appreciate all the responses
already, the Device Enrollment
Program is not a MDM server.
Come on, say it with me,
Device Enrollment Program
is not an MDM server.
Thank you.
Though you'll note they're both
3 letter acronyms, those of you
with eagle eyes with note
they're not the same 3 letters.
In fact, the Device Enrollment
Program is the best way
to get your devices enrolled
in whatever MDM solution
you're going to use.
It's an easy button to get your
devices in your MDM server.
It's really 2 parts: A way
for administrators to specify
which settings they want to use
when their devices are enrolled
in their management solution.
And the integration
of the completion
of that enrollment process
right into the normal set
of assistant process
that the user will go
through on both iOS and OS X.
As I mentioned, we
launched this in February
with devices eligible that
are purchased via direct sales
in the U.S. And we've heard all
of your feedback loud and clear
that you'd like to
see us expanded
to additional countries
and channels.
So I'm very pleased that,
although we've only launched
this a few months ago,
we've already expanded access
to our neighbors to the North.
Any Canadians here?
I'm so sorry about the
Canadians, but, in fact,
the Rangers knocked my Flyers
out in the first round;
so get them next year.
We've also made a number
of other changes already
since launch that I
wanted to point out.
Devices are now eligible
up to 3 years in the past
if you've purchased
them up to 3 years ago.
And there's some enhancements
to the portal that allow you
to set a default MDM server so
that any new device purchases
with automatically be
assigned to that MDM server
without you needing to
take further action.
You can also now see which
administrators assigned
which devices to
which MDM servers.
And another, coming soon,
expansion of eligibility is
that when devices that are
in the Device Enrollment
Program are replaced by service,
those devices will
soon be remain
in the Device Enrollment Program
including, retroactively,
devices that have been
replaced over the past 3 years.
We think customers will
really appreciate that too.
So let's quickly recap exactly
how this service works before I
go into details, especially
for the MDM vendors.
Customer purchases devices,
that information is fed
into the Device Enrollment
Program.
When the customer provides
their account information
to their MDM solution, the MDM
solution can download the device
information from the program.
The administrator can then
specify their settings
and upload those to the program.
Then, when users open
the box and start walking
through the setup assistant,
the device receives its settings
from the Device Enrollment
Program which tell it
to enroll with the MDM server.
And I also, again, want
to emphasize that once
that happens, Device Enrollment
Program has done its job.
It's out of the picture,
and your MDM solution is the
only thing that's talking
to the devices.
So we're going to talk about
3 topics a few moments here
related to the Device
Enrollment Program and how best
to integrate this into
your MDM solutions.
So the first concept is, where
should the ultimate repository
of the truth relating to
the program, the devices
and the settings reside?
The device information
should really be
in the Device Enrollment Program
and treat that as the truth.
You can always fetch
that information
from the service
to your MDM server.
But the settings that the
administrator decides to apply
to certain groups of devices,
your server should really treat
itself as the truth for that.
It can always upload new
settings to the program.
One caveat here to keep in mind,
though, is what I explained
on the previous slide: Even
if the administrator
changes the settings that are
in the Device Enrollment
Program for a particular device
or devices, those devices
will not see those settings
until the next time that they go
through activation after wiping
and going back through
the setup assistant.
So if the device is already
enrolled and you happen
to change the setting to
say, Well, now I want it
to be supervised,
that won't take effect
until the next time
the device is set up.
All right.
So disowning devices, you may be
thinking, what does that mean?
Well, this removing a device
from the Device Enrollment
Program.
And I'm here to scare you.
Our recommendation is to
not implement this feature.
Why is that?
Well, and if you're
going to break Rule No.
1, you need to really,
really how many "reallys"
did I put on there?
really make sure they
understand the consequences:
That they will not be able
to undo this action and get
that device back
into the program.
So, again, we recommend
following Rule 1.
All right.
Our final topic is thinking
about the combinations of two
of the specific enrollment
settings that you can configure
for a device: Whether
it's supervised or not,
and whether that MDM
enrollment can be removed or not
by the user on the device.
And there our own Profile
Manager has taken the approach
of not separating
these settings.
That if you choose to supervise
a device, it automatically,
the MDM enrollment is not
removable, that top right box.
The bottom right
box is forbidden.
If you try to upload settings
where the device
is not supervised
and the MDM enrollment is
not removable by the user,
the service will
reject those settings.
The lower left box
may be interesting,
again Profile Manager
doesn't well,
that's what profile manger does
if you don't check
the supervised box
that it's completely open.
It's not supervised; end user
can undo the MDM enrollment.
Those 2 are really
the interesting ones.
The kind of half one in
the upper left is allowed,
but probably not
super interesting
to supervise a device
but still allow the user
to un enroll from MDM.
So that's a couple notes about
the Device Enrollment Program.
Let's talk a bit about
Apple Configurator.
So again Apple Configurator
is also not an MDM server.
I want to make sure
everyone's clear about that.
But it is an alternative way
to install enrollment settings
on a particular iOS
device over USB.
As an alternative to using
Device Enrollment Program
over the Air.
Once those settings have
been loaded to the device,
the actual requests that
go to the MDM server
to complete the enrollment
are indistinguishable
from whether they were
done the settings got there
over the Air or over USB.
However, you can teach
your server to distinguish
between the 2 if
you check to see
if that particular device
that's enrolling is in the list
that you've gotten from the
Device Enrollment Program.
Also, if a device has
already gotten its settings
from the Device Enrollment
Program,
Configurator will not
overwrite those settings.
One additional caveat is
that delivering your enrollment
settings via the Device
Enrollment Program
is the only way
that you can make your MDM
enrollment not removable
by the user.
Another recommendation and
one that we followed ourselves
in Profile Manager is that
it's probably a good idea
to offer administrators
the option
to disallow installing settings
over USB if you want to ensure
that they only get your
institution's devices only get
the settings that
you specify via DEP.
That would present a user
from using Configurator
to install settings that allow
enrollment in your MDM server
without supervising for example.
Let's now talk a little bit
about Activation
Lock Management.
So by default a supervised
device does not allow the user
to enroll in or to
enable Activation Lock.
But there is now a way that
we introduced in the spring
that MDM can request a bypass
code that allows the MDM server
to later or the administrator
to later clear Activation Lock
without needing the
user's password.
At that time, there's
also a MDM command
that can tell the device, well,
okay, now you can allow the user
to enable Activation Lock.
So you want to do all of
this at enrollment time.
If, in fact, your institution
wants to use Activation Lock,
which is a great feature.
We also recommend
that once you retrieve
that Activation Lock bypass
code that you provide access
to the administrator to in the
UI because it may be useful
to maybe enter it
manually on a device
that for whatever reason
is not currently reachable
by the MDM server.
There are 3 new MDM commands
to retrieve the code,
to then delete it
from the device
so that no one can
grab it off the device
if they get physical access
to it, and then, of course,
to enable or allow the device
to enable Activation Lock.
And we strongly recommend
that when you're completing
the MDM enrollment, that,
at that time, you
always retrieve
and then clear the bypass
code from the device
because it's only
available for 15 days
after the device was supervised.
You should also save
that bypass code even
if a particular device
is un-enrolled from MDM
because Activation Lock
may still be enabled.
And you may still
need to clear it.
And the device can
later re enroll.
And there won't be another
opportunity to get a bypass code
until the device is
wiped and re supervised.
So those are the topics I
wanted to cover on enrolling.
But I'm also happy to tell you
that there's important change
in how the device responds
when the enrollment is being
completed in Setup Assistant.
And I know your servers
are all real excited.
The administrators have no
doubt specified lots of settings
and apps and all
sorts of things.
They want to deliver to the
device as soon as it's enrolled;
however, the device
isn't ready to respond
to all those requests while
the user is still completing
Setup Assistant.
So now when any of these
MDM commands are sent
to the device while it is
still in the Setup Assistant,
it will return the
"not now" status.
So your server can know,
hey, device isn't ready.
I'm going to wait until
it returns success
for that enrollment.
And then you can start
completing your enrollment tasks
or configuration tasks.
So without further ado, I'd
like to show you how this works,
and I'm going to invite my
colleagues Jussi Pekka and Mark
up to show you a demo
of enrolling devices.
[ Applause ]
>> All right, thank you, Todd.
So here we have an out of box,
freshly delivered, new iPad.
Basically it was purchased by
the institution and it didn't go
through some boiler room.
It was just handed
straight to the user
and our Profile Manager
server this is our MDM server
for this demo knows about
this device because the time
between Device Enrollment
Program and Profile Manager
and the device the purchase
was made through the channels.
So we know that this device is
configured for our services.
So I'm going to walk
through the setup as usual.
I'm going to pick my language.
Go pick my country.
Connect to my network.
So at this point, the
device is now talking
to the Apple Services
and obtaining its
activation information.
And as part of that information
is the notice that we are now
in the DEP and we got prompted
for enrolling in the MDM server.
So just in a second we are still
returning some information.
And now we are talking
to our server.
So this is as far as DEP
has talked to the device.
Now we're talking
to our MDM server.
And I can find more
information about our instance.
So if I need to know
what to do next,
I can call the ACME Help Desk.
And now I go to the next.
And you see that when I go
forward, I'm now prompted
for my user name and password.
And I cannot bypass this;
so I do have to enroll this.
So this device has been
configured to be supervised,
and the MDM profile
is mandatory.
So I have no way of
bypassing this step.
So I'll provide my log in
information and move on.
And now we're downloading the
profiles from our MDM server.
So, again the DEP phase has been
completed, and now we're talking
to our management server.
And Mark has set some
screens to be bypassed here,
so we're not seeing
registration and other pieces.
And while I complete my setup
logging into my iCloud account,
I'll have Mark show you
the setup in the backside.
>> Yep. So Jussi is going to
finish setting up his iPad.
And I want to walk
you through how
in Profile Manager we've
implemented this UI
to support configuring
Device Enrollment Program.
So on the left side
you see the devices
that my server has retrieved
from the Device Enrollment
Program.
My server is configured
to download these devices,
and then I have Jussi's
iPad selected here.
And you can see the
enrollment settings
that I've got selected here.
Our first option is whether
to turn on this configuration
for this device or not.
You can also put
these configurations
on device groups as well.
So you can get a
whole collection
of devices get the
same settings.
So we have this checked
on because we wanted
to send the settings down.
The next option is whether
or not the user is
allowed to skip enrollment.
And, as you saw in the case of
Jussi's device, he's not allowed
to skip enrollment; he's going
to be prompted for credentials,
credentials for his
directory server.
Our next option is whether
or not we want to do
over the air supervision
of the device.
Now, in addition to being
able to supervise the device,
when you supervise the device,
you also have the option
of locking the MDM Profile
so it can't be removed
from the device.
In our case, we've combined
those into one option
because we think our customers,
whenever they supervise,
they're going to want
to have locked MDM.
But if you're a third party MDM
developer, you can always break
that out and have it
as a separate option.
The next thing is whether or
not you want to allow pairing.
So I have that turned on
so the device can pair
with another Mac if you want.
Next is to request
credentials for enrollment.
You saw Jussi's device was
prompted for credentials.
And then there are
various things
that we can skip
during the setup show
or skip during the
Setup Assistant.
In our case, we have Apple
ID enabled because we want
to caption on, Jussi's
device will get Activation
Lock enabled.
So Jussi is finished actually
setting up his device.
So I am going to show
you, our security settings
for the device right now show
that Activation Lock
is not enabled.
But I do have the
Activation Lock bypass code.
This what Profile
Manager grabbed
from the device when
it was enrolled.
If I update my info
now that he's done,
we'll see in a moment here
that Activation Lock is
going to change to yes.
And find my iPhone is
enabled, is set to yes.
So when this device comes
back to me, I'll be able
to run this clear
Activation Lock
if Activation Lock
is still enabled.
And I and clear that
and hand this device
out to the next user.
So back to Todd.
>> All right.
Thank you, guys.
[ Applause ]
So Jussi and Mark just
showed you how you can enroll
and supervise an iOS device
using the Device Enrollment
Program and how to configure
the enrollment settings
that were used using
Profile Manager.
But, of course, that can be
done with any MDM solution
that supports the Device
Enrollment Program.
And we hope all of them do.
Mark showed you how Profile
Manager had retrieved the
Activation Lock bypass code
as it completed enrollment
of that device.
And then Profile Manager
actually automatically allows
or there's a setting, enrollment
setting which I don't know
that Mark showed that the
administrator can choose
to always automatically allow
Activation Lock once it's
retrieved, successfully
retrieved the bypass code.
So let's move on to the next
section of our talk and talk
about distributing
content to our devices.
We're, of course, going to talk
about the Volume
Purchase Program
and managed distribution.
We'll talk a little bit about
managed apps and then conclude
with the significant
enhancements in iOS 8
and OS X Yosemite to
fill in some gaps here.
So, again, to recap, managed
distribution allows the
administrator to buy
licenses instead of codes,
which can be revoked and
reallocated to a different user
for both apps and books.
And we provided API so that
MDM solutions can integrate the
service into their solutions.
And it's currently
available in 10 countries.
So, again a refresher of
exactly how this works:
The administrator can
purchase apps and books
in the VPP Portal, that
information is stored
in the iBookstore
and the App Store.
When they provide their
account information
to their management solution,
it can download information
about which apps and
books have been purchased
and are available
for assignment.
It can send assignments
up to the iTunes Store
and credit a particular app
or book to a user account.
When the user configures
their Apple ID
on a particular Apple device,
they'll see those assignments
in their purchase list and
can download the bits directly
from the store just as if they
had purchased them themselves.
And, also, the administrator
can send MDM commands
from the server to the devices
to say download this app
to make sure that it
is actually installed
on that particular device.
So, again, dive into a
number of topics related
to the Volume Purchase Program
to give you some advice on how
to best integrate this
program into your solutions.
Starting off again with where
should the different pieces
of truth reside?
And the VPP service itself
should really be the truth
for the status of
user enrollment,
whether a user has
accepted an invitation
and associate the their
Apple ID with the VPP user,
which licenses have
been purchased,
as I showed on the previous
slide, as well as tracking
in irrevocable book
assignments that have been made.
You're MDM server should
actually be the truth
for everything else including
revocable app assignments.
And you might be
wondering why shouldn't
that be in the VPP service?
Well if your MDM solution
supports group assignments,
you'll need to keep that
information in your MDM server
because there's no way to
store group information
in the VPP service.
So if you're going to be able to
reconstitute that, you're going
to need to have all that
within your database.
Let's talk a little bit
about account management.
When a particular administrator
provides their credentials,
their VPP account to your
solution, and you want
to establish that
initial connection
with the Volume Purchase
Program you're going to need
to check the client
context attribute.
And if it's empty that means
that no other server
has claimed this account
or is using this account.
And you should go
ahead and claim it
by providing the host name of
your server and a unique a GUID
so that you'll be able to tell
whether your server is still the
one managing.
If the client context
has a value
and it doesn't match the GUID
that you have for that server,
some other server is
actually using that account.
And you're going to want
to alert the administrator
that some other server is
managing the licenses tied
to this account and ask them
to confirm that they, in fact,
want this server to
take over that account.
That may, in fact, be the right
thing if they're transitioning
from one server to the next.
And then further, whenever you
re establish the connection
to the service, you need to
check client context again
to make sure that your server is
still the one that's connected
to this account.
If it doesn't match
any longer, you, again,
need to stop making
requests to the service
and alert the administrator
that this other host name
has now claimed this account
so they can take
appropriate action.
If I've mentioned
invitations already,
that's part of bootstrapping
this program is
that the administrator
needs it to invite each user
to link their Apple ID to
this particular VPP account
so that licenses
can be assigned.
We strongly recommend that you
do this invitation via MDM.
You can easily send
that invitation via an
MDM command directly
to an enrolled device.
It's much more secure
and reliable.
Email is a fall back if you
have a user you need to invite
that doesn't currently
have an enrolled device.
But there's a concern that
you need to be aware of that
because the invitation URL,
there's an example on screen,
is for the apple.com domain.
Many mail servers will
treat an email coming
from your server's domain,
including a URL from apple.com
as a phishing attack and
they filter them out.
There are a number
of alternative ways
to avoid this problem.
You could create your invitation
email URL that brings the user,
first, back to your MDM
server before redirected them
to the VPP URL.
Or you could integrate the
invitation process right
into your user portal
if you have one.
Let's spend a few
moments talking, again,
about user IDs relating to
Volume Purchase Program.
I showed this slide last year.
There are really 3 ideas of who
the user is from the perspective
of the MDM server, from the
perspective of the VPP service,
and the end user's Apple ID,
which your MDM server will never
see directly but will see a hash
of it to protect
the user's privacy.
Now, this is would be
very simple if we lived
in the ideal world
where each user had one
and only one Apple ID
associated with your VPP account
and would never change
that Apple ID.
In this case, there would be
a simple one to one mapping
between all 3 of these
representations of the user.
Sadly, as many of
you may be aware,
we don't live in an ideal world.
In the real world, multiple
VPP users can accept their
individual invitations
with the same Apple ID.
And you need to be aware
of the implications
of the sharing of Apple IDs.
Specifically if you've
assigned a license to a user
that than is connected to
that particular Apple ID.
If you revoke that assignment,
it's going to revoke it
from every Apple every VPP
user sharing that Apple ID.
Also, if you try to
assign an app or a book
to a VPP user that's
associated with an Apple ID
that already has that
app or book assigned,
that second assignment
will fail.
Another issue in the real
world is that users can,
after accepting an
invitation with one Apple ID,
can disassociate from that Apple
ID and associate and accept
that invitation with
a different Apple ID.
This becomes a problem if you've
assigned any irrevocable book
licenses to that Apple,
that retired Apple ID.
And you'll have to keep track
and think about whether you want
to allocate another
irrevocable book license
to the new Apple ID or not.
So the MDM server's
representation of the user,
the client user ID string,
is something that's
under your control.
And we strongly recommend
you pick a value
that will never change,
for example,
the user ID from your
directory services
where you're getting your
user and group information.
You shouldn't choose something
like an email address
which can change.
And it's very simple.
I had to have a slide with
some SQL on, I'm sorry.
It's very easy, then, to
look up which VPP account
that that particular MDM
user is associated with.
Whether it's just registered
and you've sent the invitation
or actually associated, whether
the user has accepted it.
And, finally, the representation
of the user's Apple ID who's
accepted the invitation takes
the form of an iTunes
store ID hash.
And you should track
this as soon
as a user has accepted
an invitation.
New in iOS 8, there's now a
MDM query, not just in iOS 8,
it's also in OS X Yosemite, a
query to get that hash value
so that you can know whether
the Apple ID that's configured
on a particular device changes.
You won't know exactly what the
Apple ID is but you'll be able
to tell if they've disassociated
and re-associated
with a different ID.
As I mentioned already on the
previous slide, you're going
to want to track those retired
values if the user switches
to a different Apple ID,
again, so you can keep track
of any irrevocable
book assignments.
There's another new change
that will allow you MDM vendors
to provide a better user
experience in your tools
for users outside the U.S. that
we now report the country code
that the account is tied to
when you get your information
down from the service so that
you can fetch the proper app
metadata, artwork, description,
app name from the
correct iTunes Store.
So managed apps is
not a new concept.
We've had it for a
couple of iOS releases.
It's a way for enterprises
to keep better control
over the data and documents
tied to particular apps.
It works with both App
Store and enterprise apps.
The managed apps must
be installed via MDM
with the install
application command
and with the management
flag set on the app itself.
One limitation is that if the
user has already installed an
app, the MDM server
cannot convert it
to manage retroactively.
However, the server
can, of course,
detect that an app is unmanaged
and then alert the administrator
so they could take action
outside of MDM, if necessary,
to have the user delete that app
and the MDM server
push it out again.
Managed apps work with Managed
Open In a new feature in iOS 7
to help, again, prevent
data leakage
from managed apps
to unmanaged apps.
So that if you have
a particular app
that has sensitive documents,
you can treat it as managed.
Turn on Managed Open In, and
then users will not be able
to open those documents
in other apps
like well, I won't name any.
So you might imagine, I
talked about filling gaps
and eliminating inconsistencies.
We have managed apps so what
are we introducing in iOS 8?
Well, of course, managed books.
And just like managed
apps, managed books works
with both iBookstore books where
you can, just like managed apps,
tell the device to download
a particular iBookstore book
and treat it as managed.
That that book must
be published,
purchased via VPP even
if the user has it.
One difference between managed
books and managed apps is
that you can retroactively
manage books
in contrast to manage apps.
Even if the user
has it installed.
This is very useful
in schools to ensure
that a particular
title is installed,
make sure the students
have all their work
and the dog didn't eat it.
Turning to enterprise books, you
can, just like enterprise apps,
can install the MDM
and remove PDFs, ePubs,
and iBooks Author books.
These documents or
these titles are stored
in a different location
than iBookstore books
with Class C data protection.
There are also a
number of restrictions
that we're introducing
in iOS 8 to, again,
give institutions
more confidence
that the sensitive
data will be protected
and not escape their control.
They can disable iCloud backups
of these enterprise books
so that they just stay on the
device where they're installed
and also disable the
user's highlights and notes
on that title from being
synced to other devices.
For you MDM vendors out there,
it's going to be pretty straight
forward to implement this.
Just like there's an install
application MDM command,
there's now an Install
Media MDM command
where if it's a managed
iBookstore book,
you'll just specify
the iTunes store ID.
And if it's an enterprise
book, you'll specify a URL back
to your server to
download the bits.
You need to specify a persistent
ID that's under your control
so that you can uniquely
identify each enterprise book
that's being installed
and its kind
and then the matching
remove media command.
There are a few limitations.
Just like managed apps, is
requires the app installation
and the end enrollment, right,
to be able to install
managed books.
And managing iBookstore books
requires that you've, again,
purchased it via VPP and
that the App Store is enabled
on the device that you're
pushing an enterprise book to.
Another distinction
between managed apps
and managed books is that the
MDM query to obtain the list
of installed books will
only show managed books
and not every book that's
installed by the user
to preserve user privacy.
And finally, again, to allow
the institutions to keep control
over these enterprise books
and their sensitive data,
enterprise books cannot
be synced off a device
using iTunes.
So turning from what's
new in iOS 8 to what's new
in OS X Yosemite, we're
going to fill another gap.
And we are, have
added the ability
to install non App Store
apps via MDM on OS X.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
You can thank you Jussi
when he gets back up here.
So you can specify a signed flat
package containing an app via
this MDM command, the install
application MDM command
which is now supported on OS
X for non App Store books.
And, in fact, your MDM
solution can do the same thing
that Profile Manager has done
that you can support the
administrator's providing you
with just a .app bundle
as long as you package it
up as a signed flat package and
send that over the MDM command.
So without any further ado,
instead of talking more
about this, I'd like to ask
Jussi and Mark to come back up
and show you installing
and removing enterprise
apps and books.
>> All right.
Thank you, Todd.
And I'm just going to go
into my iBooks library.
So here we have some books
that we already downloaded.
I've been a keen reader
of the Human Interface
Guidelines, apparently.
And we just downloaded the
Swift book so we're going
to learn some new things.
And Mark's now going to
push a PDF for the device.
So this is going to
be an enterprise book.
And this is will have
the same open rules
as any other managed
assets on the device.
So we'll have data protection
between applications.
And we won't be able to
share the book anywhere else.
So this our fancy new PDF
that just got installed.
And now, since this is a
managed book controlled
by our MDM solution, Mark
can also remove the book.
So Mark can now remove the book
and it disappears
from our bookshelf.
So that's managing
books on iOS 8.
And we're.
[ Applause ]
Thank you.
And on iOS we've had the Apple
Teaching Store enterprise
application so that we have
our fancy new Swift application
here, ACME Hub.
But as Todd mentioned,
we also have support
for installing applications
on OS X.
So here we go into our
Launchpad and Mark is now going
to install our fancy ACME app
onto the OS X client
and no hands.
This is all installed
by the system.
So sparkles fly and the ACME
app landed on the system.
So over here's OS X using
the DEP app installation.
So thank you, Mark.
And now back to Todd.
>> All right.
Thank you very much, guys.
That app was written
using Swift, right?
>> Of course.
>> They stayed up all night.
All right.
So Mark and Jussi just showed
installing a PDF on iOS 8 device
and removing it as well as
installing an enterprise app
on a Mac running OS X Yosemite.
So let's proceed on to
our final section and talk
about ongoing management
of devices.
We're going to complete
the Activation Lock story
to show you, to talk
about how you use
that bypass code you
obtained at enrollment time.
Talk a little bit about
integrating you're MDM solutions
with external data sources.
Talk about something new
called MDM service config.
We'll come on to that
in a few minutes.
And, then again, conclude
with what's coming
in this year's OS releases.
So one thing to keep in mind
with Activation Lock is,
it's a little bit different
from some other services.
When you get the device
information query,
and Mark showed this
in Profile Manager
when he re fetched
the device information
and it reflected the change
and Activation Lock status.
There's a key that tells you
whether the device thinks it's
Activation Locked.
And there's a request that
you send not to the device,
but to our activation server
to clear the Activation Lock
and specify the bypass
code that you have.
Now, because that request
doesn't go to the device,
the device isn't checking
with the activation server,
it's not going to know
that it's been cleared.
So it's going to
continue to report
that it's Activation
Locked to your MDM server.
Also, even after
you have cleared
on the activation server,
the user, if they log out of
or remove their Apple
ID and log in again,
that will re enable
Activation Lock.
So you want to definitely
keep hold
of that bypass code even
if you've cleared it.
This isn't going to,
in the real world,
going to usually be an issue
because typically you're going
to use this when you have
the device in your hands.
But you definitely want
to keep that bypass codes
because you might
need to use it again.
All right.
So one of the most important
external data sources
that your MDM server
needs to integrate
with is directory services.
There are a number
of different ones
that your server
probably supports.
However, compared to
the database that's back
in your MDM solution,
most directory services
have some capabilities
which make them limited
in this context.
Usually you can't get a full
enumeration of their contents.
And there's not an easy
way to discover the changes
from the last time you
fetched some subsection
of those contents.
They can be intermittently
available and slow.
So you're going to want
to need to mirror some
of the information
into your server.
In contrast, we've designed both
the Device Enrollment Program
service and the Volume Purchase
Program service to be simple
and efficient to mirror that
data into your MDM solution.
You can fully enumerate
the licenses for VPP
or the device list for the
Device Enrollment Program.
And it's easy to get the
changes from the last time
that you got the enumeration.
So you should definitely
mirror this information
down in your database and
not use those services
for live access.
Similarly, you're
going to want to mirror
in the directory
services information
to get better performance
and reliability
and all the benefits
of your database.
But definitely leave
the authentication piece
in directory services.
It's less frequently
used, and you need
to have a single source
of truth for that.
Also, you're not going to want
to mirror your entire
directory services
into your database, of course.
You want to just mirror in
records that are related to MDM.
Next, I want to talk about
a new concept that those
of you familiar with the
StoreBag from iTunes,
we could also call
this the URL bag.
It's something that would
make it much easier for tools
like Apple Configurator and
other device management tools
to just ask the MDM server what
information they can obtain
from it.
We specify this new
URI MDM service config
that any tool could then make
an unauthenticated HTTPS request
to your server and ask for it to
provide a UTF8 JSON encoded hash
for example, the URL for your
MDM server's Device Enrollment
Program enrollment.
This would allow a tool
like Apple Configurator
to make it much easier for
administrator to use it
to configure settings
because they wouldn't have
to type the entire
enrollment URL.
They'd only have to type
the domain of your server.
And it could then ask the
server what's your URL
and complete that for the user.
So we're going to
be implementing this
in Profile Manager and we strong
we would really like to see
that in your MDM
solutions as well.
So, again, let's turn to what's
coming new in iOS 8 in terms
of MDM commands and queries.
We've seen some of
these already.
But it's now possible for
supervised devices to tell them
to set their device
name via MDM.
You can also clear the
restrictions passcode
in the user has themselves
configured
in the settings UI
restrictions and set a passcode.
That would have prevented,
in the past the administrator
from overriding those
restrictions.
Now, you can send an MDM command
that removes those settings
and allows the MDM server to
configure its own settings.
We've already seen
the new install
and remove media commands
as well as the query
that allows you to ask which
iTunes account is configured
on the device via the
iTunes Store ID hash.
But it's also now possible
to query the device to ask,
when did it last
back up to iCloud?
There are a number of new
payloads and additions
to existing payloads in iOS 8.
There's a new VPN
connection type.
We've added new plug in content
filters to expand on the built
in content filters that
we shipped in iOS 7.
There's a new payload,
called Managed Domains,
which we're going to show
you a little bit later
that you can have managed
email and web domains that work
in conjunction with managed apps
and books and managed open end
and help institutions
keep their data secure.
I think they actually mentioned,
Craig actually mentioned
the message S/MIME switch
in mail yesterday.
And it's possible to configure
whether that's available
to you user for both
email and exchange.
You can specify a certificate
in the single sign-on payload
that allows automatic refreshing
of the Kerberos credentials
without the user having
to take any action.
And there are a number
of new restrictions,
both for unsupervised devices,
the 5 at the top including
disabling the it's a really cool
feature Handoff, but that also
may worry certain institutions
about data that they consider
sensitive transitioning
from a managed device to another
device outside of their control.
We also already saw
the restrictions
on enterprise books.
And there are 2 new
supervised restrictions
that you can prevent the
user from erasing all content
and settings and wiping
the device and undoing all
that hard work you did
to configure that device.
As well as a pair
for the MDM command
that once you've
cleared the restrictions,
you can disable the user
from actually configuring them
using the device UI in settings.
Speaking of the device
UI in settings,
the iOS team has
done a lot of work
to dramatically improve
the end user experience
to see the effects
of an MDM enrollment
and any configuration profiles.
An MDM relationship is now
represented with a single item
that coalesces all the
profiles that are installed via
that MDM channel showing
all the settings, apps,
and books that have come down
via that MDM relationship
with the most important
things likes accounts and apps
and books and restrictions
at the top.
What this also means is
that users cannot no
longer cherry pick
and remove individual profiles
that the MDM server has
delivered to the device
because they're just
not shown that way.
Another improvement
in the settings UI is
that if there are particular
features like the camera
or in the restrictions UI in
settings, it will indicate
to the user that this particular
feature has been disabled due
to a profile being installed.
So that they aren't confused
and need to come to Genius Bar
to ask them why their
camera's disabled.
It's also much easier to see
all the certificate details
that have been delivered
via MDM.
And finally provision profiles
no longer appear at all
in settings because it's handled
completely automatically.
The device will automatically
prune expired provision profiles
when they're no longer needed.
[ Applause ]
One less thing to worry about.
Turning to OS X Yosemite,
you'll see that we have support
for a number of the
new payloads.
I already talked about on
iOS 8 as well as the query
to determine which iTunes
account has been configured
on that particular Mac.
And we also have plugged another
gap in adding the command
that tells a Mac to
initiate AirPlay Mirroring
to a destination.
So without further ado,
I'm going to ask the guys
to come back up and show you a
few things that I just talked
about and completing
the device duty cycle.
>> So we go to the settings and
we'll see what we have active
as manage settings
from our MDM server.
So you'll notice that you
don't have a profile setting
under general anymore.
This is called Device
Management.
If I just had regular
configuration profiles
installed, this tab
would be called Profiles.
If I have both Device
Management setting
and Profiles installed it will
be called Device Management
and Profiles.
So but since we only have the
MDM enrollment profile here,
I'm going to look into that.
And, as you notice, this now
a non-removable MDM profile.
And you'll notice that
every single profile
that the server has
pushed is now collated
into some sensical category.
So we have restrictions
so you can tell
which restrictions have been
configured by the server.
And we have applications that
have been installed here.
And we have also accounts
that have been configured.
So we don't show the
individual profiles
that actually configured this.
We just collate all
this information
so that's it's more readily
accessible and discoverable.
And in more details,
as Todd mentioned,
we have better information
about certificates.
We can now actually see the full
signatures and how they keyed it
up so it's not just
like dot, dot, dot.
And you can also
have information
about other settings
that come down.
And here we have
managed domains.
So I'm going to show
you managed domains.
How those are working in mail.
So we are in ACME, Inc.
in acmeinc.private.
And as I'm going to
start composing an email,
I'm going to pick
mark@mdm.apple.com.
And this is now Mark's address.
This is not something that I
should probably be sending email
to so it's marked as red.
If I use a different address,
use my acme in private mail
that's marked as a valid email
that meets our email rules.
And this also applies
to my sending account
so since I have configured
this device for iCloud,
I also have my iCloud account.
So my iCloud account
is also marked
as not something I should
be sending mail with.
So that's managed
domains inside mail.
And then we are basically
done with the device.
So now we can return
this device to service
so the next user is going
to grab this machine.
And what Mark's going to do,
he's going to issue an erase
command onto the device.
So basically the user has left
the company or has graduated
from the school and
magic happens now.
So we're going to unplug
this device and plug
to a different device.
So here we go.
And now we have just
received the same device
and we're back in
the home screen.
I'm going to as a new
user, I'm going to walk
through the setup screens
and configure this device.
So.
>> This a device that's come
back for the duty cycle.
And I've got the Activation Lock
bypass code for this device.
And so he's just
going to walk through,
go ahead, and set it up.
And when he encounters the fact
that it's locked, I'll be able
to clear it; and he'll be able
to actually finish
activation and continue on.
>> Right. So as soon
as the device talks
to the Apple services
again, I'm getting prompted
for some random Apple ID because
the previous user had enabled
iCloud even though this
was a supervised device,
we had allowed people
to use find my iPad
and now I have no idea what
this user's account is,
so Mark has just issued an
Activation Lock unlock command
from Profile Manager
and if I now go back
to the activation phase, now
I'm going to prompted to enroll
in my MDM server, again all
ACME help desk for an issue.
And my next user is now
going to get prompted
to enter their password,
and we're good to go.
So that's the duty cycle
of using iPads with MDM
and Device Enrollment Program.
So thank you, Mark,
and back to Todd.
>> So Jussi just gave you a
brief tour of the new easier
to understand user interface
in settings in iOS 8.
Make it easier for a user to
understand what the impacts
of that MDM relationship
is on their device.
Showed you how managed
email domains work
to help users prevent data
leakage sending documents
to the wrong email addresses.
We also showed how to use the
Activation Lock bypass code
that we captured when enrolling
device to enable the device
to be wiped and returned
to service
by completing the duty cycle.
And, again, getting that device
through Device Enrollment
Program settings
to reenroll in your
MDM solution.
That brings us to the
end of our session.
I'd like to sum up for, again,
the different audiences
for this session.
If you're an administrator,
you should use the Device
Enrollment Program if you want
to enroll your devices
wirelessly or Apple Configurator
if you want to do it wired.
You should use the Volume
Purchase Program managed
distribution and
managed apps and books
to distribute content
to your devices.
If you are a MDM
solution provider,
please support all
these services:
Device Enrollment Program,
Volume Purchase Program,
and Activation Lock
management as well
as all the new futures
we talked about today
in both iOS 8 and OS X Yosemite.
If you're an app developer,
for your enterprise we've got
this great new page that talks
about how you can use
iOS to the best effect
within your enterprise
doing in-house development.
We have a number of
resources, again,
for developers both
MDM and app developers.
Our documentation
of or MDM protocol,
the configuration
profile reference,
the developer forums for MDM.
And if there are any
administrators out there,
we've got documentation for
the Device Enrollment Program
and Apple Configurator and a
number of discussion boards
that are great places to ask
your questions and get help,
both from your fellow
administrators
and Apple representatives.
There are a number of additional
sessions this week including 2
following this session right
here in Pacific Heights.
Some of our colleagues that help
make that great new UI in iOS
and implement a lot
of these features.
And with that, I will thank
you for your attention
and hope you have a
great rest of the show.
Thank you.