>> Good morning!
Hi there!
[ Applause ]
Welcome to Session
704, "Building Apps
for Enterprise and Education."
My name is Dave Rahardja.
I'm a software developer in
iOS, and today I'll be joined
by Alex Botkin, who
also works with me
on iOS device management.
So building apps
for the enterprise
and for the education
market really is not
that much different
from building apps
in the App Store, right?
You've got to get an app
that solves a problem.
You have to have an app
that is well-designed.
And it's got to be a
pleasure to use for the user.
But in an enterprise,
you've got some unique
requirements usually.
Your client's devices are very
likely going to be managed
under mobile device management.
These devices may be supervised.
And if you're not familiar
with what supervised means,
we'll talk about
that in a minute.
And there may be special use
cases that are kind of peculiar
to the business and
education market.
So today what I'm going to
present to you is some tips
and tricks to help you to
write your next enterprise
and education apps
so that they're
that much more pleasurable
to use
and makes you a much better
developer in this field.
So let's get started by talking
about mobile device management.
So what's mobile
device management?
Mobile device management is a
protocol that's built into iOS
and OS X that allows a server
to remotely manage that device.
A server that's managing a
device using MDM can install
network access such
as VPN or Wi-Fi.
It can install accounts
such as email,
calendar contacts and so forth.
New in iOS 8, they can now
install books such as PDFs,
ePubs and iBooks
Author as well as books
from the iBookstore
and manage them.
They can install single
sign-on using Kerberos.
And new in iOS 8, Kerberos can
now use an identity certificate
so that their identity
can be renewed
without the user ever having
to type in a password.
[ Applause ]
And most important to you
today, an MDM server can install
and configure your apps,
so this is very important.
And here's your first
tip for today.
Allow MDM to configure
your apps.
And we'll talk about how
that can be done
exactly in a few minutes.
So mobile device management.
Let's talk a few minutes about
managed apps and accounts.
So this is a little bit of
a terminology that we have.
Anything that MDM installs
on iOS, we call "managed".
These include everything that
you saw from the last slide.
Managed apps.
Managed accounts.
In iOS 8, as you know, you
can install third party
keyboard extensions.
The way you install third
party keyboard extensions
on iOS 8 is you install an app
that has an extension in it.
If that app was installed
using MDM,
that keyboard extension is then
considered as managed as well.
Of course in iOS 8 we have
this great new feature called
"document providers," thank you.
It's a really powerful feature.
And if you install
an app that happens
to vend a document provider
extension, such as an app
that gives access to your
intranet resources, or you know,
your network file storage, that
app also becomes "managed."
So this is in contrast
with things
that the user installed
themselves.
If the user goes out
and installs an app
from the App Store on their
own BYOD device for example,
those things are
considered not managed.
So we have managed, which is
the stuff that MDM installed.
And you have not managed, which
is what the user installs.
So why do we do this?
Well it helps iOS to
restrict data flow
so that your enterprise
data doesn't flow
into your user's data
space and vice versa.
So for example, if you are in a
managed app and you are looking
at a document and you tap open
in - you know that list of apps
that shows up on the
bottom of your screen?
All the apps that can
handle that document.
That list of apps will
be filtered down so that,
because you started
from a managed app,
only other managed apps
and accounts will
show up on that list.
And we do this automatically.
Conversely, when you
are in an unmanaged app
and you tap open
in, the list of apps
that you see will not
include managed apps.
So in that way, without
the user ever having
to do any switching
of, you know,
work and home, we
protect your data.
And we do this everywhere.
Emails. So you can't forward
a corporate email using your
iCloud account for example.
We do it in calendars.
In attachments.
We do it - in iOS 8 we have
managed domains in Safari.
So if you specify certain
domains in Safari as belonging
to your corporate intranet,
documents that you download
from those domains will
only go into managed apps.
Make sense?
[ Applause ]
And managed apps get
access to Per-App VPN.
This is a feature
we've had since iOS 7,
and it's proven very popular.
And what this is,
just as a review,
is that managed apps will
get the data tunneled
through this VPN, but
not anything else,
not the user's data.
So your VPN carries your
data and not the user's data.
Yet another way to separate
enterprise and personal data.
So what's the takeaway?
Rely on iOS to manage the data
flow between apps and accounts.
Don't try to do it yourself.
iOS has a great way of allowing
this to happen in a very clean
and intuitive way,
using the fact
that you're managing
a device over MDM.
All right.
So that's MDM.
Next let's talk about
supervised devices.
So what's this?
A supervised device is a device
that has been activated into,
you know, a supervision.
It tells iOS that the device
is owned by the enterprise.
This is in contrast to a
device that's owned by a user
such as Bring Your Own Device.
Right? Supervision can
only be set at activation.
There are two ways to set
supervision during activation.
The first way, and you saw
this in the keynote yesterday,
is Device Enrollment Program.
With DEP, devices that
your enterprise purchased
from Apple can be configured
so that they're supervised
and enrolled into your
MDM right out of the box.
You don't have to
touch it at all.
You hand the shrink-wrapped
box to the end user.
They unbox it.
They walk through
the setup assistant.
And they're supervised
and enrolled.
The second way is Apple
Configurator, which requires you
to take the device out
and plug it into USB.
Depending on your use
case and your scenarios,
one of these should
serve your needs.
So why do we supervise devices?
Well, I'll tell you why.
You get access to a whole
bunch of different restrictions
and controls that we only allow
on enterprise-owned devices.
Such as Always-On
VPN -- new in iOS 8.
Global HTTP proxy.
Third-party content
filter, also new in iOS 8.
Single App Mode, which locks
your device into a single app.
Perfect for kiosks.
And we'll see some
examples of that later.
We've got restriction
to prevent the user
from erasing their own device
-- anyone with students here?
And preventing enabling
restrictions -- also students.
When you're local, you
know, in your settings.
And many more.
The takeaway here is
please supervise your
enterprise-owned devices.
If you own it, supervise it.
You won't regret it.
OK. So for the next part
of our presentation,
we're going to show
you some example apps
that may illustrate some of
the use cases that you may face
when developing apps
for the enterprise.
The first app we're going
to show you is a
Document Access app.
This app is designed to
access a secure document,
like a sensitive document maybe
over your intranet, and store it
on the device in
a secure manner.
The second app that we're going
to see is a Point of Sale app.
This may be something like you
use in a retail store to check
out customers, you
know, buying your items.
And the third will be something
that education may use,
an Assessment app where
the student uses your app
to take exams.
All right, so three
example apps.
Document Access.
Point of Sale.
And Assessment.
And along the way, we will
illustrate some of the things
that we talked about earlier.
So let's start with
the first app.
Okay, Secure Document Access.
Again, this app retrieves
a document securely
and displays it to the end user.
All right.
So let's talk a little bit
about MDM App Configuration.
So you remember a few
minutes ago I talked
about allowing an MDM server
to configure your apps.
Well how do you do this?
It's really very simple.
All you have to do is to
watch for the special key
in NSUserDefaults
com.apple.configuration.managed.
When you read this key
from your NSUserDefaults,
you get a dictionary
that magically appears
when the MDM server pushes a
configuration down to your app.
So the MDM server
pushes down a dictionary,
and you can access
it using this key.
Your app can then respond
to configuration changes.
So why do you want to do this?
Well what's the first
thing that you want to do
when you install an app?
You want to configure its URL
probably, hit some server.
You may have an app that is
deployed in more than one branch
of your business, and
you want to configure it
for that particular location.
Instead of having the end user
read instructions and say,
"Oh tap this and tap that
and go here and go there.
Type this URL in.
What could go wrong?"
You define your own keys and
say, "Hey if you install my app
over MDM, push down these
keys and I'll see them
and I'll use them for my app
without any user intervention."
Right? So app configuration.
So URLs are great, so in
this example we are going
to do some URL configuration.
And a trusted list of server
root certificates is also
very important.
It helps you to prevent
man-in-the-middle attacks.
And we'll show you how to
do that in the code example.
I'm going to ask
Alex to come up here.
And he's going to show
you a little code example
that demonstrates MDM
App Configuration.
>> So, good morning developers.
So, we're going to switch
over to our demo laptop.
We're going to look
at some code.
So our first application
that we're looking
at today is our Secured
Document Access App.
Which we've called
"Secretive" in our example.
With MDM App Configuration,
the most important thing
that you need to do is to
make sure that you register
for the NSUserDefaultsDid
ChangeNotification.
This is the notification
that will be sent
out when an MDM app
configuration is pushed
down to your device.
So you need to be listening
to this notification,
and then rereading the
defaults when you receive it.
So in our example I
have a ViewController.
When the ViewController
loads, I'm going to register
for this notification.
And every time I receive it, I'm
going to call re-default values
so that I can get my
values back again.
And in this example, I'm going
to load up re-default values
as soon as I get the view up,
so that I can get the
first initial load.
So in my example here - so
you remember that we talked
about the
com.apple.configuration.manage
key?
This is the key in
NSUserDefault where we're going
to be stuffing the NSDictionary
with your configuration.
And so you'll notice that I've
suggested some other keys here.
And in my dictionary
I'm going to have a key
which has a string
for my server URL.
Which is going to be the URL
for the document I'm
going to be retrieving.
And you'll also notice
that I have a key
for a server root certificate.
We'll get to this later
in the presentation,
but that's also why
I'm going to be pushing
down in this MDM
App Configuration.
So you'll notice
some re-defaults.
All I do is I call
into NSUserDefaults.
I make sure I call into
that configuration key.
And then from the
dictionary I pull
out the relevant
information that I need,
such as the server URL.
An important thing to note is
do put error checking on this
to make sure that you're
not loading bad values.
And so now what we'll do is
I'll switch over to the iPad
and I'll push down an examp
MDM App Configuration.
So you'll notice
that I have my app
over here called "Secretive."
And when I open it up, I don't
have an MDM App Configuration
here currently.
I've installed the
managed app, but you know,
right now I don't
have my server URL.
So over on my MDM server, I've
loaded up a command to send
down the magical
app configuration.
And so I'm going to send
that notification down.
And you'll notice that when
I receive the notification
for NSUserDefaultsDidChange,
I automatically started
up a session and
retrieved this document
from the server URL
that I was given.
So that is MDM App
Configuration.
And we'll return to Dave.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks Alex.
It's like magic.
Your apps get configured
correctly,
without having your
user do anything.
It's great.
I hope you caught that
little remark that Alex made.
"Please validate the input
that you get from the server."
Because as far as you are
concerned as an app writer,
the server is an unknown network
entity, and they're going
to be pushing down keys
that may be misformatted
or of the wrong type.
So please validate
the keys and make sure
that you understand
what they are.
Also publish what you understand
so that the server admins
can configure you correctly.
So that's MDM App Configuration.
Next. All right.
Let's talk about Single Sign-on.
Single sign-on is a Kerberos -
we offer a Kerberos
single sign-on on iOS
that can be applied by the MDM
server across the entire system.
So that once you log
in, you will be logged
in across several different apps
when you're accessing the
same network resource.
So using Single Sign-on
couldn't be easier.
You just have to
use HTTP or HTTPS.
Which most of you probably are.
If you use NSURLConnection,
or NSURLSession,
Kerberos Single Sign-on
is free to you.
So here's the takeaway.
Don't do anything, and
it works; it's great.
The MDM server will
apply the configuration,
and your apps will either
get a 200 OK or a 401 Fail.
If it's a 200 OK, assume that
the resource is available
to you and just use it.
Of course your apps may provide
alternate authentication,
such as you know, HTTP Digest.
And Kerberos authentication
will be attempted first.
And if that doesn't
work, iOS will fall back
to reporting an error to your
app, and you get the chance
to authenticate using
a different scheme.
So don't do anything.
No example.
Next. Okay.
Here is something that we've
gotten asked several times.
How do I download files securely
all the way from my server
down to the flash on iOS?
As you may or may not know,
all files that you create
from your app already get
this protection level.
FileProtectionCompleteUntil
FirstUserAuthentication.
So just a recap, this means
that the file is encrypted.
Unreadable after you
restart your iOS device.
Once you enter your
passcode, the device -
the file is readable
and it remains readable
across device locks.
Until you restart
the device again.
So what we want to do is we
want to upgrade this file.
If you do nothing and you use,
you know, just write a file
to disk, this is what
you're going to get.
But we want to upgrade that.
So we want to have
the file be specified
as data protection complete.
Which means that whenever
you lock the device,
the file becomes
unreadable, cryptographically.
And the next time the user
enters their passcode,
the file becomes
readable again etcetera.
So we're going
to use NSURLSession
data task to do this.
And as a little bonus here,
so maybe this document
is extra sensitive,
you don't want this document to
appear in your user's backup.
So iCloud backup
or iTunes backup.
So we're going to show
you how to mark files
so that they don't
get backed up.
All right, let's switch over
back to Alex and he's going
to show you some
code to do this.
>> So back on our demo machine.
You'll notice that we have
on our ViewController set it
as implementing the delegates
of NSURLSession and
NSURLSessionData.
And the reason we've
done this is we're going
to use those delegate callbacks
during our secure download.
So down here in SecureURLSession
that I have set up here,
I'm going to take that
server URL that I pulled
down from MDM App Configuration,
and I going to create an
NSURLSessionDataTask right here.
And you'll notice that I've left
the completionHandler as a nil.
And the reason I've done
this is by setting nil
for the completionHandler,
I will get the delegate
callbacks for the data task.
And that's the most
important thing for me.
So in URLSession
DataTaskDid ReceiveResponse.
I'm going to get this call as
soon as we make the connection,
and I'm going to create
a file where I'm going
to download my strategic
plan PDF.
And so you'll notice that I call
NSFileManager defaultManager
createFileAtPath
contents and attributes.
And the attribute
I'm going to pass
into it is this
NSFileProtectionKey.
And in that NSFileProtectionKey
I'm going to specify
that I want NSFile protection
complete and less open.
What this means is that
the file will be unreadable
when the device is locked,
unless the file is already open
when the device locks.
So while I'm downloading
I'm going
to set the attribute to that.
And so the other important thing
that we've mentioned already is
that we want to turn
off file backup.
And so what I'm going to
do is I'm going to set
onto the file URL
a resource value.
The key I'm going to set it
on is NSURLisExcluded
fromBackupKey.
And this key will make it
so that this file
will not be backed
up in iTunes or in iCloud.
And so we'll go
on in URLSessionDataTask
to receive data.
This delegate method
is going to be called,
every time I receive
new data from my server.
And I'm just going
to store it all
into that file I
created earlier.
And then at the very end
in URLSession
taskDidCompleteWithError.
I'm going to make sure
there were no errors.
And if there were no errors
I'm going to then change it
so that the attribute
for NSFileProtectionKey
is changed to complete.
Because at this point I decided,
you know, when the device locks,
I want this file
to be unreadable.
And that's pretty much it.
I would show you the demo,
but we've already shown you
that in MDM App Configurations.
So let's go back to Dave.
>> Thanks Alex.
So Downloading to a Secure File.
Here's how you do it.
You create an NSURLSession.
Create a file, when the
request begins, create a file
with dataProtection
CompleteUnlessOpen
so that you can continue
to write data to that file
as you're downloading it,
even if your device is locked.
When the file has
completely downloaded,
upgrade that protection
to FileProtectionComplete.
And as you can tell,
as you can see,
there's an NSURLMethod
you can call to set a bit
that says don't backup this
file to iTunes and iCloud.
All right.
Next. HTTPS Certificate Pinning.
We all know that HTTPS
is a way for the client
to tell whether it's talking
to the correct server.
This only works
if the certificate
chain is trustworthy.
So one of the things that we
usually do is we can specify
for this connection that
only these certificates are
to be trusted and not any other
certificate in your database
that may otherwise be
trusted, for example, Safari.
And to do this of
course you need HTTPS.
You need to specify your
trusted root certificates during
HTTPS authentication.
And you do this to prevent
man-in-the-middle attacks
that pretend to be your server.
And here's the takeaway - use
certificate pinning instead
of doing things like
SSID detection.
Especially in, you know,
like retail scenarios.
A lot of people use SSIDs or
some other kind of heuristic
to tell whether or not they're
talking to the correct server.
Instead of doing that,
make sure you are talking
to the correct server regardless
of the environment
that you're in.
All right.
To show you a short example of
how we do certificate pinning,
let's switch back to
Alex and his code.
>> So you will remember
that I mentioned that we had
that root certificate
key that I set.
So when I push down the
MDM App Configuration,
I push down the data for my
server's root certificate.
Because I want to check to make
sure that I'm not connecting
to the wrong server, and verify
that my users are connecting
to the server I want them to.
So you will notice that
I have here a method
that I've implemented called
URLSession didReceiveChallenge
with completionHandler.
And this is going to
be called when I try
and connect to my HTTPS server.
And when I try and connect,
I want to double check
that the authentication
method that was
in the challenge's protection
space is a NSURLAuthentication
MethodServerTrust.
If so, I'm going to get the
SecTrustRef from the server,
which is in challenge.protection
Space.serverTrust.
The next thing I'm going
to do is I'm going to load
up that root certificate that I
got from MDM App Configuration.
In this example,
I've already loaded
that when I did the
NSUserDefaultsReadback.
I put it into a variable
called self -
or into
serverRootCertificateData.
So I'm going to load
up that data.
And I'm going to create
a SecCertificate with it.
And I want to double check
that the certificate
was created correctly
by making sure that's not null.
If so, I'm going to then
set the anchor certificates
on the server's challenge
trust that I got.
The reason I do this
is I want to make sure
that I only trust the root
certificate I sent down.
I don't want to trust any
of the default certificates
that are included
in the iOS device.
And by saying the root
anchor certificates,
I can exclude them.
You'll notice that I've called -
also have this method
SecTrustSetAnchor
CertificatesOnly.
If I wanted to make it so
that I also trust the default
certificates installed
on the device,
I would set this yes
value at the end to no.
If you are only setting it
for the anchor certificates
that you trust, you do
not have to set this.
I've only done it
in this example
to show you how you can trust
the device's certificates
if you want to.
And so the last thing that
I'm going to do is I'm going
to do a SecTrustEvaluate with
the serversChallengeTrust
and I'm going to
get a trust result.
From that trust result I'm going
to make sure that, you know,
I didn't receive any errors.
And make sure that the
SecTrustResult is either
unspecified or proceed.
And then if I find out that
I do trust this certificate,
or if I've turned off
certificate pinning,
I'm going to automatically just
say, call the completionHandler
with NSURLSessionAuth
ChallengeUseCredential
and give it the credential
that the server gave me.
If I don't trust
the certificate,
I will call instead
completionHandler
NSURLSessionAuthChallengeReject
ProtectionSpace.
And that will tell the
app that no, I'm not going
to allow you to download this.
So in our example, we'll
go back to the iPad again.
You'll notice I've already
downloaded this file.
In settings I've set up a pin
here called certificate pinning,
and I'm going to turn it on.
The next thing I'm going to
do is - oop they already went
through this, so let
me just reset this.
So when I call into
the app - yeah,
so you'll notice,
ignore the crash.
With this, when I called back
into the app it tried to load
up the document again
from the server.
And you'll notice
that it's telling me
that my certificate
pinned by the server -
the certificate presented by
the server is not the same
as my pin certificate.
Let me go back to my server,
and I'm going to change it
so that it presents
the right certificate.
So I've set up my server;
I've fixed the certificate.
Everything's good.
So I'm going to click
on my refresh.
And when I refresh, the pin
certificate was correct this
time, and so I was able
to load the document.
And so that is how you
do certificate pinning.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks Alex.
HTTPS Certificate
Pinning assures you
that there's no
man-in-the-middle attack
with your connection
to your trusted server.
So what have we learned
from the first example app?
The Secure Document Viewer?
We learned that MDM App
Configuration is awesome.
It's magical.
Server can configure
your apps just right.
The user doesn't have to do it.
And you can offer keys to the
server admin to configure,
to set up your app just
the way they'd like it.
By the way, app configuration
can be delivered
as you're installing the app.
There is no race between app
installation and configuration.
We also learned that Single
Sign-on is also awesome.
Because you don't have to
do anything and it works.
All you have to do
is use HTTP or HTTPS.
And if your admin has configured
Single Sign-on on the device,
then it will just work or
you will get an auth failure.
We learned how to download files
securely using NSURLSession
DataTask and setting the
correct protection level
at different parts of
the download as well
as excluding from backup.
And, of course, we saw how to
pin our HTTPS certificates.
So that's our first app.
All right, next app.
Point of sale.
For this example we're
going to show you a little -
maybe a device that a sales
associate might carry.
So we have a scanner on
the left-hand side here
on the tab bar which
will scan barcodes.
And we have a catalog that
lets them look up prices
for products, etcetera.
Baby clothes.
So the first thing I
want to talk to you
about is Single App Mode.
Single App Mode is a way that an
MDM server can lock the device
into just your app.
You can send a command down
and tell the device
just run this app.
If the app crashes,
it relaunches the app.
If the user presses
the Home button,
this gets stuck in the app.
So that's all in
Single App Mode.
We'll show that later
in a later example.
But first, I'd like
to talk about iBeacon.
So iBeacon is awesome.
It gives you context.
It tells your device,
it tells your app
that you're near
something, right?
You're near something
that you specify.
So you can use iBeacon to
provide your app with context.
In this case, for the
Point of Sale app,
we want to provide
the app the knowledge
that you're actually using
the barcode scanner near the
checkout register, right?
So if you take the
device elsewhere,
they will not allow you to
scan prices, to scan barcodes.
So using iBeacon in conjunction
with other core location
technologies such as, you know,
GPS and location, gives you
a really fine-grained control
over how your app is used.
And it gives you an ability
using MDM App Configuration
to let the admins
configure your apps
so that your app
can only be used
in this particular retail store.
Or in that particular context.
Right? So here's a tip.
Use iBeacon to verify your
location-sensitive operation.
So now I'm going to hand it off
to Alex again, and he's going
to show you a little example.
>> So for our point of sale app,
I have a [inaudible] app called
"Moolah," which is for
selling baby clothes.
And so in my example,
what I have is I have
this app delegate.
In this app delegate I'm going
to create a CLLocationManager
object.
I'm going to set the app
delegate as the delegate
for the Location Manager.
The important thing for the
iBeacon, where we're going
to this method here
of
startMonitoringForRegisterBeacon
is that what I need to do is
I need to set up an NSUUID
for the region that I
want this to work in.
In my example, let's imagine
in our point of sale example
that we have - we want our
people at the register to be,
you know, in a general area.
We don't want them in the
back room scanning things
and selling things without the
security cameras around them.
So for our region I'm going to
create a UUID specified here,
and I'm going to give an
identifier of the app -
so "Moolah" in this case.
And I'm going to create a
CLBeaconRegion using the
proximityUUID I created
and the identifier.
I'm going to call on
to the location manager
to start monitoring
for this region.
One of the important
things that you need
to make sure you
implement is this method
of locationManager
didDetermineState forRegion.
This method will be called
when your app is not -
is in the background, so that
your app can receive region
notification changes.
So let's say, they
closed my register app.
They walked out of the store.
And then they opened -
walked out of the store.
You will receive
this method callback
when they leave the region.
And so in this example I'm just
going to - I have it so that
when you are inside the Beacon
region, I want to start figuring
out how far away they
are from the iBeacon.
Because I want to make sure
that my cashiers are
right close to the beacon.
I don't want them, you know,
all the way on the
other side of the store.
So I'm going to start ranging
the beacons in the region,
and one of the things I'm
going to do is I'm going
to implement this method
of locationManager
didRangeBeacons inRegion.
And I'm just going to
get the closest beacon,
because I don't particularly
care
about which iBeacon
they're close to,
as long as they're
close to one of them.
And I'm going to check the
proximity and make sure
that it's not far or unknown.
If it's not, I'm going to say
that they're near the register.
Otherwise they're not
near the register,
and I set that variable
appropriately.
One of the other
things you're going
to notice is I've also
implemented the methods
of locationManager
didEnterRegion
and locationManager
didExitRegion.
Which will be called when
the app is in the foreground.
For my example I'm going to go
over to the trusty
iPhone I have over here.
You'll notice I have
my "Moolah" app here.
I'm going to open it up.
You'll notice right here I
have my Scan Barcodes View.
You'll notice right now
it's telling them to return
to the register area
because there's no iBeacon
that it can currently detect.
So back here on my
demo machines I'm going
to start up an iBeacon.
And so you'll notice that
as soon as it detected
that the iBeacon - that
I was within the region
and that I was ranged correctly,
I got this nice little
barcode view,
so I have a nice little camera.
My cashiers can just run through
the barcodes and do that.
This view will only show
up while I'm in the -
near the iBeacon that's
appropriate for it.
And so when I turn this off,
eventually this app will
receive a notification
that I've left the region
and that this view should
probably be turned off.
And you'll notice that I
also have a catalog section.
So you'll notice now that
I've turned off the iBeacon
that I am no longer
near the register,
and so the view is turned off.
And that is how you
use iBeacons.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks Alex.
There's so much you
can do with iBeacons
that can provide a really
awesome user experience.
Both for your admins
and for the end users.
All right, next I'd like to
talk about Network Reachability.
Network Reachability
is a set of APIs
that lets you know whether
a server is reachable
at all on the network.
And best of all, it
actually tells you
when the server becomes
reachable
or becomes unreachable.
So for the following
example I want you
to note you can use
Network Reachability
to provide intelligent,
offline behavior.
So back to Alex, and he's going
to show you how that's done.
>> So back in our "Moolah"
app, I have this method.
So I created an
SCNetworkReachabiltyFlags.
And I'm going to create
a reachability reference.
Which I do
by SCNetworkReachability
CreateWithName.
And the name I'm going to
pass into here is a domain.
So in my example up above,
I have defined apple.com
as the domain I want to watch
for and see the reachability of.
So once I do that, if
the reachability is null,
I can call
SCNetworkReachabilityGetFlags.
Then once I do that I can
check the flags, and I'm going
to check
that SCNetworkReachabilityFlags
is reachable.
And using that flag I'll know
when I cannot send a network
operations because the user is
in airplane mode for example.
Now this is nice and good, but
this is just one off method.
I don't want to be
calling this all the time.
So what I really want to do
is I want to register this
so that every time the
reachability configuration
changes, I get notified.
And so what I've done down
here is I've created an
SCNetworkReachabilityContext,
which I'm feeding
in the nice little block that
I've created to check the flags.
If the flags say that
it's not reachable,
I'm going to set my offline
variable appropriately.
And what I'm going to do is
I'm going to is I'm going
to call SCNetworkReachability
SetCallback.
I'm going to feed
it the reachability.
And I have to give it this
method, reachability change,
which is written in C.
The reason I put earlier
in that context that info
with that call block is I want
to keep all my code
in Objective-C.
So all I'm going to have my C
method reachabilityChanged do
up here is I'm just going
to have it call that block
that I feed into the info.
So that I don't have to mess
around with C code that much.
With the SCNetworkReachability
I set the callback.
I set the C method that I'm
calling into in the context.
And the next thing I
need to do is I need
to make sure I schedule this
so that this gets called
every once in a while.
The way I do that is I
call SCNetworkReachability
SetDispatchQueue.
I give it the reachability
reference I've created.
And I'm going to call this on
the main queue in my example.
You can do this on other queues.
I've chosen this
just for simplicity.
So now, if we return to my
iPhone example, you're going
to notice I have this
nice little catalog
of baby clothes that I can buy.
What I want to do
is I'm just going
to switch the app
into airplane mode.
When I switch it off
you're going to notice
that SCNetworkReachability
has changed my label
to inform the user that
they are currently offline.
And so you can use
this to gate behavior
that you don't want users to do
while they're offline, like try
and edit a document
that you want to sync
up between multiple users.
And so that's SCNetwork
Reachability.
>> Well thanks Alex.
Network Reachability allows
you to provide intelligent,
offline behavior without having
to send a request and timing
out and things like that.
You know up front
that the network,
or your particular server
actually is not reachable
and you can take the
appropriate action.
So in summary, our second
app example shows us
that you can put an app into
Single App Mode using MDM,
again example to follow.
You can use iBeacon to
provide context for your app
and change your app's behavior,
depending on whether
it's near something.
You can use this with core
location to allow your admins
to really configure your
apps to a very fine grain.
And finally, network
reachability allows you
to behave intelligently when
a server is not available.
Let's talk about our third and
final app example, Assessment.
So this is your typical
exam-taking app.
There are several modes of
operation here for exams.
For our example the
flow that we want
to show you is a
student operating
on an iPad, taking an exam.
And we're going to
download the exam packet
from a document provider from
your school's file system.
Once the user begins
taking the exam,
the exam app will lock them
in and they'll take the exam
and they'll submit it.
And the students will be
allowed to use the iPad again.
So let's start with
Document Providers.
So document Providers,
as I mentioned before,
is a really awesome,
new feature of iOS 8.
It allows you to exchange
documents between apps.
When you install an app
as a document provider,
you are actually installing
network access for other apps.
To access Document Providers,
use the
UIDocumentPickerViewController.
This is the same one you
use for iCloud Doc folder.
Use Document Providers
to get access
to enterprise network resources.
Don't build in network
protocols into your app.
Instead, rely on the admin to
configure network access apps
that allows your app to access
those network resources.
All right.
So let's go back to
Alex and he's going
to show you a little
bit of an example.
>> So you'll notice that
I have an application,
which I've called
"Pencils Down."
What Pencils Down
is going to do is
that when the user starts
the test, I want them to go
into their high school's
document app,
and I want them to
retrieve the test.
And then I'm going
to proctor the exam
on behalf of the high school.
So in this example,
when I do start tests,
I have this
UIDocumentPickerViewController.
And I'm going to create one
in initWithDocumentTypes
that I'm going to allow.
In this case I'm going to choose
HTML, Tacs [phonetic] and RTF.
I'm going to set the mode.
In this case I'm going to use
UIDocumentPickerModeImport.
Because I want to get the file
and keep it in my app bundle.
The other thing I'm going to do
is I'm going to set the delegate
on the
UIDocumentPickerViewController
to myself.
And I'm going to present that
ViewController to the user.
Now when they go into
that document pick,
I can get two different
callbacks.
If, for example, they
fail to pick something,
they click done they don't find
the test file that they want,
I'm going to get
this documentPicker
WasCancelled callback.
And in this case I'm just
going to send a notification
on the console that "Hey, I
couldn't find the document."
If, for example, they
actually did pick a document,
I will call this documentPicker
didPickDocumentAtURL will get
called by the system.
What I'll do is I will double
check that there's a natural URL
and then I'm going to
open up the document.
And if I am successful in
opening up the document,
I am going to request
Single App Mode
and load up the test for them.
If we go over to the simulator,
we have our example here.
So I have "Pencils Down."
I go into my app.
You notice I have this
nice little testing view.
I'm going to click start test,
because I want to start a test
with - that my high
school has given me.
So I go into locations.
And you'll notice that
I have this MHS Doc
which is a Document Provider.
I'm going to go into
here, and you'll notice
that it has this view.
This view is actually
coming from the MHS Docs App
that I have installed
in the simulator.
This view is not
created by your app.
And so in this case if I
wanted to, I could log in.
MHS Docs would check
my credentials;
make sure I'm actually
a high school student.
So I'm just going to log in
with some blank credentials,
and I'm going to select
my programming test
that I need to do.
And so you'll notice
that once I selected it,
my app got that document
back, and I loaded it
up into my nice little web
views, and started the test.
And so that's how
Document Providers work.
>> All right.
[ Applause ]
Document Providers are very
powerful, but they're very easy
to use as you can tell.
Next, let's talk about
Autonomous Single App Mode.
We've mentioned before that
MDM can put your device
into Single App Mode.
Which means that it
will only run one app.
But in the case of this exam
app, we want the app to be able
to put itself into
Single App Mode.
So this mode of operation
is called Autonomous Single
App Mode.
Your app has to be preauthorized
by the MDM Server to do this.
This can only be done
on a supervised device.
But once that's in place,
your app can offer itself
and say "Hey, I want
control of the iPad for now."
So use Autonomous
Single App Mode
to lock the user into your app.
But please do it sparingly
because the user will get stuck
in your app if you
don't get them out.
Your app will crash and
restart, crash and restart.
And the user will
not get out of it.
So please be careful
when you do this.
But it is a really
powerful feature.
So Alex is going to
demonstrate how you can do this.
>> So we're back to my
"Pencils Down" application.
You're going to notice that here
I have this requestSingleAppMode
method that I've created.
What I'm going to call into
is UIAccessibilityRequest
GuidedAccessSession.
This is the method that will
start up Single App Mode.
What I do is I feed it a Boolean
of whether I want Single
App Mode on or off.
The other thing I'll feed
into it is a completion block
which is void BOOL didSucceed.
This Boolean that I get
will tell me if I was able
to successfully enter
or exit Single App Mode,
depending on which mode I
set in the other Boolean.
It's very important
to balance your calls.
Because as we mentioned, you
will lock the user into your app
if you don't call back into this
to turn off Single
App Mode as well.
Another important point is to
make sure that you register
for the
UIAccessibilityGuidedAccess
StatusDidChangeNotification.
This notification will be sent
out when Single App
Mode changes.
And so what I've done is I've
created a little method called
GuidedAccess DidChange
Notification.
When I receive that
notification, I am just going
to update my Single
App Mode - what is it?
State. So you'll notice here I
have GuidedAccess StatusChanged.
And I said, you know,
I am in Single App Mode
if I receive this notification.
And so we'll move
over to our iPad.
On this iPad is a supervised
device I've already set up.
I've also pushed down an MDM
profile that defined that
"Pencils Down," giving
its bundle ID is allowed
to start Single App
Mode autonomously.
So if I go into "Pencils Down."
I'm going to start my tests.
I'm going to skip over the
file provider section for now.
You'll notice that
I am now in my test.
If I try and exit the app
by pressing the Home
button, nothing happens.
I'm locked into here.
Let's say I don't know
any of these questions
so I'm just going
to submit the test.
And the test was
successfully submitted.
And so you'll now notice if I
press the Home button I'm able
to exit because I
balanced the calls.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks Alex.
Autonomous Single App Mode.
Very powerful.
Use it sparingly.
Make sure the user can
get out of it eventually.
Okay. Summary of the third app.
Document Providers.
Super powerful.
New feature in iOS 8.
Use it to gain access to network
resources in your enterprise.
Add an app equals
at network access.
Autonomous Single App Mode.
Allows you to lock your own
app into Single App Mode
so the user cannot go
to a different app.
So what have we learned today?
We learned that we should
assume that MDM will be used
to manage your apps and devices.
When you're writing apps
for business and education,
assume MDM's going to
be there and is going
to configure the
environment for your app.
You can safely assume
that enterprise owned
devices will be supervised.
So check out the list of
features that are available
to you when the device is
supervised and use them.
On the other hand,
if you're writing
for Bring Your Own Device
environment, you can assume
that the devices will
not be supervised.
So if your app is going to
work in both environments,
be aware of the features that
are available in each case.
And finally, rely on iOS
to provide a great set
of systemwide features that
your apps can leverage.
Single Sign-on.
VPN. Global Proxy.
Manage data flow
between the managed apps
and the unmanaged
apps and accounts.
Single App Mode.
Both MDM driven and autonomous.
Document Providers.
iBeacon and Core
Location for context.
All right, finally I want
to call your attention
to a great new portal that
we've just put online,
developer.apple.com/enterprise,
made for developers
just like you.
[ Applause ]
For more information, our
Evangelist is Paul Danbold.
There's that enterprise
portal again.
You will find most of
what you need in there.
And of course the developer
forums is a great resource.
Some related sessions.
This morning we had
"Managing Apple Devices."
Please check out that video.
We have "Distributing
Enterprise Apps" right here,
following this session.
And if you're interested in
digging into Doc Providers -
Document Providers - "Building
a Document-Based App" is
a must-attend.
Thursday, 11:30.
Thank you very much.
[ Applause ]