>> Good afternoon everyone.
I'm Nav Patel.
I'm a software engineer
on the Core Location team,
and today I want to tell you
about the next great leap we're
taking in location services.
We're taking Core
Location indoors.
So we'll start off by covering
what indoor positioning is,
how does it work,
how does it fit
in with the other Core
Location technologies?
We'll also cover how you use
it, what APIs you'll use,
and we also will talk
about indoor positioning
and iBeacon technology and
how they work together.
Finally, we'll cover
some next steps
on how venues can get signed up
and how you guys
can start looking
at the documentation
and the APIs.
So with today's technology,
Core Location
on iOS is the best
location service you can get
on a mobile device.
We have the best accuracy.
We have the best response time.
We have the best
Time To First Fix,
and this comes from
the tight hardware
and software integration
we have.
The hardware team and
the software team work
with each other to make
sure we get the most
out of the hardware we
have on our devices.
So our Core Location
technologies today start off
with cellular.
Now, cellular is great
for iPhones and iPads
with data connectivity
because it's essentially free.
You're already connected
to these cell towers,
and it's good enough to
give you an approximation
of which area of
a city you're in.
Now, because you're already
associated with a tower,
you're not spending any more
energy or power to get this fix
and it's usually available.
So, for cases like: you're
landing in an airplane
and you turn on your phone, this
is the first fix you'll get,
and it's good enough
to set your time zone.
Next we have GPS technology.
Now, GPS is based on satellite,
and it was the first big
revolution in location services.
It was accurate enough
to do outdoor navigation
and responsive enough to
do outdoor navigation.
Now, we didn't stop there.
GPS was introduced
a little while ago,
but we've been constantly
improving the accuracy
and the Time To First
Fix of GPS as well.
What's great about GPS is we
launched satellites into space.
We use both the American Navstar
and the Russian GLONASS
satellite constellation,
and this gives us really
great global coverage.
Now, the issue with
GPS is urban canyons.
When you're in a city
with tall buildings,
they can obscure your
view to the satellite,
and so you might
not get a signal,
and when you do get a signal,
that signal can suffer
from multipath.
So the signal will bounce
off in between buildings,
and you might not get a
very good fix at first.
So to solve this
problem, we use Wi-Fi.
Now, Wi-Fi is good enough
to give you position
within a city block.
Often it will put you in
front of the right building,
and this is really for
those cases like New York
and San Francisco where you have
tons of Wi-Fi already out there
where you can use this
to give you position
in urban canyon environments.
What's great is that this also
gives you location services
on Wi-Fi only devices.
So if you have an
iPod or an iPad Wi-Fi,
you can get location using this.
So their entire location
experience is based on Wi-Fi.
So the existing technologies
work great.
They'll let you navigate
outdoors.
They also work well globally.
You don't need to put
up any infrastructure.
You don't need to launch
satellites as an app developer,
and the Wi-Fi AP's
already out there,
and so it actually
works very well.
But there's an issue, and
that's when you move indoors.
Today we do give you
some position indoors,
and you might have had that
experience where you pull
out your phone in a mall at a
Starbucks, and it will tell you,
"Hey, it actually
found my exact spot.
How are they doing that?"
And that is using a combination
of GPS that may have come
in through the windows or
skylights or using Wi-Fi,
and that can work indoors, but
it's really not good enough
to do any sort of
navigation indoors.
Also, Core Location
gives you an altitude,
and when you're thinking
about the context of being
in a building, you really
want floor information.
Altitude is hard to use.
So we heard you guys really
want to build applications
for indoor venues, and for
that we're announcing
Indoor Positioning.
So here's a look at
what it looks like.
This is me a couple of days
ago in the California Academy
of Sciences in Golden Gate Park.
Now, you can see me walking
around the planetarium here.
The playback has
been sped up by 10x
so you can actually see
me move through the space.
Here I'll walk past the giant
swinging pendulum towards the
swamp, the albino
alligator, and as you can see,
this is pretty accurate, and it
works amazingly well indoors.
It's also very responsive.
You know, hypothetically, you
could build a game of Pac-Man
in your office, and a bunch
of engineers could run
around and piss off HR...
[ Laughter ]
...hypothetically.
But it's quite good.
So indoor positioning works
using RF parametric data that's
in your venue already.
We also use motion sensors.
We use the M7 chip, and these
sensors and these RF signals
that are in the air
is what we use
to give you your
indoor position.
So how does this all work?
Well, we use your existing
technologies: your cell,
GPS and Wi-Fi, and
these are running,
and they'll put you close
to or inside a venue
like we just talked about.
When you approach a venue
that's indoor position enabled,
we'll start scanning
your Wi-Fi and using more
of your motion sensors.
We use your motion
sensors at this point
because it gives us information
for our estimation algorithms
of where you're moving indoors,
but it also gives
us key information
about how quickly you're moving.
If you're moving at 40
miles per hour in a car,
you're probably not indoors.
Hopefully, you're not indoors.
So when we get a good fix
and we're confident, hey,
you are indoors, we'll also
turn down your GPS chip.
So this is the hardware
and software integration I
was talking about earlier.
We do this to save power.
So that indoor positioning,
even though we're using RF more,
we're not consuming more power.
Now, all of this is really
cool and it looks really great.
But why indoors?
Why do we care?
Well, there are a lot
of amazing applications
for large indoor venues today.
We have things like directories.
So here's the Heathrow
application, and it's great.
It shows you all the
shops and restaurants
that are throughout
the entire airport.
We also have venue maps.
Now, venue maps will tell
you: "Oh, the Nordstrom's is
on this side, the Macy's
is on the other side,"
and it gives you
useful information,
and we have some level
of interactivity.
So this is the MOMA application,
and a user can browse
the catalog
and pick a particular thing that
they're looking at and listen
to commentary about it.
But there's only limited
context over here.
What we want to do is more.
With indoors you can enable
things like way-finding.
So here you can imagine you're
going through the airport,
now we can route you
to the right gate.
You can also imagine
the impact this can have
on the visually impaired
community.
They get great GPS
services outdoors today
and that helps them get around.
Venues can also build
this experience
into their applications so that
you can navigate indoors inside
a mall.
And not just for the
visually impaired,
but think about when you're
visiting a new large indoor
venue for the first time.
If you're at a hospital,
you don't want
to follow a 10-step direction
you got at the reception.
You don't want to
parse floor plans.
You just want to find
your loved one's room,
and this is where indoor
positioning and navigating
with way-finding steps in.
Now, with location we
can also do other really
interesting things.
We can help you find each other.
So you can think
about applications
like Find My Friends.
Here you can imagine a kid
gets dropped off at the mall
and pulls out his
phone and says, hey,
where are all my
friends hanging out?
Okay, they're at that the food
court on the ground floor.
I can head there.
That's pretty cool.
You can also find you.
So the venue in this
case could be aware
of where you're using
your application.
This is one of my
favorite use cases.
Imagine you're in
a Vegas casino.
You're in your hotel room.
You pull out your phone,
and as you're leaving,
you order a drink.
You go downstairs, settle
down on a poker table,
and the drink arrives to
exactly where you are.
That's a pretty awesome
experience.
Now, these use cases are pretty
location centric, but I want you
to think about how you
can use indoor positioning
to be the last piece of
the puzzle in a problem.
So here you can imagine
something
like an airport application.
Now, I have my flight
leaving soon,
but I need to grab a quick bite.
So I'm going to walk over to
a restaurant and sit down.
My application knows which
gate I'm leaving from,
knows what time my
flight is boarding,
and it knows how far away
I am from the gate now,
and so we can start
incorporating this information
to, say, give you a
quick buzz and say, "Hey,
you better start heading
back to your gate if you want
to board this flight."
So these are some pretty
exciting use cases you can build
with indoor positioning.
So how do you start using it?
Well, you need to
have your Wi-Fi on.
We depend on RF parametric
data in these venues.
We also want your users
to be actively engaged
in the application.
We use aggressive Wi-Fi
scanning and motion sensors,
so we want to make sure
we're not just running this
if the user isn't actually
using that indoor positioning.
Now, in terms of API, what
API do you need to use
for indoor positioning?
Well, you can use the exact same
Core Location API you've already
been using.
Now, this is really cool because
if your application today is
requesting best accuracy,
you'll start seeing indoor fixes
when your user wanders into
an indoor-enabled environment.
You won't have to make
any code change for that.
Now, one problem we talked
about earlier was altitude
versus floors and if you
want to build an indoor app,
you really want to
know the floor number.
So in iOS 8 we're adding floor
number to the Core Location API.
It looks something like this:
in the CLLocation object
you'll see a "floor" property.
This property will usually
be nil, but when you walk
into a venue and we're
serving you indoor fixes,
we'll populate this number
with the level of floor
that you're on, zero
being the ground floor.
Positive numbers up.
Negative numbers down.
We'll still show you 13.
[ Laughter ]
So we have your floor number,
but Core Location is giving
you a latitude and longitude,
and you're usually displaying
your floor plan on a flat image.
So how do you deal with this?
How do you go from your
latitude and longitude
onto your X, Y on your floor?
To help you figure
this out I'm going
to call my colleague Vitali.
>> Thanks, Nav.
Hi, I'm Vitali Lovich.
I'm from the Core Location
team, and I'm going
to show you how you can
integrate your existing Core
Location API with an
existing app that you have
that shows an indoor floor plan.
So a geographic coordinate
system,
as you may be familiar with,
is a latitude and a longitude.
It's very common and convenient.
Two numbers represent any
place in the world; however,
there are some challenges
that you may have
when you work with them.
For instance, finding the
distance between two latitudes
and longitudes or a direction
between them is very
complicated math.
But when you show
a floor plan image,
you want to show a floor
plan image to the user,
and it's very easy to display.
It maps to the display
coordinate frame system very
well, and its in pixels,
and it's X is positive
to the right, Y is
positive down.
And so we want to somehow
bridge the two by converting
and so there are three
coordinate systems that you want
to keep in mind when
doing these conversions:
There's the geographic
coordinate system,
which is spherical; There's the
floor plan coordinate system,
which is in pixels
and it's planar;
And then there's the display
coordinate frame system,
where you show what part of the
floor plan you're interested in,
and for this talk we're
going to cover the conversion
from geographic to floor
plan coordinate frames.
So you want to make
sure that you account
for spherical distortion,
because any time you go
from a sphere and
you try to map it
onto a rectangular plane you'll
have all sorts of distortions
where straight lines aren't
straight lines anymore .
So to help us accomplish this
task, we're going to make use
of some amazing MapKit
helper functions,
and so the first
one I want to call
out is MKMapPointForCoordinate.
Now, what this does is it
takes a geographical latitude
and longitude and converts
it to a MapKit point,
which is just an X, Y coordinate
on a Mercator projection,
and so positive-- so,
X and Y represent east
and south and it's in points.
MKMetersBetweenMapPoints
is a very accurate
and very precise way
of finding the distance
between two MK map points
in meters, and it accounts
for your spherical distortions,
and then we'll take a look
at MKMetersPerMapPointAtLatitude
a little bit later.
So now that we have this primer,
what do we need to get started?
Well, we want to find
two points on our map,
and we'll call them
anchor points,
and an anchor point is simply
a latitude and longitude mapped
to a floor plan pixel so we
know how the floor plan exists
in the real world.
So what you want
to do is you want
to find two identifying
features in your floor plan
that are very easy to find on an
aerial map, like you might find
in Apple Maps, and then you
find the corresponding latitude
and longitude for
that floor plan pixel.
So now that we have these two
anchor points, we need to figure
out how the floor plan in
pixels maps to the real world.
So we need to figure
out a scale.
So how many pixels
represent a single meter?
So to accomplish
this we're going
to use the MapKit helper
functions I pointed out earlier
and we're going to convert our
anchor points' geographical
coordinates into
Mercator projection,
and then we use MapKit
again to figure
out the distance in meters.
So now we have distance
in meters.
And then the distance in a floor
plan is very easy to calculate.
It's just the Pythagorean
Theorem, and we're just going
to call hypot to do it for us,
and now we have a
distance in pixels.
So now we have pixels.
We have meters.
We know how many pixels
represent 1 meter.
Orientation is a little
bit more complicated,
and so your floor plan, when
you show it to the user,
is usually aligned to
some logical orientation.
You might show it to them
so that X is positive
on the screen, and Y is down.
That doesn't necessarily
correspond to your north
and east coordinates,
and so we need to figure
out how we would rotate
to that floor plan
to make it show up correctly.
So what we're going to do is
we're going to align the east
and south to the X and
Y, and we can see now
that our two anchor points in
yellow are relative to the east
and south, but they're
somewhat different.
They're rotated relative to
the green, which is relative
to the floor plan, and so
what we're going to do is try
to calculate the angle
between the green line
and the yellow line using
some existing angles
that we know about,
and so the way to do
that is you simply
subtract the two angles.
So now we know how much to
rotate the floor plan by to get
into your logical
orientation that you want.
So now we have these
two precomputed values.
What do we do with them?
Well, we're going to
get a user position
in geographical coordinates,
latitudes and longitudes.
As you may have guessed,
we convert it
into the Mercator projection,
and so that gives us a user
point, and now what we're going
to do is subtract the
user points from one
of our anchor points, and that
gives us how many MapKit points
we are east and south
from the floor plan.
But we want to account
for the fact
that MapKit points are not
the same thing as meters.
So we want to account for the
fact that MapKit is a projection
of the globe, and so
it has distortion,
and so the distortion
changes depending
on which latitude you're at.
And so, by multiplying
by this meter scale,
we know how many meters
east and south the user is
on your floor plan, and so
now we just apply the scale we
precomputed previously.
That gives us how many
pixels east and south,
and then once we apply the
rotation, we get pixels
in X, Y of your floor plan.
And so, if you were to
apply this backwards,
you would have a mechanism
-- like, literally,
the exact same steps
backwards --
you would have a mechanism
converting your floor plan
pixels into geographic
coordinates.
So I hope I've demonstrated
a way for you
to incorporate the existing
geographic coordinates
that you get from Core Location
into your indoor floor plan.
Thank you.
>> So with that information you
can take your Core Location fix,
map it to your floor plan
and start displaying
it to your user.
Now that's really cool; you can
build an application with that.
Where can you start
building these applications?
Well, in terms of availability,
I'd like to tell you
about three venues.
There's the California Academy
of Sciences that I demoed
to you earlier, in Golden
Gate Park in San Francisco,
which is a big natural
history museum.
There's the Westfield SF Mall
a couple of blocks from here.
Has many floors, and it's
a quintessential mall
in a big city.
You may have also flown in
from the San Jose International
Airport, and so we're going
to be enabling that soon,
and all of these will be
enabled in upcoming seeds
of the developer build along
with sample code that walk you
through the process that
Vitali just described.
So keep an eye out on
developer.apple.com for when
that sample code comes out, and
you guys can run out and start,
and we'll enable these venues,
and you guys can start
using indoor positioning.
Now, these are not the
only set of venues.
There are very many, many more
that are going to be coming
up in the upcoming months,
and so we'll be announcing
them as that happens.
So you build this application.
How do we get people to
start using this application?
install this application?
Well, there's a traditional way,
which is just advertise
at your venue.
Put up a giant sign
with an ugly QR code,
but we don't like
that very much.
So last year we introduced
the Near Me feature
in the App Store,
and that allowed you
to launch the App Store,
look at that particular view,
and it would tell
you the relevant
and popular applications
near you.
But that still relies on the
user to launch the application
and look for nearby venues,
which they might have
never thought about.
So as a continuity
feature, we're bubbling
up that popular application
onto your Lock screen.
So now when you open your
phone and wake your device,
you'll see this in the
bottom left corner.
I'll show a little
App Store icon
so that you can launch the
App Store directly to the page
that will tell you the
popular applications near you,
and once that application
is installed,
we'll actually show you the icon
for that particular application.
And when the user
swipes this up,
we'll launch your application
directly from the Lock screen.
Now that's really cool.
Now people can show up at your
venue, pull out their phone
and launch the appropriate
application without ever having
to go through multiple steps.
But let's say I have a specific
venue with a really great app
and I want to notify people
when they walk into my venue.
Well, here we're thinking about
when we're close to, let's say,
the entrance of a
venue, and we're thinking
about notifying your
application,
and that's when we want to
think about iBeacon technology.
So, indoor positioning
and iBeacon technology
really complement each other.
They complete the indoor
experience that we expect.
Now, iBeacon technology, we
covered this last year in the
"What's New in Core
Location" talk.
Devices with iBeacon technology,
these little beacons,
can run on little coin
batteries and last a few months.
You can also take any
iOS device with Bluetooth
and advertise beacons with them.
So if you have a point of
sale device, you can turn
that into a beacon as well,
and we can use these beacons
to advertise that, "Hey, I
have a region over here,"
and your application can
register to get notified
when the device sees
that region.
So when we're thinking
about indoor positioning
and iBeacon technology,
indoor positioning is really
about your position in the
geographic space, where you're
on the floor plan, and it's
about navigation and getting you
from one place to another.
iBeacon technology
is about proximity.
What is near me?
It's also about notification.
Because it's based on Bluetooth
for energy, you can register
for beacon regions, and we'll
notify your application --
even if it's in the background
-- when the device sees this.
So let's ground all
of this in an example.
I want you think
about an art gallery,
and in this art gallery we
have an amazing application
that really creates an immersive
experience for our visitors,
and we love this
application so much,
we want to notify our
users when they enter
into this art gallery.
Well, you could use
a CLCircularRegion.
Now, this is a region with a
point in the middle in lat/long
and a radius, and a
CLCircularRegion is a great API
that lets you notify the
same way beacons would
in the background.
But CLCircularRegions rely on
Wi-Fi, and so we really want
to make the radius about
as small as 100 meters,
not much less than that.
Now, this would work great
if you have a colossal
building that's perfectly round,
but that might not be the case.
So for our floor plan, if
we have a round region,
this might be an issue.
Now, if someone is walking
into your parking lot,
they'll get notified.
If you're on the second
floor of a building
and you're just walking
on the first floor,
they'll get notified.
Here's where we want to use the
power of iBeacon technology.
What we can do is install
beacons at the entrances
of your floor plan,
and the great thing
about these beacons is
we can really tune them
and drop them exactly
where we want
and with what power we want
them to emit their signal
so that we can control, "I
want to notify at this point."
And now the device can say...
when you have your application,
the application can register
with Core Location and say,
"when you see this
beacon, notify me."
And when the device
enters your region,
it will trigger that API.
So we use the
startMonitoringForRegion API
with a beaconRegion
where you specify
which unique identifier
you are looking for on
that iBeacon technology device.
And when you see that region,
we'll trigger the
didEnterRegion delegate,
and this is when you can
start notifying your user
when appropriate.
At this point the user sees the
notification, and they think,
oh great, I do have
this application.
Let me launch it.
And here you can create your
indoor positioning experience.
So you can display your
user's position on the map,
and as the user walks around,
the little dot will follow them,
which is pretty cool, and while
they're browsing your catalog,
they can pick something that
they really want to see,
and you can navigate them
to that particular exhibit.
This can provide
step-by-step direction exactly
where you want to go.
So once we're at this place,
we want to also show the
user relevant commentary
about the exhibits
that are around them.
And again, here we're
talking about proximity,
and when we're thinking
about proximity,
we want to think about iBeacons.
We need fine-grain proximity.
So what we can do
now is deploy beacons
at all the various exhibits
where we have commentary
on our floor plan, and when a
user is using your application
and enters the region, we can
start ranging from that beacon,
and we can say, "Oh,
am I just seeing it
or am I very close to it?
Am I right up next to it?"
And when you are, you
can start doing things
like providing commentary
or showing the appropriate
item in the catalog.
Now, this uses the Ranging API.
So you can call
startRangingBeaconsInRegion,
and then your delegate
will get called
with all the beacons
that it sees.
Here you can use the
proximity value to filter
for how close you want
to be from that beacon.
Now, these beacons will
also advertise a major
and a minor code.
Now, this major code can
encode something like,
"Is this an entry beacon or
is this an exhibit beacon,"
and the minor code
can tell you exactly
which exhibit this exhibit
beacon is advertising,
and then you can
do a local lookup
and show relevant
information for that.
So we can build these
amazing features with beacons
and indoor positioning, and this
really completes that experience
of what your application needs
to do for an indoor venue.
Now, when you're thinking
about these amazing features,
you have to keep
the user in mind.
You have a lot of power
with these features,
and with great power...
comes strict security
and privacy guidelines.
[ Laughter ]
So we want you and your users
to be on the same page here.
You, as the app developer, need
to anticipate how am I going
to be, how is my user going
to be using their location?
Your user also needs to
be able to anticipate,
"How is this application
using my location?"
So forming this trust
between the user
and the app developers is what
allows users to trust you,
as the app developer,
with their location.
So there's a couple
of things you can do.
You can request location
only as you need it.
So if you have a particular view
in your application
that's not using location
and you're just logging in,
don't start requesting
location immediately.
Wait till you actually launch
a view that has a map on it
or you need to use
some location services.
Also use When In
Use authorization.
Now, this is something new
that was introduced in iOS 8.
If you missed the "What's
New In Core Location" talk
that just happened
prior to this one,
be sure to check out that video.
There's some amazing
new features,
and When In Use authorization
really makes it clear
to the user that I can tell
when this application is using
my location so I can trust it.
Also have a clear
purpose string.
Tell your users what you're
doing with your location.
This is a really great
opportunity to communicate
with them so that they're
on the same page as you.
So let's talk about
some next steps.
We have the Maps Connect
website, and here,
if you're a venue owner or if
you're building an application
for a particular venue, you can
head on over to this website
and tell us all about it.
Tell us what you plan
on doing at this venue.
Tell us what kind of
applications you plan
on building, and we can get
you started on the pipeline
so that we can enable indoor
positioning in your venue.
There's also the Maps page,
which is a great resource
for maps and Core Location APIs,
and there's also a new iBeacon
page, where it will tell you
about iBeacon technology, again,
all the API and documentation
that you'll need, and
also licensing information
if you're interested
in manufacturing
iBeacon technology.
So as a summary, we talked
about indoor positioning today.
We talked about some
amazing use cases
that we can enable with this.
We also talked about
Core Location APIs
and how there's very little you
need to add to your application
to make them indoor enabled.
We're just using indoor position
to create a new amazing
experience for your users,
and with indoor positioning
and iBeacon technology,
these two technologies
really work perfectly well
with each other, and they
complete the indoor experience
that you expect from
your application
so that you start breaking
out of the barriers of, "Hey,
this is what's happening
in my phone,
and this is what's
happening around me."
Now the environment and
the device can interact
with each other.
For more information, be sure to
check out the developer forums
and the documentation.
There was a related
session, as I mentioned,
of "What's New In
Core Location".
So please make sure
to check that out.
Also there's a "User Privacy in
iOS and OS X" talk on Thursday,
and here we'll discuss how
you should be using location,
how you can communicate
appropriately with your users.
Thank you very much.
[ Applause ]